<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Theoretical Foundations of the Multicultural Systems Approach (MSA): A Meta-Framework for Intercultural Management</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2005-10-12">12/10/2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andres</forename><surname>Molina</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Theoretical Foundations of the Multicultural Systems Approach (MSA): A Meta-Framework for Intercultural Management</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2005-10-12">12/10/2005</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">33D7E1A56C58751B4EB9F160547E5967</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>intercultural negotiation</term>
					<term>systems theory</term>
					<term>cultural intelligence</term>
					<term>organizational behavior</term>
					<term>union-management relations</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Multicultural Systems Approach (MSA) proposes a shift from viewing culture as a set of static, national traits toward understanding it as a dynamic system of interdependent cultural logics operating within organizations. Building upon general systems theory, intercultural management, and organizational behavior, the MSA conceptualizes multicultural interaction as the negotiation of equilibrium among diverse cultural subsystems, each with distinct assumptions about hierarchy, communication, time, and coordination.</p><p>Unlike established frameworks such as Hofstede's dimensions or the GLOBE project, the MSA emphasizes interactional dynamics and feedback loops rather than categorical differences. It accounts for how multicultural teams and institutions co-create hybrid cultural orders, shaping both performance and cohesion. This article introduces the theoretical architecture of MSA, clarifying its axioms, levels of analysis, and principles of Cultural Alignment. By reframing intercultural management through a systemic lens, MSA contributes to theory by explaining how and why multicultural collaboration succeeds or fails-and provides an integrative platform for future empirical research on cultural systems in organizations.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction: The Crisis of Cultural Reductionism in Management Theory</head><p>For decades, the field of cross-cultural management has been characterized by debates concerning convergence versus divergence <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Pudelko &amp; Harzing, 2007)</ref> and standardization versus localization, particularly within Multinational Corporations (MNCs). Despite the extensive development of taxonomic models, which map cultural differences using dimensions like power distance or individualism/collectivism, predicting and influencing intercultural effectiveness remains challenging. This is largely due to the pervasive issue of cultural reductionism, or the tendency to simplify complex organizational dynamics into static national categories and binary cultural traits (e.g., USA vs. Japan).</p><p>The consequence of this reductionism is particularly acute in high-stakes organizational settings like labor-management negotiations. Traditional industrial relations models (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Dunlop, 1958;</ref><ref type="bibr">Walton &amp; McKersie, 1965)</ref> prioritize economic interests, power dynamics, and legal frameworks. When cultural factors emerge, such as conflicting communication styles <ref type="bibr">(high-context vs. low-context)</ref> or disparate time orientations (sequential vs. synchronic), they are often dismissed as interpersonal misunderstandings or irrational behavior, rather than systemic properties of interacting subcultures.</p><p>This article introduces the Multicultural Systems Approach (MSA) as a novel theoretical metaframework designed to overcome this fragmentation and bridge the gap between static cultural categorization and dynamic organizational reality. The MSA reframes organizations as multicultural ecosystems where management and labor operate as distinct, yet interdependent, cultural subsystems. It is the misalignment between these subcultural logics, rather than solely conflicting economic interests, that explains persistent conflict and negotiation failures <ref type="bibr">(Bacharach &amp; Bamberger, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Doucouliagos &amp; Laroche, 2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Note on the Origin of this Framework:</head><p>The core insights driving this framework originated from applied research and consulting practice in complex intercultural labor negotiation systems, particularly in Latin America. This applied perspective is detailed in Más allá del Conflicto: Un Enfoque Multicultural para las Relaciones entre Sindicatos y Empresas [Beyond Conflict: A Multicultural Approach to Union-Management Relations] <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Molina, 2024)</ref> and provides the empirical origin for the generalized theoretical structure formalized herein.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Theoretical Background: From Cultural Dimensions to Cultural Systems</head><p>To establish the theoretical necessity of MSA, we must first review the evolution and limitations of existing models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">The Limits of Categorical Cultural Models</head><p>Models developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hofstede (2001</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">), Trompenaars &amp; Hampden-Turner (1997)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">House et al. (2004)</ref> among others provided foundational language for cultural differences. However, these frameworks, rooted primarily in national culture, struggle to account for the complexity of contemporary organizational life, and are inconsistent with the view of the organization as a carrier of culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Louis, 1983)</ref>:</p><p>1. Static and Essentialist View: They often treat culture as a fixed entity, failing to capture how cultural meanings are co-created, adapted, or changed during interaction (e.g., negotiation).</p><p>2. Focus on the Nation: They neglect the potent influence of organizational subcultures (managerial, technical, functional, union) that exist within nations <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Martin, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Mendonca, 1994)</ref> and often override national distinctions in specific contexts.</p><p>3. Fragmented Analysis: They present dimensions or dilemmas (like Universalism vs. Particularism) but often fail to model the systemic interdependence that makes organizations function as cohesive wholes (or fail entirely).</p><p>The limitations of these models become particularly clear in complex contexts, such as transnational trade union cooperation in Europe, where cultural obstacles arise not just from national differences but from differences in language, translation, and varying conceptual understandings of terms like 'austerity' or 'public sector' .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">The Shift to Interactional and Organizational Culture</head><p>The conceptual inadequacy of relying purely on national categories led to parallel developments emphasizing the local, dynamic, and organizational nature of culture:</p><p>• Organizational Culture: Scholars like Edgar H. Schein (2010) defined culture through shared basic assumptions used to manage internal integration and external adaptation. This view naturally implies the existence of subcultures within the organization (e.g., between different occupational groups).</p><p>• Cultural Pragmatics: Edward T. <ref type="bibr">Hall's work (1976)</ref> on communication context and time orientation provides the mechanism for how subcultures interact. The MSA adopts this focus, emphasizing that difficulties in organizational communication are often related to differences in communication style (e.g., high-context vs. low-context).</p><p>• Intercultural Organizational Communication: Some scholars like <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lauring (2011)</ref> stress that cultural differences are negotiated and socially organized in the local setting, rather than being static a priori entities. The local organizational context must be taken into account, linking micro-level interaction patterns to intercultural communication failure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Systems Theory Foundations of MSA</head><p>The MSA draws its meta-framework from General Systems Theory (GST) and autopoietic social systems theory to overcome the limitations of static cultural models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">General Systems Theory (GST) and Emergence</head><p>Ludwig von <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bertalanffy (1968</ref>) defined systems theory to analyze "open systems" that interact with their environment and maintain a "steady state" despite entropy. James <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Gleick (1988)</ref> further characterized such complex systems as exhibiting non-linear emergent properties. The MSA utilizes GST to define the organization (or the negotiation system) as an open system, where the outcome (the negotiated agreement or conflict recurrence) is an emergent property <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Tsoukas, 2005)</ref> of the dynamic interaction between the cultural subsystems, not a simple summation of individual preferences or traits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Social Systems and Autopoiesis</head><p>Niklas Luhmann's Social Systems theory (1995) defines social systems as autopoietic, or selfreproducing and closed systems that operate through communication.</p><p>• Meaning as Operation: Luhmann posits that social systems process meaning. Negotiation, therefore, is fundamentally an ongoing, recursive process of communication and co-creation of social reality.</p><p>• Systemic Conflict: Conflict arises not just from opposing interests, but from contradictions within the system. From the MSA perspective, a breakdown in communication occurs when there is a failure of sensemaking: when one subculture attempts to interpret the actions of the other through its own, incompatible internal logic (e.g., low-context management misinterpreting high-context union behavior).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Architecture of the Multicultural Systems Approach (MSA)</head><p>The MSA formalizes the interaction between company management and labor (or any two distinct organizational groups) as an interdependent system of cultural logics.</p><p>4.1. Core Assumptions of MSA 1. Pluralism: Organizations are composed of semi-autonomous, culturally distinct subcultures (e.g., management, labor, technical staff).</p><p>2. Negotiation as Interface: Negotiation is the systemic interface where these subcultures confront their differing assumptions about fairness, power, and temporal orientation.</p><p>3. Culture as Infrastructure: Culture acts as the cognitive and relational infrastructure that shapes the interpretation of actions and the legitimacy of outcomes.</p><p>4. Adaptation via Feedback: System stability and sustainability depend on feedback mechanisms that enable mutual learning, adaptation, and recalibration of assumptions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Mechanisms of System Dynamics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mechanism</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Role in Negotiation</head><p>Cultural Logics (Subcultural Inputs) Shared, deeply held assumptions (e.g., efficiency/short-term vs. equity/long-term continuity).</p><p>Determine perceived interests and definitions of acceptable outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cultural Interface (Interaction)</head><p>Points of communication where differences in style (context level, assertiveness) become evident.</p><p>High friction here leads to misattribution, misinterpretation, and conflict escalation.</p><p>Alignment Mechanisms (Feedback Loops)</p><p>Deliberate processes (facilitation, joint reflection, training in Cultural Intelligence (CQ)).</p><p>Allow the system to achieve intercultural homeostasis-a dynamic state of mutual intelligibility and co-creation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cultural</head><p>Alignment/Synergy (Output)</p><p>The outcome where differences are leveraged to innovate solutions, resulting in durable agreements and high relational legitimacy.</p><p>The MSA emphasizes that conflict escalation can occur rapidly in intercultural settings (a "leap" or acceleration of conflict) because discrepancies often generate misunderstandings immediately, bypassing early stages of conflict resolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">MSA as a Paradigm Shift in Negotiation Theory</head><p>MSA offers a systemic alternative to traditional negotiation models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Challenging Universal Rationality</head><p>Traditional integrative negotiation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Fisher &amp; Ury, 1981)</ref> assumes that focusing on underlying interests is sufficient. MSA argues that interests themselves are culturally mediated. A union focused on continuity and community interprets interests through a collective, long-term frame, whereas a managerial team focused on efficiency and agility uses an individualistic, short-term frame. Ignoring this underlying cultural logic makes genuine integration virtually impossible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Introduction of Adaptive Negotiation</head><p>MSA shifts the focus from managing outcomes (distributive/integrative) to managing the system itself. This introduces the concept of Adaptive Negotiation, where the process involves mutual transformation and cultural learning. The effectiveness of this process is driven by Cultural Intelligence (CQ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Earley &amp; Ang, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Joo-seng, 2004)</ref>, particularly the metacognitive component, as discovered by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Chua, Morris &amp; Mor (2012)</ref>, which enables negotiators to anticipate cultural preferences and adjust their own schemes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Core Testable Propositions</head><p>The utility of MSA can be tested through a set of foundational propositions:</p><p>• P1: Negotiation outcomes (quality and sustainability) are determined by the degree of Cultural Alignment between the subcultural logics of the negotiating parties, rather than merely the structural compatibility <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Posthuma, 2009)</ref> of their economic interests.</p><p>(This tests the core relational and cultural hypothesis of the MSA against structural models).</p><p>• P2: The explicit establishment of Feedback Mechanisms (e.g., joint reflection sessions, intercultural training, third-party cultural facilitation) significantly moderates the negative impact of high Cultural Misalignment on negotiation duration and conflict recurrence. (This tests the systems theory principle that feedback prevents systemic drift and entropy).</p><p>• P3: Negotiators exhibiting high Cultural Metacognition <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ang &amp; Van Dyne, 2008)</ref> are significantly more likely to achieve synergistic solutions that integrate seemingly contradictory cultural logics, compared to those relying on general negotiation competence. (This validates the importance of conscious cultural reflection and adaptation).</p><p>• P4: Agreements developed through a process of Mutual Identity Recognition (validating the legitimacy of the other subculture's worldview) yield higher Relational Legitimacy and lower instances of post-agreement conflict escalation. (This incorporates social identity theory and ethical considerations into the predictive power of the framework).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Illustrative Case: Company-Union Negotiations through the MSA Lens</head><p>The MSA framework is designed to diagnose and address systemic breakdowns where traditional negotiation models fail to explain persistent conflict. Consider the case of Cementos Argos, a multinational Colombian company that produces and markets cement, concrete, and aggregates. This case, drawn from the author's consulting experience, illustrates how cultural dynamics can critically influence negotiation outcomes. As the largest cement and concrete producer in Colombia and a major player in the United States, Central America, and the Caribbean, Cementos Argos was facing an episode of adversarial labor negotiations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Failure of Traditional Models:</head><p>Management, representing a predominantly low-context, efficiency-oriented subculture, presented proposals grounded in detailed quantitative data and focused on short-term quarterly performance. The union, operating from a high-context, collectivist, and continuityoriented subculture, interpreted these data-driven presentations as threats to their group stability and historical relationships, perceiving them as cold, incomplete, or even aggressive.</p><p>The company attributed the resulting conflict to the union's "stubbornness" or "irrationality," overlooking the deeper cultural misalignment that underpinned the communication breakdown.</p><p>MSA Intervention and Synergy:</p><p>1. Cultural Mapping: Workshops made the core subcultural logics explicit. Management valued Innovation/Agility; the Union valued Community/Continuity.</p><p>2. Adaptive Communication: Negotiators trained in CQ began adjusting their communication (CQ Behavioral). Management learned to introduce data relationally (high-context style), while the union learned to use more explicit data when framing their continuity concerns (low-context style).</p><p>3. Mutual Recognition: Both sides acknowledged the legitimacy of the other's temporal frame (P4). The union's focus on the long-term was accepted not as obstruction, but as genuine systemic concern.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Synergistic Outcome (P1):</head><p>The resulting agreement integrated both logics. The union accepted technology adoption (Management's interest) in exchange for co-managing a continuous worker re-training fund that guaranteed job continuity (Union's interest). This surpassed a simple compromise by generating value based on harnessing the differences. The establishment of a joint "Cultural Committee" served as a formal Feedback Mechanism (P2) to ensure ongoing alignment.</p><p>The success here was driven by cultural awareness, confirming that recognizing the distinct subcultures (even within the same nation) transforms a zero-sum contest into a process of coevolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Implications for Theory and Practice</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.">Theoretical Implications</head><p>The MSA establishes a path for Multilevel Analysis in organizational research:</p><p>1. Shift in Unit of Analysis: MSA shifts the primary unit of analysis in negotiation and conflict research from the individual actor or the national culture to the interacting subcultural system.</p><p>2. Dynamics of Culture: It moves cross-cultural theory toward a process-based, dynamic model, reframing culture as self-organizing meaning (following Luhmann, 1995) rather than static traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Hofstede, 2001)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">New Negotiation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Future Research Directions</head><p>The formalization of the MSA model invites several key empirical research directions:</p><p>1. Operationalization and Validation: Developing quantitative instruments to measure "Cultural Alignment" and "Relational Legitimacy" within organizationally diverse groups for P1 and P4 <ref type="bibr">(Mannix &amp; Neale, 1993)</ref>.</p><p>2. Network Modeling: Use network modeling to map the Cultural Interfaces within negotiation teams <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Hinds &amp; Mortensen, 2005)</ref> and examine how stereotypes and cultural knowledge spread through internal social networks. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Longitudinal</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">Conclusion</head><p>The Multicultural Systems Approach (MSA) provides the essential meta-framework for understanding complex interactions within diverse organizational contexts. By recognizing that organizations are defined by their multicultural systems of meaning, and that negotiation is an opportunity for those systems to learn and co-evolve, MSA moves scholarship beyond static comparisons. Its value lies not in offering simple prescriptions, but in illuminating the systemic mechanisms-cultural alignment, adaptive communication, and feedback learning-that transform the friction of difference into sustainable synergistic outcomes. The MSA invites researchers and practitioners alike to embrace cultural not as a challenge to be managed, but as a dynamic resource to be harnessed for organizational success.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Domain: It defines Adaptive Negotiation as a theoretical category, contrasting with the traditional integrative/distributive dichotomy, focusing instead on the cultural capacity for synergistic value creation.</figDesc><table><row><cell>7.2. Practical Implications</cell></row><row><cell>1. Redesigning Negotiation Preparation: MSA mandates that pre-negotiation activities</cell></row><row><cell>include Cultural Diagnostics to map the communication contexts, hierarchy</cell></row><row><cell>assumptions (Power Distance), and temporal orientations of all subcultural groups</cell></row><row><cell>involved.</cell></row><row><cell>2. Cultural Integration Leadership: Leadership is redefined as the systemic function of a</cell></row><row><cell>cultural integrator, whose primary task is to maintain the cultural alignment of the</cell></row><row><cell>system (P3).</cell></row><row><cell>3. CQ Training: It justifies the critical importance of training in Cultural Intelligence (CQ)</cell></row><row><cell>for negotiators, specifically emphasizing metacognitive and behavioral adaptation</cell></row><row><cell>allowing negotiators to consciously avoid schematic overcompensation.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Case Studies: Conducting comparative case studies of company-union negotiations to analyze how the presence of explicit Feedback Mechanisms (P2) sustains cultural adaptation over time. 4. Comparative Analysis: Contrasting negotiation systems in cultures with strong professional subcultures (e.g., healthcare, engineering) with those dominated by national or political culture, to test the boundary conditions of the MSA.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conceptualization of Cultural Intelligence: Definition, Distinctiveness, and Nomological Network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Van Dyne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Cultural Intelligence: Theory, Measurement, and Applications</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sharpe</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Bacharach</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Samuel</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Peter</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Bamberger</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Armonk, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2008. 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="418" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Diversity and the Union: The Effect of Demo-graphic Dissimilarity on Members&apos; Union Attachment</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bertalanffy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">General System Theory: Foundations, Development, Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>George Braziller</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collaborating across cultures: cultural metacognition and affect-based trust in creative collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Y J</forename><surname>Chua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Doucouliagos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Laroche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/irel.12020</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/irel.12020" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Unions and Innovation: New Insights From the Cross-Country Evidence</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="491" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Industrial relations systems (rev</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Dunlop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Harvard Business School Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Earley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cultural Intelligence: Individual Interactions Across Cultures</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Getting to Yes: Negotiating Agreement Without Giving In</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Patton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<pubPlace>Houghton Mifflin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gleick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Chaos: Life Is Non-Linear</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Penguin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Beyond culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>Anchor Books/Doubleday</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Garden City, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding conflict in geographically distributed teams: the moderating effects of shared identity, shared context, and spontaneous communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hinds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mortensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1287/orsc.1050.0122</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organ. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="307" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hofstede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Culture&apos;s consequences</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Beverly Hills, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Culture, leadership, and organizations: The GLOBE study of 62 societies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>House</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<pubPlace>Thousand Oaks, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cultural intelligence and the global economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Joo-Seng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leadership in Action</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intercultural organizational communication: The social organizing of interaction in international encounters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lauring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizations as culture bearing milieux</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Louis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Organizational Symbolism</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pondy</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Frost</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dandridge</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Greenwich, CT</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>JAI Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Luhmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>J. Bednarz &amp; D. Baecker, Trans.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of power, distribution norms and task meeting struc-ture on resource allocation in small group negotiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mannix</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Con-flict Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cultures in organizations: Three perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing human resources: The issue of cultural fit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mendonca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kanungo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management Inquiry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Molina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Más allá del Conflicto: Un enfoque multicultural para las relaciones entre sindicatos y empresas</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Beyond Conflict: A Multicultural Approach to Union-Company Relations</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">National Culture and Union Membership: A Cultural-Cognitive Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Posthuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Relations Industrielles / Industrial Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="529" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Country-of-Origin, Localization, or Dominance Effect? An Empirical Investigation of HRM Practices in Foreign Subsidiaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Markus</forename><forename type="middle">&amp;</forename><surname>Pudelko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anne-Wil</forename><surname>Harzing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">46.535-559.10.1002/hrm.20181</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Resource Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Organizational culture and leadership</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Jossey-Bass</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Riding the waves of culture: Understanding cultural diversity in business</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Trompenaars</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hampden-Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Nicholas Brealey Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Complex knowledge: Studies in organizational epistemology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tsoukas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
