<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
							<email>mmillers@med.umich.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">D R</forename><surname>Higgins</surname></persName>
							<email>phiggins@med.umich.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, FASGE</roleName><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Philips</surname></persName>
							<email>philipsg@med.umich.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Samuel</forename><surname>Tanner</surname></persName>
							<email>tannesam@med.umich.edu-datavisualization</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Gastroenterology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Internal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan Ann Arbor</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Assistant Professor of Medicine Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<address>
									<postCode>48109</postCode>
									<settlement>Reception D Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9F04AE4863FF91503D52337967B9661F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-18T23:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>IBD</term>
					<term>Crohn&apos;s</term>
					<term>LAMS</term>
					<term>dilation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent to participate</head><p>Patients in this study verbally consented to the novel therapeutic and were informed of and consented to having their retrospective information used for research purposes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent for publication</head><p>To the extent reasonable, patient-related information was de-identified and data collection was covered by the IRB. Verbal permission was given and documented in patient used for example endoscopic images.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Strictures are commonly seen in inflammatory bowel diseases (IBD), especially Crohn's disease, with a 10-15% prevalence at diagnosis, increasing to 50% after ten years <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> . Management of strictures is medical, endoscopic, and surgical. Due to characteristics of the stricture including length and refractoriness to medical and endoscopic balloon therapy, many patients will require surgical management of strictures <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> . Post-operative complications, however, are frequently seen in IBD regardless of age, and have been estimated to occur in up to half of patients in some studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> . Thus, optimizing endoscopic management of strictures has been a major focus in IBD care.</p><p>For decades, endoscopic management of strictures has been accomplished primarily via endoscopic ballon dilation (EBD). EBD has a high technical success rate (&gt;90%) and short-term clinical efficacy (&gt;80%), but nearly half of patients have symptom recurrence with frequent need for repeat dilation and future surgery <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> .</p><p>Complications of EBD include perforation and bleeding in approximately 5% of patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> . Endoscopic lumenapposing metal stent (LAMS) placement has been previously explored for primary management of Crohn's strictures, but its utility has been dismissed due to lower efficacy and high rate of complications, especially early distal stent migration (reported &gt;50% in some studies) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> . More recently, endoscopic stricturotomy (ESt) has emerged as an alternative, which utilizes an endoscopic knife to mechanically open the stenotic segment of bowel. ESt is theoretically more durable in alleviating luminal fibrotic narrowing, similar to surgical stricturoplasty. Meta-analysis has shown similar technical success and superior clinical success compared with EBD <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> . While rates of perforation are like EBD, an ongoing challenge has been bleeding, complicating at least 10% of ESt in a meta-analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> .</p><p>Given the prior reported success in using self-expanding metal stents for treatment of bleeding after use of endoscopic cutting tools <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> , we were interested in technical and clinical success as well as complication rates when LAMS are used after ESt. We hypothesize that placement of LAMS may serve to tamponade the site of stricturotomy to prevent delayed bleeding complications and help prevent re-stenosis during the healing process post-ESt. We aimed to evaluate the feasibility of managing IBD-related strictures with a dual modality of endoscopic stricturotomy and LAMS placement, a so-called "cut and cover" technique.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Population</head><p>This is a retrospective study of adults (≥18 years) seen at a single academic tertiary referral center (Michigan Medicine). We identified all patients with history of inflammatory bowel disease and endoluminal strictures who underwent endoscopic stricturotomy with subsequent LAMS placement from July 1, 2023 through June 30, 2024.</p><p>The Institutional Review Board of the University of Michigan approved this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Collection</head><p>All data was collected retrospectively from a prospectively collected endoscopy database. Baseline characteristics included patient demographics, previous therapy (e.g., endoscopic balloon dilation), and specific IBD treatment at time of stricturotomy with LAMS placement. Procedure-related data included the type of stricture (anastomotic or non-anastomotic), location of the stricture, stricture length and diameter, number of incisions made, and diameter of LAMS used. All procedure-related adverse events were recorded and evaluated. Follow-up data included duration of follow-up, treatment outcomes (i. e. stricture improvement, resolution, recurrence), and need for additional interventions. We used the CARE checklist when writing our report <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definitions</head><p>Immediate technical success was defined as conversion of a non-traversable stricture (by single channel therapeutic gastroscope) to a traversable stricture after stricturotomy and LAMS placement. Long-term technical success was defined by a traversable stricture ≥3 months after stent removal. Short-term clinical success was defined as improvement or resolution of obstructive symptoms including postprandial fullness, bloating and/or hospitalizations at initial follow-up clinic visit or endoscopy for stent removal. Short-term follow-up was the stent indwell time (eg, the time between stent deployment and follow-up endoscopy for removal). Long-term follow-up was the time between stent removal and follow-up endoscopy to assess patency (≥3 months after removal).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient Characteristics</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows baseline and procedure characteristics for the total of five patients who underwent stricturotomy with LAMS placement during the study period. All patients had Crohn's disease, with two of five (40%) with prior diagnosis of ulcerative colitis with subsequent Crohn's of the pouch. All patients returned for endoscopic removal of LAMS, with all but one (4/5) returning ≥3 months after LAMS removal to assess luminal traversability. The mean age was 49 years (range 33 to 68). Two of five patients (40%) were male. Two of five (40%) had anastomotic strictures after ileocolonic resection, two of five (40%) had strictures within an ileal pouch anastomosis, and one (20%) was surgery naïve with stricturing at the ileocecal valve. Two of five (40%) had previous EBD to attempt dilation of their strictures. All strictures were less than 2 cm. One of five (20%) patients was actively using tobacco at the time of the intervention.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Endoscopic Technique</head><p>In all cases, a therapeutic gastroscope (GIF-1TH190; Olympus America, Center Valley, PA) was used to perform the stricturotomy and subsequent LAMS stent placement (AXIOS; Boston Scientific Corp., Marlborough, Massachusetts, USA). Fluoroscopy was not used in any case. The gastroscope was advanced and the stricture(s) were assessed and dimensions measured. If the target stenosis walls were less distinct, the endoscopic ultrasound 20 mHz miniature probe (UM-3R-3; Olympus America, Center Valley, PA) was advanced through the endoscopic channel to estimate the depth of the electrosurgical incision (ESi). In three of five patients, this added modality was utilized to safely optimize the depth of the electrosurgical incision. The ESi was performed at preset sphincterotomy settings (Endocut I mode; effect 2, duration 3, interval 2) with an IT-2 endoscopy knife (Olympus America, Center Valley, PA) in 2 or 3 quadrants at the discretion of the endoscopist based on the endoscopic appearance. After the ESi the endoscope was advanced across the stenosis to test patency. After stricturotomy, a 15 mm (diameter) by 10 mm (length) or 20 mm by 10 mm stent was advanced freehand through the stricture and the stent was deployed at the discretion of the endoscopist.</p><p>Intraprocedural balloon dilation occurred after stent placement in two of five patients at the discretion of the endoscopist. Patients were instructed to follow a modified "stent diet" while the stent was in place (handout on 'Easy to Chew and Swallow Diet (IDDSI 7EC)' created by University of Virginia Health System) <ref type="bibr">10</ref> . All patients had a stent indwell time of at least 36 days (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, mean 64.6 days [range 36-99]), with removal subject to scheduling and at the discretion of the patient. A follow up endoscopy was performed at least 3 months after stent extraction (4/5 patients completed; mean 170 days [range 97-239] post stent removal) and 6-9 months after the index stricturotomy. Example endoscopic images are provided in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Technical Success</head><p>Six stents were placed in five patients (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Stricturotomy was performed in all patients, with most (3/5) patients undergoing ESi in three quadrants. Only one of five patients required the larger diameter 20 mm by 10 mm LAMS placed. Five of five (100%) patients had endoscopies with immediate technical success. There was no evidence of intraprocedural or post-procedural bleeding or perforation in any patient. While stent migration was common by the time of follow-up endoscopy for stent removal (60% of patients), this was not associated with any complications or need for emergent endoscopy, and all stents were removed at a scheduled follow-up endoscopy. At long-term follow-up endoscopy (completed at a mean of 5.6 months poststricturotomy [Table <ref type="table">2</ref>]), long-term technical success (traversability) was reported in all patients who returned for follow-up.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Success</head><p>Immediately post-procedure, one out of five (20%) patients was hospitalized post-procedure for undefined abdominal pain. There was no evidence of perforation, bleeding, stent migration, or other complication with a one-night observation stay and imaging. Otherwise, there were no adverse events that required surgery or endoscopic reintervention. All patients reported symptomatic improvement at short-term follow-up despite frequent stent migration. Among the five patients, they had cumulatively undergone seven endoscopic procedures in the prior year to treat or investigate obstructive symptoms; none required endoscopic treatment for obstructive symptoms in the year following ESt and LAMS placement (swimmer plot, Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>Among five patients undergoing endoscopic stricturotomy with subsequent LAMS placement, the procedure was technically and clinically successful in all patients. To our knowledge, this is the first study to examine the use of LAMS post-stricturotomy in a series of patients and demonstrate longer term outcomes. Previous studies have examined the use of LAMS for treatment of stricturing in Crohn's disease. In one study <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> , stent migration was reported in 80% of patients with only one of ten patients returning for scheduled endoscopic extraction and others requiring sooner re-intervention or treatment for complications. Despite stent migration in 60% of patients at the time of follow-up endoscopy in our study group, there were no patients who required repeat endoscopy at sooner than 1 month due to stent intolerance, bleeding, or other issues. By performing stricturotomy first, LAMS placement may be safer and more effective in the treatment of Crohn's strictures.</p><p>The patients evaluated in our study were successfully treated with varying states of disease activity and medical therapy. All patients were on advanced IBD therapies at the time of the procedure, with one patient who benefited by way of reduction of obstructive symptoms despite active disease at long-term follow-up endoscopy. Patients with severe ulceration at the site of stricture could not be treated in all quadrants with stricturotomy. Further study is needed to determine if the efficacy of ESt is reduced by decreased number of incisions. Strictures &gt;4 cm usually require surgery <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> , but the strictures managed in our study were all short (&lt;2 cm); thus, the feasibility of managing longer strictures with this technique requires further evaluation and longer LAMS. Patients in our study experienced no complications aside from one patient briefly hospitalized for post-procedural pain, but this did not require stent removal or re-intervention. Notably, previous studies demonstrated a 10% bleeding rate when stricturotomy was performed alone <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> ; however there were no bleedingrelated complications in our small cohort.</p><p>Our study provides a novel approach to address refractory strictures in the IBD population by combining stricturotomy with luminal stenting. While stricturotomy has demonstrated greater effectiveness than balloon dilation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> , it has been associated with significant complications. This pilot study demonstrates that endoscopists can utilize a tandem approach of stricturotomy followed by LAMS stenting to address the luminal stricture with a sustained response endoscopically and clinically while averting significant immediate procedural complications. Interestingly, there was a 60% migration rate when the stents were used in tandem. It is unknown as to the optimal duration of stent indwell time since all patients with stent migration had it noted incidentally at the follow up endoscopy for stent extraction. It is also unknown if stricturotomy increases the risk of stent migration; however, in our series there was no clear association between the number of incisions and stent migration. Of note, the smaller 15 mm LAMS stent was chosen in most cases, but it is possible that opting for a larger diameter stent, if the proximal small bowel can accommodate it, may reduce the likelihood of stent migration. While our cohort was too small to fully explore this, the one patient with larger 20 mm stent deployed did not experience stent migration. Overall, our stent migration rate was similar to previous studies but associated with no need for urgent or emergent repeat endoscopy. A second novel concept that was explored in this pilot study was the utilization of the endoscopic miniature ultrasound probe to estimate the safe depth of the ESi. This added modality conceptually provided a more objective assessment and safe stricturotomy.</p><p>Limitations of our study include the small sample size and the lack of delineation in the type of stricture (anastomotic vs non-anastomotic). One clear limitation with this endoscopic technique is the need for a therapeutic gastroscope (Olympus GIF-1T was utilized) for LAMS stent placement. For patients with prior surgical resection, reaching the site of small bowel stricture is not a major concern, but in patients with native anatomy and small bowel stricturing, reaching the site of stricture may not be feasible. However, this is the first pilot study to demonstrate the technical feasibility of this approach and provide prolonged clinical follow-up data.</p><p>In summary, in a retrospective study of five patients with IBD strictures treated with a dual modal treatment of ESt with LAMS placement, the procedure did not result in any complications of bleeding or perforation and was technically and clinically successful. The case series demonstrates that this is a feasible endoscopic approach but will need more rigorous evaluation in multiple centers and larger sample sizes.  #11d The primary "take-away" lessons from this case report.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>8-9</head><p>Patient perspective #12 The patient can share their perspective on their case N/A, patient reported outcomes not included</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Informed consent</head><p>#13 The patient should give informed consent. 5</p><p>Notes:</p><p>• 10c: 7, Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> The CARE checklist is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY-NC. This checklist was completed on 26. June 2025 using https://www.goodreports.org/, a tool made by the EQUATOR Network in collaboration with</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Endoscopic images. An example patient is provided, with images A) pre-stricturotomy, B) post-stricturotomy, C) post-stent placement, D) post-stent removal (at first follow-up endoscopy), and at E) patency re-assessment endoscopy.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,72.00,72.00,650.25,103.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="14,72.00,72.00,600.00,240.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="15,0.00,0.00,650.40,103.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="16,0.00,0.00,600.00,240.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Baseline patient and procedural characteristics.</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Dimensions given are inner diameter by length. EBD, endoscopic balloon dilation. IBD, inflammatory bowel disease. ICR, ileocolonic resection. IPAA, ileal pouch anal anastomosis. LAMS, lumen-apposing metal stent. TI, terminal ileum.</figDesc><table><row><cell>#4</cell><cell>Briefly summarize why this case is unique</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>with medical literature references.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Patient</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>information</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">#5a De-identified demographic and other patient</cell><cell>5, Table 1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>information.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">#5b Main concerns and symptoms of the patient.</cell><cell>5, Table 1</cell></row><row><cell>#5c</cell><cell>Medical, family, and psychosocial history</cell><cell>Table 1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>including genetic information.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">#5d Relevant past interventions and their</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>outcomes.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Clinical findings</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>#6</cell><cell>Relevant physical examination (PE) and</cell><cell>Table 1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>other clinical findings.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Timeline</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>#7</cell><cell>Relevant data from this episode of care</cell><cell>Figure 2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>organized as a timeline (figure or table).</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Diagnostic</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>assessment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">#8a Diagnostic methods (PE, laboratory testing,</cell><cell>N/A, patients presented</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>imaging, surveys).</cell><cell>with strictures</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">#8b Diagnostic challenges.</cell><cell>N/A, see above</cell></row><row><cell>#8c</cell><cell>Diagnostic reasoning including differential</cell><cell>N/A, see above</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>diagnosis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">#8d Prognostic characteristics when applicable</cell><cell>Table 1</cell></row><row><cell>Therapeutic</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Intervention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">#9a Types of intervention (pharmacologic,</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>surgical, preventive).</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">#9b Administration of intervention (dosage,</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Reporting checklist for case report or case series.</p><p>Based on the CARE guidelines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Instructions to authors</head><p>Complete this checklist by entering the page numbers from your manuscript where readers will find each of the items listed below.</p><p>Your article may not currently address all the items on the checklist. Please modify your text to include the missing information. If you are certain that an item does not apply, please write "n/a" and provide a short explanation.</p><p>Upload your completed checklist as an extra file when you submit to a journal.</p><p>In your methods section, say that you used the CAREreporting guidelines, and cite them as: </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crohn&apos;s disease complicated by strictures: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rieder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zimmermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Remzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sandborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gut</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1072" to="1084" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-07">2013 Jul</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The burden of surgery and postoperative complications in children with inflammatory bowel disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fehmel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Teague</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mcleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rosenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alex</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatr Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2440" to="2443" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-12">2018 Dec</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Post-operative complications in elderly onset inflammatory bowel disease: a population-based study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sacleux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sarter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fumery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Charpentier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Guillon-Dellac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Coevoet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pariente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Peyrin-Biroulet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gower-Rousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Savoye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">29737553</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aliment Pharmacol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1652" to="1660" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-06">2018 Jun</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic review with metaanalysis: efficacy of balloon-assisted enteroscopy for dilation of small bowel Crohn&apos;s disease strictures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bettenworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bokemeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lopez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">El</forename><surname>Ouali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kurada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bhatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beyna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Halloran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Reeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hosomi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hirai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ohmiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rieder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC8052861</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aliment Pharmacol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1104" to="1116" />
			<date type="published" when="2020-10">2020 Oct</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Safety and efficacy of extractible self-expandable metal stents in the treatment of Crohnʼs disease intestinal strictures: A prospective pilot study: Inflamm Bowel Dis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Attar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Maunoury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vahedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vernier-Massouille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bulois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Colombel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bouhnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-10">2012 Oct</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1849" to="1854" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extractible selfexpandable metal stent in the treatment of Crohn&apos;s disease anastomotic strictures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Branche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Attar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vernier-Massouille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bulois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Colombel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bouhnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Maunoury</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endoscopy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">S 02</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="E326" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-09-25">2012 Sep 25</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficacy and Safety of Endoscopic Stricturotomy in Inflammatory Bowel Disease-Related Strictures: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jaber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Numan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ayyad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abuelazm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Imran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Albarakat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aboutaleb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Alsakarneh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bilal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dig Dis Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4152" to="4166" />
			<date type="published" when="2024-11">2024 Nov</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporary self-expandable metal stent placement for treatment of post-sphincterotomy bleeding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Binmoeller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastrointest Endosc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1274" to="1278" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-12">2010 Dec</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CARE guidelines: consensus-based clinical case reporting guideline development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gagnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kienle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">24266334</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Headache</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1541" to="1547" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
