<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">How ‘Critically Open-Minded’ Are We? An Australian Perspective Through the World Values Survey</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Springer Science and Business Media LLC</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-03-17">17 March 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A Hamed</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
							<email>hamed.hosseini@newcastle.edu.au</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-8674-4569</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Senior Lecturer in Sociology and Anthropology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Newcastle</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2308</postCode>
									<settlement>Callaghan</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country>Australia, Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Saha</surname></persName>
							<email>lawrence.saha@anu.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Professor of Sociology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>ACT 0200</postCode>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">How ‘Critically Open-Minded’ Are We? An Australian Perspective Through the World Values Survey</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Social Indicators Research</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Soc Indic Res</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0303-8300</idno>
						<idno type="eISSN">1573-0921</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1211" to="1236"/>
							<date type="published" when="2017-03-17">17 March 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">50494ED953F50E66C2D2483B29376971</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11205-017-1608-2</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted: 9 March 2017 /</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Critical open-mindedness</term>
					<term>Socio-cognitive open-mindedness</term>
					<term>Integrative social index</term>
					<term>World Values Survey</term>
					<term>Australia How &apos;Critically Open-Minded&apos; Are We? An Australian… 1213</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This article introduces 'critical open-mindedness' as a new sociological construct, which can be employed particularly in the studies of social attitudes and attitude change, social values, social identities, cross-cultural relations and social discrimination. By drawing on the data collected through the 2005 World Values Survey in Australia, we have operationalized the construct into an integrative social index, called 'critical openmindedness index' consisting of five dimensional composite indicators (CIs; i.e. the social, political, cultural, economic, and environmental). We have adopted an integrative approach to constructing these composite indicators in which we pragmatically select and incorporate a variety of techniques with the purpose of maximizing the validity of the end results. The findings with respect to Australians' critical open-mindedness, both in general and in reference to its five dimensions are discussed. We have also developed and examined a social psychological index of 'socio-cognitive open-mindedness' inspired by a number of commonly used international scales and by drawing on the same dataset. We have shown that these two types of open-mindedness are qualitatively different. Our analysis does not support the idea that individuals' social psychological open-mindedness determines their critical open-mindedness. It is rather the opposite which is the case.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Australian society is known for its strong and official endorsement of multiculturalism as both its core value system and as a guiding general policy framework. As a modern society historically formed by immigration, Australia has become more accommodative and open to a broad range of cultural norms and social traditions. Despite the relatively successful shifts to a more culturally inclusive organization of diverse social relations <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Collins 2013)</ref>, racism, sexism, and negative attitudes towards refugees and ethnic minorities not only persist but also continue to challenge the social cohesion in the country <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Poynting and Mason 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Markus 2015)</ref>. The Australian economy and politics have also been significantly reshaped under the influence of corporate globalization forces. Economic globalization, the escalation of population movements of non-Western background into Australia in recent decades, as well as the proliferation of new communication technologies are, at least in theory, expected to enhance people's cultural openness and cosmopolitanism. Despite all these advancements, a number of studies and polls have observed that many Australians exhibit mixed feelings and uncertain, if not fully apprehensive, views about non-Western cultures and their ability to integrate, adopt or accommodate mainstream Western life-style and values <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(McKay et al. 2012)</ref>. The economic liberalization trend has been associated with growing socio-economic gaps <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Healey 2015)</ref> and thereby has posed serious challenges to Australia's multiculturalism, its universally known commitment to egalitarianism and environmental conservationism <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Walsh 2014)</ref>. The impact of these macro-scale changes on the social attitudes and values of Australian citizens in terms of their openness to the changing context and potential progressive responses needs to be explored. This would require the development of notions and indices that help us measure the level of open/closed-mindedness at a sociological level.</p><p>In terms of theoretical background, despite a long trajectory of attention to the issue of 'open-mindedness' outside the discipline of sociology (see Sect. 2), and the popularity of many subjects of sociological investigation that are directly related to this issue, little effort has been made to develop a uniquely sociological definition based on a social theory of open-mindedness. Therefore, sociology's contribution to this interdisciplinary field of study remains underdeveloped. Against this context, this article introduces 'critical openmindedness' as a new 'sociological construct', in contrast to the social psychological formulations of the concept. The new concept can be employed more broadly than the existing ones in the studies of social attitudes and attitude change, social values, social identities, cross-cultural relations and social discriminations. This article then develops an integrated social index, named the critical open-mindedness index (COI) to measure the construct. The index consists of five dimensional composite indicators for quantitative data analyses. Each dimension represents one of the five major domains of societal life, i.e. the social, the cultural, the political, the economic and the ecological. Using the data from the 2005 World Values Survey in Australia, Australians' critical open-mindedness, both in general and in reference to its five relatively independent dimensions, will be investigated. Exploratory factor analysis (EFA), in combination with a few other techniques, are used in the process of developing the dimensional indicators.</p><p>Multiple ways of validation are employed, including confirmatory factor analysis (CFA), path analysis and group ranking. In our pragmatic approach to constructing our integrative indices, we have considered a higher validity of the end result as our goal. Therefore, our proposed approach is flexible and open to the use of a combination of existing methods and techniques, in order to maximize validity. Moreover, for the first time, in order to make a case for the necessity of a sociological notion of open-mindedness, using the same method and dataset, and by drawing on a thorough review of commonly used social psychological scales, we have developed an index of socio-cognitive openmindedness index (SCOI). Using non-recursive structural equation modelling and CFA we have explored if the two constructs are independent, in terms of both their factor structure and causal relationship. In other words, as part of our research question, we would like to examine whether socio-cognitively open-minded individuals are also sociologically openminded.</p><p>2 Open-Mindedness: Beyond a Social Psychological Concept</p><p>The notion of 'open-mindedness' has been widely discussed in philosophy, education studies, organizational studies, and more particularly in social psychological studies. A variety of definitions of this concept have been developed in each of these disciplines in accordance with the nature of their problems and the objectives of their inquiries. In social psychology, open-mindedness is primarily defined as a mode of critical thinking, openness to new experiences, unbiased information processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Ottati et al. 2015)</ref>, tolerance for ambiguity, receptivity toward and curiosity about unconventional ideas or 'intellectual non-conformity' <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kruglanski and Boyatzi 2012)</ref>, and the ability to handle conflictive situations <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Pilisuk 1963)</ref>. Therefore, open-mindedness is largely reduced to an 'intra-individual ideational quality', i.e. an individual's cognitive performance in different situations as opposed to their performance in relation to other individuals. In contrast, political and social psychological studies of dogmatism-intolerance among different social groups have focused on open/closed-mindedness as an individual's cognitive (pre-)disposition more distinctively defined in relation to out-groups, ideologies and social values. In such studies, open-mindedness is dualistically viewed as a psycho-political phenomenon <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Etchezahar and Brussino 2013)</ref>, where there is a lack of a dogmatic and authoritarian attitude, rather than as a positive quality per se.</p><p>Some of the abovementioned non-sociological efforts to measure open-mindedness deserve a reflexive consideration. To avoid the so-called ideological bias embedded in the F scale developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adorno (1950)</ref> to measure (fascistic) authoritarian personality, <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Rokeach (1960)</ref> argued for the separation of the structure of ideological systems and their content. In this way, he argued, it would be possible to develop a scale totally based on the 'structure of dogmatism' and therefore to be able to measure dogmatism of any type, even of those who advocate tolerance and social equity in intolerant ways. From his point of view, an open-minded person is less dogmatic, less rigid and less concrete in solving problems, and can more easily change an attitude or not be resistant to change <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Rokeach 1951)</ref>. Moreover, such a person avoids pre-judging others, or in other words, he/she is not ''prejudiced'' (towards Jews and African-Americans, laborers, communists, or even towards fascists). According to Rokeach, ''the objects of these prejudices'' may be different but all are nevertheless 'structurally' the same <ref type="bibr">(Rokeach 1951, p. 235)</ref>. He claimed that the ''opposite extremes of the ethnocentrism continuum represent equally pre-judgment systems.'' Therefore, in <ref type="bibr">Rokeach's (1951, p. 236)</ref> terms, closed or open mindedness is an ''underlying cognitive organization of aspects of one's social world.'' Coser, however, criticized Rokeach's approach for ignoring the sociological fact that cognitive abilities are rooted in (and may reflect) social circumstances and experiences. We agree with Coser that Rokeach's Dogmatism (D) scale represented the middle class way of valuing the 'desirability of mixing' and lack of commitment to political causes in the post-WWII era of the so-called ''end of ideology'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bell 1960)</ref>. Therefore despite its selfproclaimed freedom from an ideological bias, the D Scale can still be considered as the product of its own ''Zeitgeist'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Coser 1960)</ref>. Moreover, as acknowledged by <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Rokeach (1960)</ref> himself, what the D scale measures ''can hardly be the relative openness of mind but rather its relative emptiness'', and thereby it confuses openness with vacuity. We tend to agree with Coser and the anti-individualistic perspectives in social psychology that minds are embedded in a larger world (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Wilson 1995)</ref>. However, this does not mean that we cannot (or should abandon attempts to) construct notions of cognitive open-mindedness based on a more narrowly individuated set of ideational states. Rokeach has been criticized for presenting a weak sociological imagination in his work. He insisted on the importance of personality variables as opposed to social situational ones. Yet, as <ref type="bibr">Francis (1960, p. 314)</ref> argued, ''personality is significant for being very open-minded and closed-minded, but that intermediate people rely on the situation for cues.''</p><p>Open-mindedness as a 'socio-cognitive disposition' seems to be in a dialectical relationship with a 'socially situated open-mindedness', rather than in an either indistinguishable or antithetical relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Hosseini 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Hosseini , 2012))</ref>. It is true that minds are embedded in their social settings, but it is in fact the nature of this embeddedness that needs to be explored. Therefore, instead of buying into the dualism of the micro-cognitive vs. the macro-collective, we prefer to explore the relations between these two levels of open-mindedness, i.e. the non-situated socio-cognitive and the more situated sociological level. The latter will be represented by our new indicator of 'COI' whereas the former will be operationalized by developing the SCOI. In this way, we take an open-minded approach to the existing differences between the two major approaches of measuring open-mindedness. Unlike the case of 'socio-cognitive openness' as a rather universally shared human virtue, the definition and method of operationalizing 'critical open-mindedness' is therefore very dependent on the socio-historical context of the study.</p><p>Our method of developing the open-mindedness indices is based on a theoretically driven selection and interpretation of a group of questions from the World Values Survey questionnaires conducted in Australia. We have also utilized a range of scales from the classical studies <ref type="bibr">(F and D scales)</ref> to later examples (developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Schwartz 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Altemeyer 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Ray 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Haiman 1964)</ref> in this selection process. Therefore, we 'analytically' differentiate between Openness as a socio-cognitive general virtue (by relying on less socially situated questions in the WVS) and critical open-mindedness as an index of the overall societal-attitudinal quality of society and its actors in relation to a number of more concrete and controversial social issues of their own social context; i.e. issues that have preoccupied the minds of Australians in recent years and shaped public discourse and debates.</p><p>3 Defining 'Critical' Open-Mindedness: Toward a New Sociological Framework</p><p>In this section, in order to make a case for the concept of 'critical open-mindedness' (especially its criticality aspect), we would like to address an important challenge from a sociological point of view. Absolute openness to all possible alternative ways of understanding a social issue is both impossible and implausible, as it prevents individuals and groups from reaching conclusions or making decisions. This raises the question of where we should then put boundaries in our definition of open-mindedness? This challenge is central to our theoretical endeavor and it seems to have grasped the attention of social philosophers. Let us start with what these experts develop as a definition of openness. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hare (2004b)</ref> 'open-mindedness', as an intellectual virtue, ''means being critically receptive to alternative possibilities, being willing to think again despite having formed an opinion, and sincerely trying to avoid those conditions and offset those factors which constrain and distort our reflections'' (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Hare 2009</ref>). An open mind of such quality is one that seeks to consider all evidence and arguments before an opinion is formed <ref type="bibr">(Hare 2004a</ref>). However, as <ref type="bibr">Lambie (2014, p. xi)</ref> argues, openness is also about acknowledging ''the fallibility of oneself and others.'' Or in other words, ''it refers to a rare, but undoubtedly real, human capacity that is also seemingly a paradox: the ability both to hold in mind different points of view and 'accept' them, and at the same time rationally criticize and shift between them.'' Open-mindedness is more than merely being non-opinionated or being passively receptive to alternative possibilities in one's social attitudes, values or beliefs. Excessive or passive openness would require the denial of the self and lack of commitment to values or beliefs that play significant roles in our personal and social worlds. A person or a group that lacks the ability to reach a conclusion or at least make decisions at the times when action is required, or a person who lacks a self-identity, commitment to a cause, or orientations, would fail to actively relate the new and the old evidence and to be creative or innovative. Creativity, which is a powerful engine behind change, requires the ability to accommodate between the old and the new experiences, to examine new evidence and develop a position with regard to social or personal issues. It is such an apparently contradictory nature of life itself that requires us to differentiate between what kind of open-mindedness takes form ultimately in real life from an idealistic, passive quality or what Lambie calls the 'anything goes' version of openness <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Lambie 2014</ref>). However, unlike Lambie's notion, as described before, we consider 'critical open-mindedness' as not just a cognitive human capacity, but also a sociological phenomenon. Open/closed mindedness as an attitudinal/behavioural attribute requires the formation of critical positions in response to the changing social environment by individuals and collectives as reflexive social agents.</p><p>Given the above considerations, we define critical open-mindedness as the capacity of social actors to be: (1) socially inclusive in their relationships with marginalized groups and in their perception of their social self (like the way they define citizenship and extend civil rights to different groups); (2) tolerant of others with different identities and cultural backgrounds while avoiding any prejudgment on the bases of the other's collective identity, as well as being critical of 'essentialist' perceptions of outgroups or other beliefs, faiths, cultures, or languages; (3) committed to democratic rights and to be aware of the necessity of the equal distribution of material or economic resources across social groups as an infrastructural precondition for a meaningful democracy; (4) sensitive to socioeconomic injustices and inequalities, to be open to the democratization of the economy, and to be critical of the extreme ideological positions in the politics of economy, such as those of statism and libertarianism; (5) mindful of serious ecological challenges that threaten not only themselves but also more vulnerable communities other than their own, and, to be willing to advocate for, and spend their resources to create, a more ecologically secure and sustainable society for everyone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Critical Open-Mindedness: A New Measure</head><p>This section describes how we have operationalized the new construct of critical openmindedness and the concept of SCOI into composite indices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Basic Indicators</head><p>The above five features of a critically open mind are the bases for the five dimensions of our construct that are relatively independent of one another. These dimensions address the main domains of societal life, namely the social, the cultural, the political, the economic, and the ecological. Each dimension is of course multidimensional itself and therefore requires the use of composite indicators. The integrated COI is composed of these five dimensional indicators (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>    Content courtesy of Springer Nature, terms of use apply. Rights reserved.</p><p>economic equity as the bases of genuine democracy; ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) economic open-mindedness, comprised of the appreciation of more democratic regulations of the economy and more economic justice; and finally ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) environmental open-mindedness which is mainly a general appreciation of environmentalist values, such as caring about nature, giving priority to ecology over economy, and a willingness to support environmentalist causes. While these five dimensions are based on our conceptual framework, the components of each dimension are determined through a factor analysis of each dimension over its basic indicators (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>).</p><p>In order to develop the COI and other composite indicators, we have used the 2005 Australian World Values Survey (WVS) dataset. The survey was conducted by a team of researchers from the Australian National University by mailing a self-administered questionnaire (containing 114 questions/variables) to a randomly selected cohort of respondents. Of 3273 eligible sample members who received the survey, 1421 responded, resulting in a response rate of 43%. A more recent survey was also conducted in 2012. However, we found the 2005 data more inclusive and more relevant to the Australian context than the 2012 version, since the former contained the necessary questions we needed for the operationalization of all five dimensions of COI. Therefore, here we have only used the 2005 WVS, since our goal is to create the open-mindedness indices and test their validity rather than portray a more recent profile of open-mindedness in Australian society.</p><p>As explained before, we also aim to measure the socio-cognitive notion of openmindedness as a social psychological construct and explore its causal relationship with critical open-mindedness as a sociological construct. Except for the Schwartz scale for measuring social values, none of the other well-known scales are used in the WVS. However, we sought to construct this CI by relying on a set of socially de-contextualized </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Constructing Integrative Indices of Open-Mindedness: A Pragmatic Approach</head><p>After a rather inclusive review of existing methods of CI construction relevant to our topic, we formulated an approach that pragmatically incorporates and integrates different techniques used in these methods (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hoskins and Mascherini 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Hlavsa 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Maggino and Zumbo 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Wu and Wang 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Boccuzzo and Gianecchini 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Mazziotta and Pareto 2016)</ref>. A pragmatic approach, in this context, acknowledges that there are different methods of constructing a composite indicator. However, the choice of method is made to facilitate the achievement of the stated goals. Our goal here is to maximize the external and construct validities of the CIs as predicted variables. The approach therefore consists of the following steps:</p><p>Step 1 Data Selection: We first selected a number of basic indicators (survey questions), from the original WVS dataset, which we, in consultation with experts and students, understood to be the most appropriate ones for the conceptual framework developed through a critical review of the literature;</p><p>Step 2 Data Manipulation: We made adjustments for directions (manipulation) through recoding the variables based on the interpretation of the answers to survey questions in terms of their connotations for critical open-mindedness in the Australian context, and then we used SPSS MVA to perform the little's 'missing completely at random' (MCAR) test. The MVA shows that the missing data are randomly distributed across all observations which makes the imputation less necessary. However, MVA also shows a number of variables with more than 5% missing. We estimated that the composite indicators would have higher percentages of missing values up to 20%. This indicates that imputation can slightly improve covariance and decrease the chance of type II error. Therefore, we imputed missing values through an EM (expectation maximization) process. Education is one of the definite predictors of socio-cognitive and critical openmindedness. We used ANOVA before and after imputation which showed that imputation through EM improves the measure of association between education and open-mindedness indicators (R 2 ) by almost 2%. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">1</ref>Step 3 Normalization: The values of all the basic indicators were normalized to a range between 0 and 1 through the calculation of what we call here Sscores:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">S i ¼ x i Àmin ð Þ = maxÀmin ð Þ</formula><p>, where x represents the basic indicator and i represents case (respondent) numbers; min and max are the mimimum and maximum values of variable x respectively.</p><p>Step 4 Complementary Factor Analysis: Factor analyses of sets of variables selected theory-wise to construct each COI's dimensional indicator were conducted, and only those variables with loadings above 0.50 were kept (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>). Overall, the COI is based on 31 basic indictors. The factor analyses helped us to determine the underlying components (sub-dimensions) for each dimensional indicator and to determine their weights (see Step 5). In order to construct the SCOI, however, due to the limited number of available basic indicators in the WVS, we only used EFA over a small number of variables relevant to our conceptual definition or what is generally defined as open-mindedness in the socialpolitical psychology literature (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>). Each principal component with an eigenvalue above 1.0 indicates the existence of an underlying dimension. This inspired the naming of dimensions which corresponds to general understandings of openmindedness as a social psychological phenomenon. The four dimensions found through this analysis are: (1) general trust, (2) anti-authoritarianism, including Schwartz' anticonformity orientation, and the preference of freedom over social order and security, (3) anti-elitism, and (4) the opposite of Schwartz' value of conservation, traditionalism and fatalism.</p><p>Step 5 Aggregation and Weighting: Since the number of basic indicators for constructing SCOI based on the WVS is limited, we had to follow a slightly different path for constructing SCOI compared to COI: 5.1. To construct the dimensional variables of SCOI, the basic variables loaded on each component (dimension) of the construct through EFA were aggregated by computing simple arithmetic means of those variables. In the next step, however, in order to aggregate these dimensional variables further into the integrative indicator of SCOI, we took a data-driven approach by performing an EFA (with a varimax rotation method) of the four dimensions to determine the weights. Two main components were found with a cumulative share of variance above 50% (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">3</ref>). Weights in this method are the product of the rotated component matrix (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">4</ref>) in absolute values by the matrix of ''the share of variance explained by selected components'' (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Hlavsa 2010)</ref>. wj ¼ X S s r js :var s w j is the weight of the dimensional variable, |r js | is the absolute value of the correlation coefficient from the rotated component matrix, j = 1, …, n (n = 4) represents the dimensional variable and s = 1, 2 represents selected components (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">3</ref> for each component's share of explained variance, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">4</ref> for correlations between components and the dimensional indicators, and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">7</ref> for the calculated weights).</p><p>Finally, socio-cognitive openness: SCOI ¼ P n j wj:DSCOIj P n j w j</p><p>; (D SCOI j is the dimensional indicator of SCOI, see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">4</ref>). 5.2. In order to construct a COI, instead of simple arithmetic averages, we used EFA from the outset to determine the weights for each basic variable comprising each dimensional indicator, and then again another EFA to determine the weights for each dimensional indicator (see Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">5</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_7">6</ref>).  Here, j = 1, …, n (n = 5) indicates the number of dimensional indictors for COI and w j represents the weight for each dimensional indicator computed through the above EFA process. However, we note that, alternatively, component/factor variables can be used instead of original variables to compose the CI, while being weighted based on their associated percentage of variance. However, the decision needs to be made as to what method should be adopted depending on the highest external validity of the CI resulting from the use of each method. In the case of our data, the aggregation method led to a more robust result.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">DI COI ¼ P s i¼1 w i Ã S i = P w i ð Þ;</formula><p>The dimensional indicators with lower weights, due to their limited variance, can be concaved. This needs to be decided upon after considering the consequences for the (external) validity of the final CI. Some authors suggest formulas like this: concaved S i ¼ S i À0:2 exp À2: S i ð Þ then weights can be re-estimated <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Luzzati and Gucciardi 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Step 6 Disaggregation and Cross-Dimensional Discrepancy: Here the aim is to develop a complementary variable to the COI. The COI is an integrated social index, meaning it is a composite of composite indicators. Therefore, like any other composite index, it is created to acknowledge the multidimensionality of social reality. Recognizing the different dimensions of a social phenomenon is essential as it helps us to address its complexity. However, there seems to be a paradox in this process as we basically start by differentiating between dimensions, normally based on sophisticated conceptual arguments, and then we end up with aggregating them all back into one totality or measure. Aggregation can be better justified when dimensions are of one nature (or in a geometrical sense, the vectors are within the same plane) but this is not often the case. This weakness can be addressed by: (1) describing the results, in a comparative manner, in terms of the aggregated indicator versus its dimensions at the same time and exploring their predictors separately; and/or (2) developing a complementary index that measures the level of discrepancy across dimensions. Such a measure can be used to penalize the cases/respondents with higher levels of inconsistency if especially the variation/ discrepancy across dimensions indicates a lower quality of the composite measure, i.e. here, the lack of a comprehensive critical open-mindedness. Those cases which are inconsistent to a greater or lesser degree across the five different realms of openmindedness can be considered less critically open-minded. However, penalization can lead to a reduction in (co-)variances. Therefore, penalization is not always justified unless it helps improve validity. Hence, we suggest that instead of (or in addition to) penalization, an index of discrepancy across dimensions should be developed as a complementary indicator. A composite indicator functions like a measure of central tendency and therefore must be complemented by a measure of dispersion.</p><p>Certainly very few people might be consistent in terms of their level of openness across different realms of open-mindedness; for example, one may be highly open-minded in the cultural realm but not as much in the economic one. We can think of different methods of measuring discrepancy; methods like measuring SD from the mean of scores across dimensional indicators, or SD from the COI's score across the dimensions (since COI is like a measure of central tendency), or deviation from maximum score across dimensions. We have performed all these three methods and found that in our case, the third method provides us with a measure with higher variance and broader range and therefore higher bivariate correlations <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Wu and Wang 2014)</ref> and regression coefficients in our causal modellings (see DIS and DR in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">7</ref>). The discrepancy (DIS) for case i will be the variation or SD from the maximum value across dimensional indicators:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">DIS i ¼ P n j¼1 |S j -Max (S j )|, or alternatively ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi P n j¼1 S j ÀMax S j À Á À Á 2 s</formula><p>S represents the S-scored dimensional indicators, j ¼ 1. . .n indicates the number of dimensional indicators. The discrepancy or penalty rate (DR, conditioned to its positive impact on the validity of CI) is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">DR i = DIS i 2 /(n Â Max DIS ð Þ); n is the number of dimensional indicators, Max DIS ð Þ.</formula><p>is the maximum value of variable DIS <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Mazziotta and Pareto 2016)</ref>; COI pen (COI after the penalization for cross dimensional discrepancy) for case i will be CIpen i = CI i -DR i.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Results</head><p>With respect to our observation, penalization improved the external validity or predictability of our CIs only slightly. However, for the aforementioned reason, the crossdimensional discrepancy rate remains crucial as a complementary measure. Paired samples T tests between every pair of dimensions show that the differences are statistically significant (with max p = 0.008). Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">7</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_10">8</ref> present more details of the open-mindedness composite indicators including the cross-dimensional discrepancy variable.</p><p>Based on the results, Australian society can be described, in general, as a moderately open-minded nation across all the domains. However, Australians in 2005 also appeared to be slightly less open-minded in domains of cross-cultural relations, politics and economy compared to the other two dimensions. On average, Australians score highest (mean = 0.632) in social open-mindedness (by trusting socially different groups, being sympathetic to gender and sexual equities and secularist values). Compared to other dimensions, Australians achieve the lowest score in economic open-mindedness (0.516)which is about valuing social justice and supporting democratic regulation of the economy, as well as in the political dimension (0.532). There have been major assaults on democratic socialist and social democratic values/ideologies by the mainstream politics and media since the rise of neoliberalism in the late 1980s, as well as a general shift from the center left to the center right in Australian politics, which was ironically initiated by the labor party. These have caused mixed feelings about the association of social justice and economic freedom in Australia <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Lambert 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Edwards 2009)</ref>.</p><p>In terms of SCOI, Australian individuals are moderately open-minded, while on average are more indeterminist (less traditionalist) and less anti-authoritarian compared to the other two dimensions (i.e. general trust and anti-elitism). This may indicate that there must be a strong relationship between SCOI and critical open-mindedness (COI), since: (1) the social dimension of COI can be interpreted as the sociological version of indeterminism (by being open to changes to traditions) and (2) the economic and political dimensions of COI can be interpreted as the sociological equivalents of anti-authoritarian personality. Therefore, one may suggest that both types can be integrated into one index. This issue needs to be investigated by further analysis of the data. Moreover, we also need to examine if it is the SCOI that translates into, or influences, the sociological open-mindedness or the opposite. We recommend the use of a non-recursive path analysis and CFA to address these concerns (see Sect. 7).   <ref type="bibr">(r &amp; 0.47)</ref>. All the correlations between the COI dimensions are statistically significant but not strong. The strongest is between the social and cultural dimensions and the weakest is between the social and political. Together with the fact that Australians are less open-minded in the economic and political realms compared to the socio-cultural and ecological domains, this may indicate a limitation on the society's capability to recognize the interdependence between the material and postmaterial aspects of social life.</p><p>The correlations between SCOI and its dimensions are quite close (between 0.55 and 0.60). The correlations between the dimensions of SCOI are weak, and in the case of the relation between anti-elitism and indeterminism it is statistically insignificant. The correlation between the sociological construct of critical open-mindedness and the social psychological construct of socio-cognitive openness is rather moderate (r &amp; 0.45). Critical open-mindedness is associated with the anti-authoritarian dimension of socio-cognitive openness more strongly (r &amp; 0.43) than with other dimensions. This confirms the established tendency in the literature to associate authoritarianism with closed-mindedness. The direction of causal influence however needs to be explored through a non-recursive structural equation model.</p><p>In terms of correlations between the dimensional variables of COI and of SCOI, both the political and economic open-mindedness show insignificant and/or very weak relations with SCOI and its dimensions. Stronger correlations happen to be between the social and cultural dimensions of COI, on the one hand, and general trust and anti-authoritarian dimensions of SCOI on the other hand. In general, the political and economic dimensions of COI show more independence from the cultural, the social and the environmental dimensions both in terms of internal relations and of relations with socio-cognitive openness. This is also confirmed through a CFA (see Sect. 6.3, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3</ref>). Moreover, the cross-dimensional discrepancy of COI (i.e. DIS) has a negative and statistically significant correlation with COI. This shows that the less a person is critically open-minded, the more he or she fails to consistently translate his/her openness across the five domains of life. The highest negative correlation is between DIS and economic open-mindedness, highlighting the autonomy of this dimension compared to others and its stronger impact on creating more consistency across the five domains. Those who are less economically open-minded tend to be more inconsistent across the five major realms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Validity of COI and SCOI</head><p>In this section, we will discuss the validity of the composite indicators of openmindedness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Concurrent Validity</head><p>To establish concurrent validity we employ 'political party preference' as a criterion on which individuals, in the Australian context, are known to differ, and that is relevant to our notions of open-mindedness <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bryman 2012)</ref>. The major political parties in 2005 Australia were the Liberal Party of Australia, the Australian Labor Party, The National Party of Australia (The Nationals), the Australian Greens, and the Australian Democrats. Liberals and Nationals have formed a rather stable coalition for many years as they both are ideologically conservative. The Liberal party traditionally represents the interests of the business class and therefore is more economically conservative, whereas the Nationals traditionally represent the regional/rural Australia and are more socially conservative. The Labor party in Australia traditionally (and still in theory) represents the interests of working class, although it has practically moved to the right of center, in terms of economic policies, while maintaining its liberal social values. The Australian Democrats were active only for a few decades until 2015 when their party was deregistered. Representing the values of the urban middle classes, they adopted social liberal values, opposed economic rationalism and advocated for sustainability and direct democracy.</p><p>The Greens are further to the left (though not the far left) of the political spectrum among the major parties. They have adopted environmentalist and social democratic values, are opposed to neoliberal or conservative economic policies, and advocate for more social justice compared to the Australian Labor Party. Therefore, the major parties (and expectedly their supporters) can be sorted from the left to the right of the political spectrum, by almost anyone with a minimum knowledge of Australian politics: Greens, Democrats, Labor, Liberals and Nationals. Critical open-mindedness as defined here clearly corresponds with these criteria (political ideologies) very clearly; i.e. the highest open-mindedness should be shown by Greens' supporters and the lowest by the supporters of the coalition. Table <ref type="table">9</ref> shows the results of ranking of the supporters of these parities in terms of COI which clearly matches our expectation. The ranking is done by using Oneway ANOVA based on pairwise differences which turned out to be statically significant at p \ 0.000 except for Labor versus Democrats, and Nationals versus Liberals (the assumption of the homogeneity of variances across groups is satisfied). Therefore, COI can be used to predict election behavior. The rankings in terms of the dimensional indicators of COI are also consistent across the groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">External Validity</head><p>External validity is about the generalizability of findings to the broader population. It is therefore dependent on the adequacy and the heterogeneity of the sampling. KMO measures calculated through EFA in the process of constructing COI and SCOI are higher than the required minimum 0.60 (see Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>) and Bartlett's test of Sphericity rejects the null hypothesis endorsing the irreducibility of dimensions. This indicates the adequacy of sampling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Construct (Convergent and Discriminant) Validity</head><p>Construct validity is about the operationalization process. ''Construct validity refers to the degree to which inferences can legitimately be made from the theoretical constructs on which operationalizations within the study are based'' <ref type="bibr">(Mathison 2005, p. 82)</ref>. To establish this validity, we have taken a multi-operationalist approach by: (1) comparing the results of a Two-way ANOVA of COI on education and gender with the results of a Two-way MANOVA of the COI's dimensions on education and gender; and (2) performing a CFA. The latter will help us to examine the fitness of our conceptual model <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Dickes and Valentova 2012)</ref>   MANOVA creates a linear combination of dependent variables (i.e. here five dimensional indicators of COI) which can be considered as an alternative operationalization method and be compared with the results of an ANOVA analysis of the COI over gender and educational groups. The Two-way ANOVA results reveals that the assumption of homogeneity of variances across gender and educational groups is satisfied (p = 0.268) whereas according to Two-way MANOVA of dimensional indicators, this assumption is not satisfied (p = 0.000). Therefore, our method of operationalization proves to be more satisfactory compared to the alternative linear combination of dimensions in MANOVA. Moreover, ANOVA shows a stronger effect of gender and education on critical openmindedness (with partial eta squared numbers of 1.7 and 12.2%, respectively, at p \ 0.001). Women are slightly more critically open-minded compared to men. However, there is no interaction between gender and education, meaning that education increases critical open-mindedness but the gap between men and women does not close significantly (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>). In contrast, MANOVA reveals a very low level of impact for education (partial eta squared of only 3.9%) for the linear combination of dimensions which appears to be substantially less realistic. The same validation story is the case with the SCOI we constructed here compared to the linear combination of its four dimensions through MANOVA.</p><p>Moreover, the outcomes of the CFA (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3</ref>) reveal that the model closely corroborates the conceptual structure proposed by theory. The model-fit indices provide us with evidence that our model based on the separation of the social psychological (SCOI) from the sociological form of open-mindedness (COI) is acceptable: CMIN/DF is 2.874 7 The Structural Independence of the Socio-Cognitive from the Critical Open-Mindedness Indicators</p><p>As we discussed before, open-mindedness has so far been theorized and empirically investigated in the literature through the development of single indices/scales containing a combination of sociological and social psychological attitude statements. We agree with <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Voas (2014)</ref> that, from a sociological point of view, social attitudes as more socially oriented ''prescriptive and evaluative perspectives'' are qualitatively different from cognitive predispositions (which have been at the center social psychologists attention). Thus, we can argue that it is possible to distinguish between decontextualized personal openmindedness and the more socially contextualized open-mindedness. We have based our conceptual model on such a distinction. Accordingly, we have drawn upon WVS indicators to develop two separate types of open-mindedness. We have also shown that there is a rather moderate and positive correlation between the two. However, to establish our claim, we need to explore the direction of influence and examine the relative autonomy of these indicators in terms of their predictabilities based on a number of important independent variables. Hence, we have performed a non-recursive path analysis (using SPSS AMOS) of COI and SCOI, both as interrelated dependent variables. This will also help us to further validate our new integrative indices. A number of independent variables are selected and constructed for the path analysis. No specific theory is used to justify the selection of these variables since the aim here is not to explain open-mindedness or to test a theory. Rather, we have selected the independent variables after consulting the literature, both the sociological and social psychological studies. Socio-demographic variables of gender, education, ethnicity and social class have been found in the literature as the most influential factors (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Francis 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Ollivier 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">de Regt et al. 2012)</ref>. Moreover, we have conducted a factor analysis of more than 40 questions measuring demographic, subjective, and social features of the population which led to the recognition of 11 composite indictors in total, out of which we have kept four of the strongest predictors which maximized the model fitness (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">10</ref>). These four composite variables are the principle components with initial eigen values above 1. Survey items with factor loadings of less than 0.40 were removed. 'Ethnic social distance' is determined based on an adjusted single basic indictor related to a question about the ethnicity of individuals, with Anglo-Australians scored 1, European background scored 2, and Non-Western background, including Australian indigenous people, scored 3.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> presents the non-recursive structural equation model tested through a path analysis. The model fits the data very well according to the achieved indices of CFI = 0.984 <ref type="bibr">([0.95)</ref>, PCLOSE = 0.859 ([0.05), RMSEA = 0.04 (\0.05) and v 2 is 52.9 (df = 15, p \ 0.001). We have inductively searched for the strongest predictors of the two open-mindedness indices with the aim of achieving the best model fit. As shown in the Figure, the direction of influence is stronger and positive from COI to SCOI (with the direct impact of 0.48, p = 0.000) whereas the impact of SCOI on COI is weaker (-0.06) and statistically insignificant (p = 0.141). Among the strongest predictors of SCOI are the Socio-economic Class Status, Ethnic Distance from Anglo-Australian Background, Education, and Gender (see the list of predictor variables in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">10</ref>). Whereas the most influential factors for COI are Active Sympathy with Political Left, Confidence in Civil Society Organizations, and System Conformism.</p><p>Clearly, the predictor variables explaining each type of open-mindedness are qualitatively different. While the factors influencing socio-cognitive openness are more sociodemographic and therefore more structural-objective, the factors that shape critical openmindedness, except for gender, are political, ideological and experiential, such as involvement in activism and educational achievement (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Vecchione et al. 2015)</ref>. While being female is associated with a slight reduction in socio-cognitive openness (less trustful, more fatalistic and less anti-authoritarian) compared to men, it is associated with more critical openness (i.e. to be more culturally inclusive, environmentally caring, politically democrat etc.). We can therefore conclude that we are dealing here with two qualitatively different types of open-mindedness. More importantly, in contrast to a commonly held belief (among both experts and the public) that people's individual characters influence their social attitudes and behaviors, our model indicates that the opposite may be true. On the one hand, socio-cognitive openness is more determined by the class and the ethnic status of individuals, and to a lesser extent their gender. On the other hand, critical open-mindedness is determined by those factors that involve sociopolitical agency, education, and ideological positions (this supports studies like <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kam 2006)</ref>. While changes in the social status of individuals are less likely to happen over a short period of time, it is the changes in their social attitudes and value systems that are more likely to influence their authoritarianist-elitist personality or their level of general trust and fatalism. Through this study, we have made important contributions to the existing literature. First, we have developed the new construct of 'critical open-mindedness' as a more suitable sociological concept. Open-mindedness is not only an individual's intellectual virtue in accommodating new information that may weaken prior opinions and positions, but also a collective capacity to be socially inclusive in relation to the Other, and to be tolerant of differences and approving of diversity. It requires avoiding essentialist perceptions of out-groups based on gender, sexual orientation, class, race, ethnicity, and ideology. However, as we have argued, openness cannot be boundlessly or passively open. Such an idealistic openness will be self-contradictory, making it difficult for a person to take positions when needed in a context mired in disparities and inequalities. What defines the contours of open-mindedness is the capacity to be 'critical' of unfairness, injustices and discriminations.</p><p>Second, we developed two integrative social indices to separately measure the 'critical open-mindedness' and 'SCOI' constructs. The indices were developed through a pragmatic approach open to different techniques with the primary aim of maximizing the external and construct validities of the end results, i.e. maximizing the correlations between the CIs and their dimensional indicators <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Wu and Wang 2014)</ref>. A combination of theory and quantitative analyses of the data (from the 2005 WVS) was used to determine the components of each construct. In general, Australians appear to be moderately open-minded in all the five dimensions of COI and in terms of their socio-cognitive qualities as well. SCOI tends to be higher in average (0.626) than the critical form of open-mindedness (0.564; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">7</ref>). Both the critical and socio-cognitive types of openness vary across their dimensions. The respondents are, however, more critically open-minded in the social, cultural and environmental realms than in the political and economic ones.</p><p>Being politically/economically open-minded is not strongly associated with openmindedness in the other realms. This may indicate that the social, cultural, and ecological dimensions are more intimately connected and relevant to the day-to-day lived experiences of individuals, as they negotiate their lives. The political, and economic constructs, in contrast, operate at a more sophisticated realm of cognitive complexity, making it difficult for people to engage. However, as shown in our path analysis, by becoming politically active and adopting the values of the political left, one can develop a more comprehensive open mind.</p><p>Third, we have taken a step forward in addressing the most common concern or criticism around the multidimensional composite indicators by introducing a 'cross-dimensional discrepancy index' to the literature for the first time. The index functions like a measure of dispersion across the dimensions of a CI. We found that with an increase in critical open-mindedness, the inconsistency across its five components will decrease. All the five main realms of social life are interconnected and, ideally speaking, a critically open-minded individual/society is expected to be coherently open-minded in all these areas. Considering the sophistication of economic and political realms, as explained before, it is reasonable to expect that open-minded people in these two areas will show lower levels of cross-dimensional discrepancy. This is confirmed by the findings in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">8</ref>.</p><p>Fourth, we employed multiple methods of validation as a way to test the robustness of the CIs. A variety of techniques are used relevant to every type of validity. Despite the fact that we had to rely on the WVS questions which were not originally devised for measuring open-mindedness, the findings including the conceptual structure of CIs turned out to be reasonably valid.</p><p>And finally, our theoretical model was based on the differentiation between two types of open-mindedness, one operating at a more social psychological level (SCOI), (measuring general trust and tolerance, and skepticism toward traditional and hierarchical social orders) and the other at a more sociologically contextualized level (COI) consisting of attitudes towards concerned social and ecological issues which involve culturally, politically, and economically different others. Although no study has ever conceptually differentiated between the two levels, the related empirical research indicates a positive association between the two. For example, political and religious polarizations are presumed to be exacerbated by dogmatic, closed-minded thinking <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Price et al. 2015)</ref>. The direction of the relation between COI and SCOI is difficult to determine a priori, but worthy of exploration.</p><p>We observed that such a model can also be confirmed ''data-wise'' and the direction of influence is more from the sociological level towards the socio-cognitive level. Social psychological research tends to suggest that it is often the individual's socio-cognitive features such as closed prior impressions or notions that may provide them with ingrained capacity to prejudice and stereotype or even give rise to complex acts of exclusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Kruglanski 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Miklikowska 2012)</ref>. Through a causal model (inductive path analysis), however, we showed that the opposite could be the case. This explored direction is more justified when we realize that the 'cognitive openness' is mostly shaped by pre-existing socio-demographic factors whereas 'critical openness' is mainly determined by collective behaviors, experiences and ideological influences. It is not reasonable to combine these two types of human qualities into one scale since they function differently in terms of their underlying conceptual factor structures, and since they are explained differently in terms of their prior causes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p>6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Terms and Conditions</head><p>Springer Nature journal content, brought to you courtesy of Springer Nature Customer Service Center GmbH ("Springer Nature"). Springer Nature supports a reasonable amount of sharing of research papers by authors, subscribers and authorised users ("Users"), for small-scale personal, non-commercial use provided that all copyright, trade and service marks and other proprietary notices are maintained. By accessing, sharing, receiving or otherwise using the Springer Nature journal content you agree to these terms of use ("Terms"). For these purposes, Springer Nature considers academic use (by researchers and students) to be non-commercial. These Terms are supplementary and will apply in addition to any applicable website terms and conditions, a relevant site licence or a personal subscription. These Terms will prevail over any conflict or ambiguity with regards to the relevant terms, a site licence or a personal subscription (to the extent of the conflict or ambiguity only). For Creative Commons-licensed articles, the terms of the Creative Commons license used will apply. We collect and use personal data to provide access to the Springer Nature journal content. We may also use these personal data internally within ResearchGate and Springer Nature and as agreed share it, in an anonymised way, for purposes of tracking, analysis and reporting. We will not otherwise disclose your personal data outside the ResearchGate or the Springer Nature group of companies unless we have your permission as detailed in the Privacy Policy. While Users may use the Springer Nature journal content for small scale, personal non-commercial use, it is important to note that Users may not: use such content for the purpose of providing other users with access on a regular or large scale basis or as a means to circumvent access control; use such content where to do so would be considered a criminal or statutory offence in any jurisdiction, or gives rise to civil liability, or is otherwise unlawful; falsely or misleadingly imply or suggest endorsement, approval , sponsorship, or association unless explicitly agreed to by Springer Nature in writing; use bots or other automated methods to access the content or redirect messages override any security feature or exclusionary protocol; or share the content in order to create substitute for Springer Nature products or services or a systematic database of Springer Nature journal content.</p><p>In line with the restriction against commercial use, Springer Nature does not permit the creation of a product or service that creates revenue, royalties, rent or income from our content or its inclusion as part of a paid for service or for other commercial gain. Springer Nature journal content cannot be used for inter-library loans and librarians may not upload Springer Nature journal content on a large scale into their, or any other, institutional repository. These terms of use are reviewed regularly and may be amended at any time. Springer Nature is not obligated to publish any information or content on this website and may remove it or features or functionality at our sole discretion, at any time with or without notice. Springer Nature may revoke this licence to you at any time and remove access to any copies of the Springer Nature journal content which have been saved. To the fullest extent permitted by law, Springer Nature makes no warranties, representations or guarantees to Users, either express or implied with respect to the Springer nature journal content and all parties disclaim and waive any implied warranties or warranties imposed by law, including merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose. Please note that these rights do not automatically extend to content, data or other material published by Springer Nature that may be licensed from third parties. If you would like to use or distribute our Springer Nature journal content to a wider audience or on a regular basis or in any other manner not expressly permitted by these Terms, please contact Springer Nature at onlineservice@springernature.com</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 A graphic presentation of the COI conceptual framework</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where DI COI is the dimensional indicator of COI; i = 1,…, s, indicates the number of basic indicators comprising a dimensional COI; w i represents the weight of each of the basic indicators determined through EFA (see Step 5.1); and S represents the normalized (S-scored) basic indicators comprising the dimensional indicator. And then finally:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>which is based on the separation of the socio-cognitive and sociological open-mindedness, whereas the former can show us to what extent the construction of COI has improved the external validity of our measures compared to an alternative linear combination of dimensions by MANOVA.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Table 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Ranking of the Australian political parties in terms of their means, concerning the composite and dimensional open-mindedness variables General party preference (number of supporters)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig.2Two-way ANOVA plot of differences between gender and educational attainment levels in terms of estimated marginal means of COI</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 Confirmatory factor analysis of dimensional indicators. Source: WVS Australia 2005</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>List of basic indicators comprising COI's five dimensional indicators. Source: WVS Australia</figDesc><table><row><cell>Code</cell><cell>Survey questions (after correction of</cell><cell cols="3">Components (determined by an EFA; principle</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>wording for direction)</cell><cell cols="3">components, promax rotation method) a</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">No. Name</cell><cell>Loading</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">1-Dimensional composite indicator: social open-mindedness (KMO = 0.649)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V129 Trusting people of another religion</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Trusting out-groups</cell><cell>0.912</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V130 Trusting people of another nationality</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Trusting out-groups</cell><cell>0.909</cell></row><row><cell>V36</cell><cell>Positive to have people with AIDS in</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Anti-homophobia</cell><cell>0.752</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>neighborhood</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V38</cell><cell>Positive to have homosexuals in</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Anti-homophobia</cell><cell>0.844</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>neighborhood</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V61</cell><cell>Men not always better political leaders</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>Anti-sexism</cell><cell>0.895</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>than women</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V63</cell><cell>Men not always better business executives</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>Anti-sexism</cell><cell>0.901</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>than women</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V202 Homosexuality can be justified</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Anti-homophobia</cell><cell>0.684</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V204 Abortion can be justified</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>Secularism</cell><cell>0.719</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V194 Atheist politicians can be fit for public</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>Secularism</cell><cell>0.635</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>office</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V197 Religious leaders should not influence</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>Secularism</cell><cell>0.583</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>government decisions</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">2-Dimensional composite indicator: cultural open-mindedness (KMO = 0.838)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V35</cell><cell>Positive to have people of a different race</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Inclusive to cultural</cell><cell>0.660</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>in neighborhood</cell><cell></cell><cell>outgroups (inclusiveness)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V37</cell><cell>Positive to have immigrants in</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Inclusive to cultural</cell><cell>0.779</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>neighborhood</cell><cell></cell><cell>outgroups</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V39</cell><cell>Positive to have people of different religion</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Inclusive to cultural</cell><cell>0.715</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>in neighborhood</cell><cell></cell><cell>outgroups</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>V42</cell><cell>Positive to have people of different</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Inclusive to cultural</cell><cell>0.783</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>language in neighborhood</cell><cell></cell><cell>outgroups</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V221 Ethnic diversity enriches life</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Positive about immigrants</cell><cell>0.701</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>and ethnic diversity</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(multi-cultural)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V217 Australian citizenship: no need to have</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>Broad definition of</cell><cell>0.916</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ancestors from Australia</cell><cell></cell><cell>citizenship</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V218 Australian citizenship: no need to born on</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>Broad definition of</cell><cell>0.915</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Australian soil</cell><cell></cell><cell>citizenship</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">V219 Australian citizenship: no need to adopt the</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>Open to asylum seekers</cell><cell>0.718</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>customs of Australia</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q87</cell><cell>Two first statements of a Likert scale</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>Open to asylum seekers</cell><cell>0.774, 0.665</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>measuring attitudes toward asylum</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>seekers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Q87</cell><cell>The last four statements of a Likert scale</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Positive about immigrants</cell><cell>0.660, 0.780,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>measuring attitudes toward immigrants in</cell><cell></cell><cell>and ethnic diversity</cell><cell>0.715, 0.780</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Australia</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>3-Dimensional composite indicator: political open-mindedness (KMO = 0.655) V152 Democracy taxes the rich and subsides the poor 1 Stressing economic equity in democracy 0.819 V155 Government benefits for unemployed in a democracy 1 Stressing economic equity in democracy 0.818 How 'Critically Open-Minded' Are We? An Australian…</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Four dimensions of the socio-cognitive open-mindedness index (SCOI), specified through an EFA (with varimax rotation) of a number of basic variables. Source: WVS Australia 2005</figDesc><table><row><cell>Dimensions a</cell><cell>Question (basic variable)</cell><cell cols="2">Code Component</cell><cell>Loadings</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>no.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1. General trust</cell><cell>Most people can be trusted</cell><cell>V23</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0.756</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Most people would try to be fair to me</cell><cell>V47</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0.688</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Trusting people met for the first time</cell><cell cols="2">V128 1</cell><cell>0.724</cell></row><row><cell>2. Anti-</cell><cell>Giving priority to freedom as the first aim of the</cell><cell>V71</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0.691</cell></row><row><cell>authoritarianism</cell><cell>country over order</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Giving priority to humane society over security</cell><cell>V73</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0.679</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Do not teach children obedience</cell><cell>V21</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0.523</cell></row><row><cell>3. Anti-elitism</cell><cell>Rejecting an undemocratic leader</cell><cell cols="2">V148 3</cell><cell>0.828</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Rejecting technocratic leadership</cell><cell cols="2">V149 3</cell><cell>0.868</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">4. Indeterminism Traditions not always important</cell><cell>V89</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0.684</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Critical of fatalism</cell><cell cols="2">V122 4</cell><cell>0.517</cell></row></table><note><p>a KMO = 0.619 [ 0.5, the overall value of Cronbach's alpha is 0.563</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Selected principal components with a cumulative share of explained variance above 50% for SCOI</figDesc><table><row><cell>Component no.</cell><cell>Initial eigen values</cell><cell cols="2">Rotation sums of squared loadings</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>% of variance</cell><cell>Cumulative %</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>1.373</cell><cell>1.291</cell><cell>Var 1 = 32.283</cell><cell>32.283</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>0.957</cell><cell>1.039</cell><cell>Var 2 = 25.981</cell><cell>58.264</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>0.869</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>0.800</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Rotated component matrix of the dimensional variables of socio-cognitive openness</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Dimensional indicators of socio-cognitive openness (D_SCOI) (r = 1, …, 4); S-scored Components</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(s = 1, 2)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>General trust [(V23 ? V47 ? V128)/3]</cell><cell>0.680</cell><cell>0.171</cell></row><row><cell>Anti-elitism [(V148 ? V149)/2]</cell><cell>0.036</cell><cell>0.921</cell></row><row><cell>Anti-authoritarian [(V71 ? V73 ? V21)/3]</cell><cell>0.525</cell><cell>0.338</cell></row><row><cell>Indeterminist [(V89 ? V122)/2]</cell><cell cols="2">0.743 -0.217</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Selected principal components with a cumulative share of explained variance above 50% for COI</figDesc><table><row><cell>Component no.</cell><cell>Initial eigen values</cell><cell cols="2">Rotation sums of squared loadings</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>% of variance</cell><cell>Cumulative %</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>1.941</cell><cell>1.722</cell><cell>Var 1 = 34.442</cell><cell>34.442</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>0.945</cell><cell>1.165</cell><cell>Var 2 = 23.293</cell><cell>57.735</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>0.812</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>0.751</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Rotated component matrix of the dimensional variables of COI DI COI or dimensional indicators of COI, developed through the first round of EFA, (r = 1, …, 5)</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Components</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(s = 1, 2)</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Descriptive statistics concerning SCOI, COI and dimensional indicators, and cross-dimensional discrepancy</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>Min</cell><cell>Max</cell><cell>Skewness</cell><cell>Weights</cell></row><row><cell>COI</cell><cell>0.564</cell><cell>0.118</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell>0.91</cell><cell>-0.167</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>COI pen</cell><cell>0.491</cell><cell>0.131</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.89</cell><cell>-0.201</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Social openness</cell><cell>0.632</cell><cell>0.186</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.734</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell>Cultural openness</cell><cell>0.557</cell><cell>0.178</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.314</cell><cell>0.23</cell></row><row><cell>Political openness</cell><cell>0.532</cell><cell>0.179</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.285</cell><cell>0.17</cell></row><row><cell>Economic openness</cell><cell>0.516</cell><cell>0.201</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.246</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell>Environmental openness</cell><cell>0.581</cell><cell>0.215</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.200</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell>DIS (discrepancy across dimensions)</cell><cell>0.994</cell><cell>0.445</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>2.72</cell><cell>0.746</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>DR (discrepancy/penalty rate)</cell><cell>0.082</cell><cell>0.074</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.65</cell><cell>2.331</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cognitive openness</cell><cell>0.626</cell><cell>0.149</cell><cell>0.14</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.235</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>General trust</cell><cell>0.622</cell><cell>0.289</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.199</cell><cell>0.21</cell></row><row><cell>Anti-elitism</cell><cell>0.649</cell><cell>0.260</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.452</cell><cell>0.29</cell></row><row><cell>Anti-authoritarian</cell><cell>0.533</cell><cell>0.277</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.052</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell>Indeterminism</cell><cell>0.663</cell><cell>0.211</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>-0.433</cell><cell>0.30</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>presents the Pearson correlations between COI, SCOI, DIS and dimensional indicators. COI has the highest correlation with cultural open-mindedness (r &amp; 0.72) and the lowest with the political dimension</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Graphical output of a non-recursive model examining the causal relations between COI and SCOI with standardized weights/impacts and correlationsThe present research provides new ways of conceptualizing and operationalizing openmindedness at the two different but interrelated social psychological and sociological levels. However, one of the limitations of this study is its dependence on secondary data from the WVS which is not originally designed to measure open-mindedness. Nevertheless, we found an adequate number of indicators to create our indices. The results of this study can help us devise more specialized and contextualized scales, beyond the limitations of WVS, to explore open-mindedness in the most recent social environments.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Socio-economic Class Status</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.24</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>e1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ethnic Social Distance</cell><cell>-.13</cell><cell></cell><cell>.29</cell></row><row><cell>.57</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Socio-Cognitive Open-</cell></row><row><cell>.25</cell><cell>.10</cell><cell>Gender</cell><cell>-.05</cell><cell cols="2">mindedness Index (SCOI)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.03</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>.11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Education Level</cell><cell>.11</cell><cell>-.06</cell><cell>.44</cell></row><row><cell>.19</cell><cell>.33</cell><cell></cell><cell>.18</cell><cell></cell><cell>.41</cell></row><row><cell>.14</cell><cell></cell><cell>Left-wing Activism Factor</cell><cell>.38</cell><cell cols="2">Critical Open-mindedness Index (COI)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>.25</cell><cell></cell><cell>.34</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-.29</cell><cell></cell><cell>Confidence in Civil Society Organization Factor</cell><cell>-.07</cell><cell>e2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>.07</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>System Conformism Factor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Fig. 4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="123" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Content courtesy of Springer Nature, terms of use apply. Rights reserved.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Moreover, Pearson correlations between critical and socio-cognitive open-mindedness were also increased by</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_2"><p>2% due to imputation. The structural equation model used later in the validation process also requires imputation.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Content courtesy of Springer Nature, terms of use apply. Rights reserved.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgements We would like to thank the journal's guest editor and the two anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments and suggestions. We are also grateful to the <rs type="institution">World Values Survey Association</rs> and the <rs type="institution">Australian Data Archive</rs> for making the original data collections available to us.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The authoritarian personality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Adorno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1950">1950</date>
			<publisher>Harper &amp; Row</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Right-wing authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Altemeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<publisher>University of Manitoba Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Winnipeg</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The end of ideology: On the exhaustion of political ideas in the fifties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring young graduates&apos; job quality through a composite indicator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Boccuzzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gianecchini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11205-014-0695-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Indicators Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="478" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bryman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford; New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiculturalism and immigrant integration in Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian Ethnic Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The open and closed mind by Milton Rokeach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Coser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commentary</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="1960-08">1960. August</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relevance of class in shaping authoritarian attitudes: A cross-national perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>De Regt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Smits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mortelmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.rssm.2012.03.001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Social Stratification and Mobility</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Construction, validation and application of the measurement of social cohesion in 47 european countries and regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dickes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Valentova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11205-012-0116-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Indicators Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="827" to="846" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disenfranchised not &apos;deficient&apos;: How the (neoliberal) state disenfranchises young people</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Australian Journal of Social Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychological perspectives in the study of authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Etchezahar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brussino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Alternative Perspectives in the Social Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="495" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Review: The open and closed mind. by Milton Rokeach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2948910</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health and Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personal and social correlates of the &apos;closed mind&apos; among 16 year old adolescents in England</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/0305569970230308</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Educational Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A revised scale for the measurement of open-mindedness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Haiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Speech Monographs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing one&apos;s own open-mindedness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hare</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophy Now</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.criticalthinking.org/pages/open-minded-inquiry/579" />
		<title level="m">Open-minded inquiry: A glossary of key concepts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-05-03">2004b. 03 May 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Socratic open-mindedness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hare</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paideusis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Healey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Income and wealth inequality (issues in society v</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Thirroul</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The Spinney Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">382</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selected approaches of variables weighting in frame of composite indicator analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hlavsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Agris On-line Papers in Economics and Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring active citizenship through the development of a composite indicator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hoskins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mascherini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11205-008-9271-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Indicators Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="488" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activist knowledge: interrogating the ideational landscape of social movements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Interdisciplinary Social Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theorizing social ideations: beyond the divide between humanities and social sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of the Humanities</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Political campaigns and open-minded thinking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="931" to="945" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The psychology of closed mindedness (essays in social psychology)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kruglanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Psychology Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The psychology of closed and open mindedness, rationality, and democracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kruglanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Boyatzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Critical Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Globalization and the erosion of class compromise in contemporary australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lambert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Politics and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">How to be critically open-minded: A psychological and historical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lambie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A non-simplistic approach to composite indicators and rankings: An illustration by comparing the sustainability of the eu countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Luzzati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gucciardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2015.02.018</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecological Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring the quality of life and the construction of social indicators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Maggino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zumbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of social indicators and quality of life research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Land</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Michalos</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sirgy</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht; Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="238" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mapping social cohesion: The scanlon foundation surveys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Markus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
			<publisher>Scanlon Foundation: Caulfield East; Victoria</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Construct validity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Encyclopedia of evaluation</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mathison</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Thousand Oaks, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On a generalized non-compensatory composite index for measuring socio-economic phenomena</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mazziotta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pareto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11205-015-0998-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Indicators Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="983" to="1003" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">It would be okay if they came through the proper channels&apos;: Community perceptions and attitudes toward asylum seekers in Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mckay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kneebone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/Jrs/Fer010</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Refugee Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychological underpinnings of democracy: Empathy, authoritarianism, self-esteem, interpersonal trust, normative identity style, and openness to experience as predictors of support for democratic values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Miklikowska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.paid.2012.04.032</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Individual Differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="608" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intercultural effectiveness, authoritarianism, and ethnic prejudice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nesdale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Robbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Van Oudenhoven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1559-1816.2011.00882.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1173" to="1191" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modes of openness to cultural diversity: humanist, populist, practical, and indifferent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ollivier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.poetic.2008.02.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Poetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When self-perceptions of expertise increase closed-minded cognition: the earned dogmatism effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ottati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sumaktoyo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jesp.2015.08.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anxiety, self-acceptance, and open-mindedness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pilisuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/1097-4679(196310)19:4\387</idno>
		<idno>AID-JCLP2270190402[3.0.CO;2-D</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Clinical Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The new integrationism, the state and islamophobia: Retreat from multiculturalism in Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Poynting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Law Crime and Justice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open-minded cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ottati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167215600528</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1488" to="1504" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Balanced dogmatism scales</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Australian Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">&apos;&apos;Narrow-mindedness&apos;&apos; and personality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rokeach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-6494.1951.tb01524.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="1951">1951</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The open and closed mind: Investigations into the nature of belief systems and personality systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rokeach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
			<publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are there universal aspects in the structure and contents of human values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personal values and political activism: A cross-national study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vecchione</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Caprara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schoen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cieciuch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Silvester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/bjop.12067</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="106" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a sociology of attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Voas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5153/sro.3289</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Research Online</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The marketization of multiculturalism: Neoliberal restructuring and cultural difference in Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01419870.2012.720693</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ethnic and Racial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cartesian psychology and physical minds: Individualism and the sciences of the mind (Cambridge studies in philosophy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel approach to construct a composite indicator by maximizing its sum of squared correlations with sub-indicators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11424-014-3089-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Systems Science and Complexity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="925" to="937" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
