<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Historic narrowing of employment gap post-pandemic, especially for people with cognitive disabilities</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Campaign for Disability Employment</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">CDE</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_5uSMV5K">
					<orgName type="full">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">HHS</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Administration for Community Living</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">ACL</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Expansion of Employment Opportunities Network</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NEON</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_ykACcXJ">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_r9v5Ax7">
					<orgName type="full">U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour Division</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_rw2M2FV">
					<orgName type="full">U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cobo-Lewis</surname></persName>
							<email>alanc@maine.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology and Center for Community Inclusion and Disability Studies</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University Maine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Orono</settlement>
									<region>ME</region>
									<country key="US">U.S.A</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology and Center for Community Inclusion and Disability Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5717 Corbett Hall</addrLine>
									<postCode>04469-5717</postCode>
									<settlement>Orono</settlement>
									<region>ME</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">U.S. Department of Labor&apos;s Wage and Hour Division</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Historic narrowing of employment gap post-pandemic, especially for people with cognitive disabilities</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">414B205281B9EE17A0F9831A18147145</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:56+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Employment</term>
					<term>Intellectual Disability</term>
					<term>Developmental Disabilities</term>
					<term>Sheltered Workshops</term>
					<term>Disabled Persons</term>
					<term>Community Rehabilitation Programs</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>BACKGROUND: People with disabilities are underemployed. This improved recently. Under federal law, employers with 14(c) certificates can pay people with disabilities far below minimum wage, typically in segregated settings (sheltered workshops). Almost everyone in 14(c) employment has an intellectual/developmental disability. Some states have eliminated sheltered workshops, but phase-out is controversial. OBJECTIVE: To examine pre-and post-pandemic trends in employment rates and subminimum wage prevalence among people with disabilities, especially cognitive disabilities, differences among states, and what national and state-by-state data reveal about associations between employment rate and subminimum wage. METHOD: I analyzed 2010-2023 U.S. Census American Community Survey data on employment rate by presence of disability and presence of cognitive disability, 2010-2024 Department of Labor (DOL) data on subminimum wage certificates in Community Rehabilitation Programs (CRPs), and 2015-2024 DOL data on number of CRP workers paid subminimum wage. I assessed trends in employment and subminimum wage prevalence graphically. With linear regressions, I assessed state-by-state patterns in employment of people with cognitive disabilities and subminimum wage prevalence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS:</head><p>Disability employment gap narrowed long-term, especially post-pandemic-moreso for people with cognitive disabilities. Long-term, every state's employment gap for people with cognitive disabilities narrowed while 14(c) enrollment decreased. States with higher subminimum wage prevalence showed much larger drops in such prevalence, but the association between employment rate and subminimum wage prevalence was modest.</p><p>Disability Employment 3 CONCLUSION: Employment improvements parallel nationwide initiatives. Research informing public policy and hiring and retention practices should take advantage of the further post-pandemic improvement, and marketing investments should promote these practices.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Employment Among People with Disabilities Through Economic Shocks</head><p>People with disabilities are employed at far lower rates than people without disabilities.</p><p>During recessions occur, their employment typically declines more sharply, and during recoveries, their employment typically recovers more slowly <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Burkhauser et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Burkhauser &amp; Stapleton, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Fogg et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kaye, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Schur et al., 2023)</ref>. This phenomenon was important enough that it was called out specifically by the National Institute for Disability and Rehabilitation Research (now the National Institute for Disability Independent Living and Innovation Research) in the first long-range plan they issued after the 2008 Great Recession (U.S. Department of Education Office of Special Education and Rehabilitative Services, 2013). Recent analyses, however, have indicated that the covid recession and recovery were different: employment among people with disabilities declined only proportionately when covid hit and recovered faster than among people without disabilities <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Ne'eman &amp; Maestas, 2023)</ref>. Employment opportunities differ by type of disability both in the U.S. and internationally <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Boman et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Pettinicchio &amp; Maroto, 2017)</ref>. Differences persist even when accounting for other variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Boman et al., 2015)</ref>. This sets the stage to examine trends specifically in people with cognitive disabilities, who have traditionally faced deep stigma and substantial barriers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Subminimum Wage Among People with Disabilities</head><p>The Fair Labor Standards <ref type="bibr">Act of 1938</ref><ref type="bibr">(Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938, n.d.)</ref> establishes the federal minimum wage-currently $7.25 per hour-but Section 14(c) of the act authorizes employers to pay subminimum wage to people with disabilities ("individuals…whose earning or productive capacity is impaired by age, physical or mental deficiency, or injury") when employers are issued a certificate by the U.S. Department of Labor. Such an authorization to pay subminimum wage is called a "14(c) certificate" (U.S. Department of Labor <ref type="bibr">Wage and Hour Division, 2025)</ref>. The purpose of subminimum wage under the act is "to prevent curtailment of opportunities for employment".</p><p>People with intellectual disabilities have long faced deep stigma. Attitudes have improved since many state institutions closed that had segregated people with intellectual disabilities <ref type="bibr">(Dell'Armo &amp; Tassé, 2021)</ref>. Nevertheless, even though the initial idea beyond 14 <ref type="bibr">(c)</ref> was that subminimum wage would apply across a wide variety of disability type, including physical disabilities (Employment of Workers with Disabilities Under Section 14(c), 2024), today almost everyone in a 14(c) program has an intellectual/developmental disability (Government Accountability Office, 2023a).</p><p>The Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (WIOA) of 2014 (Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act, 2014) amended the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 to call for maximizing opportunities for subminimum wage earners to achieve competitive integrated employment (CIE) at least at minimum wage. Segregated vocational services reduce the potential for future positive outcomes toward competitive integrated employment, and integrated vocational service models incorporating strategies such as supported and customized employment lead to improved outcomes in economics, quality of life, and mental health <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Taylor et al., 2023)</ref>. Subminimum wage programs have been extremely controversial. Their promoters typically argue that they provide productive work and socialization for people who could not otherwise work. Their detractors typically decry the segregation experienced by people employed at subminimum wage in 14(c) programs and note that people typically work for years in 14(c) without an opportunity to transition to competitive integrated employment (possibly with support) notwithstanding WIOA's expectation of such a goal.</p><p>In one state (Maine) that closed its last sheltered workshop in 2010, employment of people with intellectual disabilities and autism supported by that state's Home and Community Based Services program through Medicaid did not increase for several years (indeed decreased over the time frame analyzed in the study) <ref type="bibr">(Phoenix &amp; Bysshe, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>The Supreme Court has ruled that that unjustified segregation of persons with disabilities constitutes discrimination under the ADA <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Olmstead v. L.C., 1999)</ref>. A federal district court has applied this ruling to sheltered workshops, holding that participation "must be a choice, not a requirement" (Lane v. <ref type="bibr">Kitzhaber, 2012)</ref>. But the Government Accountability Office (GAO) has identified structural and policy barriers preventing people from transitioning from 14(c) programs to competitive integrated employment (Government Accountability Office, 2023a), and the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights has recommended repealing 14(c) <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, 2000)</ref>. However, some groups have opposed repeal. They argue that repeal would hurt people with intellectual/developmental disabilities (Coalition for the Preservation of Employment Choice, 2022; Voice of Reason, 2021). Fifteen states have enacted legislation since 2015 to phase out subminimum wage and sheltered workshops (J. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Christensen, 2024)</ref>. The most recent substantive update to federal regulation of 14(c) programs was issued in 1989, but the U.S. Department of Labor proposed a new rule in December 2024 that would phase out issuance of 14(c) certificates (Employment of Workers with Disabilities Under Section 14(c), 2024).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Research Questions</head><p>In an effort to go beyond case studies of experiences by an individual state, this paper Responses are collected online, by mail, or by a field representative by computer-assisted interviewing (and were previously also collected by telephone). The ACS is the largest household survey that the Census Bureau conducts. It is sent to about 3.5 million addresses each year and includes processes to collect data from individual households (U.S. Census Bureau, 2024) as well as institutional and noninstitutional group quarters <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, 2024</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2025a)</ref>. If a person or household is selected into the sample, responding to the ACS is required by law <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Gamboa, 2002)</ref>. In addition, the census engages in statistical and other methodological efforts to both minimize nonresponse bias and to correct for it <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, 2024)</ref> and annually publishes sample size and other data quality measures <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, n.d.-b)</ref>.</p><p>For households, there are 3-4 modes of data collection, depending on year: mail, personal visit, internet (starting in January 2013), and computer-assisted telephone interview (until September 2017) <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, 2023)</ref>. For group quarters the Census Bureau makes an appointment with a manager, director, administrator, or other contact person for the group quarter, interviews that person to collect information about the group quarter and compile a list of people staying there, and then conducts interviews with a sample of residents randomly selected from that list <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, 2025a)</ref>.</p><p>The ACS data reported in this paper are specific to the civilian noninstitutionalized population of people age 18-64 ("working age"), including both people living in households and people living in noninstitutional group quarters. The category of noninstitutional group quarters includes people in college/university student housing and other noninstitutional facilities including group homes intended for adults, emergency and transitional shelters for people experiencing homelessness, residential treatment centers for adults, workers' group living quarters and job corps centers, and other noninstitutional group quarters <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Gamble et al., 2022)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2">ACS Sample Size</head><p>Because the ACS has procedures to reach both people in households and people in group quarters, the Census Bureau describes sample size separately in terms of number of household units (for people not in group quarters) and in terms of number of "group quarters people" for people in group quarters. For both groups (households and group quarters), the Census Bureau reports number of "final interviews" across all modes of data collection. For households, ACS final interview sample size for the years in the present paper ranged from 1,917,799 household interviews (in 2010) to 2,322,722 household interviews (in 2014) <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, n.d.-b)</ref>.</p><p>For people in group quarters, ACS final interview sample size for the years in the present paper ranged from 119,144 interviews with people in group quarters (in 2021) to 165,116 interviews with people in group quarters (in 2014) <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, n.d.-b)</ref>.</p><p>The Census Bureau does not publish total sample size of persons per se, because the sampling unit of the larger survey is household rather than person. However, a lower bound to the number of noninstitutionalized working-age people in the full ACS sample can be calculated Disability Employment 10 by analyzing the ACS Public Use Microdata Sample (PUMS). Whereas the full ACS has reliable aggregate estimates, the PUMS has redacted person-level information-but the PUMS is only a sub-sample in order to preserve respondent confidentiality. This is why sample sizes calculated from PUMS are only a lower bound on the full ACS sample sizes. To calculate these lower bounds on the sample size, I analyzed PUMS data downloaded from IPUMS <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Ruggles et al., 2025)</ref>. Based on this analysis, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> presents number of noninstitutionalized working-age persons in each annual PUMS sample (total, by whether the person had any disability, and by whether the person had a cognitive disability). It can be seen that, in an annual PUMS sample, the total number of such persons was never less than 1,869,759, the number of such persons with a disability was never less than 193,231, and the number of such persons with a cognitive disability was never less than 77,663.</p><p>The PUMS sample sizes are about two-thirds of the ACS sample sizes (U.S. Census Bureau, 2021a). The total number of persons in the ACS analyses in this paper were therefore generally about 1.5 times the PUMS sample sizes. The ACS sample in this paper thus had upwards of 2.8 million noninstitutionalized working-age persons per year, upwards of 290,000 such persons with a disability per year, and upwards of 116,000 such persons with a cognitive disability per year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.3">Disability Status</head><p>Since 2008, ACS has collected data from respondents about whether they have each of six "disability types": hearing difficulty, vision difficulty, cognitive disability, ambulatory disability, self-care disability, and independent living difficulty; respondents who report any one of the six disability types are considered to have a disability <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, 2021b)</ref>. This set of six questions was designed with from the point of view of the social model of disability and has also been selected as the standard for all U.S. Department of Health and Human Services sponsored data collection, per amendments to the Public Health Service Act enacted by Section 4302 of the Affordable Care Act <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, 2025c;</ref><ref type="bibr">Data Collection, Analysis, and Quality, n.d.)</ref>. This paper analyzes data by three categories of disability status, two of which overlap: people with no disability (not in any of the ACS "disability type" categories), people with any disability (in at least one of the six ACS "disability type" categories), and people with a cognitive disability (in the ACS "cognitive disability" category, regardless of whether they were also in another "disability type" category).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.4">Employment Status as Defined by ACS</head><p>ACS categories respondents into one of the these categories: "employed" (has a job), "unemployed" (does not have a job and has actively looked for work in the past four weeks), or "not in the labor force" (does not have a job and has not actively looked for work in the past four weeks) <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Shepard et al., 2023)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.5">Accessing and Processing ACS Data</head><p>ACS data can be accessed efficiently in computer code via the Census Bureau's Application Programming Interface (API) (U.S. Census Bureau, 2025b). Data can be accessed by year, by geography, and by sub-population. Because this is a survey from a broader population, the ACS API provides not just best estimates for each of the quantities downloaded for this paper but also the margin of error of these quantities.</p><p>Using the R package tidycensus <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Walker &amp; Herman, 2024)</ref> to interface with the Census Bureau's API, I downloaded employment data, by disability status and state (including DC and Puerto Rico), from the year of the 2010 decennial census through the most recent data available (2023), except that, due to low response rate at the beginning of the pandemic, the Census Bureau did not publish data on the target variables for 2020. All such ACS data came from Census table B18120 ("Employment Status by Disability Status and Type"), which is specific to the civilian non-institutionalized working age population, where "working age" is defined as 18-64 years old <ref type="bibr">(U.S. Census Bureau, n.d.-a)</ref>. For each group and year, ACS data provides both point estimates and margins of error for number of people employed, number of people unemployed, and number of people not in labor force. This detailed breakdown provides the raw data for computing employment rate and employment ratio, as described in the next paragraph.</p><p>For each combination of year, disability status, and state, I calculated employment rate as the number of people employed divided by the sum of people employed, unemployed, and not in labor force. To control for broader trends in the overall labor market, I also calculated employment ratio as employment rate for that disability status divided by employment rate for people with no disability. (For each disability status, an employment ratio of 1 would indicate that people with that disability status are employed at a rate equal to that of people without a disability, an employment ratio of 0.5 would indicate that people with that disability status are employed at a rate one-half that of people without a disability, and an employment ratio of 0.25 would indicate that people with that disability status are employed at a rate one-quarter that of people without a disability.)</p><p>Because employment rates and employment ratios are calculated by combining information across downloaded quantities, they are known as derived quantities. For every such derived quantity I calculated standard errors using the margin-of-errors for a derived quantity as recommended by the Census Bureau and implemented by tidycensus <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Walker &amp; Herman, 2024)</ref>.</p><p>I then plotted the national ACS employment data, by year, for the employment rate for each disability status and for people without a disability and the national data for the employment ratio for each disability status (except that the plots omit employment ratio for people with no disability because that employment ratio is 1 by construction).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Department of Labor 14(c) Subminimum Wage Data</head><p>For data on 14(c) Community Rehabilitation Programs, I downloaded all data directly available from the U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour Division website, with availability starting October 2021. To access data from before this date I also downloaded all unique data releases from the "Wayback Machine" at archive.org. The Wayback Machine is a digital archive of web pages that allows users to "go back in time" to see how websites looked in the past ("Wayback Machine," 2025), which enabled me to access historical data (before October 2021) that the Wage and Hour Division had previously publicly posted, in order to augment the data currently posted online with data that were previously posted by the same authoritative source.</p><p>The URLs for all downloaded Department of Education data are at https://github.com/acobolew/disability-employment, as are Excel files containing the downloaded data. Number of programs was available starting in January 2010, and number of people employed at subminimum wage was available starting in October 2015. (Because there were periods when the Department of Labor processed applications particularly slowly, I calculated number of programs as the sum of current and pending.) Department of Labor data includes the geography included in the ACS as well as Guam. To calculate per-capita rate of people paid subminimum wage I divided the number of such people by census population estimates (which excluded Guam). Because census population estimates by state were available only through 2023, I also used 2023 estimates in 2024. (Given population trends by state, this would be expected to introduce error of less than 1.8%.) I then plotted the national Department of Labor data, by year, for the number of workers paid subminimum wage in CRP programs and for the number of such programs. Because the changes over time in these quantities (especially in number of workers paid subminimum wage) did not follow a straight line, I added curvilinear fits to the graphs to highlight the trends over time, using the geom_smooth() function in the R package ggplot2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Wickham, 2016)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">State-by-State Data</head><p>To examine state-by-state patterns over time (Research Question 4), I applied curvilinear fits (generalized additive models) to the state-by-state data on employment ratio and on workers per capita paid subminimum wages in 14(c) CRP programs, using the mgcv package in R <ref type="bibr">(Wood, 2011)</ref>. Generalized additive models are a generalization of linear regression models in statistics that can naturally model curvilinear changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Wood, 2017)</ref>. The fits incorporated "random effects" that allowed the specific shape of the change over time to vary by states. This facilitated graphical assessment of trends over time, by state.</p><p>To explore the potential for covariation state-by-state between employment ratio and workers paid subminimum wages (Research Question 5), I conducted an additional analysis in which I restricted attention to 2015-2023 (the years that ACS and per-capita rate of people paid 14(c) subminimum wage were both available). In this additional analysis for each of the 50 states, DC, and Puerto Rico, I linearly regressed the cognitive disability employment ratio and the per-capita rate of people earning subminimum wage in 14(c) programs against year (centered on 2019, as that is the middle of the 2015-2023 time window). In order for both regressions to weight year equally (except that 2020 was absent from ACS dataset), I inversely weighted the per-capita 14(c) data by number of time points per year. These regressions produced four parameters for each state: an intercept and a slope for cognitive disability employment ratio (for the average value of a state's cognitive disability employment ratio and the broad change over time in the state's cognitive disability employment ratio), and an intercept and a slope for numbers of workers per capita paid subminimum wage in CRP programs (for the average value of a state's prevalence of subminimum wage and the broad change over time in the state's prevalence of subminimum wage). I then examined the covariation of these four parameters across states.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Demographics of Research Population by Year and Disability Status</head><p>Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> present demographic characteristics of the research population by year and disability status.</p><p>All but the rightmost portion of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> presents the sex and age characteristics, both by whether a person has any disability and by whether a person has a cognitive disability. Sex distribution was stable over time: for every year, 49-51% of the population was female, regardless of disability status.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> dichotomizes age according to how it is reported in the ACS aggregate tables (age 18-34 versus 35-64). For people with no disability and for people with no cognitive disability, age distribution on this coarse scale was fairly stable, with 37-39% younger than 35.</p><p>In contrast, for people with any disability, the population shifted younger over time, with 20% younger than 35 in 2010 versus 29% younger by 2023. For people with a cognitive disability there was a parallel trend: 28% younger than 35 in 2010 versus 40% younger by 2023.</p><p>The rightmost portion of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> presents ethnic status (percent Hispanic or Latino versus White non-Hispanic/Latino). This is reported only by presence of disability because the ACS aggregate data do not report this characteristic by cognitive disability status. The population shifted more Hispanic/Latino over time: Among people without a disability, the shift was from 21% Hispanic/Latino in 2010 to 27% by 2023. There was a similar though slightly steeper trend among people with a disability: 18% Hispanic/Latino in 2010 to 24% by 2023. Thus, people with a disability were disproportionately not Hispanic/Latino, but this disproportionality narrowed over time.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> presents race of the research population by year and by whether a respondent had any disability, as the ACS aggregate data do not report these characteristics by cognitive disability status. The population became more racially diverse over time, regardless of presence of disability: Among people with a disability it went from 74% White alone in 2010 to 72% White alone in 2019. This was almost identical among people without a disability, for whom it went from 75% White alone in 2010 to 71% White alone in 2019. In 2021 the percentage White alone dropped about 10%, regardless of presence of disability, as the Census Bureau made major changes to how it collected and coded information about race <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Marks &amp; Rios-Vargas, 2021)</ref>. This is reflected as well in the simultaneous jump of about 10% in "Two or More Races", from 2-3% in 2010-2019 to 12% in 2021-2023, regardless of disability status.</p><p>People with a disability were disproportionately Black: regardless of year, 15-17% of people with a disability were Black alone versus only 12-13% of people without a disability being Black alone. The percentage American Indian or Alaska Native was constant at 1% regardless of year or disability status. People with a disability were disproportionately not Asian: among people with a disability, 2-3% were Asian alone, whereas among people without a disability 6-7% were Asian alone. Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander was less than 0.5% of the research population regardless of year or presence of disability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Research Questions 1 and 2 Answered with American Community Survey Employment Data</head><p>From 2010 to 2023, employment increased for all groups (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1A</ref>). It rose especially steeply among people with any disability. It rose even more steeply among people with a cognitive disability. This resulted in a long-term narrowing of the employment gap, as seen in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1B</ref>: since 2010 employment ratio grew for people with any disability-but grew even more steeply for people with a cognitive disability. Since the pandemic, these trends only accelerated.</p><p>From 2010 to 2023, employment among people without disabilities rose from 72.8% to 79.4%, employment among people with any disability rose from 33.3% to 46.2%, and employment among people with cognitive disabilities rose from 23.4% to 40.6%. The employment ratio for people with any disability thus rose from 0.46 to 0.58 (a 1.3-fold increase), and the employment ratio for people with a cognitive disability thus rose from 0.32 to 0.51 (a 1.6-fold increase).</p><p>In other words, the employment rate for people with a cognitive disability rose from about one-third the employment rate for people without a disability to about one-half the employment rate of people with a disability.</p><p>For further context, applying the employment rates from 2010 and 2023 to the estimates 2023 population of people with cognitive disabilities reveals a large shift: the employment gap for people with a cognitive disability narrowed by 1.8 million people. This employment gap narrowed especially in 2021 and 2022.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Research Question 3 Answered with Department of Labor 14(c) Subminimum Wage Data</head><p>The number of people earning subminimum wages in 14(c) community rehabilitation programs dropped by about 70% from 2015 (the first year that such data were available online) Disability Employment 18 through roughly the end of 2020 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1C</ref>) during a time when employment ratio among people with cognitive disabilities was rising. The number of people earning subminimum wage in such programs has since plateaued. The number of 14(c) certificates to operate such programs has fallen since 2011 (the first year that data on number of certificates were available online) and has continued to fall-down three-quarters from 2011 to 2024 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1D</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Research Question 4 Answered with State-by-State ACS and Department of Labor Data</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref> presents state-by-state data on employment ratio for people with cognitive disabilities and number of 14(c) CRP subminimum wage earners in programs per capita, with curvilinear fits. All states experienced an increase in employment ratio among people with cognitive disabilities, and the number of such subminimum wage earners fell in all states (except in New Hampshire, which had already eliminated subminimum wage jobs by the time the time series began in October 2015).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Research Question 5 Answered with Further Analysis of State-by-State Data</head><p>To further explore the potential relationship between number of 14(c) subminimum wage earners per capita and employment ratio for people with a cognitive disability, linear regressions were performed, separately for the 50 states, DC, and Puerto Rico, for the time interval where those time series overlapped (2015-2023, a period immediately after WIOA's passage that also captures most of the national trend for rising employment ratios and falling subminimum wage jobs). Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref> presents a scatterplot matrix of the parameters of those state-by-state regressions.</p><p>The first cell on the principal diagonal (that is, the upper left cell in the scatterplot matrix) displays the distribution of the intercept of subminimum wage workers per 100k-that is, the number of such workers per capita by state, averaged across the years 2015-2023. The distribution is not symmetrical, instead being right-skewed (having a sharp peak on the left and a long tail on the right). This reflects that most states have few if any subminimum wage workers (peaking below 25 per 100k population) while there is a long tail of states with proportionately more (approaching 150 per 150k population).</p><p>The second cell on principal diagonal shows the distribution of the slope (change over time) for subminimum wage workers per 100k. The most important feature of this cell is that every state has slope ≤ 0 (note that the x-axis labels at the bottom of the second column are all zero or negative. This reflects that number of subminimum wage earners fell in every state (except in New Hampshire where there were already zero).</p><p>The fourth cell on principal diagonal shows the distribution of the slope (change over time) for employment ratio for people with cognitive disabilities. The most important feature of this cell is that every state has slope &gt; 0 (note that the x-axis labels at the bottom of the fourth column are all positive) for cognitive disability employment ratio, reflecting that employment ratio for people with cognitive disabilities rose in every state.</p><p>The few states that, pre-pandemic, already had many subminimum wage earners per capita (for example, Minnesota in first column second row of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref>) had a strong tendency to experience the largest decrease in subminimum wage earners per capita. This is seen in the tight scatterplot in the first column second row of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref> and the very negative Pearson correlation of -0.90. Other correlations among regression parameters are weak (all other correlation magnitudes ≤ 0.35). There was a slight tendency (correlation = 0.35) for states that, pre-pandemic, had many subminimum wage earners per capita to have higher cognitive disability employment ratio midway through the interval (for example Minnesota in first column third row of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref>). There was an even slighter tendency (correlation = -0.27) for such states to experience only modest improvements over time in employment ratio for cognitive disabilities (for example, Minnesota in first column bottom row of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussion</head><p>Employment ratio has improved for people with any disability, but has improved even more for people with a cognitive disability. While employment rate remains lower among people with a cognitive disability than among people with any disability, that gap is also narrowing. For the first time in the data record, employment ratio for people with cognitive disabilities has exceeded 0.5. This is unprecedented. It means that people with cognitive disabilities are now employed at more than half the rate of people with no disability.</p><p>Interpreting these results requires attention to two distinct timeframes. The first involves long-term improvements in employment ratio, coinciding with dramatic decline in sheltered workshops. The second reflects the post-pandemic acceleration in employment ratio after most sheltered workshops had closed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Longer-Term Employment Increases Coincide with Increased Resources and Supports for Competitive Integrated Employment</head><p>The post-pandemic improvement in employment is superimposed on a longer-term improvement, dating back to at least 2011-a period during which employment ratio for people with cognitive disabilities increased 1.6-fold while number of sheltered workshops decreased 3.9-fold. These sustained trends across more than a decade likely reflect the combined impact of a series of policy changes and federal initiatives undertaken during the same period of time that have shifted the landscape away from segregated settings and toward competitive integrated employment. Indeed, since the most recent substantive changes in federal 14(c) regulations, there  <ref type="table">4</ref> itemizes key initiatives at the federal level, along with their specific domains and timing. They are described below, including links to the evidence base in the scientific literature.  <ref type="bibr">Supporting Employment First, 2023)</ref>. There is an evidence base for practices that promote competitive integrated employment: Supported Employment and Individual Placement and Supports have demonstrated positive employment outcomes and cost effectiveness for people with severe mental illness <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bush et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">T. N. Christensen et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr">Drake et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kinoshita et al., 2013)</ref>, and cognitive rehabilitation has been shown to lead to substantial improvements in cognitive functioning and quality of life <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(McGurk &amp; Wykes, 2008)</ref>.</p><p>Customized Employment has also emerged as a promising practice, with evidence from model descriptions and project evaluations that it that may produce quality employment outcomes for persons with disabilities, though studies of Customized Employment to date have typically lacked comprehensive fidelity measurement and random assignment <ref type="bibr">(Riesen et al., 2023)</ref>. Supported Employment has been part of the Rehabilitation Act since 1986 (Rehabilitation Act <ref type="bibr">Amendments of 1986</ref><ref type="bibr">Amendments of , 1986))</ref>, and Supported Employment and Customized Employment are both specifically included in WIOA. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competitive integrated employment is also promoted by the Home and Community</head><p>Based Services (HCBS) Final Rule (the "settings rule"), which passed in 2014 with compliance deadline extended to 2023 <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Lynch, 2020)</ref>. The settings rule promotes competitive integrated employment by requiring that such settings be integrated into the greater community and that the settings include opportunities for people with disabilities supported by HCBS to seek and engage in competitive integrated employment <ref type="bibr">(Home and Community-Based Setting, n.d.)</ref>. By requiring that people supported by HCBS have a choice of service providers, the settings rule also effectively creates more choice in supports, including decoupling the choice of work supports from who provides other supports. Empirically, HCBS investment is related to employment of people with disabilities: state-by-state, greater allocation of long-term services and supports expenditures to HCBS is powerful predictor of employment among people with disabilities <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bixby, 2025)</ref>. Indirect and direct federal contractors have also been required not to pay subminimum wage. The AbilityOne Program, operated by an independent federal agency, is a large source of employment for people who are blind or who have significant disabilities (U.S. AbilityOne Commission, 2025a). More than 420 nonprofits employ people through the program (U.S. AbilityOne Commission, 2025b). In 2022 the AbilityOne Commission issued a rule prohibiting payment of subminimum wages under 14(c) through the AbilityOne Program (Prohibition on the Payment of Subminimum Wages Under 14(c) Certificates, 2022). In addition, by executive order, federal agencies have been directed since 2014 to contract only with entities paying at least minimum wage <ref type="bibr">(Executive Order 13658, 2014)</ref>. While a subsequent executive order raising that minimum wage for people employed by federal contractors <ref type="bibr">(Executive Order 14026, 2021)</ref> has been rescinded (Executive Order 14236, 2025), the 2014 executive order remains in effect.</p><p>The overwhelming long-term trend, nationally and in every state, for employment ratio to increase while sheltered workshops decrease suggests that these extensive coordinated policy efforts and initiatives to promote competitive integrated employment have been effective over the long haul.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Post-pandemic Employment Increase</head><p>As encouraging as the long-term trend is in employment ratio for people with cognitive disabilities, it accelerated dramatically post-pandemic. In the 7-year span from 2012 to 2019, employment ratio for people with a cognitive disability increased by a factor of 1.25 (equivalent to 3.3% per year compounded over those 7 years). In the 4-year span from 2019 to 2023, the employment ratio increased by a factor of 1.32 (equivalent to 7.2% per year compounded over those 4 years). In other words, post-pandemic the employment ratio for people with a cognitive disability increased at more than double the rate that it increased pre-pandemic. This finding contrasts with historic trends where this population experiences a slower recovery following economic downturns. The swift and substantial improvement in the employment ratio for people with any disability-and especially for people with a cognitive disability-suggests that the dynamics of the post-pandemic labor market may have created unique opportunities for competitive integrated employment. The increased availability of telework opportunities during the pandemic may have reduced some traditional barriers to employment for people with disabilities, offering more flexible and accessible work arrangements. This finding validates previous calls from the National Institute for Disability and Rehabilitation Research to identify effective strategies for enhancing employment opportunities through telecommuting-calls dating back to 2013, long before the pandemic. During the pandemic, the World Health Organization endorsed flexible working arrangements allowing people with disabilities to telework (World Health Organization, 2020). Practice followed policy recommendations: Prevalence of telework in the U.S. tripled during the pandemic (Government Accountability Office, 2023b). There was a positive link to employment of people with a disability, as gains in overall disability employment post-pandemic have been concentrated in teleworkable, essential, and non-frontline occupations (Ne'eman &amp; Maestas, 2023). The link to employment of people with a cognitive disability was even stronger, as workers with cognitive disabilities were especially likely to telework during the pandemic <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ameri et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Accommodations (which can include telework but need not be limited to telework) also increased during the pandemic, especially for people with cognitive disabilities. In 2021, 19% of employees with cognitive disabilities enjoyed a full or partial fulfillment of an accommodation request. This was the highest rate among any of the six ACS disability categories that year and represented more than a doubling of the rate that employees with cognitive disabilities experienced nine years earlier <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Kruse et al., 2024)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Employer Practice</head><p>The public sector is not alone in promoting employment of people with disabilities.</p><p>Shortly before the pandemic, the Society for Human Resource Management (2019) issued a research report on employment of people with disabilities with a number of findings and recommendations. Among the findings was that 60% of surveyed HR professionals, 49% of employees, and 40% of managers felt at least moderately comfortable working with colleague with intellectual disabilities (rates that were higher than for colleagues with physical disabilities but lower than for colleagues with mental health disabilities). But the survey also found significant barriers rooted in attitudes and in concerns about costs of accommodations. Informed by the report, the society launched an Employing Abilities @Work Certificate as the pandemic was hitting (Society for Human Resource Management, n.d.). The certificate is just one part of a broader initiative promoting recruitment, hiring, and retention of people with disabilities that has persisted into the post-pandemic era (Society for Human Resource Management, 2025). A recent analysis of longitudinal employer survey data <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Houston &amp; Kruse, 2025)</ref> indicates that (1) accessibility practices are associated with increased employment through both increased hiring and decreased exits, (2) self-identification encouragement practices and promotion of disability initiatives are associated with increased employment of people with disabilities specifically through increased hiring, and (3) disability training and education and accommodation practices are associated with increased employment through decreased exits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Tightening Labor Market</head><p>The data in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1B</ref> show the employment ratio for people with cognitive disability increasing through a long period when Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1A</ref> shows the employment rate for people with no disability was also increasing (with the exception of the transient pandemic shock). This is consistent with the interpretation that the tightening labor market is driving improved employment outcomes among people with cognitive disabilities. However, note that an analysis of Current Population Survey data indicated that, among people with disabilities overall, the employment ratio was essentially constant at 0.42 when employment cratered from February 2020 to April 2020 <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Houtenville et al., 2021)</ref>. This suggests that employment of people with disabilities may no longer be as pro-cyclic as it was years earlier (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Ne'eman &amp; Maestas, 2023)</ref>. This further suggests that there may be genuine change in policy, culture, and practice promoting employment of people with disabilities. It is an open question, however, whether this conclusion applies as well to people with a cognitive disability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">State-by-State Patterns</head><p>Viewed across almost a decade, every state exhibited an increased employment ratio for people with cognitive disabilities-even including Maine, where employment for people with cognitive disabilities had not initially increased immediately after Maine closed its last sheltered workshop in 2010 <ref type="bibr">(Phoenix &amp; Bysshe, 2015)</ref>. In addition, no state increased subminimum wage jobs over the long-term. By far the biggest co-variation state-by-state (correlation -0.90 in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref> between subminimum wage intercept and subminimum wage slope) is that states with the most subminimum wage jobs per capita saw the largest per-capita decrease in such jobs.</p><p>The long-term decline in the number of people paid subminimum wage occurred even in states that saw recent increases in number of people paid subminimum wage. For example, in Missouri the number of people per 100k population paid subminimum wages in 14(c) CRP programs fell from about 130 in 2015 down to about 25 in 2021 before rebounding and then plateauing around 55. Similar patterns occurred in Arkansas (about 110 in 2015, down to about 20, rebounding to about 50), Kansas (about 110 in 2015, down to below 10, rebounding to about 25), Ohio (about 140 in 2015, down to below 10, rebounding to about 25), Pennsylvania (about 95 in 2015, down to about 20, rebounding to about 30), and Indiana (about 80 in 2015, down to about 10, rebounding to about 15). There was a modest tendency, however, for employment ratio to rise more steeply in states where subminimum wage employment fell less (the 0.28 correlation between slopes in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref>)-but employment ratio nevertheless improved in every state.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.6">Recommendations</head><p>It seems likely that the post-pandemic labor market may have created significant opportunities for competitive integrated employment of all people with disabilities, especially for people with cognitive disabilities. As labor market conditions shift, it will be important to consolidate these gains and use successful work placement settings as a model for future initiatives to promote competitive integrated employment. The following recommendations are supported:</p><p>• RSA and the SWTCIE model demonstration projects should consider engaging in a mid-point review to ensure they are taking advantage of the opportunities provided by the post-pandemic rise in employment ratio for people with cognitive disabilities.</p><p>• Research funders such as NIDILRR should encourage proposals that identify post-pandemic hires of people with disabilities-especially people with cognitive disabilities-to identify successful practices that can be sustained regardless of future changes in the labor market. For example, to what extent can the postpandemic rise in employment ratio be attributed to factors beyond telework?</p><p>• NIDILRR should also encourage proposals that propose to grow the evidence base on the extent to which telework options and accommodations could benefit specifically people who might otherwise be employed in sheltered workshops.</p><p>• ODEP's Campaign for Disability Employment should promote the promising practices identified as being responsible for the dramatic post-pandemic improvement in employment ratio. Taking advantage of these opportunities is Disability Employment 29 especially important to ensure that transition to competitive integrated employment is successful.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.7">Limitations</head><p>Assessing the presence of a disability solely through the six "disability type" questions in the American Community Survey may fail to identify some people with a disability when they are enrolled in income support programs like Social Security Disability Insurance (SSDI) or Supplemental Security Income (SSI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Burkhauser et al., 2014)</ref>, thus biasing upward the estimates of employment rate for people with disabilities reported in this paper and biasing upward the employment ratios reported in this paper. While this paper may thus overestimate employment ratio, however, such bias would be unlikely to change systematically over time in a way to affect the trends reported in the present paper. The result about the historic increase in employment ratio is thus likely to be robust, even if the result about the absolute level of employment by people with a disability may be optimistic.</p><p>Another limitation is that, although this paper documents changes in employment ratio and in subminimum wage prevalence, it does not follow trajectories of individual people currently or previously paid subminimum wage.</p><p>In addition, this study considers variation among states but does not analyze differences within states, such as urban versus rural contexts. Including such analyses in future work could clarify whether the association between sheltered workshops and employment might differ by local labor market.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.8">Conclusion</head><p>While there remains a large employment gap for persons with any disability, the gap has narrowed over the long term and especially post-pandemic. Improvements over both of these Disability Employment 30 timeframes are even more pronounced for people with a cognitive disability. Research to inform public policy and hiring and retention practices by all employers should take advantage of this.</p><p>The long range plan of the National Institute on Disability, Independent Living, and Rehabilitation Research continues a focus on building the evidence base for employers to successfully hire, retain, and promote people with disabilities (National Institute on Disability, 5 Independent Living, and Rehabilitation Research, 2024). Research and other investments should identify post-pandemic hires of people with disabilities-especially people with cognitive disabilities-to identify successful practices that can be sustained regardless of future changes in the labor market, potentially going beyond telework, but also including the extent to which telework could benefit people who might otherwise be in sheltered workshops, and there should 10 be a marketing investment to promote those practices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diversity, equity, ethics, and inclusion</head><p>The author is the parent of two adults, one of whom has an intellectual/developmental disability.  Note: 0% indicates &lt; 0.5%.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure Captions</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>poses and answers five research questions about the overall patterns and long-term trends in the landscape of disability employment and subminimum wage across the nation and the broader patterns among states. Research questions 3, 4, and 5 focus on sheltered workshops, whose Disability Employment 7 workers overwhelmingly have intellectual/developmental disabilities. The U.S. Census American Community Survey does not collect data on intellectual/developmental disability, but it does collect data on cognitive disability. Research questions 2, 4, and 5 therefore focus on cognitive disability. The five research questions are: 1. What are the nationwide trends-both long-term and post-pandemic-in employment of people with any disability, relative to employment people without a disability? 2. What are these trends for people with a cognitive disability? 3. What are the nationwide trends-both long-term and post-pandemic-in prevalence of sheltered workshops? 4. How similar or different are states from one another, and from the nationwide trends, in employment of people with a cognitive disability and in the use of sheltered workshops? 5. What is the relationship, seen from comparisons among states, between employment of people with a cognitive disability and the use of sheltered workshops? 2 Materials and Methods To answer the research questions, this paper describes systematic analysis of time series from two data sources: U.S. Census American Community Survey (ACS) data on employment by disability status since the 2010 census and U.S. Department of Labor data about 14(c) sheltered workshops (more formally known as Community Rehabilitation Programs or CRPs (U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour Division, n.d.). The Department of Labor data included both the number of CRP programs (available since 2011) and number of people employed at subminimum wages in such programs (available since 2015). Data from the U.S. Census Bureau helped answer Research Questions 1, 2, 4, and 5, and data from the U.S. Department of Labor helped answer Research Questions 3, 4, and 5. All analyses used R 4.2.1 (R Core Team, 2024), with code and data at https://github.com/acobolew/disability-employment 2.1 American Community Survey Employment by Disability Status 2.1.1 Description of ACS Annually, the U.S. Census Bureau conducts the American Community Survey (ACS) through random sampling (U.S. Census Bureau, 2024). The ACS includes the Puerto Rico Community Survey (PRCS), which is the ACS customized for Puerto Rico (US Census Bureau, 2025).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>have been many strategies and resources developed for competitive integrated employment of Disability Employment 21 persons with disabilities. They represent a combination of actions by Congress, the federal executive branch, and states. They also span five policy domains that correspond to five distinct titles of the federal code: Labor (Title 29), Health &amp; Welfare (Title 42), Tax (Title 26), Public Contracts (Title 41), and Education (Title 20). Table</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>For example, under the national Employment First framework (U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy, n.d.-c), publicly financed systems are urged to pursue policies and practices to promote competitive integrated employment. Indeed, as of September 2023, all states have taken some action promoting Employment First: 31 have passed Employment First legislation, 16 have issued Employment First executive orders, and 32 have administrative policies or regulations supporting Employment First (Association of People</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The U.S. Department of Labor's Office of Disability Employment Policy (ODEP) has engaged in several efforts to promote competitive integrated employment, such as the Campaign for Disability Employment (U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy, n.d.-a), the Disability Employment Initiative to fund expanded employment opportunities for people with disabilities to California, Connecticut, Idaho, Massachusetts, Minnesota, and Maryland (U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy, 2016), the Employment First State Leadership Mentoring Program (U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy, n.d.-c), an Employment First Community of Practice (U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy, n.d.-c), and the online CIE Transformation Hub (U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy, n.d.-b). In addition, ODEP's National Expansion of Employment Opportunities Network (NEON) works with sheltered workshops to extend competitive integrated employment opportunities to people in segregated settings or paid subminimum wages (U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy, n.d.-d).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Competitive integrated employment is also related to the Achieving a Better Life Experience Act (ABLE Act), which Congress passed in 2014 in Division B of Public Law 113-295 (Public Law 113-295, 2014), with the Internal Revenue Service (IRS) releasing final regulations in 2020 (Guidance Under Section 529A: Qualified ABLE Programs, 2020). Under the ABLE Act, people with disabilities can establish tax-advantaged savings accounts ("ABLE accounts") without jeopardizing access to public benefits. The ABLE Act promotes competitive integrated employment because workers can save more without jeopardizing access to meanstested public benefits like SSI and Medicaid (ABLE National Resource Center, 2025). In addition, in 2022 the U.S. Department of Education's Rehabilitation Services Administration (RSA) awarded five-year grants for the federal fiscal year 2022 Disability Innovation Fund demonstration project to provide 14 state vocational rehabilitation agencies with funding to implement Subminimum Wage to Competitive Integrated Employment (SWTCIE) Innovative Model Demonstration projects, informed by a systematic review of the evidence base (U.S. Department of Education, 2022).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. National trends over time. (A) Employment rate by type of disability status</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. State-by-state trends for employment ratio for people with cognitive</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Scatterplot matrix showing patterns among states in linear regressions</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="54,162.00,104.40,288.00,576.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="55,118.00,98.40,411.80,575.94" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="56,90.00,138.00,432.00,432.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Number of Noninstitutionalized Working-age Persons in PUMS Sample (Total and by DisabilityStatus).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No Cognitive</cell><cell>Has Cognitive</cell></row><row><cell>Year</cell><cell cols="3">Total No Disability Has Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell></row><row><cell>2023</cell><cell>1,946,501</cell><cell>1,719,045</cell><cell>227,456</cell><cell>1,835,737</cell><cell>110,764</cell></row><row><cell>2022</cell><cell>1,940,959</cell><cell>1,715,895</cell><cell>225,064</cell><cell>1,833,427</cell><cell>107,532</cell></row><row><cell>2021</cell><cell>1,878,823</cell><cell>1,667,859</cell><cell>210,964</cell><cell>1,782,168</cell><cell>96,655</cell></row><row><cell>2019</cell><cell>1,895,667</cell><cell>1,691,049</cell><cell>204,618</cell><cell>1,804,468</cell><cell>91,199</cell></row><row><cell>2018</cell><cell>1,897,181</cell><cell>1,693,890</cell><cell>203,291</cell><cell>1,809,325</cell><cell>87,856</cell></row><row><cell>2017</cell><cell>1,891,167</cell><cell>1,685,174</cell><cell>205,993</cell><cell>1,802,802</cell><cell>88,365</cell></row><row><cell>2016</cell><cell>1,878,698</cell><cell>1,668,855</cell><cell>209,843</cell><cell>1,789,858</cell><cell>88,840</cell></row><row><cell>2015</cell><cell>1,884,038</cell><cell>1,674,764</cell><cell>209,274</cell><cell>1,795,293</cell><cell>88,745</cell></row><row><cell>2014</cell><cell>1,880,566</cell><cell>1,669,009</cell><cell>211,557</cell><cell>1,791,506</cell><cell>89,060</cell></row><row><cell>2013</cell><cell>1,891,325</cell><cell>1,680,211</cell><cell>211,114</cell><cell>1,804,102</cell><cell>87,223</cell></row><row><cell>2012</cell><cell>1,877,392</cell><cell>1,671,764</cell><cell>205,628</cell><cell>1,790,490</cell><cell>86,902</cell></row><row><cell>2011</cell><cell>1,882,313</cell><cell>1,672,070</cell><cell>210,243</cell><cell>1,793,894</cell><cell>88,419</cell></row><row><cell>2010</cell><cell>1,869,759</cell><cell>1,676,528</cell><cell>193,231</cell><cell>1,792,096</cell><cell>77,663</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Sex,Age, and Ethnic Characteristics of Working-Age Noninstitutionalized Population, by Year and Disability Status.    </figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">% Female</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">% Younger Than 35</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">% Hispanic or Latino</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>With Cog</cell><cell>No Cog</cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>With Cog</cell><cell>No Cog</cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>Year</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell><cell>Disability</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>29%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>40%</cell><cell>37%</cell><cell>24%</cell><cell>27%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>28%</cell><cell>39%</cell><cell>40%</cell><cell>37%</cell><cell>24%</cell><cell>27%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>26%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>37%</cell><cell>23%</cell><cell>26%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>49%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>24%</cell><cell>39%</cell><cell>35%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>20%</cell><cell>25%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>49%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>23%</cell><cell>39%</cell><cell>34%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>20%</cell><cell>25%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>49%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>23%</cell><cell>39%</cell><cell>34%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>20%</cell><cell>24%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>49%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>22%</cell><cell>39%</cell><cell>33%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>20%</cell><cell>24%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>49%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>22%</cell><cell>39%</cell><cell>31%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>19%</cell><cell>23%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>49%</cell><cell>51%</cell><cell>21%</cell><cell>39%</cell><cell>31%</cell><cell>38%</cell><cell>19%</cell><cell>23%</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Racial Characteristics ofWorking-Age Noninstitutionalized Population, by Year and Disability Status.    </figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">% American</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">% Native</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Indian or</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Hawaiian or</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Alaska Native</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Other Pacific</cell><cell cols="2">% Some Other</cell><cell cols="2">% Two or More</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">% White Alone % Black Alone</cell><cell cols="2">Alone</cell><cell cols="2">% Asian Alone</cell><cell cols="2">Islander Alone</cell><cell cols="2">Race Alone</cell><cell cols="2">Races</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>With</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>Year</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell><cell>Disab</cell></row><row><cell>2023</cell><cell>61%</cell><cell>59%</cell><cell>15%</cell><cell>12%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>7%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>7%</cell><cell>8%</cell><cell>12%</cell><cell>12%</cell></row><row><cell>2022</cell><cell>61%</cell><cell>60%</cell><cell>16%</cell><cell>12%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>7%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>7%</cell><cell>8%</cell><cell>12%</cell><cell>12%</cell></row><row><cell>2021</cell><cell>62%</cell><cell>60%</cell><cell>15%</cell><cell>12%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>7%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>6%</cell><cell>8%</cell><cell>12%</cell><cell>12%</cell></row><row><cell>2019</cell><cell>72%</cell><cell>71%</cell><cell>17%</cell><cell>13%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>7%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>4%</cell><cell>5%</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>3%</cell></row><row><cell>2018</cell><cell>72%</cell><cell>72%</cell><cell>16%</cell><cell>12%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>7%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>4%</cell><cell>5%</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>3%</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>Thanks to <rs type="person">Oladayo Akinyode</rs> for help downloading the 14(c) data.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>Employment Policy. (n.d.-a). <rs type="funder">Campaign for Disability Employment (CDE)</rs>. Retrieved June 21, 2025, from https://www.dol.gov/agencies/odep/initiatives/campaign-for-disability-employment <rs type="funder">U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy</rs>. (n.d.-b). CIE Transformation Hub. Retrieved June 21, 2025, from https://www.dol.gov/agencies/odep/programareas/cie/hub <rs type="funder">U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy</rs>. (n.d.-c). Employment First. Retrieved June 21, 2025, from https://www.dol.gov/agencies/odep/initiatives/employment-first <rs type="funder">U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy</rs>. (n.d.-d). <rs type="funder">National Expansion of Employment Opportunities Network (NEON)</rs>. Retrieved June 21, 2025, from https://www.dol.gov/agencies/odep/initiatives/neon <rs type="funder">U.S. Department of Labor Office of Disability Employment Policy</rs>. (2016, September <rs type="grantNumber">14</rs>). Six States Receive Nearly $15M in Grants to <rs type="institution">Expand Employment Opportunities for People with Disabilities</rs>. https://www.dol.gov/newsroom/releases/odep/odep20160914 <rs type="funder">U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour Division</rs>. (n.d.). Field Operations Handbook-Chapter 64. Retrieved June 20, 2025, from https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fieldoperations-handbook/Chapter-64#<rs type="grantNumber">b64b00</rs> <rs type="funder">U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour Division</rs>. (2025). Annual Report to Authorizing and</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><head>Funding</head><p>Supported by <rs type="funder">Administration for Community Living (ACL)</rs>, <rs type="funder">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS)</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">90DDUC0136</rs>. Contents are author's and do not necessarily represent the official views of, nor an endorsement by, <rs type="institution">ACL/HHS</rs>, or the <rs type="institution">U.S. Government</rs>.</p></div>
<div><head>Informed consent</head><p>This was an analysis of publicly available aggregate data that did not involve the collection or analysis of human subjects data as defined in Federal Policy for the <rs type="projectName">Protection of Human Subjects ("Common Rule</rs>"), so informed consent was not needed.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_rw2M2FV">
					<idno type="grant-number">14</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_r9v5Ax7">
					<idno type="grant-number">b64b00</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_5uSMV5K">
					<idno type="grant-number">90DDUC0136</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_ykACcXJ">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Protection of Human Subjects (&quot;Common Rule</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data sharing</head><p>All code and data (including code to access data from Census API) are available at https://github.com/acobolew/disability-employment Data Collection, Analysis, and Quality, 42 U.S. Code § 300kk. ( <ref type="formula">2023</ref>) https://www.govinfo.gov/app/details/USCODE-2023-title42/USCODE-2023-title42-chap6A-subchapXXIX-sec300kk Dell'Armo, K. A., &amp; Tassé, M. J. (2021). Attitudes, stigma, and ableism toward people with intellectual disability. In L. M. Glidden, L. Abbeduto, L. L. McIntyre, &amp; M. J. Tassé (Eds.), APA handbook of intellectual and developmental disabilities: Foundations (Vol. 1). (pp. 473-497). American Psychological Association. https://doi.org/10.1037/0000194-018 Drake, R. E., Becker, D. R., Clark, R. E., &amp; Mueser, K. T. (1999). Research on the Individual Placement and Support Model of Supported Employment. Psychiatric Quarterly, 70(4), 289-301. https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1022086131916 Employment of Workers With Disabilities Under Section 14(c) of the Fair Labor Standards Act (Notice of Proposed Rulemaking), 89 Federal Register 96467 (2024). https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2024/12/04/2024-27880/employment-ofworkers-with-disabilities-under-section-14c-of-the-fair-labor-standards-act Executive Order 13658, 79 Federal Register 9851 (2014). https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2014/02/20/2014-03805/establishing-aminimum-wage-for-contractors Executive Order 14026, 86 Federal Register 22835 (2021). https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2021/04/30/2021-09263/increasing-theminimum-wage-for-federal-contractors Phoenix, J. A., &amp; Bysshe, T. (2015). Transitions: A Case Study of the Conversion from Sheltered Workshops to Integrated Employment in Maine. https://www.moworkshops.org/newsFolder/shutdown/REPORT_Transitions_Conversion FromShelteredWorkshops_Maine_July2015.pdf Prohibition on the Payment of Subminimum Wages Under 14(c) Certificates as a Qualification for Participation as a Nonprofit Agency Under the Javits Wagner O'Day Act, 87 Federal Register 43427 (2022). https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2022/07/21/2022-15561/prohibition-on-the-payment-of-subminimum-wages-under-14c-certificates-as-aqualification-for Public Law 113 -295 -An Act to Amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to Extend Certain Expiring Provisions and Make Technical Corrections, to Amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to Provide for the Tax Treatment of ABLE Accounts Established under State Programs for the Care of Family Members with Disabilities, and for Other Purposes, Pub. L. No. 113-295 (2014). https://www.govinfo.gov/app/details/PLAW-113publ295 R Core Team. (2024). R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing [Computer software]. R Foundation for Statistical Computing. www.R-project.org Rehabilitation Act Amendments of 1986, Pub. L. No. 99-506 (1986). https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/STATUTE-100/pdf/STATUTE-100-Pg1807.pdf Riesen, T., Snyder, A., Byers, R., Keeton, B., &amp; Inge, K. (2023). An updated review of the customized employment literature. Journal of Vocational Rehabilitation, 58(1), 27-38. https://doi.org/10.3233/JVR-221222</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p>The author declares that he has no conflict of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethics statement</head><p>This was an analysis of publicly available aggregate data that did not involve the collection or analysis of human subjects data as defined in Federal Policy for the Protection of Human Subjects ("Common Rule"), so ethical approval from an Institutional Review Board was not needed. Underlying data are from 2015 through 2023 (with ACS employment ratio missing for 2020), 5 and year is centered on 2019 (the middle of the time interval). Linear regressions of 14(c) data inversely weighted by number of time samples per year so each year would be weighted equally.</p><note type="other">Disability Employment 54 Figure 1 Disability Employment 55 Figure 2</note></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.ablenrc.org/what-is-able/debunking-able-myths/" />
		<title level="m">Debunking ABLE Myths. ABLE National Resource Center</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ABLE National Resource Center</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Telework during the pandemic: Patterns, challenges, and opportunities for people with disabilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ameri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rodgers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.dhjo.2022.101406</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dhjo.2022.101406" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Disability and Health Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101406</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://apse.org/home-v2-2/employment-first/" />
		<title level="m">Employment First Map. Association of People Supporting Employment First</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association of People Supporting Employment First</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dismantling Structural Ableism: The Influence of State Medicaid and Long-Term Services and Supports Policies on Disability-Based Employment Inequalities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bixby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/S1479-354720250000016005</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1108/S1479-354720250000016005" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Disability and the Future of Work</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hyseni</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schur</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Blanck</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Emerald Publishing Limited</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="85" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Employment opportunities for persons with different types of disability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Boman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kjellberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Danermark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Boman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.alter.2014.11.003</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alter.2014.11.003" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Alter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Economic outcomes of working-age people with disabilities over the business cycle: An examination of the 1980s and 1990s (Nos. 2001-07</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Burkhauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Daly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Houtenville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nargis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.frbsf.org/wp-content/uploads/wp01-07bk.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco</title>
		<title level="s">Working Paper Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capturing the Elusive Working-Age Population With Disabilities: Reconciling Conflicting Social Success Estimates From the Current Population Survey and American Community Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Burkhauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Houtenville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tennant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1044207312446226</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1044207312446226" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Disability Policy Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Review of the Evidence and Its Implications for Policy Change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Burkhauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stapleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.17848/9780585473666.ch11</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.17848/9780585473666.ch11" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Decline in Employment of People with Disabilities: A Policy Puzzle</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stapleton</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Burkhauser</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>W.E. Upjohn Institute</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="406" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Long-Term Impact of Employment on Mental Health Service Use and Costs for Persons With Severe Mental Illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Bush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Drake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mchugo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Haslett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1176/ps.2009.60.8.1024</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1176/ps.2009.60.8.1024" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychiatric Services</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1024" to="1031" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Association of People Supporting Employment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://apse.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/APSE-14c-Update-REV-Jul24.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Trends and Current Status of 14(c)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cost-utility and costeffectiveness of individual placement support and cognitive remediation in people with severe mental illness: Results from a randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hellström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Eplov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2020.111</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1192/j.eurpsy.2020.111" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coalition for the Preservation of Employment Choice</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2025/03/20/2025-04866/additional-rescissions-of-harmful-executive-orders-and-actions" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Protecting Employment for Individuals with Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-01">2022. January. 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">29 U.S. Code § 214.</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.govinfo.gov/app/details/USCODE-2023-title29/USCODE-2023-title29-chap8-sec214" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1938">1938. 2023</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Fair Labor Standards Act</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The underemployment of persons with disabilities during the Great Recession</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Harrington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcmahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Rehabilitation Professional</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gamble</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">ACS) Group Quarters Data. U.S. Census Bureau</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">ACS) Group Quarters Data. U.S. Census Bureau</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Koerber</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">ACS) Group Quarters Data. U.S. Census Bureau</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www2.census.gov/training-workshops/2022/2022-07-20-acs-presentation.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Introduction to American Community Survey</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-07-20">2022, July 20</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subminimum Wage Program: DOL Could Do More to Ensure Timely Oversight (No. GAO-23-105116)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gamboa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.gao.gov/products/gao-23-105116" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Legal Authority for American Community Survey</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S Government Accountability Office</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002-04-04">2002. April 4</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Government Accountability Office. (2023a)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Telework Growth Supported Economic Activity during the Pandemic, but Future Impacts are Uncertain (No. GAO-23-105999)</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.gao.gov/products/gao-23-105999" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023b</date>
			<publisher>U.S Government Accountability Office</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">section-529a-qualified-able-programs Home and Community-Based Setting, 42 Code of Federal Regulations § 441</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title-42/part-441/section-441.530#p-441.530" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Federal Register</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020-06-20">2020. June 20, 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Guidance Under Section 529A: Qualified ABLE Programs. i</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enabling Employment: How Do Employer Disability Practices Affect Disability Employment Outcomes?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/pandp.20251078</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1257/pandp.20251078" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AEA Papers and Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="536" to="542" />
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in the Employment Status of People With and Without Disabilities in the United States During the COVID-19 Pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Houtenville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Brucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.apmr.2021.03.019</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2021.03.019" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1420" to="1423" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of the 2007-09 recession on workers with disabilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kaye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.bls.gov/opub/mlr/2010/10/art2full.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Labor Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-05-26">2010. May 26, 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supported employment for adults with severe mental illness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kinoshita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Furukawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kinoshita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Honyashiki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Omori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Huxley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Amano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kingdon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/14651858.CD008297.pub2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD008297.pub2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assistive Technology&apos;s Potential to Improve Employment of People with Disabilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-A</forename><surname>Johnson-Marcus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Di Lallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10926-023-10164-wLanev.Kitzhaber</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10926-023-10164-wLanev.Kitzhaber" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Occupational Rehabilitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">841</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Supp. 2d 1199 (D. Or. 2012</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Re: Home and Community-Based Settings Regulation -Implementation Timeline Extension and Revised Frequently Asked Questions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.medicaid.gov/Federal-Policy-Guidance/Downloads/smd20003.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Center for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-07-14">2020, July 14</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improvements to the 2020 Census Race and Hispanic Origin Question Designs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rios-Vargas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.census.gov/newsroom/blogs/random-samplings/2021/08/improvements-to-2020-census-race-hispanic-origin-question-designs.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Data Processing, and Coding Procedures</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognitive remediation and vocational rehabilitation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mcgurk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wykes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2975/31.4.2008.350.359</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2975/31.4.2008.350.359" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychiatric Rehabilitation Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="350" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://acl.gov/sites/default/files/about-acl/2024-01/ACL_Final%20Transmitted_NIDILRR%20LRP%202024-2028.pdf" />
		<title level="m">2024-2028 Long-Range Plan</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Institute on Disability, Independent Living, and Rehabilitation Research</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How has COVID-19 impacted disability employment?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ne'eman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Maestas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.dhjo.2022.101429</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dhjo.2022.101429" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Disability and Health Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101429</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">L C</forename><surname>Olmstead V</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">527</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>U.S. 581 (U.S. Supreme Court</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Employment Outcomes Among Men and Women with Disabilities: How the Intersection of Gender and Disability Status Shapes Labor Market Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pettinicchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maroto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/S1479-</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1108/S1479-" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Social Science and Disability</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Emerald Publishing Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ruggles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Flood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sobek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Backman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A R</forename><surname>Drew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rodgers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>IPUMS USA: Version 16.0 (Version 16.0</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Dataset</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">IPUMS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Minneapolis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.18128/D010.V16.0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.18128/D010.V16.0" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">5 COVID-19 and Employment Losses for Workers with Disabilities: An Intersectional Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">V D</forename><surname>Meulen Rodgers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1515/9783110743647-006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110743647-006" />
		<editor>J. Beatty, S. Hennekam, &amp; M. Kulkarni</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>De Gruyter</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="104" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">American Community Survey 2021 (No. Data Note 83; Data Note Series)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shepard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Winson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Butterworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Migliore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Domin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zalewska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://employingabilities.org/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Employing Abilities @Work: 2019 research report. Society for Human Resource Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>pdf Society for Human Resource Management</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2023. August 25, 2025. 2019. 2025</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Massachusetts Boston</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>?article=1249&amp;context=ici_pubs Society for Human Resource Management. SHRM Foundation Employing Disabilities | Delivering a Talent Development Solution for HR</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The efficacy of competitive integrated employment versus segregated employment for persons with disabilities: A systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Avellone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Brooke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3233/JVR-221225</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3233/JVR-221225" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Vocational Rehabilitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.abilityone.gov/abilityone_program/faqs.html#1" />
		<title level="m">FAQs</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. AbilityOne Commission</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://data.census.gov/table/ACSDT1Y2022.B18120?q=B18120" />
		<title level="m">B18120: Employment Status by ... -Census Bureau Table</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Census Bureau</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025-06-22">June 22, 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.census.gov/acs/www/methodology/sample_size_and_data_quality/" />
		<title level="m">Sample Size and Data Quality</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Census Bureau</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025-05-27">May 27, 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Understanding and Using the American Community Survey Public Use Microdata Sample Files: What Data Users Need to Know</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.census.gov/content/dam/Census/library/publications/2021/acs/acs_pums_handbook_2021.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Census Bureau</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">U.S. Government Printing Office</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Disability Data are Collected from The American Community Survey</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/acs/methodology/sample-size-and-data-quality/sample-size-definitions.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Census.Gov</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-11-21">2021b, November 21. 2023. August 22</date>
			<publisher>html U.S. Census Bureau</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">American Community Survey and Puerto Rico Community Survey Design and Methodology Version 4</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.census.gov/topics/health/disability/about.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">acs_design_methodology_repo rt_2024.pdf US Census Bureau</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>html U.S. Census Bureau</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024. 2025. 2025b, January 7. 2025c, June 12</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Census.Gov. About Disability. Census.Gov</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Subminimum Wages: Impacts on the Civil Rights of People with Disabilities</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.usccr.gov/reports/2020/subminimum-wages-impacts-civil-rights-people-disabilities" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>U.S. Commission on Civil Rights</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Annual Statutory Enforcement, Briefing Reports</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">S. Department of Education.</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://web.archive.org/web/20241214055923/https://www.ed.gov/about/news/press-release/education-department-awards-177-million-new-grants-increase-competitive" />
		<title level="m">Education Department Awards $177 Million in New Grants to Increase Competitive Integrated Employment for People with Disabilities</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-09-21">2022. September 21</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">)_Report_to _Congress.pdf Voice of Reason</title>
		<ptr target="https://vor.net/images/stories/2020-2021/VOR_-_In_Support_of_Protecting_Vocational_Centers_and_14c_Wage_Certificates_2-4-21.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">VOR in Support of Protecting Vocational Centers and 14(c) Wage Certificates</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>S. Department of Education Office of Special Education and Rehabilitative Services</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="4" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Institute on Disability and Rehabilitation Research</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Long-Range Plan for Fiscal Section</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">tidycensus: Load US Census Boundary and Attribute Data as &quot;tidyverse&quot; and &apos;sf&apos;-Ready Data Frames (Version 1.6.5) [Computer software</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=tidycensus" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wayback</forename><surname>Machine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wayback_Machine&amp;oldid=1294949710" />
		<title level="m">Wikipedia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wickham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-319-24277-4</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-24277-4" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Imprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Generalized additive models: An introduction with R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1201/9781315370279</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1201/9781315370279" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis Group</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disability considerations during the COVID-19 outbreak</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-Disability-2020-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Health Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2020. 2019-nCoV/Disability/2020.1</date>
			<publisher>World Health Organization</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
