<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing Gaze and Hand Movement Patterns in Leader-Follower Interactions During a Time-Continuous Cooperative Manipulation Task</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Minghao</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Minija</forename><surname>Tamosiunaite</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vytautas Magnus University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kaunas</settlement>
									<country key="LT">Lithuania</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anoushiravan</forename><surname>Zahedi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Munster</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Munster</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ricarda</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Schubotz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Munster</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Munster</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">0tto-Creutzfeldt-Center of Behavioral and Cognitive Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Munster</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Munster</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Florentin</forename><surname>Worgotter</surname></persName>
							<email>worgott@gwdg.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Computational Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georg-August University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 1nst. Physics 3</addrLine>
									<settlement>Gottingen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing Gaze and Hand Movement Patterns in Leader-Follower Interactions During a Time-Continuous Cooperative Manipulation Task</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B8680EE4AA9B8F4D6CF0D45EA5AA23FA</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:57+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Humans often interact with each other during daily life and many times one finds that one person (at least for some time) takes the lead while the other follows. Different from usual experimental settings in a lab, this happens without external influences and in a time-continuous manner. While knowledge that gazes onto the object to be manipulated precede a then-following manipulation action emerged long ago, little is known how gaze-and hand movement patterns develop in c omplex interac tive sc enarios where one person needs to consider the other's action when planning their own. To address this question in this study we investigate predictive, planning-related behavior during a two-player (Leader and Follower) table-top game. In this game -c alled "do-undo" -the Leader has to perform pic k and place actions, following simple rules, to c hange the configuration of objects on the table. The Follower then has to use different objects to re-c reate the object-configuration back to the one that had existed before the Leader had acted. We track eyes, hand-movements and individual objects on the table and determine relations between eyes and hands of both players, with emphasis on the differences in behavior of Leader and Follower. Data is recorded using a setup where gaze tracking is combined with multi camera tracking of motion of the subjects and of the configuration on the table. The game proceeds without any external trigger signals and we address the problem of finding accurate time-points for phasing of the cooperative manipulation by using touch sensors on the hands of the players to record touching and untouching events by whic h we c an unequivocally define the different temporal (inter-)action intervals for analysis. While gaze clearly prec edes manipulation in all c ases, we find clear differences in eye-movement patterns of Leader and Follower. The Leader makes more and earlier gazes on the objects to be manipulated. In a substantial proportion of trials, the Leader is predic ting by his gaze not only their own, but also the required potential Follower-actions before their own manipulation. Also, the gaze data shows that the Leader takes more interest in re-checking the outcome of the do-undo manipulation pair. Indications of trying to memorize a configuration are also found in the gaze pattern of both. In addition, we often find sequenc es of alternating gazes towards objec ts and loc ation where to put, whic h are muc h more expressed by the Leader than by the Follower. Intriguingly some patterns show that players pre-plan over longer periods and not just for their next action. This clearly indicates different decision-making and planning characteristics for Leader as compared to Follower, which happen not only for own plan but also for potential action plans by the other shining a light on the complex cognitive processes that exist in daily human-human interaction.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Collaborative human-human interaction happens all the time in our daily lives, for example, when two people assemble a piece of furniture, when they fix a bike, cook a meal together. In these everyday moments of shared action, one person many times takes the lead -at least for some duration -and the other follows suit performing those actions that the leader currently does not do, to arrive at their conjoint action goals. Such interactions involve an ongoing acquisition of information by both agents, often from receiving a verbal instruction from the other but typically by using vision to find out what  Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>) Histogramsfor two situaƟons and belonging base lines. Here and in the following: when a diagram islabeled "Object" (panels A,C) it represents the gazes at that parƟcular object that is being manipulated during this episode and similarly for " LocaƟon" (see next Figure ) of where that object is being put down. Histograms are calculated to represent the number of fixaƟonsonto object or locaƟon over all parƟcipants and all objects/ locaƟons, where the ordinate isnormalized by the number of episodes analyzed (see Method secƟon). On the right side again, a schemaƟc is shown how the configuraƟon of the table looks like at the given moment in Ɵme and also what happens for Leader and Follower (touching an object, untouching t he object aŌer placing it at a new locaƟon). Hence, panel (A) leŌside belongs to t he situaƟon where the Leader touchesan object (pictogram of the small red disk) and the histogram(s) show here the start of the Leader's hand movement (black) and -as pictogrammaƟcally indicated by the eye -the staƟsƟcs of the Leader's gazes at t his object (blue). Diagrams are labeled by different acƟon-as well as inacƟvity-intervals (numbers and orange, green markers). only only not</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure1) A) Objects used in the ACA-game and their allowed configuraƟons. B) Simple example of an acƟon-counteracƟon pair (glass inverƟng). C) More complex compound acƟon example.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,102.48,641.94,390.84,88.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. A) View as seen by the camera of the eye-tracker with object bounding box and gaze-indicator (red dot) of the person in front included. This view is essenƟally idenƟcal to the way parƟcipants see the scenery. B) Eye track over Ɵme. Start of fixaƟons are marked by red dots.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,70.92,461.46,453.96,154.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,91.50,70.86,412.26,163.86" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="12,128.28,70.86,339.24,347.46" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
