<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">How does the built environment affect you? Autistic students&apos; experiences of University lecture theatres and teaching spaces</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-07-10">10 July 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">How does the built environment affect you? Autistic students&apos; experiences of University lecture theatres and teaching spaces</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-07-10">10 July 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">71C37A70F530898F512C156E8FFCDC95</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:20+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Tavassoli</term>
					<term>T.</term>
					<term>Marcham</term>
					<term>H.</term>
					<term>Harvey</term>
					<term>K</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Background: Autistic individuals often experience the sensory world differently and it is unclear how this impacts on the learning experiences of autistic university students, specifically. It is plausible that differences in sensory reactivity, such as hyperreactivity (e.g. being overwhelmed by overhead lights), affects autistic students' ability to engage with teaching. Currently, there is little empirical research exploring autistic students' experiences of teaching spaces, in particular in lecture theatres.</p><p>The aim of this study was to explore autistic university students' lived experiences of teaching spaces and how aspects of these spaces affect them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods:</head><p>We conducted a qualitative study comprising one-to-one semi-structured interviews with 10 autistic students from three UK universities. Participants were asked about the aspects of teaching spaces that affect them, the effect these aspects have, and the adaptations they would consider helpful. Data were analysed using Reflective Thematic Analysis.</p><p>Results: We identified 3 themes: Aspects of Teaching Spaces, Outcomes, and Coping Strategies and Adaptations, each of which contained sub-themes. Aspects of Teaching Spaces included sensory aspects, people, seating, screens, and predictability and control. Outcomes included physical symptoms (e.g. headaches, nausea), mood (e.g. anxiety) and cognition (e.g. attention).</p><p>Coping and Adaptations included personal coping strategies (e.g. wearing headphones, dressing in layers) and environmental modifications (e.g. have dimmer switches).</p><p>Conclusions: This study is the first to establish that the built environment of university teaching spaces affects autistic students' learning experiences. It identifies both personal and environmental modifications and adaptations that could be adopted to support university students' learning experiences. Future research should explore how differently adapted teaching spaces can best influence autistic students' wellbeing to increase positive learning experiences.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The built environment around us has an impact on our experiences and can influence our-wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Song et al., 2020)</ref>. Autistic individuals perceive the sensory environment differently from nonautistic individuals. In addition to social and communication difficulties, the most recent DSM 5 lists sensory reactivity differences under repetitive behaviours and restricted interests <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(APA, 2013)</ref>. This includes being hyperreactive (e.g. being overwhelmed by overhead lights), or hyporeactive (e.g. not noticing if being hot or cold) as well as sensory seeking (e.g. being fascinated with textures) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(APA, 2013)</ref>. It is important to note that autistic individuals have expressed that their sensory reactivity differences can bring them comfort and reassurance <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(MacLennan et al., 2022)</ref>, however they can also cause distress and anxiety and have been linked to mental health difficulties <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(MacLennan, O'Brien &amp; Tavassoli, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rossow, MacLennan &amp; Tavassoli, 2022)</ref>.</p><p>Several sensory taxonomies have been suggested such as Dunn's, <ref type="bibr">Miller's and He's (He et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Little et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Metz et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Miller et al., 2017)</ref>. We follow the most recent taxonomy by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">He et al. (2023)</ref> and sensory reactivity differences are described here depending on the level of analysis. Relevant to this study is the level of affective reactivity (how someone feels about the sensory world, e.g. feeling irritated by bright lights in a lecture theatre) and behavioural responsivity (how someone reacts towards sensory stimuli e.g. leaving the lecture theatre when noises are too overwhelming) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(He et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Given that sensory reactivity differences are common in autism and are seen in up to 95% of autistic adults <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(MacLennan et al., 2022)</ref> there is growing acknowledgement of the need to design more accessible environments for autistic and neurodivergent individuals <ref type="bibr">(Goldsmiths, n.d.)</ref>. One of the authors (TT) was involved in design guidance for 'housing for autistic adults' <ref type="bibr">(Brand, n.d.)</ref>.</p><p>Recommendations from this housing guidance for the home environment were to consider: environmental triggers; robustness of designs; environments that allow growth and development; and supporting tools. In relation to environmental triggers, sensory sensitivities to colours, noises, textures were identified as important. Designing consistent, low-arousing environments with appropriate lighting, acoustics, and ventilation, with the aim of minimising sensory overload is recommended. Moreover, providing stimulation for residents who seek out sensations, offering private spaces and environments in which stimulation can be calibrated, providing a sense of control and considering the properties of floors.</p><p>In addition to Brand's recommendations, there have been other built environment guidance. A frontrunner focussing on the built environment is Dr. Mustafa, who created The Autism ASPECTSS™ Design Index <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Mostafa, 2014)</ref> as a design guide for environments for autistic people.</p><p>It consists of seven principles: acoustics, spatial sequencing, escape space, compartmentalization, transition zones, sensory zoning and safety. The index is based on surveys of around 100 families and their views of the most impacting sensory environment difficulties. Mostafa (2019) also developed a university design guidance, based on online surveys for autistic students and focus groups with academic staff. Some of the findings identified challenges with higher education teaching spaces such as bright lights in lecture halls and noisy projectors. Challenges in other areas included public spaces and transitions, it was reported that signage and navigation was difficult to use and hindered the location of buildings and rooms. Further, a more recent review by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Tola et al. (2021)</ref> summarises previous work on design guidance, with a focus on sensory hyperreactivity. The three main resulting design recommendations were the following: "sensory quality" (how to reduce the impact of sensory stimuli), "intelligibility" (space being easily understood and clear) and "predictability" (creating an environment that is easy to navigate with visual supports such as signs).</p><p>Further three categories that relate to recommendations more generally were suggested, "identification of a quiet and accessible location", "safety and security" and "flexibility and customisation".</p><p>The British Standard Institute (BSI) also came up with design guidance including (Design for the <ref type="bibr">Mind-Neurodiversity and the Built Environment-Guide Publishing and Copyright Information, 2022)</ref>.</p><p>The BSI PAS covers lighting, acoustics, décor, flooring, layout, wayfinding, familiarity, clarity, safety, thermal comfort, odour, preview of an environment and other sensory design considerations. There is more specific guidance, such as from the NHS for healthcare settings ("It's Not Rocket Science"</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Considering and Meeting the Sensory Needs of Autistic Children and Young People in CAMHS</head><p>Inpatient <ref type="bibr">Services, 2020)</ref>. In this guide, published by the NHS, recommendations are related to making environments more predictable, involving autistic individuals in design decisions, swapping alarms for silent alarms, to reduce noise and the impact of smells and touch and textures. Despite the movement in design recommendations, it is unclear if these are being put into practice (Van der Linden, Dong &amp; Heylighen, 2016). Furthermore, to our knowledge only limited research has explored the experiences of autistic students in higher education settings. One study found that autistic university students report how environmental aspects, such as volume levels and number of people can mean they are unable to attend social events, increasing feeling of loneliness <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Madriaga, 2010)</ref>. Given that the prevalence of autism is higher than 1% and, in the UK, 2.4% of our university students are autistic, better understanding their learning experiences is a crucial step to improve their higher education experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Madriaga &amp; Goodley, 2010)</ref>. To address the need for a better understanding of autistic students learning experiences, we conducted a qualitative study which aimed to explore autistic students' perceptions and experiences of the built environment of university teaching spaces such as lecture theatres and classrooms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>The study was approved by the University of Reading Research Ethics Committee (2023-004-TT) and is reported in accordance with the Consolidated Criteria for Reporting Qualitative Research (COREQ) checklist <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Tong et al., 2007)</ref>. The research team comprised three members all of whom were female: TT who is an experienced autism researcher specialising in sensory reactivity; HM who is a doctoral researcher investigating sensory differences and impact of indoor environment and who has experience in supporting autistic children with high support needs in residential and educational settings; and KH who is does not work in the field of autism but contributed extensive expertise in qualitative methodologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>Participants were eligible if they attended a UK university and had either a clinical diagnosis of autism, or had been identified as autistic and were on an NHS waiting list for an autism diagnosis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recruitment</head><p>All students at a UK university (University A) were emailed with study information explaining that the researchers were interesting in investigating autistic students' perceptions and experiences of the built environment of university teaching spaces. Those who met the eligibility criteria were invited to participate by contacting the researchers. All students who expressed an interest and met the eligibility criteria were included. Snowball sampling was then used, whereby some of those who received the information forwarded it to their contacts at other universities (Universities B and C).</p><p>All ten students who expressed an interest participated in the study. Table <ref type="table">1</ref> shows the sample characteristics, highlighting the diversity among participants in relation to the key characteristics of age, sex, autism diagnosis, university attending, and degree stage. </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1 21 f diagnosed A UG2 2 22 f diagnosed A UG3 3 19 f diagnosed A Foundation 4 24 f diagnosed A UG3 5 26 f diagnosed B UG3 6 20 f awaiting A UG1 7 20 f awaiting A UG3 8 49 f diagnosed C PGT 9 23 m diagnosed A UG2 10 22 m diagnosed A UG2</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedure</head><p>One-to-one semi-structured interviews were conducted via MS Teams by TT; each lasted between 20 and 40 minutes. Online interviews were chosen because they were judged to be more accessible and inclusive for autistic students because they could be in their own environment and could choose whether or not to have the video camera on. A Topic Guide (Supplementary Materials 1) was developed based on relevant research, the researchers' expertise, and previous design guidance.</p><p>Questions were asked one at a time and participants were advised that they could take a break if they needed to. Auto-produced transcripts were edited for accuracy and anonymised. Information power was used to judge the sufficiency of the sample size <ref type="bibr">(Malterud et al. 2015)</ref>; given the study aim, the specificity of the sample, the richness of interviews and the analytical approach, it was judged that ten interviews were sufficient to address the research question.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Analysis</head><p>Data were analysed using Reflective Thematic Analysis (RTA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Braun &amp; Clarke, 2021)</ref>; an essentialist/realist epistemological approach was adopted which assumes that participants use language to express their experience and meaning <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Potter &amp; Wetherell, 1987)</ref>. Data analysis followed the six stages of RTA outlined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Braun &amp; Clarke (2021)</ref>. The analysis was led by TT who met regularly with HM and KH to discuss codes, candidate themes, and alternative interpretations of the data. NVivo was used to facilitate coding <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Lumivero, 2023)</ref>. Initial coding was undertaken by one coder (TT) and followed Braun &amp; Clarke's six steps (C. Braun, 2021; V. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Braun &amp; Clarke, 2006)</ref>],</p><p>Candidate themes were discussed in coding meetings (TT, HM &amp; KH) during which themes and sub-themes were reviewed and refined to ensure the thematic structure provided a coherent and credible interpretation of the data that did not only reflect a single researcher's perspective <ref type="bibr">(Braun and Clark, 2022)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Three themes were developed, each with sub-themes: 1) Aspects of Teaching Spaces; 2)</p><p>Outcomes and 3) Coping Strategies and Adaptations (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Physical Aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Space</head><p>Participants described space in and outside of the lecture theatre as of crucial importance, affecting their mood and wellbeing:</p><p>Because that be very overwhelming and there's a lot of chitchat beforehand and the space outside the lecture theatres tends to be quite small and cramped, and everyone's kind of huddling.(P09)</p><p>I do like to have a lot of space because you can feel kind of irritated when you're waiting for a break and there's not a lot of foot space in the lecture theatre, I feel. I think that's one thing I didn't really like. (P01)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Seating</head><p>Seating was mentioned as a problem when space is restricted:</p><p>I guess I would like to start would like the idea of the seating and sometimes if it's very compact that could be, you know more and more like the one row in front of the other. That could be quite claustrophobic in a way. And feels like everything's touching. (P03)</p><p>It's very picky, but I don't like lecture theatres where the rows so you have to shuffle along a whole row.(P05)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Screens</head><p>The number of screens in the lecture theatre were often mentioned, mostly highlighting that the number of screens and their locations can be distracting: </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">I</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control and Predictability</head><p>Participants reported that it was easier to deal with environmental factors if they were within their control and more difficult if they were outside of their control or unpredictable. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>And in terms of</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mood</head><p>Participants described the impact the built environment can have on their mood as well as a bidirectional relationship between sensory effects of the environment and mood, for example with sounds in the environment overwhelming them but their mood also impacting their sensitivity to sound.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>It makes feel like tense. Like, feel very tense.(P2)</head><p>I think the echoing it can be a bit much sometimes, but mostly when I'm anxious... Like I said, whenever I'm feeling anxious, I feel like it's this effect is enhanced.(P1)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Physical Symptoms</head><p>Respondents described the environment as impacting their physical state, for example dizziness, nausea, headache and appetite loss and, in an extreme case, vomiting:</p><p>So I think, yes, sometimes they're too bright and it could, like, give me headaches and stuff.</p><p>(P02)</p><p>It could also impact sometimes like my desire or like want to eat food as well.(P5)</p><p>I feel just really uncomfortable and not able to eat lunch if it's like directly afterwards. (P3)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cognition</head><p>The environment also affected participants cognitive functioning, including the ability to focus, pay attention and concentrate.: They also described used timing as a coping strategy, arriving either early or slightly late to avoid crowds of people entering at the same time. Some participants found the only effective coping approach was to leave the lecture theatre for a break.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">And</formula><p>And yeah, I usually arrive kind of later so that I'm not in that busy space. And then I tend to not be like sensory overloaded, (if there) not too long before the lecture begins. (P1)</p><p>I had (to leave) the two or three times... because my head just felt so full.(P1)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adaptations</head><p>Participants suggested aspects of the environment that could be adapted to make it more enabling.</p><p>Relating to the Sensory Aspects theme, where artificial heat and clinical lights were described negatively, the introduction of natural features were described positively, for example natural </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Autistic students were asked directly about their experiences of the built environment teaching spaces in higher educational settings and described Aspects of Teaching Spaces; Outcomes; and</p><p>Coping Strategies and Adaptations. While some of these themes align with previous design guidance and recommendations <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Mostafa, 2014</ref><ref type="bibr">(Mostafa, , 2019) )</ref> others are specific to the learning environment of university classrooms and teaching spaces, namely lecture theatre seating arrangements and the amount of screens in a classroom.</p><p>In relation to aspects of teaching spaces, several sensory aspects of lecture theatres were reported by autistic students in this study as distracting and overwhelming, such as bright lights, echoey rooms, smells, textures of seats. As identified in the 'housing design for autistic adults' booklet codeveloped by on of the authors (TT), sensory triggers were mentioned, such as colours, textures and smells <ref type="bibr">(Brand, n.d.)</ref>. As Mustafa pointed out in her ASPECTs guidance, designers should consider acoustics as well <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Mostafa, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Here the examples provided by autistic students were more specific to lecture theatres that you experience when attending classes at a University. For example, the glare that some tables or screens have, the amount of screens in a classroom, the sound of typing when other students are taking notes. Notably, participants described the importance of control and predictability, noting that teaching spaces did not create difficulties for them when they were able to have some. This is in line with both Tola (2021) and MacLennan's findings highlighting the importance of creating predictable environments. Given that lecture theatres are shared spaces, control over lighting or volume poses challenges but participants' comments indicate that a lack of control may be ameliorated if the room does not change over time.</p><p>This indicates that consistency in room allocation and enabling students to become familiar with the room before the lecture starts could be supportive. This would further allow autistic students as well as non-autistic students to identify what support or adaptations may be needed within a given classroom, e.g. dressing in layers for rooms that are on the warmer side.</p><p>In their recent study investigating autistic adults' sensory experiences, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">MacLennan et al. (2022)</ref> found outcomes could be categorised as short term (e.g. overwhelm) and long-term (e.g. mental and physical health challenges) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(MacLennan et al., 2022)</ref>. In this study participants reported outcomes that were short term, for example that the environment of the lecture theatre influenced their mood (e.g. being irritated) and cognition (e.g. not being able to concentrate, zoning out) and also produced physical outcomes such as feeling nausea and headaches. While these outcomes were shorter lived compared to long term outcomes such as mental health challenges, some autistic students said the rest of their day could negatively impacted by spending time in a sensory unfriendly environment. University life was also compared to school life where it was more difficult as there were fewer breaks and less independence. Thus, for some autistic students having the chance to leave the lecture theatre when required seems beneficial and should be incorporated into learning practices. Increasing awareness among teaching staff of how sensory aspects of the environment can affect autistic students could improve autistic students learning experiences.</p><p>A novel aspect to this study was that autistic students' coping strategies were explored. Students described using personal coping strategies, such as adjusting their clothes, using headphones and timing their attendance. Based on this, one recommendation for better supporting autistic students may be for sensory toolkits to be made available in teaching spaces so that students could borrow sensory equipment if required.</p><p>Aligning with <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Tola et al's (2021)</ref> suggestion for 'flexibility and customisation' <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Tola et al., 2021)</ref>.</p><p>environmental adaptations based on participants' experiences may also be possible to adopt in current teaching spaces, for example dimmer switches, and adjustable artificial heat. Some of the arising issues described by participants related to teaching spaces being shared environments, and some autistic students mentioned the advantages of being able to listen to recordings in their own home where they can control the amount of light, heat and noise better then in a shared lecture theatre. Recording lectures thus could be a beneficial as autistic students could review recordings once in their own environments. Many adaptations suggested by autistic students could potentially be beneficial for non-autistic students as well and should not hinder learning for anyone. A lecture theatre that is too hot can affect everyone's learning, thus recommendations could be effective more broadly. Future studies should explore the impact of teaching spaces on non-autistic students.</p><p>In conclusion, this study describes autistic students' experiences of the lecture theatre environment at University. Its findings should be used to guide those who design university teaching spaces as well as university teachers. Furthermore, future experimental work should involve experimentally manipulating the environment (e.g. changing brightness of the room) to see if it can improve autistic students learning so that in future teaching spaces can be improved and made flexible to support different learners within a higher education environment.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: This figure illustrates what aspects of teaching spaces (sensory, physical layout, social aspects, control/predictability) affect autistic students, how they are affected (outcomes), and how they might be supported to cope (coping strategies and adaptations).</figDesc><graphic coords="7,66.00,38.27,465.75,305.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Theme 1: Aspects of Teaching Spaces Sensory Aspects Sounds</head><label></label><figDesc>But look, if people are stuck in a room for several hours at a time, it's gonna get a smell. So if it gets like hot and stuffy as well.P05</figDesc><table><row><cell>Lighting</cell></row><row><cell>Most participants also described the lighting negatively:</cell></row><row><cell>I think sometimes like the lights like they're quite bright. (P02)</cell></row><row><cell>And then the light… there's a glare on the screen. (P03)</cell></row><row><cell>Temperature</cell></row><row><cell>Temperature was mentioned by several participants, mostly in relation to the room being too</cell></row><row><cell>warm:</cell></row><row><cell>So yeah, that's temperature as well, so normally I get too hot in lecture theatres because</cell></row><row><cell>Proprioception</cell></row><row><cell>Proprioceptive issues were mentioned, such as clumsiness affecting the experience of walking up</cell></row><row><cell>and down aisles:</cell></row><row><cell>I think it's because that the stairs are always weirdly shallow, so my feet aren't as this is</cell></row><row><cell>gonna sound silly, but my feet aren't as used to walking down incredibly shallow steps, so</cell></row><row><cell>I'm always worried. I'm gonna like, trip.(P05)</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p>Sounds were described by every participant as distracting, including echoes, sounds made by other people such as tapping, and wall clocks ticking: So I would say that the noise within the room has had an effect on me. Sometimes the echoing that can happen in the hall.... I find myself like being distracted by the sound compared to like what is said. So like I'm too busy focused on the sound of it instead of focusing on what is being said by the lecturer. [P1] But like you know, sometimes I have clocks on the walls and you can hear the ticking. So I don't know like that because it's just like not everyone can hear it, but I can hear it and it's just like, very distracting and repetitive and yeah.(P2) I'm very overly sensitive to overheating. (P05) And definitely temperature 100%. Usually on the most high temperature. So if if the room is too warm... in winter. So if it's, if it's like a fake heat..(P03)</p>Touch and Texture</p>Touch and texture were mentioned by participants, but the experience varied. Seats were described by some as too soft :</p>We usually have hard seats, whereas sometimes in lectures they have weird soft seats and that can be quite itchy and just not very comfortable. (P03) So, like I tend to be very clumsy and like drop things a lot and I think when again when I'm in an area with tight space and…, it can be quite difficult because it creates again I don't like it. So it's like I think fine motor skills. I end up just dropping stuff and it gets very frustrating. (P07) Smell Odours, for example caused by bins or others in the room, were described by participants as noticeable and aversive:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>You've got screens on both sides, right? So usually they'll be some sort of slides. If you set anywhere in the middle, you're kind of like looking diagonally. Then if you sit on the right,</figDesc><table><row><cell>the teacher won't be standing on the right, but you'll be able to stare at the screen, stand on</cell></row><row><cell>the left. You're making direct eye contact with the teacher.(P9)</cell></row><row><cell>Social Aspects</cell></row><row><cell>People</cell></row><row><cell>Participants described other students as a cause of distraction and distress for a range of reasons:</cell></row></table><note><p>think this too many screens like I think I don't think it needs that many screens to be honest. So maybe if there was less screens, it would be better as well because it's like I have my laptop, I have the lecture on my laptop and then I see the same slide on like probably like six other screens (P01) Like 'cos a lecture hall has a lot of other people. So there's so many other things to look at, to be distracted by. I wanna space myself out from my friends, cause it's kind of like rude and stuff, but I will have to sit next to them and the seats are quite close, so I guess, but I don't really like to be too close to people. (P01) ...like with like noise and stuff like I think, I mean it's not really something about the actual lecture theatre. Just like, you know, other people are talking over like the lecture like other people have their own conversation. I can find that a bit like distracting, annoying sometimes, but it's not really anything to do with the actual, like, theatre itself. (P02) I do not like that, so I'm very aware of, like other people coughing or just shifting in their seats or talking. (P05)</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>to an extent, a lecture a certain seminar. We've got a room, so when it kind of like....So when I had like a lecture where they would like to change the room every week... It felt like I was always going into unfamiliar territory...This is annoying as well, but when like one week I'm bringing round and taking into a building we've never been before.</figDesc><table><row><cell>And then it can kind of become like more of warning because it's like I'm suddenly going</cell></row><row><cell>somewhere, which is, like, completely unfamiliar....P07</cell></row><row><cell>I feel like the softness (of the seats) is getting on to me and there might there might be like</cell></row><row><cell>crumbs or sensations that I can't see or control. So it kind of increases my feeling of</cell></row><row><cell>uncertainty. And whereas if it's something hard, I can easily feel my body sitting and yeah, I</cell></row><row><cell>just feel like I have more control over my body in the space. And how that impacts my</cell></row><row><cell>learning. Well, I guess I would be less I'll be more attentive to the lecturer and broader than</cell></row><row><cell>like how I I might feel more like uncertain and anxious, yeah.P09</cell></row><row><cell>Theme 2: Outcomes</cell></row></table><note><p>the spacing and feeling crowded, I can try and mitigate that by going at the front or at the edge or just avoiding other people, whereas the big ones like the lights and the noise and the temperature and the ventilation, you can't really do anything about.(P05) But I always liked it when there was kind of like a consistency in terms of rooms. So I'm not sure how related to stability, but I think there's like, so that's quite a relevant because I kind of always associated</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Apa</forename><surname>References</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Living in the Community Housing Design for Adults with Autism The Kingwood Trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.hhc.rca.ac.uk" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Thematic analysis: a practical guide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using thematic analysis in psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1191/1478088706qp063oa</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1191/1478088706qp063oa" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qualitative Research in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can I use TA? Should I use TA? Should I not use TA? Comparing reflexive thematic analysis and other pattern-based qualitative analytic approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/capr.12360</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/capr.12360" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Couns Psychother Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design for the mind-Neurodiversity and the built environment-Guide Publishing and copyright information</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Goldsmiths</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/257536232" />
		<title level="m">Designing inclusive environments and the significance of universal design</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A working taxonomy for describing the sensory differences of autism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schaaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tavassoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A J</forename><surname>Puts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s13229-022-00534-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13229-022-00534-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular Autism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">It&apos;s Not Rocket Science&quot; Considering and meeting the sensory needs of autistic children and young people in CAMHS inpatient services</title>
		<ptr target="www.ndti.org.uk" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tomchek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01942638.2017.1390809</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01942638.2017.1390809" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sensory Processing Patterns in Autism, Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, and Typical Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="254" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lumivero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>14) www.lumivero.com</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In Our Own Words: The Complex Sensory Experiences of Autistic Adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Maclennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>O'brien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tavassoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10803-021-05186-3</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-021-05186-3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3061" to="3075" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moving beyond the minimum: Socially just pedagogies and Asperger&apos;s syndrome in UK higher education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Madriaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goodley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13603110802504168</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13603110802504168" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Inclusive Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sample Size in Qualitative Interview Studies: Guided by Information Power</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Malterud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Siersma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Guassora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1049732315617444</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qualitative Health Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1753" to="1760" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dunn&apos;s model of sensory processing: An investigation of the axes of the four-quadrant model in healthy adults running head: Dunn&apos;s model of sensory processing in healthy adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Metz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Boling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Devore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Holladay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vlutch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/brainsci9020035</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/brainsci9020035" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of Sensory Processing and Integration Symptom Clusters: A Preliminary Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schoen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mulligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2017/2876080</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/2876080" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Occupational Therapy International</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Architecture for autism: Autism aspectss TM in school design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mostafa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.26687/archnet-ijar.v8i1.314</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.26687/archnet-ijar.v8i1.314" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Archnet-IJAR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Discourse and social psychology: Beyond attitudes and behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Potter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wetherell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Sage Publications, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neighbourhood built Environment, physical activity, and physical health among older adults in Singapore: A simultaneous equations approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yuen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jth.2020.100881</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jth.2020.100881" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Transport and Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): a 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sainsbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/intqhc/mzm042</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/intqhc/mzm042" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal for Quality in Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Built environment design and people with autism spectrum disorder (Asd): A scoping review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Talu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Congiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lindert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/ijerph18063203</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18063203" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
