<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Intersectional perspectives on technology-facilitated sexualized violence: A mixedmethods investigation of post-secondary institution materials</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Flora</forename><surname>Oswald</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Connecticut</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Storrs</settlement>
									<country>Connecticut</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Amanda</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Champion</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Criminology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Simon Fraser University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Burnaby</settlement>
									<country>British Columbia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kwantlen Polytechnic University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Surrey</settlement>
									<region>British Columbia</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sean</forename><surname>Pearson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Criminology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Simon Fraser University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Burnaby</settlement>
									<country>British Columbia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cory</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pedersen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kwantlen Polytechnic University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Surrey</settlement>
									<region>British Columbia</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Intersectional perspectives on technology-facilitated sexualized violence: A mixedmethods investigation of post-secondary institution materials</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0266E11A8DB88F610C33FD14EB1358B2</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>disparities</term>
					<term>qualitative methodology</term>
					<term>environmental scan</term>
					<term>university context</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Introduction: Technology-facilitated sexualized violence (TFSV) is a growing concern in educational, public health, and public policy spaces, with severe implications for health and wellbeing. In particular, young adults are at particularly high risk of TFSV victimization, which is compounded by structural sexism, heterosexism, colonialism, racism, and additional forms of oppression. Applied research on current TFSV educational awareness, prevention, and intervention materials/resources available for post-secondary students and employees (e.g., staff, administrators, and faculty) is lacking. Methods: In late 2022 and early 2023, we conducted an environmental scan of TFSV resources at 25 public post-secondary institutions (PSIs) in British Columbia, Canada. The purpose was to identify TFSV-specific institutional materials/resources including support services for TFSV victim-survivors and educational training/resources on TFSV victimization (e.g., response workshops, awareness campaigns, etc.). In addition, our environmental scan examined intersectional considerations among TFSV resources. Results: We identified an overwhelming lack of TFSV-specific resources, with only one PSI indicating any such resources. Follow-up interviews with PSI employees in sexualized violence responding roles (N = 6) confirmed a dearth of institutional TFSV information and resources. Conclusion: We identified a pressing need for additional funding to support the development and implementation of TFSV-specific resources, particularly those incorporating intersectional frameworks. Policy Implications: To reduce the harms associated with TFSV, which are shaped by systems of oppression, we call for the development of "living" TFSV resources, centralization of these resources, increased funding for professional development and policy implementation, and the incorporation and valuation of intersectional praxis at all stages of policy development and implementation.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intersectional perspectives on technology-facilitated sexualized violence: A mixedmethods investigation of post-secondary institution materials</head><p>As technology increasingly permeates our social lives, experiences of technologyfacilitated sexualized violence (TFSV) and abuse are increasing <ref type="bibr">(Powell &amp; Henry, 2017)</ref>. Such incidents are referred to as revenge porn, sextortion, doxing, etc., and carry adverse consequences for victim-survivors<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> , ranging from embarrassment, humiliation, depression, anxiety, helplessness, and substance use to self-harm and suicide (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bates, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Champion et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Snaychuk &amp; O'Neill, 2020)</ref>. A recent study conducted with a Canadian sample of university students revealed extremely high rates of TFSV victimization (defined broadly) spanning from 74% for male students to 88% for female students <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Snaychuk &amp; O'Neill, 2020)</ref>. Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Champion et al. (2021)</ref> reported that being a victim-survivor of TFSV "increased levels of suicide risk significantly through experiences with increased bullying victimization, which subsequently increased depression symptomology, and, as a result, increased feelings of burdensomeness" among a sample of adults (p. 11). These significant negative outcomes render TFSV an emerging concern for spaces including public health, public policy, and education <ref type="bibr">(Patel &amp; Roesch, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Though campus sexual violence is a prominent current concern <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Colpitts, 2022)</ref>, TFSV is an underacknowledged risk. This is in part due to traditional understandings of violence which center physical harm and thus trivialize digitally-mediated harms <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Bailey &amp; Burkell, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Henry &amp; Powell, 2015)</ref> in tandem with individualistic framings of violence and perpetration which depoliticize violence and undermine attention to systemic factors shaping vulnerability and resource access <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Colpitts, 2022)</ref>. However, the high severity and prevalence of TFSV, particularly among university students (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Snaychuk &amp; O'Neill, 2020)</ref> necessitates institutional responses; for educational institutions, this may include strategies such as public health campaigns, educational awareness, and school policies <ref type="bibr">(Patel &amp; Roesch, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>In the current study, we sought to understand how educational institutions in one Canadian province, British Columbia (BC), are responding to increasing rates of and concerns surrounding TFSV. We conducted an environmental scan of the TFSV resources currently available at 25 public post-secondary institutions (PSIs) in BC, Canada. We critically assessed (a) the presence of TFSV resources (e.g., trainings, support services) and (b) whether and how TFSV materials adopted an intersectional approach. We sought to understand how these resources engaged with TFSV's roots in broader systems of oppression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluating TFSV Resources</head><p>Evaluations of sexualized violence trainings in Canadian university contexts suggest that university-based resources can be effective in reducing the incidence and severity of harms relating to sexualized violence generally (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Senn, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Senn et al., 2015)</ref>, though such evaluations also note a lack of intersectional engagement among such resources, diminishing their capacity for transformative structural change <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Colpitts, 2022)</ref>. Intersectional approaches to sexualized violence, and to TFSV in particular, are necessary to account for its roots in systemic oppression and to highlight how oppressive forces shape uneven distributions of risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Carbado et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Crenshaw, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Colpitts, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Rajani, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Roskin-Frazee, 2020)</ref>. Intersectional approaches have the capacity to re-politicize technology-facilitated forms of violence and situate them in broader discourses surrounding violence, domination, and oppression <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Rajani, 2022)</ref>.</p><p>An intersectional lens that conceptualizes TFSV incidents as both a mechanism and an outcome of existing power hierarchies and can interrogate structural-level interventions and responses, including those necessitated by institutional-level university policies and resources.</p><p>We thus sought to examine whether and how institutions engaged intersectionality in their TFSV-related policies and materials (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Colpitts, 2022)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Current Study</head><p>We conducted an environmental scan of the TFSV resources currently available at 25 public PSIs in BC, Canada to identify TFSV-specific resources at various PSIs that take the form of support services for TFSV victim-survivors and educational resources on TFSV victimization (e.g., response workshops, awareness campaigns, etc.). In addition, we examined intersectional considerations among the existing TFSV response or educational resources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methodology</head><p>We conducted an environmental scan as needs-assessment tool for gathering information about existing materials and identifying gaps in institutional resources <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Albright, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rowel et al., 2005)</ref>. We first conducted content analyses of existing resources (e.g., website information) and then conducted follow-up interviews with key informants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sampling</head><p>We identified all public PSIs (N = 25, see OSM for full list) in BC using information from the Government of B.C.'s "Find an Institution" webpage. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">2</ref> We visited each PSI's website to compile a list of key contacts holding positions responsible for sexual violence education and awareness, and counseling services. Based on this search, we identified 67 key contacts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Part A: Content Analysis of Online Materials</head><p>In December 2022, we screened each PSI's website for resources relevant to TFSV.</p><p>Our primary outcomes of interest in this content analysis were: (a) whether institutions described materials/resources relevant to TFSV; (b) if yes, what type of materials/resources were available; and (c) whether institutions engaged intersectionality in these materials (e.g., by acknowledging systemic oppression as a contributing factor to violence and victimization).</p><p>Coding of website data was completed in a structured excel sheet (see OSM).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Part B: Informational Interviews</head><p>Our list of PSI key contacts (N = 67; 50 individuals and 17 general department emails)</p><p>were sent an email request to complete an initial brief information-gathering online survey through Qualtrics. The purpose of this survey was to individualize semi-structured interview questions to ask during a follow-up interview. The initial information-gathering survey of PSIs consisted of 10 closed-and open-ended questions regarding awareness of TFSV-specific resources, materials, or programming targeted specifically toward TFSV (see OSM). A total of 17 (68%) PSI contacts completed our initial information-gathering survey.</p><p>Fourteen of the 17 (82%) PSI key contacts who completed the initial survey were sent a request via email to participate in a 30-minute informational interview with our research team. Of the 14 survey completions, we received nine interview-request responses. Six participants consented to participate in interviews (67%); three participants were not interviewed due to a lack of knowledge of TFSV materials at their schools, and the remaining five did not respond to our repeated requests for a follow-up interview.. Interviews focused on whether and how TFSV training prepared service providers for dealing with issues unique to marginalized populations, whether available resources or educational materials adopted an intersectional perspective (i.e., understanding the multiplicative nature of violence, oppression, and discrimination associated with interconnecting identities), and the perceived strengths and weaknesses of existing TFSV training approaches, allowing us to conduct a gap analysis and provide recommendations. The interviews also solicited input concerning possible improvements to existing training resources. All interviews were conducted by the second author via online conferencing software. The full list of semistructured interview questions for PSIs with and without TFSV training and resources are available in OSM.</p><p>Once the six interviews were completed, relevant information was extracted and entered into an Excel spreadsheet and, using thematic analysis <ref type="bibr">(Braun &amp; Clarke, 2006)</ref>, qualitatively analyzed by the first and second authors for deductive and inductive common themes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings Part A: Content Analysis of Online Materials</head><p>We sought to examine (a) whether institutions described materials/resources relevant to TFSV; (b) if yes, what type of materials/resources were available; and (c) whether institutions engaged intersectionality in these materials.</p><p>We first scrutinized whether institutional definitions of sexualized violence incorporated TFSV. We found that 100% (n = 25) of institutions incorporated TFSV into their formal definitions of sexualized violence/sexual misconduct, suggesting that all of our PSIs note a responsibility to respond to incidences of TFSV in their communities. Despite this acknowledgement and incorporation of TFSV into PSI policies, we identified only one PSI (4%) that indicated or presented on their website any materials or resources specific to TFSV. Simon Fraser University (SFU) had both informational resources (online blog posts) as well as information about an in-person workshop, offered by request, which seeks to: "Define the concepts of cyberconsent and technology-facilitated sexual violence; Identify strategies to set and maintain digital boundaries and to respect others' boundaries; <ref type="bibr">[and]</ref> Gain awareness of relevant resources and support services at SFU and in the community." 3 These offerings did not indicate an explicit intersectional lens; however, SFU's general materials on sexual violence indicate a "culturally sensitive" lens to responding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Part B: Informational Interviews</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Initial Information-Gathering Survey</head><p>Seventeen PSIs responded to the survey of the 25 we contacted (68%). In contrast to the findings of our content analysis, nearly 59% (n = 10) of responding institutions indicated that they were aware of TFSV materials at their institutions. Furthermore, approximately 65% (n = 11) indicated that their institution had managed cases of TFSV in the past. Of the 10 PSIs that 3 https://www.sfu.ca/sexual-violence/education-prevention/request-a-workshop.html indicated having/using TFSV-specific materials, four indicated TFSV workshops for employees, two indicated TFSV training manuals or documents for employees, one indicated TFSV training videos for employees, five indicated TFSV workshops, one indicated TFSV manuals, four indicated website resources for students, nine specified TFSV internal resources for students (e.g., counselling services, etc.), and eight specified TFSV external resources for students (e.g., links to community organizations).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interviews</head><p>Our thematic analysis of interview data identified three major themes and seven subthemes associated with PSI's current TFSV materials, training, and resources. We labelled the themes as follows: (a) Conceptual Challenges in Incorporating TFSV, (b) Practical Challenges and Opportunities in Incorporating TFSV, and (c) Intersectional Challenges and Opportunities in Incorporating TFSV. Table <ref type="table">1</ref> presents the structure of the themes and related subthemes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theme 1: Conceptual Challenges in Incorporating TFSV</head><p>Participants identified several challenges unique to the nature of TFSV as an evolving phenomenon. Specifically, participants articulated challenges regarding the pervasive and everevolving nature of TFSV and TFSV-related impacts, definitional clarity, and problematic issues embedded in TFSV investigations and evidence gathering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subtheme: TFSV as a Subcategory of Sexualized Violence</head><p>Many participants explained that TFSV at their respective PSI was covered under existing broad sexual violence and misconduct policies. Several participants spoke about how incidents of TFSV are given the same level of rigorous investigation, attention, student support, resources, and accommodation plans as any other form of sexualized violence. Even so, many PSIs noted the need for more comprehensive TFSV-specific educational materials and victimsurvivor resources within their current sexualized violence materials and resources, and recognized the uniqueness of incidents of TFSV, including distinctive issues with disclosure, investigations, and support resources.</p><p>In some cases, participants mentioned an underlying misconception of TFSV incidents, especially among students; TFSV may be perceived as less serious than other forms of sexualized violence because of the technological component. Several participants noted that TFSV is "new to them [students]" and potentially not discussed in educational settings prior to college/university, potentially leaving students with the impression that TFSV is not taken seriously by educational institutions. Many students may be unaware of the channels through which TFSV cases can be managed or the re-victimization potential of TFSV (e.g., sexual images may be captured online indefinitely creating the potential for re-traumatization in the future). Thus, awareness, education, and accessible reporting are particularly important areas to address for TFSV, which in our estimation should begin even at the high school institutional level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subtheme: The Need for "Living" Definitions and Materials for TFSV</head><p>A salient concern among participants was defining clearly the concept of TFSV. TFSV was perceived to be an evasive concept, difficult to define, and including many different forms of sexualized and gender-based violence facilitated through various technologies and platforms.</p><p>Participants recommended that a "living definition" be constructed on a centralized portal with "agreed upon" definitions and examples that all PSIs can access. Examples were noted as particularly important given the multifarious nature of TFSV; examples included in definitions were seen as providing grounding and specificity for defining the complex nature of the phenomenon.</p><p>Participants recommended that in order to "stay ahead of the curve", TFSV materials be kept updated and continuously modified as the nature of TFSV evolves, as digital platforms and technologies change, and as complex cases arise. Further, though many PSIs have been resourceful in drawing upon external resources to bridge gaps in TFSV resources, participants noted that this strategy proves resource-demanding, as URLs to external resources need to be consistently monitored to circumvent broken webpage links. Participants thus indicated that inhouse resources, or resources drawn from a centralized repository with consistent updating, were necessary to ensure that materials were accessible when needed. However, participants also indicated a need for definitions to be flexible for adaptation purposes. As new technologies have evolved, including artificial intelligence platforms which can generate images potentially falling under the scope of TFSV, definitions and materials must also evolve to encompass these technologies, enabling PSIs to respond appropriately to a wide variety of possible situations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subtheme: Challenges with Investigating TFSV Complaints</head><p>Participants reported complex challenges surrounding TFSV investigations. For example, evidence gathering on cases of TFSV usually included screenshots on numerous different platforms, which are impossible to authenticate. Also, participants disclosed a lack of access to information on third-party platforms and the need for cybersecurity consultants in certain cases of TFSV. PSIs were unlikely to have the resources necessary to manage these challenges and fully investigate TFSV cases in-house. Some additional TFSV case considerations centered around the nature of TFSV as not tied to a particular location; for example, (1) TFSV incidents being unrelated to campus activities; (2) TFSV incidents occurring among individuals who had never been on university property; and (3) TFSV incidents taking place prior to official student status. All participants understood that the PSI was responsible for supporting and accommodating students regardless of these challenges in order to promote successful post-secondary completion and facilitate student mental, physical, and social well-being. However, the fluid and potentially remote nature of TFSV posed novel challenges to PSIs, necessitating re-examination of the university's role and scope in investigating incidences of sexualized violence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theme 2: Practical Challenges and Opportunities in Incorporating TFSV</head><p>Participants identified four salient practical dimensions for consideration: (1) lack of resources for implementing TFSV-specific resources, especially at smaller PSIs; (2) understanding and incorporating students' perspectives in material and resource development; and (3) evaluating the effectiveness or success of training and resource materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subtheme: Lack of Resources</head><p>All participants, whether employed at a large, mid-sized, or smaller PSI, expressed the challenges associated with resource shortages. PSIs may not have enough resources/funds to develop specific materials, access paid materials/resources, maintain changing student and employee needs, or manage additional duties, such as integrating educational coordinator duties with a primary student crisis support and safety services role. These challenges were particularly salient at smaller PSIs and commuter PSIs, both of which may have fewer resources allotted to student life spending.</p><p>Adapting materials from larger PSIs or using open-sourced materials was reported as being extremely helpful, in addition to relying on educational campaigns and training sessions from external organizations. Participants noted the importance of provincially consistent programs in reducing resource burden, allowing for definitional clarity, and developing similar policies across BC PSIs. Moreover, participants noted appreciation for the ability to modify content for their specific PSI's needs. Still, some noted that currently available training resources have the potential to obscure differences between institutions, suiting the needs of certain PSIs better than others. Smaller PSIs or PSIs with unique foci may thus experience a need to dedicate additional resources to adapting these materials, despite being less likely to have available resources for these tasks.</p><p>Furthermore, given the lack of available resources at certain PSIs, participants expressed that, although not ideal, response and disclosure management training for employees were typically prioritized over other forms of awareness/educational training.</p><p>Essentially, these concerns suggested a "defensive/response approach" instead of an "offensive/active approach." Additionally, participants from some PSIs noted that this lack of resources (e.g., overtaxed staff, etc.) at times prevented resources that were available from being utilized to their full potential.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subtheme: Incorporating Student Perspectives</head><p>Almost all participants stressed the value of student perspectives when piloting training, educational materials such as awareness or poster campaigns, or resource materials. In some cases, participants reported that students took the initiative to develop SV or TFSV materials.</p><p>Despite the value of these contributions, participants worried that the materials were not properly vetted/evaluated by other PSIs or topic experts, thereby contributing to a lack of consistency in definitions across PSIs.</p><p>Student perspectives were also valuable in informing discussions regarding the modality and compulsoriness of TFSV resource implementation. Many participants held mixed perspectives on making TFSV training and/or educational sessions mandatory for students and staff, administrators, and faculty. Some suggested that mandatory TFSV training might backfire and result in student discomfort or rejection of resources. Participants also recognized that many students (and staff, administrators, and faculty) already have low bandwidth with several existing commitments and that requiring mandatory TFSV training may unintentionally create additional frustrations.</p><p>Nonetheless, participants also noted that the values of their PSI necessitate training and awareness. For example, some participants stated a sense of obligation, such that understanding sexualized violence, and TFSV in particular, is an important component of supporting students. Participants thus described a complex relationship between their personal and institutional values, which prioritized trauma-informed responding to student experiences, and the needs of faculty and staff members themselves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subtheme: Evaluating Resources</head><p>Participants spoke of challenges with understanding who is accessing materials and assessing the effectiveness of materials overall. Though PSIs understand the importance of trainee, employee, and victim-survivor anonymity when accessing materials and resources, many alluded to an overall discomfort with reporting statistics on attendees or users of SV or TFSV materials. Participants recommended caution in interpreting PSI's current statistical reporting systems overall, as data should be evaluated and contextualized with the conditions of the PSI in mind (e.g., campuses without student housing, campuses with high enrollment for online programs, etc.).</p><p>Participants also stressed the importance of evaluating programs and suggested the incorporation of both quality (e.g., knowledge application/awareness) and quantity (e.g., how many people attend a session or testing pre versus post-test knowledge) in the evaluations.</p><p>Several participants reported that there was no built-in evaluation of programs and that as a result, this labor falls on individuals who are often already overburdened.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theme 3: Intersectional Challenges and Opportunities in Incorporating TFSV</head><p>Participants agreed that there were both challenges and opportunities in incorporating an intersectional approach into the development and implementation of TFSV training and resource materials. All participants supported the incorporation of intersectional concepts/themes within their PSI institutional values, policies, and awards. Nonetheless, participants noted some challenges with this incorporation. Given the lack of TFSV-specific materials identified in our scan, the themes presented here describe conceptual reflections on intersectional approaches, rather than discussing how intersectionality is incorporated into existing materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Need to Incorporate Intersectional Lens</head><p>All participants noted the importance of including diverse perspectives in the development and implementation of sexual violence and TFSV-specific training sessions, materials, and resources for staff, administrators, faculty, and student alike. Participants described how incorporating diverse perspectives could allow materials and resources to better suit the needs of diverse student populations and counter multiple forms of systemic oppression. In particular, participants noted efforts to incorporate marginalized voices and experts from the following communities: Indigenous, LGBTQIA2S+, and people of colour, as well as the consideration of unique barriers experienced by international students (e.g., language and/or cultural considerations), mature students, and students with families. Despite placing value on intersectional approaches, some noted challenges with implementation, particularly when staff or community diversity is lacking; participants often did not have a specific background in feminist theory and some did not feel qualified to build intersectionality into their materials, but also did not have resources to develop this expertise or bring in consultants with expertise or lived experience.</p><p>Other participants stated the benefits of incorporating external community agencies/organizations/institutions as partners in delivering training sessions, awareness/educational campaigns, and promoting services and resources, as well as serving as experts on PSI committees. These same participants acknowledged that multiagency/organizational/institutional partnerships, while valuable, can take a significant amount of time, thereby elongating the process of material development, taxing resources for smaller PSIs, and posing challenges for "living" [continuously updated] materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The prevalence and devastating consequences of TFSV -with related outcomes including depression, extreme distress, PTSD, problematic alcohol use, self-harm, and suicidality <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bates, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Champion et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Powell &amp; Henry, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Snaychuk &amp; O'Neill, 2020)</ref> -render TFSV an emerging public health concern (see also <ref type="bibr">Patel &amp; Roesch, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Much like for general sexualized violence, institutional policies and resources -including those in higher education contexts -are an important component of TFSV responding <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Colpitts, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr">Patel &amp; Roesch, 2020</ref>). Yet, little is known about how institutions are responding to these concerns. We conducted an environmental scan to better understanding existing resource availabilities and gaps. Our dual-pronged approach scanned for TFSV materials and resources available at PSIs and critically assessed whether and how these materials and resources applied an intersectional lens. We identified an overwhelming lack of TFSV-specific resources, with only one PSI indicating any such resources in their online information, and follow-up interviews revealed few additional focused resources.</p><p>We identified a number of conceptual and practical barriers to the development and implementation of TFSV-specific resources. Conceptual barriers included the somewhat contradictory notions of TFSV as a subtype of generalized sexualized violence and the notion of TFSV as scoping and ever-evolving, which suggests that TFSV pushes the boundaries of sexualized violence responding and may necessitate unique approaches (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Henry &amp; Powell, 2016)</ref>. Additionally, PSIs noted challenges with investigating TFSV incidents due to the unique nature of TFSV. Practical challenges included lacking resources, challenges surrounding the evaluation of TFSV resources, and a need for the incorporation of intersectionalitychallenges also noted in traditional sexualized violence responding (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Corcoran et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Colpitts, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">McCauley et al., 2019)</ref>.</p><p>These findings are necessarily situated in the Canadian context and in the province of British Columbia, where our authorship team is rooted. However, the scope of this project included a range of institution types and sizes, which we believe to be broadly representative of the post-secondary education context, and of the broad lack of TFSV-specific resources.</p><p>Additionally, concerns surrounding TFSV are broadly of interest in current health and education discourses, and we provide initial insight into this gap and recommendations for practice which we believe to be generalizable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Policy Implications</head><p>Policy change and resource availability are essential for eradicating TFSV. Based on our findings, we provide three recommendations for future development. First, we urge the development of centralized, "living" resources to standardize materials and reduce the burden on individual PSIs. Keeping content current and accessible is a noted challenge in sexualized violence responding <ref type="bibr">(Corcoran et al., 2022)</ref>, and is exacerbated in the rapidly changing technological environment. However, this technological immersion also provides novel opportunities for centralized resource development and rapid dissemination.</p><p>Second, we urge the development of and funding for TFSV-specific training, implementation, and training evaluation following from recognition that TFSV is a unique but legitimate form of violence and mechanism of ongoing oppression <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Henry &amp; Powell, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Rajani, 2022)</ref>. We do recognize that agencies are currently funded for PSI TFSV training development in BC 4 ; yet, we recommend similar approaches in other jurisdictions as well as the evaluation of these resources after implementation. Finally, we highlight the urgent necessity of incorporating intersectionality into all stages of TFSV material/resource development and implementation (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">McCauley et al., 2019)</ref>. We note that the mere representation of diverse perspectives is necessary but insufficient for an intersectional approach, and discussions of TFSV must be situated in broader discourses of privilege and oppression (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Colpitts, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Kelly et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Rajani, 2022)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>The current environmental scan provides an overview of TFSV materials and resources at PSIs in BC. We identified an overwhelming lack of TFSV-specific resources. Follow-up interviews revealed few additional focused resources. In order to reduce the harms associated with TFSV, which disproportionately impact people with marginalized identities, we call for the development of living TFSV resources, centralization of these resources, increased funding for professional development and implementation, and the incorporation and valuation of intersectional praxis at all stages of resource development and implementation.</p><p>4 see https://bccampus.ca/projects/intersectional-sexualized-violence-project/</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="9,77.30,70.70,468.00,250.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>We use the term "victim-survivor" to refer to those who have been subjected to TFSV; we opted to use this terminology as it defies binaries between victim and survivor identities, is frequently represented as a selected identity label(Boyle &amp; Rogers,  </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>2020), and better acknowledges the intersecting oppressions which (re)produce the trauma of sexualized violence(Covert, n.d.).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_2"><p>https://www2.gov.bc.ca/gov/content/education-training/post-secondary-education/find-a-program-orinstitution/find-an-institution</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental scanning: radar for success</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Albright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tech-facilitated violence: Thinking structurally and intersectionally</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burkell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1332/239868021X16286662118554</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1332/239868021X16286662118554" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Gender-Based Violence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="542" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revenge porn and mental health: A qualitative analysis of the mental health effects of revenge porn on female survivors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1557085116654565</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1557085116654565" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Feminist Criminology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond the rape &quot;victim&quot;-&quot;survivor&quot; binary: How race, gender, and identity processes interact to shape distress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Boyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/socf.12584</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/socf.12584" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intersectionality: Mapping the movements of a theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Carbado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Crenshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mays</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tomlinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/S1742058X13000349</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1742058X13000349" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Du Bois Review: Social Science Research on Race</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technology-facilitated sexual violence and suicide risk: A serial mediation model investigating bullying, depression, perceived burdensomeness, and thwarted belongingness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Champion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Oswald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pedersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3138/cjhs.2020-0044</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3138/cjhs.2020-0044" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Canadian Journal of Human Sexuality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Not even close to enough:&apos; Sexual violence, intersectionality, and the neoliberal university</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Colpitts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09540253.2021.1924362</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09540253.2021.1924362" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gender and Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The development and piloting of a digital checklist to increase access and usage of campus online sexual violence resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Corcoran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Chugani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1090198120911879</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1090198120911879" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Education &amp; Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36S" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Covert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://upsettingrapeculture.com/survivor-victim/" />
		<title level="m">Survivor, victim, victim-survivor. Force: Upsetting rape culture</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping the margins: Intersectionality, identity politics, and violence against women of color</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Crenshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stanford Law Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1241" to="1299" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Embodied harms: Gender, shame, and technology-facilitated sexual violence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1077801215576581</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1077801215576581" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Violence Against Women</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="758" to="779" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technology-facilitated sexual violence: A literature review of empirical research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/26638194" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trauma, Violence, &amp; Abuse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Doing&apos; or &apos;using&apos; intersectionality? Opportunities and challenges in incorporating intersectionality into knowledge translation theory and practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kasperavicius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Etherington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Giangregorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Presseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sibley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Straus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12939-021-01509-z</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12939-021-01509-z" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal for Equity in Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advancing theory, methods, and dissemination in sexual violence research to build a more equitable future: an intersectional, community-engaged approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mccauley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Buchanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moylan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1077801219875823</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1077801219875823" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Violence Against Women</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1906" to="1931" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prevalence of technology-facilitated sexual violence: A meta-analysis and systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Roesch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1524838020958057</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1524838020958057" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trauma, Violence, &amp; Abuse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="428" to="443" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technology-facilitated sexual violence victimization: Results from an online survey of Australian adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0886260516672055</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0886260516672055" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Interpersonal Violence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3637" to="3665" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">I bet you don&apos;t get what we get&quot;: An intersectional analysis of technologyfacilitated violence experienced by racialized women anti-violence online activists in Canada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rajani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://digitalcommons.schulichlaw.dal.ca/cjlt/vol19/iss2/2/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian Journal of Law and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">217</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protections for marginalised women in university sexual violence policies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Roskin-Frazee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5204/ijcjsd.v9i1.1451</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5204/ijcjsd.v9i1.1451" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal for Crime, Justice and Social Democracy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The utility of the environmental scan for public health practice: lessons from an urban program to increase cancer screening</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rowel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nowrojee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Memiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bronner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the National Medical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An imperfect feminist journey: Reflections on the process to develop an effective sexual assault resistance programme for university women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Senn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0959353510386094</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0959353510386094" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Feminism &amp; Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficacy of a sexual assault resistance program for university women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Senn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eliasziw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Barata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Thurston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Newby-Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Radtke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hobden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMsa1411131</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMsa1411131" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New England Journal of Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2326" to="2335" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technology-facilitated sexual violence: Prevalence, risk, and resiliency in undergraduate students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Snaychuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>O'neill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10926771.2019.1710636</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10926771.2019.1710636" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Aggression, Maltreatment &amp; Trauma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="984" to="999" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
