<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Inattentive respondents cause attenuation bias in conjoint experiments</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-07">July, 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Agabek</forename><surname>Kabdullin</surname></persName>
							<email>ak5996@nyu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Social Science Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">New York University Abu Dhabi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Inattentive respondents cause attenuation bias in conjoint experiments</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-07">July, 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">150BD7CD025A00C1975966B7BFBF023E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:18+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In forced choice conjoint experiments, in expectation, the respondents should be picking between two answer options at the same rate thanks to randomization of profile attributes. Using replication data, I demonstrate that this empirical regularity does not always hold across various political science experiments: respondents pick the first option more often. I employ data from seven original conjoint experiments to show that it is inattentive respondents who are driving this result. I derive that this primacy bias leads to attenuation of estimates. Finally, I present a research design that pins down the mechanism behind primacy bias and elucidates whether it is the product of the language of instruction or survey layout.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Conjoint experiments popularized by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Hainmueller et al. (2014)</ref> are entering the mainstream and are slowly becoming a staple in political science. Scholars have paid close attention to the interpretation of the main metrics of interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abramson et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Ganter, 2023)</ref>, potential measurement problems that could occur in conjoint experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Clayton et al., 2023)</ref> and the issue of survey satisficing <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Bansak et al., 2018)</ref>. The challenge of inattentive respondents in online surveys in general has also been acknowledged in recent work <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Peyton et al., 2022)</ref>. Some propose ways to track attention of survey takers <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Kane et al., 2023)</ref>, and others caution that ignoring respondents failing manipulation checks may bias results <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Aronow et al., 2019)</ref>. Ultimately, the question of what to do with inattentive respondents depends on the nature of the problem at hand <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alvarez et al., 2019)</ref>.</p><p>While existing work has discussed the problem of inattentive respondents in various surveys and survey experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Atsusaka and Kim, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Blair et al., 2019)</ref>, inattention poses a specific challenge in conjoint experiments. In particular, I demonstrate that in forced-choice (and rank-based conjoint experiments), inattentive respondents produce attenuation bias because they do not pick options at random -rather, they flock to the first answer option that they read. Using data from seven original forced-choice conjoint experiments (and seven rank-based conjoint experiments) in five different languages across six countries, I find evidence that inattentive respondents pick the first option that they read. I show that this results in attenuation bias. To see why, consider that if all respondents chose the same response (e.g. option A) across all conjoint rounds, the average marginal component effect (AMCE) across all attributes would go to zero. Thus, the inclusion of inattentive respondents in a forced-choice conjoint experiment attenuates the estimates. 2 These findings have consequences for the interpretation of the magnitude of the AMCEs for both forced-choice and rating-based conjoint experiments: scholars are likely underestimating the strength of their findings. 3   The rest of this research note proceeds as follows. First, using replication data from more than twenty political science forced-choice conjoint experiments, I demonstrate that there is indeed imbalance in the distribution of answer options that respondents pick.</p><p>Second, by employing data from seven original forced-choice conjoints, I show that inattentive respondents are driving the imbalance. Third, I present an experimental design that is aimed to capture the mechanism behind behavior of inattentive respondents. In particular, I check whether it is the language of instruction or the survey design that effects the primacy bias.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Prevalence of Skewed Distributions</head><p>In a forced-choice conjoint experiment with two outcome levels (say, "Candidate A" and "Candidate B"), in expectation, thanks to randomization, respondents should pick among the two options at the same rate. However, I find that this is not always the case. Among those taking a survey in English, German, Spanish, Dutch, Chinese and other languages respondents are disproportionately likely to pick the left-most choice or top answer option (when answer options are presented vertically), while those taking the survey in Arabic and Urdu are disproportionately likely to pick the right-most choice, which corresponds with the first option they encounter in the direction in which they read: left to right, and right to left, respectively.</p><p>3 There are a couple of avenues that experimenters could take to tackle the issue of inattentive respondents in conjoint experiments. In the absence of instructional manipulation checks (IMCs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alvarez et al., 2019)</ref> and pre-treatment mock vignette checks (MVCs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Kane et al., 2023)</ref> and if multiple rounds have been conducted, researchers could post factum run a simple sensitivity analysis and check how their results would change with varying proportion of inattentive respondents. One could also check whether the distribution of answer options is balanced across tasks. Finally, at the survey designing stage, I suggest including IMCs and/or MVCs, and test whether survey-takers failing IMC/MVC creates an imbalance in the proportion of options picked. If imbalance is detected, researchers could exclude inattentive respondents from the analysis.</p><p>To capture evidence of primacy bias in forced choice conjoint experiments, I have examined replication data from 21 studies. I focused on recent papers from some of the top political science journals (American Political Science Review, American Journal of Political Science, Journal of Politics, Political Science Research and Methods, Journal of Experimental Political Science). There are many more conjoint studies published in these journals. I focus on papers in which I could identify which answer option respondents read first (i.e., I present results for papers in which the profiles were identified as "left", "right", "1", "2" etc.) Whenever possible, I also teased out what the survey layout was like and if the answer options were presented horizontally (left-right) or vertically <ref type="bibr">(topdown)</ref>. If an experiment was run on two samples, I examine the distribution of answers for two samples separately.</p><p>For many of the studies, it is clear that the distribution of answers in the first round is skewed. Across the surveys, respondents disproportionately pick the first option (e.g., option on the left or top answer option). I run a simple chi-squared test to establish whether a skew is statistically significant. In 19 experiments out of 24, this result is statistically significant and persists across languages, countries, survey companies and number of attributes. My suspicion is that the first round of a conjoint experiment confuses respondents which is why they gravitate towards the first option on the screen (or the first option that they read). For instance, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Holland et al. (2021)</ref> study, the same experiment was run on Colombian citizens in Colombia and on Venezuelan migrants residing in Colombia. In the first round, 527 Colombian citizens out of a thousand, picked option A. In stark contrast, in the first round, 919 Venezuelan migrants out of 1605, picked option A. "[T]he vast majority [of the Venezuelan participants] worked in the informal economy in Colombia" <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Holland et al., 2021)</ref>, which may suggest that the Venezuelan sample was bearing more cognitive load during the survey and, thus, picked the first option to proceed (see Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</p><p>In a few of the studies, the skew persists across multiple rounds: respondents kept picking the first option disproportionately more often. In some cases, many respondents kept "straightlining", i.e., picking the same option (A or B) across multiple rounds. For instance, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Kao et al. (2024)</ref>, the proportion of respondents that selected the first answer option across all six rounds is 3.9% (the expected value is ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>2 ) 6 = 1.5625%; 2.7% of the respondents picked the second answer option exclusively). Similarly, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dai and Kustov (2023)</ref>, 10.5% of respondents picked the first option in all four rounds (the expected value is ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>2 ) 4 = 6.25%). Interestingly, respondents flock to the first option they view even when presented with pictorial treatment instead of text even in the presence of enumerators. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Clary and Siddiqui (2021)</ref> conducted a conjoint experiment in the fall of 2015 in Pakistan in which they employed pictures instead of text to present respondents with profiles. Still, there is evidence of primacy bias: 23% of the respondents picked the first option in all three rounds (( <ref type="formula">1</ref>2 ) 3 = 12.5% is the expected value). What explains variation in primacy bias? There are too few experiments presented here to establish conclusively (I work with more replication data and I will add those results in the future iteration of the paper), but one factor that could potentially predict primacy bias is the type of sample. Largely, whenever experiment targets highly selective groups, the primacy effect dies down. For instance, one arm of <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bush et al. (2023)</ref> experiment targets international development workers, a highly educated and small sample, that is less likely to be inattentive (or to be confused by the layout of a conjoint experiment). <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fabbe et al. (2023)</ref> recruited Greek municipal officials via email and the response was not very high (and neither was sample size) which implies that only highly motivated and interested officials took the survey. In both cases, primacy bias was not detected (see Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). Respondents not recruited via survey companies are likely not driven by a promise of monetary compensation and, therefore, they rush less and they take surveys in a more meaningful way.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>: Across studies that target adult population, there is a statistically significant skew towards the first option that respondents read in the first round of tasks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6</head><p>Inattentive respondents are rarely identified in the replication data, however, so to check whether inattentiveness is at the core of primacy bias (and the resulting attenuation), I compare the original data from <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hainmueller and Hopkins (2015)</ref> to <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Peyton et al. (2022)</ref> replication of the same study during Covid. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Peyton et al. (2022)</ref> demonstrate that Covid lockdown has led to increasing lack of attention in respondents and moderation in estimates. While <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Peyton et al. (2022)</ref> rightly ascribe attenuation to inattentiveness, I suggest a potential mechanism behind this result. When comparing the distribution of selected options (Immigrant One vs Immigrant Two) across rounds in the original study and the replication study, it is clear that the distributions are more skewed during Covid which one could think of as a booster of inattention (see Tables <ref type="table">1</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>).</p><p>Table <ref type="table">1</ref>: Distribution of option picks in the original immigration study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Hainmueller and Hopkins (2015)</ref>. Pre-Covid respondents were more attentive. The distribution across answer options is roughly even.   Respondents are also less selective about answer options when it comes to less consequential questions. For instance, in the experiment S-GA respondents disproportionately picked the first option in both rounds potentially because the experiment asked respondents to pick between two cups of coffee (a choice that is less consequential than, say, picking between two hypothetical immigrants to be let into country). In experiment A-I-LR conducted in India, respondents were asked which of the two hypothetical migrants they would prefer to be resettled in Mumbai. When answering that question, respondents were more likely to go for the first answer option since respondents were predominantly not from Mumbai and did not really have an opinion about migration there.</p><p>Inattentive respondents also cause attenuation in rank-based conjoint experiments.</p><p>Since inattentive respondents tend to go for the neutral non-attitude options <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alvarez et al., 2019)</ref>, I find that inclusion of inattentive respondents in rating-based conjoint ex-periments attenuates the results as well. In two separate rating-based conjoints conducted in the US in February of 2024, inattentive respondents were flagged via post-treatment memory checks (in experiment L-U, 60.4% passed the check and in R-U, 48.9% passed).</p><p>The AMCE estimates for inattentive respondents are closer to zero than the full sample estimates, and AMCEs for attentive respondents are larger in magnitude than full sample estimates (see Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4a</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4b</ref>).  4 How serious is the attenuation problem?</p><p>Having inattentive respondents that only pick the first option across all rounds in the sample leads to attenuation of AMCE. Intuitively, if all respondents picked the first option across all rounds, AMCEs would go to zero since none of the levels of any of the attributes would be effecting a preference. Also, when estimating AMCE, (this specific type of) inattentive respondents would be contributing to the denominator, but not the numerator. 6</p><p>One way to tackle this issue would be list-wise deletion of inattentive respondents.</p><p>This updated estimate would be reverse proportionate to the ratio of attentive respondents in the sample. If the proportion of inattentive respondents in the sample was p, then AM CE u α for some level α would be AM CE ). In other words, while the "true" AMCE is larger, so is the confidence interval around it (which follows from losing observations).</p><p>If 4% of the sample are inattentive respondents that keep picking the same option 7 , then AMCE is attenuated roughly by 4% <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Peyton et al. (2022)</ref> come to a similar conclusion).</p><p>Importantly, if this is the type of careless respondent that is prevalent in the sample,</p><p>6 Suppose there was an attribute with two levels: α and β. Then marginal mean for β would be</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">M M β = 0.5N I #β+ A I(choice=β) (N I +N A )#β</formula><p>where N I is the number of inattentive respondents picking the first option and N A is the number of attentive respondents manifesting true preferences. #β is the number of profiles with β level present in them (inattentive respondents pick those profiles half of the time) and A I(choice = β) is the number of profiles with level β present in them that attentive respondents picked.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">M M α = 0.5N I #α+ A I(choice=α) (N I +N A )#α</formula><p>is the marginal mean for α. If β was the reference level, then AMCE for</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">α is nothing but AM CE b α = A I(choice=α)- A I(choice=β) (N I +N A )#α</formula><p>. Without inattentive respondents, the AMCE for α would be</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">AM CE u α = A I(choice=α)- A I(choice=β) (N A )#α</formula><p>since inattentive respondents do not add anything to the numerator. If p was proportion of inattentive respondents to the total number of respondents p = 7 In three rounds the probability of observing three consecutive choices of the first option is ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>2 ) 3 = 12.5%; if the observed proportion is 16.5%, chances are, 4% of the respondents picked the first option due to inattentiveness then estimates are likely attenuated, but statistical significance is probably not affected (confidence intervals scale by the same amount).</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">N I (N I +N A ) , then AM CE u α = 1 (1-p) AM CE b α .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">What Drives Primacy Bias: Research Design</head><p>While authors provide replication data for their conjoint experiments, they don't always present the layout of the survey. Thus, although one can spot that the distributions between options A and B are not even, one can't be sure what drives the skew. For instance, there is a clear skew in answer options distribution in Ridge ( <ref type="formula">2024</ref>): Moroccan respondents who took the survey in Arabic clearly picked the right most option more often than the option on the left (see Table <ref type="table">3</ref>). However, it is not clear whether this is the result of the language of instruction or the survey layout. In this particular instance, the "Next question" button is situated right below "Option 1" (the right most option), which could result in inattentive respondents choosing it to save time (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>).  To empirically test this, I leverage the sizable bilingual population in Pakistan who speak both Urdu and English.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">8</ref> Given that in Urdu people read from right to left, and in English they read from left to right, I manipulate the language of instruction thereby checking whether it is indeed the first read item that inattentive respondents gravitate towards. Half of the respondents that identify themselves as bilingual will be assigned to the English language of instruction and the other half will be assigned to the Urdu language of instruction. The position of the "Next/Skip Question" button will also be randomly assigned: for half of the respondents, the button will be to the right of the right most option (no matter the language)<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">9</ref> and for the other half, the button will be situated between the two choice options. The findings of the study would have implications for survey layout in conjoint experiments as well as the magnitudes of the effects derived from conjoint studies. This experiment received institutional review board (IRB) approval from New York University Abu Dhabi #HRPP-2024-79 and is to be pre-registered at OSF.</p><p>I target the population of Pakistan and assign half of the bilingual respondents to the survey in English and half of them to the survey in Urdu. The answer options will be laid out horizontally and not from top to bottom.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">10</ref> I further split each language group into two. The first half will see the "Next Question/Skip Question" button between two options A and B (at the same distance away from A and B). The other half will see the "Next" button to the right of option B (see Table <ref type="table">4</ref>). Respondents that are not bilingual will take the survey in their preferred language and still would be randomly assigned to either (i) centered "Next" button group or (ii) group that has "Next" button to the right of option B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Urdu</head><p>English "Next" button on the left Not needed (implicitly covered by "Next" button being on the left)</p><p>Not needed (implicitly covered by "Next" button being on the left) "Next" button in the middle Under language hypothesis, more people will pick "Right" Under language hypothesis, more people will pick "Left" "Next" button on the right Under layout hypothesis, more people will pick "Right"</p><p>Under layout hypothesis, more people will pick "Right" Table <ref type="table">4</ref>: Some of the expectations of choice distributions under various hypotheses.</p><p>• Hypothesis 1 (not-at-random picks): Inattentive respondents pick option choices not at random button no matter the language. Finally, if inattentive respondents are driven both by the language in which they take the survey and the survey layout, then respondents taking the survey in Urdu will select option on the right more often when the "Next" button is put between options A and B. Likewise, when the "Next" button is put between options A and B, respondents taking the survey in English will select option on the left more often (see Table <ref type="table">4</ref>).</p><p>Finding support for Hypothesis 1 (not-at-random picks) would have implications on how to properly adjust AMCEs. If there is no support for not-at-random picks, then AMCEs need to be adjusted for measurement error via <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Clayton et al. (2023)</ref> method.</p><p>However, if respondents indeed pick options not randomly, then AMCEs need to be adjusted for attenuation bias. 11 Importantly, identifying the mechanism behind choices of inattentive respondents would have implications for how to properly lay out conjoint experiments.</p><p>I spot inattentive respondents in the survey using a gamut of methods. Before exposing them to treatment I will present respondents with IMCs, instruction manipulation checks <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alvarez et al., 2019)</ref> as well as MVCs, mock vignette checks <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Kane et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>I will also give the respondents the same task in the first and final (six) round to check if the respondents are consistent in their choices <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Clayton et al., 2023)</ref>. Finally, to test whether it is indeed the reading direction that shapes inattentive respondents' choices, I present the respondents with the same task in the first and an intermediate (fourth)</p><p>round, but with the profiles flipped (i.e., what was scenario A in round one would be scenario B in round four; under one of the hypotheses an inattentive respondent would pick the same option -the option that they read first -in both cases). In addition, I measure how long respondents spend on each round. Finally, I check how well the respondents remember the last task (I ask what the outcome question was and whether a certain level was present in the task).</p><p>The conjoint experiment that the respondents will be exposed to would be the replication of <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Arias and Blair (2022)</ref> experiment on climate migration <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Arias and Blair, 2022)</ref> (see Table <ref type="table">5</ref>). Respondents will be exposed to six tasks. Inattentiveness will be induced via positioning of the experiment in the survey: Arias and Blair (2022) replication experiment will be randomly presented to the respondents before or after an additional experiment on intimate partner violence (IPV).</p><p>Select parts of the survey instrument are presented in the next section.</p><p>11 Currently working on the demonstration of attenuation bias and bias-adjusted estimator.</p><p>6 Survey Instrument NB: The following is a trap question with a position of the instruction manipulation check randomized in a grid <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alvarez et al., 2019)</ref>. The order of items would be randomized. For quality purposes, please select "always justifiable" 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10</p><p>• NB: The following are mock vignette checks <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Kane et al., 2023)</ref>. The order of answer options would be randomized. This question is also used to spot whether respondents have natural proclivity for left-most or right-most answer options.</p><p>C MVC Please carefully read the following stories and click either button to proceed.</p><p>Scenario A Scenario B Noor's brother sometimes pays for the meals at a restaurant. Noor's mother thinks that it's okay.</p><p>Noor's sister often pays for the coffee whenever they go out. Noor's father is not sure whether that's appropriate. Example task below:</p><p>• Language of instruction: reading from left to right</p><p>• "Next" button position: in between Options A and B</p><p>• Outcome question: police Scenario A Scenario B A friend approaches you and tells you about their cousin. Your friend tells you that cousin's husband has recently assaulted her. This happens occasionally. Your friend tells you that family and friends doubt that their cousin should reach out to somebody.</p><p>A friend approaches you and tells you about their cousin. Your friend tells you that cousin's ex-husband has recently cussed her out. This happens routinely. Your friend tells you that family and friends support their cousin's decision to reach out to somebody. • True</p><p>• False</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Presented are p-values from chi-square tests across thirty rounds of Bansak et al.(2018)  study. Participants that have identified that they've seen a conjoint experiment only four times before flocked to the left-most answer option in the first seven rounds (left panel). For more experienced respondents the distribution between answer options is more balanced (right panel).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Across experiments and rounds, inattentive respondents flock towards the first option they read. This result is exacerbated by the time spent on each round of tasks.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,101.89,72.00,722.07,430.33" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>for rating-based conjoint experiment, L-U. Conducted in the US in 2024. Sample split based on pre-treatment memory check which 60.4% of the respondents passed. for rating-based conjoint experiment, R-U. Conducted in the US in 2024. Sample split based on posttreatment memory check which 48.9% of the respondents passed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Inattentive respondents lead to attenuation in rating-based conjoints as well.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>p) AM CE b α , where AM CE b α is the estimate for the full sample and AM CE u α is the updated estimate. As for standard errors, of course, s.e.(AM CE u α ) = 1 (1-p) s.e.(AM CE b α</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Distribution of option picks in<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ridge (2024)</ref>. Survey conducted in Arabic. Option A (Option 1) was to the right of Option B (Option 2) in the survey (see Figure3the mechanism behind the exact observed discrepancies, I propose a simple factorial experiment. I test whether inattentive respondents are driven either by the language of instruction or by the layout of the survey. Inattentive respondents are likely either picking the first option that they read or the option that is closest to the "Next Question/Skip Question" button.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Survey layout in<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Ridge (2024)</ref>. Survey conducted in Morocco in Arabic. Respondents picked option A (Option 1) disproportionately more often. This could be driven by the language of instruction (Option 1 is read first in Arabic) or the position of the "Next" button (it's closer to Option 1).</figDesc><graphic coords="15,72.00,130.46,465.00,520.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>Hypothesis 2 a (language driven choice): Inattentive respondents pick the first option that they read -Hypothesis 2 b (layout driven choice): Inattentive respondents pick the option that is closest to the "Next" button on the webpage If the inattentive respondents are driven purely by the language of instruction (and not survey layout), then the position of the "Next" button should not affect the distribution between choices A and B. If, on the other hand, the inattentive respondents are driven purely by the survey layout, they would consistently pick the option closer to the "Next"</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Q1 In the stories you just read, the name of the main character was. . . Q2 In the stories you just read, who was NOT one of the characters? -Noor's brother -Noor's sister -Noor's cousin -Noor's father The following is the template for the scenarios presented to the respondents in the intimate partner violence (IPV) part of the experiment (levels of attributes presented in brackets): A friend approaches you and tells you about their cousin. Your friend tells you that the cousin's [husband/ex-husband/partner] has recently [assaulted her/cussed her out]. [This happens routinely/This happens occasionally/This is the first time it happened]. Your friend [tells you that family and friends support their cousin's decision to reach out to somebody/tells you that family and friends doubt that their cousin should reach out to somebody].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Question:•</head><label></label><figDesc>Which case do you think would be better handled by the police? Language of instruction: reading from left to right• "Next" button position: to the right of option B• Outcome question: imam Scenario A Scenario B A friend approaches you and tells you about their cousin. Your friend tells you that the cousin's partner has recently assaulted her. This is the first time it happened. Your friend tells you that family and friends doubt that their cousin should reach out to somebody.A friend approaches you and tells you about their cousin. Your friend tells you that the cousin's ex-husband has recently assaulted her. This happens routinely. Your friend tells you that family and friends support their cousin's decision to reach out to somebody.Question: Which case do you think would be better handled by an imam? check]: The question on the previous page was about... check]: One of the migrants on the previous page was from Ukraine.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Distribution of option picks in the replication immigration study by<ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Peyton et al. (2022)</ref>. During Covid respondents were less attentive. Respondents picked the first option disproportionately more often in the first three rounds.Another reason behind skewed distributions could be inexperience or confusion.<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bansak et al. (2018)</ref> demonstrate that conjoint experiments do not have a concerning issue of survey satisficing since respondents do not seem to demonstrate fatigue across thirty rounds of tasks. Authors support this result by showing that AMCE remains stable across rounds: after initial slight drop, the estimates do not attenuate. While it is hard to argue with that result, it is important to note that the respondents in the survey had previous experience with conjoint experiments. All 565 respondents from the MTurk sample have seen a "similar survey" four times before. Out of 1617 respondents from the SSI sample, 716 have seen a similar survey four times, 466 have seen it five times</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">Round Immigrant 1 Immigrant 2 Chi-squared p value</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>718</cell><cell>678</cell><cell>0.280</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>677</cell><cell>719</cell><cell>0.260</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>708</cell><cell>688</cell><cell>0.590</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>701</cell><cell>695</cell><cell>0.870</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>738</cell><cell>658</cell><cell>0.032</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Round Immigrant 1 Immigrant 2 Chi-squared p value</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>597</cell><cell>520</cell><cell>0.02</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>561</cell><cell>538</cell><cell>0.50</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>579</cell><cell>508</cell><cell>0.03</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>517</cell><cell>564</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>540</cell><cell>537</cell><cell>0.90</cell></row></table><note><p>and 435 have seen it eight times or more. I compare SSI respondents who only saw a similar survey four times before to those who saw it five times or more. Less experienced respondents gravitate toward the left option in the first seven rounds.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Question borrowed from World Values Survey Wave 6.C IMC Please tell us for each of the following actions whether you think it can always be justified, never be justified, or something in between.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Never justifiable</cell><cell></cell><cell>Always justifiable</cell></row><row><cell>Claiming government</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>benefits to which you are not</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>entitled</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Avoiding a fare on public</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>transport</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Stealing property</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Cheating on taxes if you</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>have a chance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Someone accepting a bribe</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>in the course of their duties</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Homosexuality</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Prostitution</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Abortion</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Divorce</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Sex before marriage</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Suicide</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Euthanasia</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>For a man to beat his wife</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Parents beating children</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Violence against other</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>people</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Since inattentive respondents tend to go for the neutral non-attitude options<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alvarez et al., 2019)</ref>, this finding also applies to rank-based conjoint experiments.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_1"><p>The same is not observed for MTurk respondents potentially because the sample size is too small.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_2"><p>While respondents' attentiveness was also tracked via instructional manipulation check (IMC) questions<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alvarez et al., 2019)</ref>, I do not use them here, because almost every respondent passes those. IMCs usually take the form of giving respondents specific instructions, e.g., "if you're reading this, please pick 'strongly agree' below."</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_3"><p>In Wave 6 of World Values Survey (WVS), although the most popular language spoken at home in Wave 6 of Pakistan was Punjabi, majority of the sample took the interview in Urdu. In Wave 7 of WVS, for 1796 out of the 1995 Pakistani respondents the interview language (Urdu) did not match the language they spoke at home.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_4"><p>I may also put the "Next/Skip Question" away from the direction from which respondents begin reading, e.g., the button would be on the left for the Urdu group and on the right for the English group</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_5"><p>To ensure that the respondents taking the survey on mobile devices do not present a challenge to this part of the design I move away from the "mobile friendly" version of the layout.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Arias and Blair (2022)</ref> </div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What do we learn about voter preferences from conjoint experiments?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Abramson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koçak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Magazinnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1008" to="1020" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Paying attention to inattentive survey respondents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Alvarez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Atkeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changing tides: public attitudes on climate migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Arias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Blair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on dropping experimental subjects who fail a manipulation check</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aronow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="589" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Addressing measurement errors in ranking questions for social sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Atsusaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Paper. 2</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The number of choice tasks and survey satisficing in conjoint experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bansak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hainmueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hopkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">List experiments with measurement error</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Blair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Imai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="480" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International rewards for gender equality reforms in autocracies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Donno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zetterberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Political Science Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Voters and foreign policy: evidence from a conjoint experiment in pakistan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Clary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Siddiqui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>orab001. 5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Foreign Policy Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correcting measurement error bias in conjoint survey experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Clayton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Horiuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Komisarchik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ebanks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">B2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The (in) effectiveness of populist rhetoric: a conjoint experiment of campaign messaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kustov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Science Research and Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control and fairness: What determines elected local leaders&apos; support for hosting refugees in their community?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fabbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kyrkopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Matakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Unan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="778" to="783" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of preferences in forced-choice conjoint experiments: Reassessing the quantity of interest</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ganter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The hidden american immigration consensus: A conjoint analysis of attitudes toward immigrants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hainmueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hopkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of political science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="548" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal inference in conjoint analysis: Understanding multidimensional choices via stated preference experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hainmueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hopkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Holland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Left out: How political ideology affects support for migrants in colombia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyze the attentive and bypass bias: Mock vignette checks in survey experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Velez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barabas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Science Research and Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do gains in political representation sweeten tax reform in china? it depends on who you ask</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lü</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Queralt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Science Research and Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="146" to="165" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The generalizability of online experiments conducted during the covid-19 pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Peyton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Coppock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>379-394. 2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Democratic commitment in the middle east: a conjoint analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Science Research and Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
