<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Altered Functional Connectivity Patterns Associated with Perceived Discrimination in Adolescents</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NINDS</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIAAA</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIMHD</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Endowment for the Arts</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NEA</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_xn4m2gu #_UsYFJ3k #_xGVzREX #_Nhrqay5 #_NGH2ftt #_jTdk9pn #_3b89gpK #_x23sDs8 #_afBrhAM #_hseMZ9N #_2scGNqU #_c8Bvb3f #_Y8vKMPn #_Hegs8NJ #_GHKsyRU">
					<orgName type="full">National Institutes of Health</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">NIH Office of Research on Women&apos;s Health</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">ORWH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_cE3Gv8x">
					<orgName type="full">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Cancer Institute</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NCI</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NICHD</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Yale ASCEND</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute of Justice</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIJ</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">CDC</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute on Drug Abuse</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIDA</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_RdM9UTQ">
					<orgName type="full">National Institute of Mental Health</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIMH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_XhBr5Fk">
					<orgName type="full">NIMH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">CDC -Division of Adolescent and School Health</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSF</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NHLBI</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">NIH Office of Behavioral and Social Sciences Research</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">OBSSR</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fields</surname></persName>
							<email>christopher.fields@yale.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Magnetic Resonance Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Radiology and Biomedical Imaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.S</roleName><forename type="first">Raimundo</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Magnetic Resonance Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Radiology and Biomedical Imaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.S</roleName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><surname>Rosenblatt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Magnetic Resonance Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Radiology and Biomedical Imaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Dustin</forename><surname>Scheinost</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Magnetic Resonance Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Radiology and Biomedical Imaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Associate Research Scientist</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Connecticut Mental Health Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Third Floor 34 Park St</addrLine>
									<postCode>06519</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Altered Functional Connectivity Patterns Associated with Perceived Discrimination in Adolescents</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6EE44066D404E2F8C97211D0601FE1E5</idno>
					<note type="submission">This work is a preprint and has not yet been peer reviewed.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Perceived discrimination</term>
					<term>Functional connectivity</term>
					<term>Resting-state fMRI</term>
					<term>Adolescent brain</term>
					<term>Network-Based Statistic (NBS)</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Perceived discrimination is a pervasive social stressor with significant implications for adolescent mental health and neurodevelopment. Using resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging (rs-fMRI) data from the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study, we investigated the relationship between perceived discrimination and functional connectivity patterns in the adolescent brain. We applied a Network-Based Statistic (NBS) analysis to 268x268 connectome data from 5,084 participants who provided data on perceived discrimination. Perceived discrimination was coded as a binary variable (Yes/No) based on participants' responses to a validated discrimination scale. Our analysis identified two primary subnetworks associated with perceived discrimination: a positive subnetwork, characterized by increased connectivity between the right prefrontal cortex, left insula, and subcortical regions, and a negative subnetwork, marked by disrupted connectivity between the right prefrontal cortex and left temporal regions. The positive subnetwork suggests enhanced cross-hemispheric communication in adolescents reporting discrimination, while the negative subnetwork indicates reduced cross-hemispheric integration in those reporting no discrimination. Additionally, significant alterations in connectivity across large-scale brain networks were observed. Specifically, adolescents reporting discrimination exhibited increased connectivity between visual processing networks and regions involved in attentional control, while showing decreased connectivity in other network interactions. These findings offer novel insights into the neural mechanisms underlying the effects of perceived discrimination on adolescent brain function, particularly in regions related to emotion regulation, social cognition, and stress responses. Our results underscore the importance of considering discriminatory experiences in the context of adolescent neurodevelopment and mental health.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p>Perceived discrimination, particularly based on race or ethnicity, is a pervasive social issue with significant implications for mental health and cognitive development, especially among adolescents. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Recent studies have highlighted the detrimental effects of perceived discrimination on various aspects of adolescent well-being, including increased stress, anxiety, and depression. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> The adolescent brain undergoes significant structural and functional changes, making it particularly vulnerable to the effects of chronic stressors such as discrimination. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> Neuroimaging studies have begun to elucidate the neural correlates of perceived discrimination, suggesting alterations in brain regions involved in emotion regulation, social cognition, and stress response. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> Resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging (rs-fMRI) has emerged as a powerful tool for investigating intrinsic brain connectivity patterns associated with various psychological and social phenomena. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> This technique allows researchers to examine functional connectivity between different brain regions in the absence of specific task demands, providing insights into the brain's baseline functioning. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> Previous research has identified alterations in functional connectivity associated with experiences of social exclusion and rejection, which share some similarities with perceived discrimination. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> However, the specific neural mechanisms underlying the perception and processing of discrimination, particularly in adolescents, remain poorly understood.</p><p>The Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study provides a unique opportunity to investigate these questions on a large scale, offering a diverse sample of adolescents and comprehensive neuroimaging data. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> Prior work by Nagata et al (2021) and Fields et al. (2024) have established a framework for assessing perceived discrimination within the ABCD cohort, paving the way for more detailed neuroimaging analyses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> Network-based approaches, such as the Network-Based Statistic (NBS) method, have shown promise in identifying subnetworks of brain regions that exhibit altered connectivity in various psychiatric and neurological conditions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> Applying these techniques to the study of perceived discrimination may reveal novel insights into the neural substrates of this important social phenomenon.</p><p>The present study aims to address this gap in the literature by examining the association between perceived discrimination and resting-state functional connectivity patterns in a large sample of adolescents from the ABCD Study. By leveraging advanced neuroimaging techniques and network analysis methods, we seek to identify specific brain networks that may be altered in adolescents who report experiences of discrimination, potentially shedding light on the neural mechanisms underlying the impact of discrimination on adolescent brain function and development. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Perceived Discrimination Measure</head><p>Perceived discrimination was measured using eight questions adapted from the Perceived Discrimination Scale, following the approach from prior research. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> These questions assessed experiences of unfair treatment based on race, ethnicity, or color, and participants' responses were used to codify perceived discrimination as a binary outcome (Yes/No).</p><p>The questions were part of follow-up assessment at ages 10-11, asking participants to reflect on their experiences over the past 12 months. The first question was:</p><p>1. In the past 12 months, have you felt discriminated against because of your race, ethnicity, or color? o Responses of "Yes" were categorized as perceived discrimination.</p><p>For the following seven questions, participants were asked how often they had experienced various forms of discrimination from different sources, rated on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = Almost Never, 5 = Very Often).</p><p>Responses of 3 (Sometimes), 4 (Often), or 5 (Very Often) were categorized as "Yes" for perceived discrimination. The questions were: 2. How often do teachers treat you unfairly or negatively because of your ethnic background?</p><p>3. How often do other adults outside school treat you unfairly or negatively because of your ethnic background?</p><p>4. How often do other students treat you unfairly or negatively because of your ethnic background? 5. I feel that others behave in an unfair or negative way toward my ethnic group.</p><p>6. I feel that I am not wanted in American society because of my ethnic background.</p><p>7. I don't feel accepted by other Americans because of my ethnic background.</p><p>8. I feel that other Americans have something against me because of my ethnic background. Participants who responded affirmatively (i.e., "Yes" to Question 1 or 3-5 on any of Questions 2-8) were categorized as having experienced perceived discrimination. Those who responded "No" to Question 1 or chose "1" or "2" for all other questions were categorized as not perceiving discrimination ("No"). Null or non-responsive answers across all eight questions resulted in exclusion from the analysis. This binary outcome was used as the primary measure in all analyses of perceived discrimination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Resting-State fMRI Data Acquisition and Preprocessing</head><p>Resting-state fMRI data were collected using a 3T MRI scanner at each site. The scanning parameters included an echo-planar imaging (EPI) sequence with the following parameters: repetition time (TR) = 800 ms, echo time (TE) = 30 ms, flip angle = 52 degrees, and voxel size = 2.4 x 2.4 x 2.4 mm. Data were preprocessed following the ABCD study pipeline, including slice-timing correction, motion correction, spatial normalization to MNI space, and smoothing with a 6-mm Gaussian kernel. Framewise displacement was calculated to identify and exclude participants with excessive head motion (threshold &gt; 0.2 mm). The functional data were then parcellated using the Shen 268-node atlas, which provides 268 regions of interest (ROIs) for connectivity analysis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Functional Connectivity Analysis</head><p>Functional connectivity was computed as the Pearson correlation coefficient between the time series of each pair of the 268 ROIs, resulting in a 268x268 functional connectivity matrix for each participant. These matrices were Fisher Z-transformed for normalization before further analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Network-Based Statistic (NBS) Analysis</head><p>We applied the Network-Based Statistic (NBS) approach to identify significant differences in functional connectivity between participants who reported perceived discrimination (Yes) and those who did not (No). The NBS is a method for identifying clusters of connections (subnetworks) that exhibit significant group differences while controlling for the family-wise error rate across the entire brain network. For this analysis, we used a primary threshold of p &lt; 0.001 to identify individual connections (edges) that significantly differed between the groups. Permutation testing (5,000 permutations) was conducted to control for multiple comparisons, and subnetworks were considered significant if the family-wise error (FWE) corrected p-value was below 0.05.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p>Statistical analyses were conducted using R (v4.3.2) and MATLAB (v2023b). Logistic regression models were used to assess the relationship between functional connectivity and perceived discrimination, adjusting for potential confounders such as age, gender, race/ethnicity, parental education, and household income. NBS was performed using the nbs package in Python, and visualization of the network map was generated using BioImageSuite. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical Considerations</head><p>The ABCD Study and this analysis were approved by the local Institutional Review Boards (IRBs) at participating institutions. Informed consent was obtained from parents or legal guardians, and assent was provided by participants before data collection. All study procedures were conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>In the current study, we conducted a whole-brain Network-Based Statistic (NBS) analysis using restingstate fMRI (rs-fMRI) 268x268 connectome data to predict perceived discrimination across participants. Perceived discrimination was codified as a binary outcome (Yes/No) following the methods used in prior research (Fields et     al., 2024). <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> The dataset included all subjects who reported perceived discrimination and had available rs-fMRI data that were not excluded for excessive head motion (threshold of framewise displacement &gt;0.2mm).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref> presents a network map of the significant subnetworks identified by the NBS analysis. This map highlights several key inter-lobar connections across multiple brain regions, showing altered connectivity associated with perceived discrimination, along with significant laterality effects. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref> primarily provides insight into the regional connections between brain areas, illustrating specific alterations in inter-and intra-lobar connectivity.</p><p>The NBS analysis identified two primary subnetworks (one positive, one negative) associated with perceived discrimination. The positive subnetwork, indicated by red connections in the network map, primarily involves inter-lobar connections between the right prefrontal cortex, left insula, and left subcortical regions (e.g., the limbic system). Notably, the right prefrontal cortex showed consistent positive connections across all left-lobe regions (insula, parietal, occipital, and temporal lobes), suggesting increased cross-hemispheric communication in participants reporting discrimination.</p><p>In contrast, the negative subnetwork, shown by blue connections, involved disrupted connectivity between the right prefrontal cortex and several left hemisphere regions, particularly the left temporal and left prefrontal lobes. This suggests that participants who did not report perceived discrimination exhibited reduced functional connectivity between these regions, reflecting potentially decreased cross-hemispheric integration. Additionally, within the left hemisphere, both positive and negative intralobar connections were identified, particularly across the prefrontal, parietal, and temporal regions. These left-lobe intralobar connections indicate more complex, localized network alterations associated with perceived discrimination, hinting at differential processing or integration within these regions.</p><p>In total, the NBS analysis revealed a significant positive component (p &lt; 0.05, family-wise error corrected) involving 72 edges, primarily linking the right prefrontal and left subcortical and temporal regions. A separate significant negative component (p &lt; 0.05) involved 58 edges, indicating disrupted connections across the left temporal and occipital lobes, as well as reduced right-to-left prefrontal connectivity.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> provides additional insights, focusing on the connectivity between major brain networks (e.g., the default mode network, salience network, and visual networks), rather than specific regional connections.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2a</ref> shows positive increases in connectivity between networks in participants reporting perceived discrimination compared to those not reporting discrimination, while Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2b</ref> illustrates decreased connectivity between networks in participants reporting discrimination versus those not reporting discrimination. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2a</ref>, a strong positive correlation is observed between the VII (visual network) and VAs (visual association area), indicating enhanced visual processing and integration in participants reporting discrimination. In contrast, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2b</ref> shows reduced connectivity between these regions in participants reporting discrimination, suggesting potential alterations in visual-spatial processing and attentional control. Additionally, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2a</ref> highlights increased connectivity between the visual networks and other large-scale brain networks, such as the salience (SAL) and default mode network (DMN), in participants reporting discrimination.</p><p>These results suggest that perceived discrimination is associated with alterations in both regional and large-scale network connectivity. The findings from Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref> highlight disruptions in inter-and intra-lobar functional connectivity, particularly in prefrontal regions, while Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> reveals changes in connectivity between major brain networks, such as the visual and default mode networks. These alterations have potential implications for emotion regulation, sensory processing, and social cognition. The identified laterality patterns, particularly the asymmetry in prefrontal connectivity, may reflect differential neural mechanisms involved in processing experiences of discrimination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Our study provides novel insights into the neural correlates of perceived discrimination in adolescents, revealing significant alterations in functional connectivity patterns associated with this pervasive social stressor. The Network-Based Statistic (NBS) analysis identified two primary subnetworks-one positive and one negative-that differentiate adolescents reporting perceived discrimination from those who do not. These findings underscore the unique neural adaptations associated with discrimination, particularly in large-scale brain networks involved in emotion regulation and social cognition. The positive subnetwork, characterized by increased connectivity primarily between the right prefrontal cortex and left subcortical and temporal regions, suggests enhanced cross-hemispheric communication in adolescents experiencing discrimination. This finding aligns with previous research indicating heightened prefrontal activation during social exclusion tasks. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> The involvement of subcortical regions, particularly the limbic system, in this network may reflect increased emotional processing and stress responses associated with discriminatory experiences. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> Conversely, the negative subnetwork, showing disrupted connectivity between the right prefrontal cortex and left temporal and prefrontal regions, may indicate altered cognitive control and emotional regulation processes in adolescents not reporting discrimination. This pattern of reduced cross-hemispheric integration could represent a more efficient or specialized neural organization in these individuals. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> The observed laterality effects, particularly the asymmetry in prefrontal connectivity, are intriguing and warrant further investigation. Lateralized brain function has been implicated in various aspects of emotion processing and social cognition. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> Our findings suggest that experiences of discrimination may be associated with distinct patterns of hemispheric integration, potentially reflecting differential strategies for processing and coping with these experiences.</p><p>The involvement of the insula in the positive subnetwork is particularly noteworthy, given its role in interoception and social cognition. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> Increased connectivity between the insula and prefrontal regions may reflect heightened awareness of bodily states and emotions in response to discriminatory experiences, consistent with theories of embodied cognition in social processing. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> Our findings also demonstrate the impacts of discrimination on visual processing and its integration with other brain networks. The observed increased connectivity between visual networks (VII and VAs) in participants reporting discrimination suggests enhanced visual processing and integration. This alteration could reflect heightened vigilance or increased attention to visual cues in the environment, potentially as a adaptive response to experiences of discrimination.</p><p>The increased connectivity between visual networks and other large-scale brain networks, such as the salience network (SAL) and default mode network (DMN), in participants reporting discrimination is particularly intriguing. This pattern might indicate a more integrated processing of visual information with networks involved in detecting salient stimuli (SAL) and self-referential thinking (DMN). Such integration could reflect a neural mechanism for heightened awareness and processing of potentially discriminatory visual cues in one's environment.</p><p>Interestingly, these findings align with recent research on altered visual processing in trauma-exposed populations, particularly in Black individuals with PTSD. Harnett and colleagues (2022) found that Black American women with PTSD exhibited increased connectivity between visual and salience networks compared to trauma-exposed controls. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> The authors suggested that this hyperconnectivity might represent a neural correlate of hypervigilance, a common symptom in PTSD that involves heightened sensitivity to potential threats in the environment. Our findings of increased visual network connectivity in adolescents reporting perceived discrimination parallel these results, suggesting that experiences of discrimination might lead to similar neural adaptations as those seen in trauma exposure. Furthermore, the reduced connectivity between visual networks observed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2b</ref> for participants reporting discrimination could indicate a more complex reorganization of visual processing. This might reflect a trade-off between enhanced integration of certain visual pathways and reduced connectivity in others, possibly as a means of optimizing attention to relevant social cues while filtering out less pertinent visual information. They suggest that the neural impact of discrimination extends beyond regions traditionally associated with emotion and social cognition to include fundamental sensory processing networks. This broader impact underscores the pervasive nature of discrimination's effects on brain function and highlights the need for comprehensive approaches in studying and addressing the neural correlates of discriminatory experiences.</p><p>Our study has several strengths, including its large sample size, the use of advanced network analysis techniques, and the focus on a critical developmental period. However, some limitations should be noted. First, the cross-sectional nature of the data precludes causal inferences about the relationship between perceived discrimination and brain connectivity. Longitudinal studies are needed to elucidate the directionality of these associations and to examine how discrimination-related brain changes may evolve over time. Second, while we controlled for several potential confounding factors, unmeasured variables may still influence the observed relationships. Future studies should consider additional factors such as family environment, peer relationships, and specific types of discriminatory experiences. Third, the binary categorization of perceived discrimination, while based on established methods, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> may not capture the full complexity of discriminatory experiences. Future research could benefit from more nuanced measures of discrimination, including frequency, severity, and specific domains of discrimination. Despite these limitations, our findings have important implications for understanding the neurodevelopmental impact of perceived discrimination. The altered connectivity patterns we observed may represent neural markers of discrimination-related stress, potentially contributing to the well-documented negative health outcomes associated with discrimination.</p><p>From a clinical perspective, these results highlight the importance of considering discriminatory experiences in assessments of adolescent mental health and well-being. Interventions aimed at reducing the impact of discrimination may need to consider its effects on brain function and connectivity. Additionally, our findings could inform the development of neuroimaging-based markers for assessing the efficacy of antidiscrimination interventions.</p><p>Future research should further explore the functional significance of these visual network alterations, perhaps through task-based fMRI studies that directly assess visual processing of socially relevant stimuli in individuals with varying levels of perceived discrimination. Additionally, longitudinal analysis within the ABCD dataset will help elucidate whether these changes in visual network connectivity are a cause or consequence of perceived discrimination, and how they might relate to long-term psychological and health outcomes.</p><p>In conclusion, this study provides evidence for altered functional brain connectivity associated with perceived discrimination in adolescents. The identified subnetworks implicate regions involved in emotion regulation, social cognition, and stress responses, offering new insights into the neural mechanisms underlying the impact of discrimination on adolescent brain function. Future research should build on these findings to further elucidate the complex relationships between discriminatory experiences, brain development, and long-term health outcomes in diverse populations. The network map visualizes significant subnetworks identified by the Network-Based Statistic (NBS) analysis using 268x268 rs-fMRI connectivity data. The outer rings represent different brain lobes, color-coded as follows:</p><p>Prefrontal (red), MotorStrip (orange), Insula (yellow), Parietal (green), Temporal (blue), Occipital (purple), Limbic (cyan), Cerebellum (brown), Subcortical (tan), and Brainstem (dark red). Red lines indicate edges in the positive subnetwork, representing increased connectivity primarily between the prefrontal cortex, insula, and subcortical regions, associated with participants who reported experiencing perceived discrimination. Blue lines represent edges in the negative subnetwork, indicating decreased connectivity between temporal, occipital, and parietal regions, primarily seen in participants who did not report perceived discrimination. The analysis included participants with available rs-fMRI data who were not excluded due to excessive head motion, and perceived discrimination was codified as a binary outcome (Yes/No). The positive and negative subnetworks were significant at p &lt; 0.05, corrected for multiple comparisons using family-wise error (FWE). This figure illustrates the differential brain network patterns linked to experiences of discrimination, suggesting functional connectivity alterations in regions related to emotion, social cognition, and sensory processing. discrimination versus those not reporting discrimination. who reported perceived discrimination compared to those who did not. The numbers in each cell of the heatmap represent the correlation coefficients between pairs of brain networks, calculated using Pearson correlation to assess the strength of connectivity between regions. Positive values in Figure 2a (red) indicate increased connectivity between networks in participants reporting discrimination, while negative values in Figure 2b (blue)</p><p>indicate decreased connectivity in these participants. For example, in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2a</ref>, the correlation between the visual network VII and the visual association area (VAs) is 0.35, suggesting stronger integration between these networks in adolescents reporting discrimination. In contrast, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2b</ref> shows a correlation of -0.11 between the same networks, indicating reduced connectivity in participants who reported discrimination. These heatmaps provide insights into the functional relationships between large-scale brain networks, such as the default mode network (DMN), salience network (SAL), visual networks (VI, VII), and motor network (Mot), across the two groups. The statistical analyses involved calculating correlation coefficients for each pair of brain networks, followed by group comparisons between participants who reported discrimination and those who did not. The heatmaps illustrate the magnitude of connectivity differences, providing a clear visual representation of how perceived discrimination is associated with both increases and decreases in large-scale network connectivity. These results suggest that discrimination experiences may influence network-level integration, with potential implications for sensory processing, emotion regulation, and attentional control in adolescents.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>Data were drawn from the 5.1 release of the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study, which includes a diverse sample of 11,868 children aged 9-10 years at baseline, recruited from 22 sites across the United States. For this analysis, we included participants who had complete resting-state fMRI (rs-fMRI) data and valid responses to the perceived discrimination questionnaire. Participants with excessive head motion (framewise displacement &gt; 0.2 mm) during the fMRI scan were excluded. The final sample consisted of 5,084 participants (after exclusions for motion).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>By leveraging data from the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study-a large, diverse, and longitudinal cohort-this research extends previous work on the neural correlates of social exclusion and rejection<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> by specifically focusing on perceived discrimination. The use of resting-state fMRI data from the ABCD cohort provides valuable insights into the intrinsic brain organization associated with discrimination experiences, complementing previous task-based studies in this area.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Whole-brain network map revealing significant components associated with perceived discrimination.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,121.00,36.00,405.85,278.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Functional connectivity between large-scale brain networks in adolescents reporting perceived</figDesc><graphic coords="13,72.00,288.88,412.95,325.79" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure</head><figDesc>Figure 2a and Figure 2b display the functional connectivity between large-scale brain networks in adolescents</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments:</head><p>The authors would like to thank the <rs type="institution">ABCD Study Consortium</rs> for providing access to the data, as well as the participants and families who contributed to this research. Special thanks to the <rs type="funder">Yale School of Medicine</rs> for its institutional support through the <rs type="programName">ASCEND grant program</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>Funding: The <rs type="projectName">Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study</rs> was supported by the <rs type="funder">National Institutes of Health (NIH)</rs> and additional federal partners under the following awards: <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041022</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041025</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041028</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041048</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041089</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041093</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041106</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041117</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041120</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041134</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041148</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041156</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041174</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U24DA041123</rs>, and <rs type="grantNumber">U24DA041147</rs>. The ABCD federal partners include the <rs type="funder">National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Cancer Institute (NCI)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">NIH Office of Behavioral and Social Sciences Research (OBSSR)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">NIH Office of Research on Women's Health (ORWH)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) -Division of Violence Prevention</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Justice (NIJ)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">CDC -Division of Adolescent and School Health</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Science Foundation (NSF)</rs>, and the <rs type="funder">National Endowment for the Arts (NEA)</rs>. This work was supported by grant support to the authors: <rs type="funder">National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">F32MH129052</rs> to CTF; and <rs type="funder">NIMH</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">5R01MH121095-05</rs> and <rs type="funder">Yale ASCEND</rs> grant to DS. The funding organizations had no role in the analysis and interpretation of the data, preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript, or the decision to submit the manuscript for publication. This manuscript reflects the views of the authors and may not represent the opinions or views of the <rs type="funder">National Institutes of Health (NIH)</rs> or the ABCD consortium investigators.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_cE3Gv8x">
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">ASCEND grant program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_xn4m2gu">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041022</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_UsYFJ3k">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041025</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_xGVzREX">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041028</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Nhrqay5">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041048</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_NGH2ftt">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041089</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jTdk9pn">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041093</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_3b89gpK">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041106</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_x23sDs8">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041117</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_afBrhAM">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041120</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_hseMZ9N">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041134</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_2scGNqU">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041148</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_c8Bvb3f">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041156</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Y8vKMPn">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041174</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Hegs8NJ">
					<idno type="grant-number">U24DA041123</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_GHKsyRU">
					<idno type="grant-number">U24DA041147</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_RdM9UTQ">
					<idno type="grant-number">F32MH129052</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_XhBr5Fk">
					<idno type="grant-number">5R01MH121095-05</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Availability:</head><p>The data supporting the findings of this study were obtained from the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study. Due to restrictions, the data are available upon reasonable request from the corresponding author or from the ABCD Study Data Access portal. The source data used in this study were openly available prior to its initiation. The ABCD data used in this report came from the fast track data release 5.1, which is accessible to qualified researchers through the NIMH Data Archive (NDA). The raw data are available at <ref type="url" target="https://nda.nih.gov/study.html?id=2313">https://nda.nih.gov/study.html?id=2313</ref>, and the data dictionary for ABCD can be found at <ref type="url" target="https://data-dict.abcdstudy.org/">https://data-dict.abcdstudy.org/</ref>. Additional details about the measures assessed for the ABCD study are provided at <ref type="url" target="https://wiki.abcdstudy.org/release-notes/start-page.html">https://wiki.abcdstudy.org/release-notes/start-page.html</ref>. Instructions for obtaining NDA data use certification are available at <ref type="url" target="https://nda.nih.gov/nda/access-data-info">https://nda.nih.gov/nda/access-data-info</ref>.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Contributions:</head><p>• Christopher Fields: Conceptualization, data analysis, drafting of the manuscript, and interpretation of results.</p><p>• Raimundo Rodriguez: Data preprocessing, methodology, and revisions to the manuscript.</p><p>• Matthew Rosenblatt: Statistical analysis, data interpretation, and revisions to the manuscript.</p><p>• Dustin Scheinost: Supervision, guidance on fMRI analysis, and critical review of the manuscript.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived discrimination and health: a meta-analytic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pascoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Smart</forename><surname>Richman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="554" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial/ethnic discrimination and health: findings from community studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Neighbors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial/ethnic discrimination and well-being during adolescence: A meta-analytic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Benner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Boyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Polk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="855" to="883" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic review of studies examining the relationship between reported racism and health and wellbeing for children and young people</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Priest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Paradies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Trenerry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Truong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Karlsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc Sci Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is adolescence a sensitive period for sociocultural processing?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Blakemore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="207" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brain development during childhood and adolescence: a longitudinal MRI study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Giedd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Blumenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Jeffries</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="861" to="863" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">More than skin deep&quot;: stress neurobiology and mental health consequences of racial discrimination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sarnyai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stress</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subjective social status and neural processing of race in Mexican American adolescents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Muscatell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mccormick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Telzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Psychopathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1837" to="1848" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward discovery science of human brain function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Biswal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mennes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4734" to="4739" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spontaneous fluctuations in brain activity observed with functional magnetic resonance imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Raichle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="700" to="711" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does rejection hurt? An FMRI study of social exclusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Eisenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5643</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="292" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural correlates of social exclusion during adolescence: understanding the distress of peer rejection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Masten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Eisenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Borofsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social status modulates neural activity in the mentalizing network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Muscatell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1771" to="1777" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The conception of the ABCD study: From substance use to a broad NIH collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Volkow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Koob</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Croyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Cogn Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Longitudinal and Geographic Trends in Perceived Racial Discrimination Among Adolescents in the U.S.: The Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fields</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Calhoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<pubPlace>medRxiv</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence of Perceived Racism and Discrimination Among US Children Aged 10 and 11 Years: The Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nagata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Ganson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sajjad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Benabou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bibbins-Domingo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA Pediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">175</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="861" to="863" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network-based statistic: identifying differences in brain networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zalesky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fornito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bullmore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1197" to="1207" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Groupwise whole-brain parcellation from resting-state fMRI data for network node identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tokoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Papademetris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Constable</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="415" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioImage Suite: An integrated medical image analysis suite: An update</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Papademetris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Jackowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rajeevan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Insight J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">209</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of neural systems for processing social exclusion from childhood to adolescence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Bolling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pitskel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Deen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crowley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pelphrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1431" to="1444" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social exclusion and punishment of excluders: neural correlates and developmental trajectories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Moor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Guroglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Op De Macks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rombouts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Der Molen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Crone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="708" to="717" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social brain development and the affective consequences of ostracism in adolescence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sebastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Viding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Blakemore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Cogn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional brain networks develop from a &quot;local to distributed&quot; organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Power</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1000381</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The social brain: neural basis of social knowledge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Adolphs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="716" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How do you feel--now? The anterior insula and human awareness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Embodiment of cognition and emotion. APA handbook of personality and social psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Winkielman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Niedenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wielgosz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Eelen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kavanagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Attitudes and social cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural covariance of the ventral visual stream predicts posttraumatic intrusion and nightmare symptoms: a multivariate data fusion analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Finegold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lam</forename><surname>Lebois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transl Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">321</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acute Posttraumatic Symptoms Are Associated With Multimodal Neuroimaging Structural Covariance Patterns: A Possible Role for the Neural Substrates of Visual Processing in Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol Psychiatry Cogn Neurosci Neuroimaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prior Sexual Trauma Exposure Impacts Posttraumatic Dysfunction and Neural Circuitry Following a Recent Traumatic Event in the AURORA Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rowland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Roeckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ely</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol Psychiatry Glob Open Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="705" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
