<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Engineering and Technology Quarterly Reviews</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Safia</forename><surname>Malallah</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Kansas State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ejiro</forename><surname>Osiobe</surname></persName>
							<email>osiobe@bakeru.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Baker University</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Jiji</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lior</forename><surname>Shamir</surname></persName>
							<email>lshamir@ksu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Kansas State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">The Asian Institute of Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">The Engineering and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">The Asian Institute of Research Engineering and Technology Quarterly Reviews</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Engineering and Technology Quarterly Reviews</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">2622-9374</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">DEAC66B640524C0E6FC776540B1EDB54</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T02:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Engineering and Technology</term>
					<term>including (but not limited to) Civil Engineering</term>
					<term>Informatics Engineering</term>
					<term>Environmental Engineering</term>
					<term>Mechanical Engineering</term>
					<term>Industrial Engineering</term>
					<term>Marine Engineering</term>
					<term>Electrical Engineering</term>
					<term>Architectural Engineering</term>
					<term>Geological Engineering</term>
					<term>Mining Engineering</term>
					<term>Bioelectronics</term>
					<term>Robotics and Automation</term>
					<term>Software Engineering</term>
					<term>and Data Science</term>
					<term>Self-Efficacy</term>
					<term>Assessment Tools</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Technology. As the journal is Open Access, it ensures high visibility and the increase of citations for all research articles published. The Engineering and Technology Quarterly Reviews aims to facilitate scholarly work on recent theoretical and practical aspects of Education.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Data science has experienced remarkable global demand, solidifying its position as one of the fastest-growing professions worldwide. However, this demand is met with a shortage of freshly graduated, qualified data scientists, raising concerns for academia and industries <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Davenport &amp; Patil, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Haben &amp; Hinton)</ref>. Additionally, research on data science education assessments is lacking, leaving many uncertainties surrounding students' pre-graduation skills. This paper addresses this limitation and develops a data science self-efficacy survey to evaluate and quantify individuals' confidence levels in applying data science skills to build data-driven solutions, intending to enhance the learning experience within data science education. Also, remedial activities were proposed to boost students' confidence based on individual confidence levels. Survey development followed a modified Vinay approach, which guided the construction of customized assessments for data science aligned with organizational needs <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Vinay, 2024)</ref>. This was carried out by collaborating with computer science, business, and statistics experts, crafting a comprehensive lens that caters to the interdisciplinary nature. The survey evaluated 13 items representing applying data science life cycle steps and using related interdisciplinary skills to fulfill step requirements identified from literature reviews. The survey comprises 48 questions organized into eight sections, answered with a 5-point Likert scale from strongly disagree to agree strongly. The survey was distributed to students and researchers in six educational institutions in Kansas (KS), the United States of America (USA), and Kuwait (KT). Pilot results showed that the survey has high reliability, stability, and suitability. The final analysis indicates that 11.56% of students report low confidence, 11.54% record high confidence, and the majority express moderate confidence. Lower confidence levels were found around "model development" and "model evaluation," which can be tied to "analysis and calculation skills," "optimization skills," and "technical and computing skills." To boost students' confidence using the remedial suggestions, individualized support sessions should be used to discuss student concerns, address any questions or misunderstandings they may have, and offer personalized guidance and encouragement. Additionally, peer support groups can show students that they are not alone and provide opportunities to encourage one another during regular check-ins. Highly confident students need opportunities for advanced learning through independent research, creative projects, or leadership roles within the learning environment, thus encouraging confident participants to share their knowledge and expertise with their peers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Limitations</head><p>A primary limitation of this study is the biases or inaccuracies that self-efficacy assessments carry. Self-efficacy often focuses on specific tasks or domains, which may not fully capture an individual's overall sense of efficacy across different situations. Moreover, self-efficacy is inherently subjective and self-reported, lacking objective measurement and increasing the prevalence of bias or inaccuracies. Our small size and distributed populations can present significant limitations in research papers by compromising generalizability, statistical power, comparability, external validity, and replicability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Background</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Confidence and Learning</head><p>Confidence plays a pivotal role in students' academic success and overall well-being. Social Cognitive Theory suggests that self-efficacy, or belief in one's ability to succeed, significantly influences behavior and performance. Students with low confidence often exhibit hesitancy, self-doubt, and reluctance to engage in academic tasks. Interventions targeting low-confidence students should build self-efficacy through incremental successes, constructive feedback, and role modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Locke, 1987)</ref>. Additionally, fostering a supportive classroom environment that encourages risk-taking and emphasizes growth mindset principles can empower students to develop resilience and confidence in their abilities <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Works, 2017)</ref>. Self-determination theory posits that autonomy, competence, and relatedness are fundamental psychological needs that drive motivation and well-being. To support moderate-confidence students, educators can provide opportunities for autonomy by offering choices and promoting student agencies in their learning process. Furthermore, scaffolding instruction and targeted interventions tailored to individual learning needs can enhance students' sense of competence and foster a positive learning experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Deci &amp; Ryan, 2012)</ref>. High-confidence students typically believe in their abilities and may seek challenges or leadership roles. However, excessive confidence without corresponding competence can lead to overestimating skills and performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Hornstra et al., 2023)</ref>. The Zone of Proximal Development suggested that learning occurs most effectively within the "zone" where tasks are challenging yet achievable with appropriate support. Educators can support high-confidence students by providing opportunities for intellectual challenge and promoting metacognitive skills, such as selfreflection and self-regulation. Encouraging collaboration and peer feedback can also help high-confidence students better understand their strengths and areas for improvement <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Training, 2017)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Data Science Assessment Pathway</head><p>Vinay proposed a nine-step assessment pathway to create a customized data science assessment aligned with organizational goals using these competencies. These steps include identifying critical competencies, categorizing and prioritizing, defining competency levels, developing assessment tools, scoring and evaluation rubrics, integrating organizational goals, feedback mechanisms, implementation and training, and iterative refinement. We incorporated the first five steps to develop our survey, which were relevant to our goal of creating an assessment process for academia <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Vinay, 2024)</ref>.</p><p>In our study, developing an instrument for assessing self-efficacy confidence in data science requires carefully considering the specific skills, tasks, and challenges relevant to the field. Here's a step-by-step foundational guide to help you create such an instrument:</p><p>1. Define the Scope: Determine the specific areas within data science that you want to assess. This could include programming skills, statistical knowledge, machine learning expertise, data visualization proficiency, problem-solving abilities, etc. 2. Review Existing Literature: Look for existing self-efficacy scales or instruments related to data science or similar fields. This can provide insights into relevant constructs and items that you might include in your instrument. Adaptation of existing scales can be a time-saving approach. 3. Item Generation: Generate a pool of items/questions that reflect the skills and tasks you want to measure in data science. These items should be clear, specific, and cover a range of difficulty levels.</p><p>Consider consulting with data science experts to ensure the items' relevance and validity. 4. Pilot Testing: Administer the initial set of items to a small sample of individuals representing your target population (e.g., students and professionals in data science). Collect feedback on the clarity, relevance, and difficulty of the items. Use this feedback to refine the items and eliminate any ambiguities. 5. Validity and Reliability: Assess the validity and reliability of your instrument. Validity ensures that the instrument measures what it intends to measure, while reliability ensures consistency in measurement. You can use techniques such as factor analysis to assess construct validity and Cronbach's alpha to measure internal consistency reliability. 6. Finalize the Instrument: Based on the results of pilot testing and validity/reliability analyses, finalize the items for your instrument. Ensure that the instrument is comprehensive yet concise enough to be administered efficiently. 7. Scoring: Determine the scoring mechanism for your instrument. This could involve assigning numerical values to responses (e.g., Likert scale) or using a categorical scoring system. Consider whether reverse scoring is necessary for specific items to prevent response bias. 8. Administration: Decide on the method of administration for your instrument. It could be administered online or in person, depending on your resources and the preferences of your target population. Ensure to work with the Institutional Review Board (IRB) within your institution, county, state, and country. 9. Data Collection: Administer the instrument to your target population and collect the responses. Ensure that participants understand the instructions and have enough time to complete the instrument accurately. 10. Analysis and Interpretation: Analyze the collected data to assess self-efficacy and confidence in data science. Calculate descriptive statistics (e.g., mean, standard deviation) to understand the distribution of scores. Compare scores across different groups (e.g., novices vs. experts) to identify patterns and trends. 11. Validation: Validate the instrument by comparing scores with external criteria (e.g., performance on data science tasks and academic achievement). This can provide evidence for the validity of your instrument. 12. Iterative Improvement: Continuously evaluate and refine your instrument based on feedback and further research findings. This iterative process helps ensure the instrument's effectiveness and relevance over time.</p><p>By following these steps, you can develop a robust instrument for assessing self-efficacy confidence in data science that can be used for research, education, or professional development purposes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Design</head><p>This study employed a quantitative approach to develop a self-efficacy survey to assess students' confidence levels in utilizing data science skills and knowledge. The experiment consisted of two phases: survey development and survey implementation. In the development phase, a framework inspired by Vinay's data science assessment pathway guided the process through four key stages <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Vinay, 2024)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Malallah, Weese, &amp; Alsalmi, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Malallah, Weese, Shamer, et al., 2023)</ref>. First, a comprehensive literature review was conducted to understand the current landscape of data science assessment. No scientific research directly addressing data science assessment was found, prompting the creation of a foundational framework for survey development.</p><p>Second, a thorough literature review was conducted to identify the requisite knowledge and skills for a data scientist, guided by educator and industry recommendations. Data saturation determined the depth of the review.</p><p>The third stage aimed to establish a coherent sequence of data science concepts within the survey, satisfying interdisciplinary needs. This involved identifying the appropriate data science cycle to guide the arrangement of concepts. Finally, the survey questions were crafted in stage four, drawing from the intersection of the data science cycle steps and the necessary knowledge to fulfill them. The research implementation phase spanned eight weeks. Initially, the survey underwent review and modification based on feedback from experts in statistics, computer science, and business analytics. Subsequently, the survey was distributed online to 163 participants enrolled in data science and data analytics courses across collaborating universities in the USA, Kuwait, and KSA. A pilot study involving 33 randomly selected students from the same population, not included in the analysis, was conducted. Participants were required to complete an online consent form before beginning the survey, with an expected survey completion time ranging between 25 minutes and 40 minutes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Sample</head><p>The sample encompassed a diverse population of 163 individuals engaged in various data science disciplines, comprising 64.7% males and 32.4% females. Participants represented fields such as computer science, statistics, mathematics, and business; they were drawn from six educational institutions, including four universities and two community colleges. Geographically, 32% of participants hailed from the USA, 38% from Kuwait, and 29% from Saudi Arabia. Among the participants, 25% were researchers. The remainder were students (46.4% seniors, 21.4% juniors, and 7.1% first-year students). A notable portion of the sample, 42.4%, possessed prior working experience, albeit only 21% had worked within the technology sector. Regarding educational background, 26% of participants had never taken research courses before, 3% had never taken statistics classes, 8.8% had never taken coding classes, and 44% had never taken machine learning/artificial intelligence (AI) courses. Additionally, 32% had never enrolled in business analytics courses. The remaining participants had varying degrees of exposure to these subjects as part of their curriculum through one or multiple courses (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). The literature reviews were conducted using specific keywords tailored to each investigation area. The first literature review searched "assessment||self-efficacy" + "data science." The second literature review used the keywords "knowledge ||skills" + "literature review" + "data science ||data science education ||teaching ||learning ||teaching and learning." The third literature review utilized the keywords "data science||statistic|| mathematics ||computer Science ||business" + "life cycle." Searches were conducted in Google, Google Scholar, and ScienceDirect. Various source types were considered, including conference papers, journals, and blogs. The results were meticulously filtered by isolating abstracts and titles aligned with the search criteria. Studies that did not primarily focus on data science were excluded from the analysis. The search was refined to include only results from 2020 to 2024, except in cases concerning the data science life cycle. Furthermore, research on specific medical fields (e.g., medicine, dentistry, nursing, health professions, neuroscience, pharmacology, toxicology, pharmaceutical science, cancer, effect, and psychological studies) was excluded.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Instruments</head><p>The survey was carefully developed based on thorough analyses from literature reviews (see the Results section).</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> presents the investigation's final findings, outlining the 13 elements assessed. Column 2 categorizes these elements as data science life cycle steps and interdisciplinary skills utilized within those steps. The last column specifies the questions targeting each skill. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> contains the survey questions-48 items that evaluate the 13 distinct aspects identified in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Responses are assessed using a 5-point Likert scale ranging from strongly disagree to agree strongly. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.">Instruments Rubric</head><p>The instrument's rubric outlines thresholds for confidence levels using a 5-point Likert scale by categorizing responses. Self-efficacy confidence scores obtained from the survey were divided into three levels: 1-2.9 (low confidence), 3-3.6 (moderate confidence), and 3.7-5 (high confidence). This categorization applies specifically to the sample analyzed in this paper and may not be generalized to all populations. Future studies aiming to replicate this research should categorize results into three quartiles to determine an appropriate threshold for the data. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Results</head><p>This study analyzed students' confidence in building data-driven solutions in a data science education environment to deliver a coherent assessment. The following research questions were considered, and the responses were analyzed through repeated measures (analysis of variance [ANOVA] and descriptive statistics) using Statistical Package for Social Science (SPSS) software and Excel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Research Questions</head><p>RQ1: What specific data science skills and knowledge are essential for students to acquire to align with the demands of the industry? RQ2: What are the key steps involved in the process of constructing data science solutions? RQ3: How can insights from industry needs and solution-building methodologies inform the creation of a tailored survey? RQ4: How reliable is the survey? (Instrument reliability and validity) RQ5: Which skills and steps do students feel less confident about, as identified through the survey? (Instrument analysis) RQ6: How can interventions be designed to address these areas?</p><p>RQ1 -What specific data science skills and knowledge are essential for students to acquire to align with the demands of the industry?</p><p>The literature reviews below were used to design and set the survey content. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> lists the 136 created data science skills, knowledge, and tool ability. The first 39 were taken from Vinay's work <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Vinay, 2024)</ref>, the next 50 items from Usama Fayyad's and Hamit Hamock's work <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Fayyad &amp; Hamutcu, 2020)</ref>, and the remaining from Guoyan's work <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Li et al., 2021)</ref>. The list was clustered and filtered to generate the final list, which has eight categories presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, Skills 8-13. Google Scholar shows seven results, and ScienceDirect shows 73. All were excluded except one. Twenty-five results were found from Google Scholar. Two were chosen as they included extensive literature reviews with new information, and data saturation was satisfied. Vinay (2024) introduced a comprehensive framework to assess and categorize the essential competencies of proficient data scientists. This framework-which stemmed from a literature review exploring technical proficiency, analytical thinking and problem-solving, domainspecific knowledge, continuous learning, and adaptability in data science-provides valuable insights into the field. Vinay defined critical skills for proficient data scientists. The 39 competencies he identified were: Technical proficiency (1-10); analytical thinking and problem-solving (11-20); domain-specific knowledge (21-30); and continuous learning and adaptability (31-39). Although we did not use all his competencies directly, we cross-referenced them with other resources in the following steps <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Vinay, 2024)</ref>.</p><p>Fayyad and Hamock, in their study, introduced a comprehensive Data Science Knowledge Framework to foster industry standardization and the creation of measurement and assessment methodologies. Emphasizing data science's dynamic and multidisciplinary nature, the authors constructed the framework through an extensive literature review, identifying pivotal topics and technologies crucial for analytics and data science professionals. The findings were systematically organized into a hierarchical knowledge structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Fayyad &amp; Hamutcu, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Guoyan Li et al. analyzed the data science and analytics skills gap in the Industry 4.0 reports to identify the critical technical skills and domain knowledge required for data science in today's manufacturing industry. The authors used Emsi job posting and profile data to gain insights into the trends in manufacturing jobs, leveraging data science <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Li et al., 2021)</ref>.</p><p>The process of clustering 136 items was extensive. The list contained various categories, making it challenging to perform definitive clustering without specifying a purpose or desired level of granularity. Several options were available for clustering: domain, function, level of expertise, and tool/technology. We clustered the terms by skill, as it is our objective. We clustered the groups several times, and with every iteration, we merged groups until 14 categories remained: domain knowledge, scientific research method, statistical proficiency, mathematics proficiency, optimization/continuous learning and adaptability, data preparation and exploration, machine learning, general computing, technical proficiency, data management handling and database proficiency, business proficiency and communication, big data, analytical thinking and problem-solving and ethic. The categories have been reduced to eight after being validated by the experts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RQ2-What are the critical steps involved in the process of constructing data science solutions?</head><p>A data science life cycle embodies an iterative series of steps crucial for project or analysis delivery, tailored to each project's unique needs. Although no standardized workflow exists for data science, selecting appropriate steps is essential for survey coherence and suitability. Four models were identified and compared for common factors to address this, ultimately revealing eight key steps presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> showcase the identified data science models, where each row represents a model with its associated steps. Model (a) emphasized a data science education lens, encompassed the holistic data life cycle, and integrated workflow with environmental and social considerations such as regulations and ethics <ref type="bibr">(Stodden, 2020)</ref>. Model (b), viewed statistically, identified seven crucial steps in the data investigation process, including framing the problem, data gathering and processing, exploration, and visualization, model consideration, and communication of findings <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(LEE et al., 2022)</ref>. Model (c), from a business and computer science perspective, leveraged Microsoft's Team Data Science Process (TDSP) framework for collaborative learning, and aimed to convert data into actionable insights <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Saltz &amp; Hotz, 2020)</ref>. Model (d), which adopted a computer science and statistic lens, relied on CRISP-DM, guided data mining projects through six phases, from understanding business objectives to deploying models into operational systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Gupta, 2022)</ref>.</p><p>All models began with problem understanding, progressed through data acquisition and comprehension, and concluded with communication, either as a standalone step or integrated within the evaluation, depending on the model. While tasks such as feature engineering were categorized differently in various models, expert feedback determined the sequence, and the last row served to structure the survey flow and cluster competencies. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RQ3 -How can insights from industry needs and solution-building methodologies inform the creation of a tailored survey?</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref> presents the fundamental elements necessary for crafting pertinent questions. It aligned the identified skills with the data science steps to create a question flow that effectively fulfills dual purposes. Based on this approach, the final formulated questions are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. The pilot stage was subjected to validation through Cronbach's alpha testing to evaluate the reliability of survey statements; the validity was assessed using the Pearson correlation coefficient, presented in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_6">7</ref>. The calculated Cronbach's α coefficient resulted in a value of 0.915, indicating a high level of internal consistency among the survey items. This implied strong reliability, with the items collectively measuring the intended construct effectively, surpassing the widely accepted threshold of 0.7. Furthermore, the Cronbach's α coefficient was separately computed for the 13 sections, revealing internal consistency validity within the range of .6-.8. All scales exhibited convergent validity, with correlations among items exceeding 0.3, indicating robust convergent validity statistically, except for the correlation between Q28 and Q21, which was not statistically significant (p = 0.45). Assessment of internal consistency validity using the Pearson correlation coefficient showed correlations ranging from .57 to 0.90 for the survey statements. All correlation coefficients were statistically significant at the 0.01 level, highlighting the high internal consistency and validity of the questionnaire.  RQ 5 -Which skills and steps do students feel less confident about, as identified through the survey? (Instrument analysis)</p><p>Four of the 130 participants did not complete the survey and were excluded. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">8</ref> results were scrutinized based on gender (male, female), major (computer science, statistics, business, math, non-STEM), and the 13 identified skills/steps (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Significant findings corresponding to associated p-values were highlighted.</p><p>The effect size, denoted by eta-squared (η² = SS_effect / SS_total), was classified as small, moderate, or large. Notably, bold font indicated a large effect (η² = .14), underlined results indicated a moderate effect (η² = .06), and no markings denoted a small effect (η² = .01). The abbreviation "M" represented the mean, and "SD" represented the standard deviation. The analysis revealed a significant difference in scores (F(4,152) = .549, p = .00, partial-eta-squared = .086). All main interactions reached statistical significance at the .05 level-except for the data planning, feature selection, and model evaluation scores. The effect size was small for data planning and feature selection and moderate for domain knowledge, data cleaning, model design, and communication.</p><p>Confidence levels exhibited similar means for data planning (M = 3.5, SD = .9) and data cleaning (M = 3.5, SD = .8), followed by a lower but comparable trend between domain knowledge (M = 3.4, SD = .8) and communication (M = 3.4, SD = 1).</p><p>Group interactions did not show any significant differences. Descriptive analysis of group interactions revealed that the highest domain knowledge scores were observed near male statistics majors and female business majors (M = 3.4). The lowest was found among non-STEM females (M = 2.7, SD = .0). For data planning, the highest scores were attributed to male computer science majors and female statistics majors (M = 3.8). The lowest scores were observed among non-STEM females (M = 2.3, SD = .0). Regarding data cleaning, male business majors scored the highest (M = 3.08, SD = .4), while the lowest scores were among non-STEM females (M = 2.9, SD = .0). Female statistics groups attained the highest scores in feature selection (M = 3.4, SD = .7). In model design, statistics majors consistently achieved the highest scores, followed by computer science and business majors, with similar scores, and then math, and finally non-STEM. Female statistics students displayed almost the highest confidence levels compared to males across all skills and steps. Notably, computer science was intermediate, with business majors scoring higher than females in the same major. Female math and non-STEM students displayed the lowest scores in all areas. Research skills were most confidently identified with math (73%) and least with math again (61%), along with non-STEM. As expected from non-STEM students, analysis skills were highest among statistics and business majors and lowest among math students. Research skills were most confidently identified with math (73%) and least with math again (61%), along with non-STEM. As expected from non-STEM students, analysis skills were highest among statistics and business majors and lowest among math students. Lastly, business and statistics majors achieved the highest scores for business knowledge skills, with a confidence level of 72%, while computer science scored the lowest at 67%. The results indicate that 11.56% identified themselves with.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">A Suggested Intermediate Plan to Support Confidence in Data Science Education</head><p>An intermediate plan was derived from the background section to bolster confidence in using data science skills across various proficiency levels. Following the application of survey data, educators in data science can pinpoint specific skills or steps in the data science life cycle that require particular attention during instruction. Educators can select activities tailored to their classes upon identifying the skills/knowledge and the corresponding confidence levels.</p><p>Low confidence: (1) Individualized Support Sessions: Schedule one-on-one meetings with participants to discuss their concerns and address any questions or misunderstandings they may have confidently. Offer personalized guidance and encouragement to help boost their confidence. (2) Additional Learning Resources: Provide supplementary materials-articles, videos, or tutorials-to reinforce key concepts and provide alternative explanations. Recommend books or online courses that align with participants' learning needs and preferences. (3) Peer Support Groups: Facilitate peer support groups where participants can collaborate, share experiences, and provide encouragement to one another. Encourage group members to discuss challenges openly and offer constructive feedback and support. (4) Regular Check-Ins: Conduct regular check-ins with participants to monitor progress, address new concerns, and provide ongoing support and encouragement. Use these opportunities to celebrate small victories and acknowledge participants' efforts and improvements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Moderate confidence:</head><p>(1) Clarification Sessions: Organize group or question-and-answer sessions where participants can ask questions, seek clarification, and discuss areas of uncertainty. Provide clear explanations and examples to reinforce understanding and address common misconceptions. (2) Practice Opportunities: Offer practice exercises, quizzes, or problem-solving tasks to allow participants to apply their knowledge and skills in a supportive environment. Please provide feedback and guidance to help participants identify areas for improvement and build confidence in their abilities. (3) Mentorship Program: Pair participants with mentors or more experienced peers who can offer guidance, advice, and encouragement. Encourage mentors to provide personalized support and share their own experiences and strategies for success. (4) Self-Reflection Activities: Encourage participants to reflect on their learning journey, identify strengths and growth areas, and set achievable goals for themselves. Provide prompts or reflection questions to guide their self-assessment and encourage deeper engagement with the material.</p><p>High confidence: (1) Advanced Learning Opportunities: Offer advanced workshops, seminars, or projects for participants confident in their abilities and eager to challenge themselves further. Provide opportunities for independent research, creative projects, or leadership roles within the learning community. (2) Peer Teaching Sessions: Encourage confident participants to share their knowledge and expertise with their peers through peer teaching sessions or mini-workshops. Facilitate opportunities for participants to develop their presentation and communication skills while helping others learn. (3) Professional Development Resources: Provide access to professional development resources such as webinars, conferences, or networking events to help participants further their skills and expertise. Offer guidance on career pathways, industry trends, and continued growth and advancement opportunities. (4) Recognition and Rewards: Acknowledge and celebrate participants' achievements and contributions within the learning community. Offer certificates of achievement, badges, or other forms of recognition to acknowledge their dedication and accomplishments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion</head><p>The field of data science is experiencing rapid global growth, yet there is a notable shortage of qualified data scientists, posing concerns for academia and industries alike. Moreover, the lack of research in data science education assessments leaves uncertainties about students' skills before graduation. This paper addresses these gaps by developing a data science self-efficacy survey to gauge individuals' confidence levels in applying data science skills and proposing activities to boost confidence based on their levels. The survey-developed with input from computer science, business, and statistics experts-evaluates 13 items representing data science life cycle steps and related interdisciplinary skills. Distributed to students and researchers across six educational institutions, pilot results indicated high reliability and stability. Analysis revealed varying confidence levels among participants, with the majority exhibiting moderate confidence. Remedial suggestions include individualized support sessions and peer support groups for those with low confidence. High-confidence individuals are encouraged to pursue advanced learning opportunities and share their expertise with peers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Future Work</head><p>The survey will compare results across a broader sample from various continents, enabling a more comprehensive understanding of trends and variations in data science proficiency across diverse geographical regions. Further investigation will be conducted regarding the threshold scale.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Sample Population Source: Authors' creation</figDesc><graphic coords="5,107.32,576.96,384.10,100.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure3illustrates that 11.56% of cases fall within the low confidence range; moderate confidence accounts for 11.54%, and high confidence is 76.92%. Lower confidence levels were observed, particularly in model design, followed by feature selection and model evaluation, which can be attributed to deficiencies in analysis and calculation, optimization, and technical and computing skills. Conversely, higher confidence levels were associated with research design, data management, and data cleaning, possibly indicating stronger proficiency in these areas.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,73.50,165.47,448.23,140.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Students' Confidence Level in Using Data Science Skills for Building Data-driven Solutions Source: Authors' Creation Note style: Note. M = mean; SD = standard deviation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,79.48,343.38,436.15,343.38" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="9,72.90,96.12,450.44,413.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="11,74.00,225.07,446.62,220.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="12,72.40,104.85,448.50,143.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="13,79.50,568.19,435.75,164.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The Data Science (DS) Skills and Knowledge of DS Life Cycles</figDesc><table /><note><p>Source: Authors' Creation</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Data Science Self-Efficacy Survey</figDesc><table /><note><p>Source: Authors' Creation</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The Identified Items from the Literature Reviews</figDesc><table /><note><p>Source: Authors' Creation</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Identified Data Science Life cycle models</figDesc><table /><note><p>Figure 2: Identified Data Science Life cycle models Source: Authors' Creation</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The Used Skills and Data Science Steps to Construct the Survey Questions</figDesc><table /><note><p>Source: Authors Creation RQ 4 -How reliable is the survey? (Instrument reliability and validity)</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Person Correlations of All the Questions</figDesc><table /><note><p>Source: Authors' Creation</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Cronbach Alpha for the 13 Sections</figDesc><table /><note><p>Source: Authors' Creation</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Mean of Participants Confidence level Over the 13 Sections</figDesc><table /><note><p>Source: Authors' Creation</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgment: The opinions expressed in this work are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the NSF. We sincerely thank <rs type="person">King AbdulAziz University</rs> and <rs type="person">Mariam Alsalmi</rs> for their invaluable support in conducting this research.</p></div>
<div><head>Acknowledgment:</head><p>The opinions expressed in this work are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the NSF. We sincerely thank <rs type="person">King AbdulAziz University</rs> and <rs type="person">Mariam Alsalmi</rs> for their invaluable support in conducting this research.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Author Contributions: All authors contributed to this research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding:</head><p>The National Science Foundation (NSF) funded this work under Grant No. DRL GEGI008182.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest:</head><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p><p>Informed Consent Statement/Ethics Approval: Not applicable.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is data scientist still the sexiest job of the 21st century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Davenport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Patil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Self-determination theory. Handbook of theories of social psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Deci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="416" to="436" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward foundations for data science and analytics: A knowledge framework for professional standards</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Fayyad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hamutcu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Data Science Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Science</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.springboard.com/blog/data-science/data-science-process/" />
		<title level="m">Data Science Process: A Beginner&apos;s Guide in Plain English</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>FROM ACADEMIA TO INDUSTRY</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teacher expectations and self-determination theory: Considering convergence and divergence of theories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hornstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stroet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rubie-Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Flint</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Educational Psychology Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">76</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating data like a data scientist: Key practices and processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mojica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Thrasher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Baumgartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics Education Research Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="3" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data science skills and domain knowledge requirements in the manufacturing industry: A gap analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kamarthi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moghaddam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Manufacturing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="692" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social foundations of thought and action: A social-cognitive view</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Locke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987. 10510</date>
			<publisher>Academy of Management Briarcliff Manor</publisher>
			<pubPlace>NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malallah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Alsalmi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malallah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shamer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The &quot;besTech&quot; Technology Practice Framework for Early Childhood Education ASEE Annual Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023. 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Data Science (Dataying) for Early Childhood ASEE Annual Conference</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying the most common frameworks data science teams use to structure and coordinate their projects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Saltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Stodden, V</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2020. 2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The data science life cycle: a disciplined approach to advancing data science as a science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">High impact teaching strategies: Excellence in teaching and learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O E</forename><surname>Training</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Education and Training, State of Victoria Melbourne</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data Scientist Competencies and Skill Assessment: A Comprehensive Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vinay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal ID</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1544</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Decades of scientific research that started a growth mindset revolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Works</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.mindsetworks.com/science/onOctober" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
