<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Measuring, understanding, and enhancing nature connectedness</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">University of Tasmania</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_zSVaTBx">
					<orgName type="full">Australian Government</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kate</forename><surname>Sollis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Geography, Planning and Spatial Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tasmania</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sandy Bay Campus</addrLine>
									<settlement>Hobart</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">TAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>7001</postCode>
									<region>AU</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lily</forename><surname>Van Eeden</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Applied Chemistry and Environmental Sciences Melbourne</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">RMIT University STEM College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">VIC</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>3000</postCode>
									<region>AU</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Usitha</forename><surname>Rajeevan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Geography, Planning and Spatial Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tasmania</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sandy Bay Campus</addrLine>
									<settlement>Hobart</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">TAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>7001</postCode>
									<region>AU</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Brenda</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">CSIRO</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Land &amp; Water Ecosystem Sciences Precinct 41 Boggo Road Dutton Park</addrLine>
									<postCode>4102</postCode>
									<region>QLD, AU</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pauline</forename><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Wicking Dementia Research and Education Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tasmania</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sandy Bay Campus</addrLine>
									<settlement>Hobart</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">TAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>7001</postCode>
									<region>AU</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kate</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Energy, Environment, and Climate Action</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Government of Victoria</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">School of Agriculture, Food and Ecosystem Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<region>Victoria</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Parkville</settlement>
									<region>Victoria, BehaviourWorks Australia</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">Monash University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Clayton</settlement>
									<region>Victoria</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Emily</forename><surname>Flies</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Geography, Planning and Spatial Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tasmania</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sandy Bay Campus</addrLine>
									<settlement>Hobart</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">TAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>7001</postCode>
									<region>AU</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Measuring, understanding, and enhancing nature connectedness</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">06F21140BD6493EC424F2256D16E1BE1</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Nature connection</term>
					<term>measurement</term>
					<term>social justice</term>
					<term>demographics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>We acknowledge the Traditional Owners of Country throughout Australia and their continuing connection to land, sea and community. We pay our respects to Traditional Owners, their cultures and their Elders past, present and emerging. In particular, we acknowledge the Palawa/Pakana peoples, the traditional owners and custodians of Lutruwita/Tasmania and the land upon which the University of Tasmania was built. We acknowledge the contemporary Tasmanian Aboriginal community, who have survived invasion and dispossession, and continue to maintain their identity, culture and Indigenous rights. We also recognise the value of continuing Aboriginal knowledge and cultural practice, in particular the practices of caring for Country and Aboriginal land management and support the sovereignty of the Tasmanian Aboriginal community over land and sea. We pay our respects to Elders past, present and emerging, to those who never made Elder status and to the Spirit of this remarkable land.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Nature connection is associated with higher wellbeing and increased likelihood of performing pro-environmental behaviours, making it an important leverage point for sustainability <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Martin et al., 2020)</ref>. Spending time in or near nature can improve health and wellbeing through many mechanisms, the most prominent of which is exposure to clean air and the opportunity for exercise, socialisation, and emotional and cognitive restoration <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Hartig et al., 2014)</ref>. Having a higher connection with nature is associated with higher levels of eudaimonic wellbeing, especially measures of personal growth, and also measures of autonomy, selfacceptance, and positive relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Pritchard et al., 2020)</ref>. It has been associated with higher levels of pro-environmental or conservation behaviours <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Mayer &amp; Frantz, 2004)</ref>: people who feel most connected with nature are also the most likely to take action to care for it. This aspect of nature connection is why it features prominently in several conservation policies, including Australia's Strategy for Nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Commonwealth of Australia, 2019</ref>), Canada's 2020 biodiversity goals and targets <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Biodivcanada, 2015)</ref>, and the United Kingdom's 25-year environment plan <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(DEFRA, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Nature connection is a concept that has been used variably across different disciplines <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Ives et al., 2017)</ref>, but generally entails combinations of elements related to sense of identity, behaviour and activity, and felt relationship with the natural world. The proposed dimensions of nature connection are multifaceted, and include cognitive, emotive, philosophical, material, experiential and behavioural elements <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hatty et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Ives et al., 2017)</ref>. For example, nature connection research ranges from examining relational interactions between people and place to studying nature connection as a distinct psychological entity that affects behaviour <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Ives et al., 2017)</ref>. A person's connection with nature may shape, or be shaped by, how they perceive of nature. For example, people with strong connection with nature tend to describe nature in experiential (e.g., positive emotions felt in nature) rather than descriptive terms (e.g., landscapes, plants) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Hatty et al., 2022)</ref>. Previous research indicates that a stronger nature connection is associated with reporting feelings of wellbeing (e.g., reduced stress) when spending time in nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Mena-García et al., 2020)</ref>. Thus, understanding relationships between nature connection, wellbeing, and pro-environmental behaviours can be useful for informing policy seeking to influence any one of these dimensions.</p><p>An increased interest in studies on human nature connectedness has resulted in numerous validated scales to measure nature connection.</p><p>Widely used scales or measures include Inclusion of Nature in Self (INS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Schultz, 2001)</ref>, Connectedness to Nature Scale (CNS) <ref type="bibr">(Mayer &amp; Franz, 2004)</ref>, Nature Relatedness (NR) <ref type="bibr">(Nisbet et al., 2009)</ref>, and the CN-12 <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hatty et al., 2020)</ref>. These scales vary in how they conceptualise and measure nature connection. Some scales are unidimensional, single item scales, such as the INS which conceptualises nature connectedness through cognitive beliefs <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Schultz, 2001)</ref>. In contrast, other scales are multi-dimensional, seeking to conceptualise a range of different ways individuals can connect with nature. For example, the CN-12 has 12 statements to measure one's connection with nature through the dimensions of identity, experience, and philosophy. These dimensions explore how one includes nature in their self-identity, thoughts and emotions, behavioural elements, enjoyment of nature, and worldviews on the interconnectedness between humans and nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hatty et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Research on the CNS, another multidimensional scale, has found that the identity dimension tends to be the most variable across population groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hatty et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Nisbet et al., 2008)</ref> Despite these scales measuring nature connectedness differently, research has indicated that they are highly correlated <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hatty et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Tam, 2013)</ref>. For example, the CN-12 and its dimensions have shown positive correlations with NR, time spent in nature, biospheric and altruistic values, and pro-environmental behaviours <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hatty et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>It has also been posited that multidimensional scales may be more appropriate for measuring nature connectedness due to them having stronger correlations with related variables such as pro-environmental behaviours <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hatty et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Tam, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Whitburn et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>These scales have been applied around the world to better understand the different ways in which communities in different countries connect with nature. Indeed, in a multidisciplinary review, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Ives et al. (2017)</ref> identified that nearly a quarter of longitudinal and cross-sectional nature connectedness research used scales to measure nature connectedness, and that researchers were interested in nature connection as both a driver of other outcomes, and a benefit in itself. Much of the research on nature connection has been biased towards western and high-income countries, with most coming from the USA, Australia, Canada, Czech Republic, Germany, Japan, Singapore, United Kingdom, and The Netherlands <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Ives et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Soga &amp; Gaston, 2023)</ref>. It is possible that this bias is linked with concern for nature connection over the detrimental effects of urbanisation in these regions <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Soga &amp; Gaston, 2023)</ref>. A global systematic review examining trends of nature connection across (predominantly) high-income countries report a general decline in nature connectedness which varies based on geographic and socioeconomic factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Soga &amp; Gaston, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Through applying a macro-level perspective on nature connectedness, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Richardson et al. (2022)</ref> compared the association of country-level factors of declining nature experience across 14 countries across the UK and Europe. They observed that nature connectedness, as measured through the INS, was most strongly correlated with biodiversity, followed by having an ageing population (positively), smartphone use (negatively), and income (negatively). This highlights the significance of the biodiversity-nature connection relationship, identifying nature connectedness as an important factor in enhancing conservation behaviours and a valuable leverage point for societal shifts towards sustainability <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Richardson et al., 2022)</ref>. At the individual level, studies are shedding light on the complex associations with nature connectedness represented around the world. For example, while the act of smelling wildflowers has been found to be associated with health and wellbeing, the same study un the UK found no association between time spent in nature and health and wellbeing <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Richardson et al., 2021)</ref>. Within Australia, several studies have shown that different sociodemographic factors are linked to one's level of connection with nature.</p><p>In general, research shows similar patterns to those found internationally with individuals who have a higher level of education, higher income, identify as female, and older generally having higher levels of nature connection <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Chawla, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fuller &amp; Irvine, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Keniger et al., 2013)</ref>.</p><p>For example, a national survey in Australia found that that age, income, education, marital status and household structure are all important influences on various types of nature engagement (nature connectedness specifically however, was not examined) <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Zuo et al., 2016)</ref>. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Sockhill et al. (2022)</ref> explored the correlates of having ecocentric (as opposed to anthrocentric) values and found that those with ecocentric values tended to be older and identify as female, but earn below median income.</p><p>A study conducted in the Australian city of Brisbane found that people with higher nature relatedness reported fewer symptoms of depression, anxiety, stress and better overall health <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Dean et al., 2018)</ref>. Overall nature relatedness was higher in older people, females, those without children living at home, not working, and people speaking English at home. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lin et al. (2017)</ref> have shown that aspects such as urban form in terms of yard size, and certain socio-demographics are connected to the frequency and time spent in private green space. House age and yard size is positively correlated with vegetation cover in yards, and people with a greater nature relatedness and lower socio-economic disadvantage also had greater vegetation cover. Finally, in the state of Victoria in Australia, women and older people were found to have stronger connection with nature and were more likely to spend increased time in nature during the COVID-19 pandemic compared with other residents <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(van Eeden et al., 2023)</ref>. Living in an area of higher socioeconomic advantage and having access to nearby nature (e.g., parks, waterways) were also predictors of spending time in nature during the pandemic.</p><p>However, prior to this study, research examining the correlates of nature connectedness in Australia was localised to a city or state. These challenges have resulted in piecemeal knowledge of nature connection in Australia with a gap in our understanding of nature connectedness for regional and rural populations. This study fills this gap by conducting the first national deep exploration of nature connection and its correlates in <ref type="bibr">Australia.</ref> This study also seeks to strengthen the evidence base examining nature connectedness and its correlates in three ways. Firstly, we provide a detailed assessment of the different demographic and geographic factors associated with nature connectedness, and contrast these with the national and international literature. Secondly, we undertake a systematic comparison of different measurement tools to better understand their measurement bias and efficacy. Finally, we draw on the findings to put forward some policy recommendations on how nature connectedness can be enhanced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methodology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data</head><p>The survey was administered to an existing panel sample run by the Online Research Unit. 4,114 participated in the survey, of which 108 responses were removed after undergoing a data cleaning process to remove speeders (those who completed the survey in less than 20% of the median completion time), straight-liners (those who give identical responses to a battery of questions), and those who responded to openended questions with non-sensical responses. While the process screened for respondents who provided illogical combinations of responses, none were identified. This resulted in a final sample of 4,006 de-identified individuals, with the response rate being 5%, reflective of response rates for large online panels which are typically lower than other traditional survey methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Daikeler et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>The sampling strategy ensured good representation was achieved across several demographic characteristics. This included a quota to obtain approximately equivalent sample sizes (n = 500) in each state and territory, and an urban/rural quota of 50% of respondents residing in capital cities, 25% residing in major cities outside capital cities, and 25% in all other areas. Quotas were also set for levels of education within each state to help ensure the sample was representative of a wide range of educational backgrounds. These quotas were broadly met, with only the quota in Northern Territory not being reached (n = 306), an area that is typically hard to reach in surveys (Australian Bureau of Statistics, 2022a). The sample characteristics indicate that there was good representation across key demographics such as gender, age, and education status, and income (Supplementary Information).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Survey design</head><p>The survey included questions on demographics, open-ended questions on nature engagement and connection, nature connection scales, nature contact, barriers to engaging with nature, wellbeing and health-related quality-of-life scales, level of interconnection with different environments, and activities undertaken in different environments (see Supplementary Information for full survey). This project was has been approved by the University of Tasmania Human Research Ethics Committee (project ID 28109). All participants fully consented to being involved in the survey.</p><p>Nature connection was measured using two different measurement tools -the Inclusion of Nature in Self scale (INS), and the CN-12. We also analysed frequency of environmental visitation to examine how these results contrast with the nature connection scales. The INS asks respondents the degree to which they feel they are interconnected with nature, while the CN-12 comprises a series of 12 questions regarding nature connection across three dimensions (identity, experience, and philosophy) <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hatty et al., 2020)</ref>. Following the approach used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Hatty et al. (2020)</ref>, the 12 data items were averaged to calculate an overall score, with the data items in each of the three dimensions also averaged to obtain the dimension scores. Finally, the question on environmental visitation asks respondents how often respondents have spent time in nature, with nine response options provided ranging from 'never' to 'every day'. These three variables were chosen as they conceptualise nature connection and contact in different ways (the INS being a single dimension scale, the second being a more standard multi-dimensional, quantitative scale, and the third being a more objective scale of nature connecting behaviour).</p><p>Barriers to nature connection were assessed based on a question asking respondents "do you wish you could spend more time in nature?". For participants who selected 'yes', eight response options were provided, while four responses options were provided for those who selected 'no' 1 . 1 Response options for those who selected 'yes' were: Too busy/not enough time; Lack of access to nature; Costs of accessing nature; Health issues prevent access; Friends and family aren't into nature; Safety concerns; Unsure of where to go; and Other. Response options for those who selected 'no' were: I don't like spending time in nature; I feel I Responses which selected 'other' were analysed and re-coded to existing codes where appropriate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Analysis</head><p>Associations were assessed using regression modelling. For outcome variables that comprised a single Likert scale (INS and environmental visitation), ordered logit models were produced with the demographic variables being the independent variable. For the CN-12, which is a continuous variable, ordinary least squares (OLS) models were produced.</p><p>Population groups examined were based on key demographic variables collected in the survey: age, gender, Indigenous status, whether the individual self-identifies as having a disability, language spoken at home, employment status, highest level of education, personal income, socioeconomic status of area, state of current location, remoteness of current location, and remoteness level respondent grew up in. To ensure no multicollinearity amongst the independent variables, variance inflation factors were calculated which indicated that multicollinearity was not an issue (Table <ref type="table">6</ref> Variance Inflation Factor analysis in Supplementary Information).</p><p>spend enough time in nature; I think nature is scary or unsafe; and Other. Note there was a minor technical error in the survey, with participants who selected 'yes' being asked "Why are you not interested in spending more time in nature?", instead of "Why are you unable to spend more time in nature?". The majority of the sample (86.3%) responded as expected using the response options, while 13.7% of the sample responded as <ref type="bibr">'Other'. 5.2% (n=154)</ref> of these responses noted an issue with the way the question was asked. These responses were removed from the analysis on specific barriers. Some data transformation was undertaken for three of the independent variables: employment status, personal income, and remoteness level respondent grew up in. For employment status, a separate category for 'student only' was created based on combining responses to this variable and a separate question on whether the respondent is currently studying. Furthermore, 97% of the 62 respondents who noted their employment status as 'other' could be recoded to a pre-existing category based on the open-ended responses they provided <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> . Similarly for remoteness level respondent grew up in, eight respondents who identified that they live in "a mix of these/other" to childhood environment were recoded as they could be clearly aligned with one of the three other categories. The remaining respondents (n=45) were from a mix of environments, so these were recoded to "A mix". Finally, personal income was transformed to income quintiles data from the Australian Bureau of Statistics (2022b).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>3.1 Who is connecting with nature? The correlations between the three variables were firstly examined, indicating that the three are highly correlated (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). OLS models were then produced to examine the key socio-demographic characteristics associated with the three measures (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). The results indicate that there are some consistencies when using the three different measures. For example, females, those with postgraduate qualifications, and those who grew up in a rural/regional area are found to have greater nature connectedness based on the two nature connection tools, and also have higher environmental visitation. While there is little variation between older and younger Australians in relation to environmental visitation, those in older age groups were found to have higher nature connectedness according to both the INS and CN-12. Indigenous Australians had higher levels of nature connectedness according to the INS, but not the CN-12.</p><p>Highest level of education was found to be associated with both nature connectedness and environmental visitation. Those with a certificate/diploma and postgraduate qualifications had greater nature connectedness when using both the INS and CN-12 compared to those whose highest level of education was high school. Individuals with undergraduate qualifications had higher nature connectedness only when measuring nature connectedness through the CN-12, and all university graduates had higher environmental visitation when compared to those whose highest level of education was high school.</p><p>One's employment status was a significant predictor for the two nature connectedness measures, and environmental visitation in particular.</p><p>Compared to those who work full-time, individuals who are self-employed were found to have higher nature connectedness based on the INS, and those who work part-time had higher levels of nature connection based on the CN-12. Those who work full-time had significantly less environmental visitation than those who work part-time, casually, are self-employed, undertake home duties/volunteer work, or are retired.</p><p>There was little variation found between states. When using the INS, the Australian Capital Territory had significantly lower levels of nature connectedness compared to New South Wales (but not when using the . There was no variation found in the CN-12 model, while both Western Australia and the Australian Capital Territory showed significantly higher levels of environmental visitation compared to New South Wales.</p><p>While those living in regional and remote areas had significantly higher levels of environmental visitation than those living in major cities, there was less variation observed when examining nature connectedness.</p><p>Those living in regional areas had significantly higher nature connection when using the CN-12, with no difference found based on the INS.</p><p>Childhood environment appears to be an important factor, with those who grew up in rural/regional areas having significantly higher nature connectedness using both the INS and CN-12, and higher environmental visitation compared to those who grew up in a large/capital city. Note: *** significant at 1% level ** significant at 5% level * significant at 10% level. Base case is aged 51-70, identifies as male, Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander, does not have a disability, speaks only English at home, highest level of education is high school completion (year 12 certificate), employed full time, is in the third income quintile, currently lives in NSW, lives in a major city, and grew up in a large/capital city.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Examining nature connectedness through dimensions</head><p>The three dimensions of the CN-12 (Identity, Experience, and Philosophy)</p><p>were analysed separately to examine what dimensions are driving the differences between population groups (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>). Overall, similar results</p><p>were observed for the three dimensions, however there were some key differences. Firstly, the differences observed by employment status appear to be driven by identity and philosophy dimensions, but not experience. Those who were working part-time, self-employed, undertaking home duties/volunteer work, or retired had a significantly higher score than those working full-time for the philosophy dimension but not the experience dimension. There were also few differences observed in the Identity dimension in relation to employment status. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Barriers to connecting with nature</head><p>We found that 74.0% of respondents would like to spend more time in nature than they currently do (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>). Time poverty was identified as the biggest barrier to spending time in nature (72.2% of respondents).</p><p>This was followed by lack of access to nature (15.8%), health issues prevent access (11.8%), unsure where to go (11.5%), and costs of accessing nature (11.5%). A small portion of respondents provided an 'other' response (2.3%), mentioning barriers such as weather, ageing, restrictions in allowing pets to certain nature areas, caring duties, access to transport, and not wanting to impact the environment.</p><p>There are notable differences for some barriers by remoteness (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>). Lack of access to nature is more commonly noted by people in remote areas and major cities, highlighting that people living in regional areas are able to more easily access natural environments to engage in. Health issues preventing access is a more common barrier in major cities and regional areas, potentially indicating that the travel required in these areas to get to natural environments is a barrier for those with health issues. Finally, safety concerns are highest in remote areas, the reasons for which would need to be explored through further research. The barriers were also analysed by income quintile (Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>). OLS models analysing all the barriers by demographic and geographic characteristics indicated that certain groups are facing multiple barriers (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>). For example, when controlling for all else, people on lower incomes were significantly more likely to identify lack of access, cost of access, and safety concerns, while people with disability were significantly more likely to identify health issues, and safety concerns.</p><p>This analysis also identifies particular areas where policy reform can help enable greater access to nature. For example, certain groups, such as younger people and those who speak a language other than English at home were significantly more likely to identify being unsure of where to go as a barrier. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Limitations</head><p>Before discussing the results in greater detail, there are some limitations in the study that should be noted. First, as this was an online survey, there may be some sample bias toward those who are online. The sample was broadly representative of the Australian population (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">5</ref> Sample characteristics in Supplementary Information), and had adequate representation from older Australians who may be more likely to be offline. However, there may be some bias through unobserved characteristics.</p><p>Second, while the sample size was adequate for this analysis and broadly representative of the population, there were some population groups who were under-represented. Indigenous Australians, those who speak a language other than English, and those with highest education level as high school were under-represented in the survey. It should be noted also that larger states and those living in major cities were also underrepresented, however this was by design through the sampling approach used to ensure that analysis could be undertaken for smaller states and those living in regional and rural areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Discussion</head><p>This is the first national survey to explore nature connectedness and its variation across diverse geographies and environments in Australia. The findings make an important contribution to the existing evidence base on nature connectedness both within Australia and globally by examining the key characteristics associated with nature connectedness and assessing the use of different measurement tools. This section will discuss these results in greater detail by firstly examining the population groups who showed greater nature connectedness and how this compares to previous literature. We will then discuss the consistencies and inconsistencies in results between the three different measures, before finally outlining how policy can help support enhanced nature connectedness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Variation in nature connectedness across Australia</head><p>The findings indicated that those identifying as female, those with postgraduate qualifications, those who work part-time, are self-employed, or retired, and those who grew up in a rural/regional area had greater nature connectedness across all three measures. Further, when examining nature connection specifically we also find that older Australians, Indigenous Australians, and those who speak a language other than English are more connected with nature. These findings align with previous studies, specifically, for age <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Lin et al., 2014</ref> At a broad scale, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Richardson et al. (2022)</ref> found that that regions with a higher proportion of older residents and higher levels of biodiversity were associated with populations who had higher connection with nature. Combined, these findings may support that access to nature is an important factor predicting connection. However, urban vs rural residence and access to local nature are not always predictors of connection with nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Meis-Harris et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">van Eeden et al., 2023)</ref> and it is important to consider that populations are heterogenous at a local scale thus there are other, perhaps cultural and demographic factors, that may drive connection with nature more so than access to nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Selinske et al., 2023)</ref>. Our findings accord with this in that while there appeared to be a link between environmental visitation and nature connection for some groups, certain population groups had higher levels of nature connection despite having lower levels of visitation.</p><p>Examining the CN-12 dimensions provides some evidence to better understand what may be driving differences in nature connectedness. For example, our results show that variation in nature connectedness by employment status was largely driven by the philosophy dimension. This indicates that the higher levels of nature connectedness found for people in certain employment types is not simply driven by these individuals having more time to engage in nature. In contrast, the differences by childhood environment are driven by divergences in identity and experience, with no difference observed in the philosophy dimension.</p><p>The divergent dimensions driving the differences in nature connectedness for different population groups may be explained by some individuals having greater control over certain demographic characteristics (e.g. employment status) compared to others (e.g. childhood environment). More specifically, there may be an association between the type of person who elects to undertake a particular style of work (e.g. self-employed) and their philosophical feelings toward nature connection which explains the finding regarding employment status.</p><p>Adults who participated in the survey likely had less control over childhood environment, which may explain why both identity and experience were the dimensions driving higher nature connection for those living in rural/regional areas.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Sangha et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Yap &amp; Yu, 2016)</ref> this finding warrants detailed examination in future. Concerns have been raised that nature connection instruments have been developed primarily based on studies conducted with samples in Western countries, and thus may have limited relevance to more diverse ways of knowing and connecting with non-human nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Keaulana et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Sedawi et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Taylor, 2018)</ref> We are unaware of other studies that have documented this difference between measurement instruments for Indigenous respondents, although differences have been detected between in the applicability of instruments for English-speaking compared with non-English-speaking populations <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Tam, 2013)</ref>. We recommend that further research consider how and why different scales might be variably relevant to Indigenous communities and culturally and linguistically diverse communities more broadly so that appropriate tools can be used (or developed) to understand the population of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">The measure we use matters</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Enhancing access to nature</head><p>Our research points to various ways that policy can help enhance nature connectedness across Australia and globally. Firstly, the significance of childhood environment highlights the importance of enhancing access to nature for those in urban areas. This is especially important when considering that around 85% of Australians live in cities <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Coffee et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Ruming &amp; Baker, 2021)</ref> and that urban areas are becoming more populated and compact, leading to reduced green space availability <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Haaland &amp; van den Bosch, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Lin et al., 2015)</ref>. Thus, cities must consider carefully how to manage green space, and increase opportunities for interacting in green space in meaningful ways in order to maintain or increase levels of connection with nature.</p><p>While much of the policy in the past decade has concentrated on increasing the availability of green space in cities <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Aronson et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Threlfall et al., 2017)</ref>, a greater understanding of motivations to be in nature is changing the perceptions of interventions. Increasingly, research is showing that one's level of nature connection impacts on the how mindfully an individual interacts with nature, and this desire to mindfully interact with nature can act as a moderating factor in the wellbeing benefits gained from the time spent in green spaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Chang et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Dean et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Pritchard et al., 2020)</ref>. Policies that consider how to increase nature connectedness and create opportunities for meaningful interactions for urban residents can then increase the benefits accrued to individuals.</p><p>Recent research on affordances of nature has helped develop a better understanding of potential interventions useful for increasing mindful nature interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Brymer et al., 2021)</ref>. Understanding that different groups of people (ages, cultures, physical abilities) will have different needs or desired ways to be in green spaces is important so that spaces can be adjusted as communities change in neighbourhoods or even at the city scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Hadavi et al., 2015)</ref>. Green spaces need to be designed along universal access principles, as well as age-and dementia-friendly environmental design principles to maximise reach <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Fleming et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>It is equally important to recognise that individuals or groups may have to learn how to use and interact with different types of greens spaces to gain the most benefit from being in those spaces. Education around science and nature may be required to help individuals overcome fears associated with insects or animals. Programs around nature play, therapeutic horticulture or outdoor exercise may be required to teach people how to interact with green space in new, mindful ways <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Araújo et al., 2019)</ref>. A combination of adjusting the environment to meet the varied needs of the community as well providing processes to help people of all ages engage with nature (and with each other) are both necessary for increased engagement -especially as the population of cities change dynamically through space and time <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lennon et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Lin &amp; Andersson, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>It has been suggested that increasing opportunities for young people to interact with nature is important, as well as supporting older people's involvement in conservation, plus focusing on the need to target and direct various policies <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Zuo et al., 2016)</ref>. Our results support these recommendations showing the importance of childhood living environment for nature connection and the need to support older people to continue active engagement in conservation and other proenvironmental behaviours.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Reducing structural barriers to engaging with nature</head><p>Our research identified numerous structural barriers to engaging with nature that indicate a need for policy reform -particularly in the areas of public health and planning. Our findings show parallels between inequities of nature access and health inequities. It is well established that people on low incomes with lower levels of education experience poorer health outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Brown &amp; Homan, 2023)</ref>. These same indicators of social determinants of health -the conditions of daily life -are associated with lower levels of nature connection. People experiencing structural barriers to health and wellbeing are also faced with structural barriers to nature connection: a double bind, in effect. Conversely, if people with high levels of education, income and employment have greater nature connectedness, they are most likely afforded even greater opportunity for good health <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Barragan-Jason et al., 2023)</ref>. This finding suggests an important role for public health policy, with great promise for addressing this discriminatory situation. The incorporation of nature connection initiatives and opportunities into health promotion and preventative health strategies, for example, could be a simple step to create positive socio-ecological determinants of health and help to restore health inequities <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Jackson, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Another significant nature connectedness inequity with policy implications is that accessing nature is prohibitive to some people due to cost. Cost may include the actual price of accessing natural spacesfrom ticketed entry to parks, or high-end glamping and guided bushwalking tours. We need parks, wetlands, beaches and wilderness areas that are publicly accessible -free -spaces to ensure equitable access. Cost may also refer to the cost of travel to access nature. In many places, availability of free green space is increasingly diminished <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Colding et al., 2020)</ref>. People who live without 'nearby nature' (nature that is proximal to the places people live <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Kaplan, 1992)</ref>) can only generate their connection experience by going elsewhere. Compounding this cost is that travel can also be difficult for people with disability or health issues, requiring additional supports. The implications for urban planning policies are evident: free and open green spaces within walking distance of everyone's home would be an invaluable strategy for enhancing nature connectedness. The benefits would not only be for people without a home garden space, but also those for whom transport is difficult or unaffordable -rectifying multiple social and health inequities.</p><p>Our findings also indicate that although an embodied experience of nature is important (physically accessing nature) so too is enabling an emotional affinity <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Richardson et al., 2022)</ref>. This means that not only is the quantity and location of accessible green spaces important, so too is the quality of those spaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Oh et al., 2022)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Triguero-Mas et al. (2021)</ref> found an unsavoury practice of government and private housing organisations using the green space branding to sell housing, while not attending to pollution and other environmental degradation at those same sites. Attention to design principles, and incorporating green space and environmental management strategies into local, state and national environment policy areas is crucial to ensure that the benefits of nature connectedness are maximised.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusion</head><p>This paper presents the first examination of nature connectedness at the national level in Australia. It also contributes to the international literature on nature connection by exploring the correlates of nature connectedness, scrutinising various nature connection measurement tools, and exploring how policy can help support individuals to be more connected with nature.</p><p>Our results have shown that certain population groups have high levels of nature connection. This includes older Australians, those who grew up in a rural/regional area, those who work part-time, are self-employed, or retired, Indigenous Australians, and those who speak a language other than English. While our analysis cannot uncover the precise reasons for certain population groups having higher levels of nature connectedness, it likely comes down to access to nature, time availability, and cultural factors. Our analysis also emphasises how important it is to choose our measure of nature connectedness carefully, with our results highlighting that an objective measure of environmental visitation does not necessarily correlate with feelings of nature connection. Moreover, the two nature connection scales we used showed inconsistent results for certain population groups. In particular, Indigenous Australians, who are widely recognised to have a profound connection with nature, had significantly higher nature connectedness according to the INS, but not the CN-12. We suggest that further research should explore reasons for this in greater depth.</p><p>Importantly, our analysis points to valuable policy levers that can be used to enhance nature connectedness. These include increasing green space in urban areas, enhancing opportunities for meaningful interactions with nature in urban spaces, and addressing structural inequalities to provide greater opportunities to access nature for certain groups such as those on lower incomes, people with disability, younger people, and those from a culturally and linguistically diverse background.</p><p>Being connected with nature can enrich the lives of individuals and help support people to develop greater awareness of the importance of our natural environment. With the world facing global environmental and sustainability challenges, enhancing nature connectedness is one way that can help generate positive change for both people and planet.</p><p>7 Supplementary information   In this section, we will ask about different aspects of your health and wellbeing including how satisfied you are with different aspects of your life. We want to understand both how different components of your wellbeing (e.g. physical, social, mental aspects) might benefit from nature engagement or connection and whether there are any aspects of your health that interfere with your engagement with nature.</p><p>Wel1: Thinking about your own life and personal circumstances, how satisfied are you with the following aspects of your life: </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>3. 1 . 1 Figure 5</head><label>115</label><figDesc>Figure 5  Responses to environmental visitation question: "Over the last year or two, about how often have you generally spent time in nature?" in Supplementary Information for distributions).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 Barriers to spending more time in nature by current remoteness level</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 Figure 4 Figure 5</head><label>345</label><figDesc>Figure 3 Distribution of Inclusion of Nature in Self scale responses</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="46,72.00,105.45,397.50,289.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="50,72.00,71.95,342.00,201.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 Correlations between three nature connection measures INS CN-12 INS CN-12</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>0.648***</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Environmental visitation</cell><cell>0.413***</cell><cell>0.509***</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Note: *** significant at 1% level ** significant at 5% level * significant at 10% level.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 Full model output using the three measures of nature connection</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>INS</cell><cell>CN-12</cell><cell>Environmenta</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>l visitation</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 Ordinary Least Squares models with CN-12 dimensions as dependent variables Identity dimension Experience dimension</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Philosophy</cell></row><row><cell>dimension</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: *** significant at 1% level ** significant at 5% level * significant at 10% level. Base case is aged 51-70, identifies as male, Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander, does not have a disability, speaks only English at home, highest level of education is high school completion (year 12 certificate), employed full time, is in the third income quintile, currently lives in NSW, lives in a major city, and grew up in a large/capital city.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Barriers to nature connection by income quintile</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>90%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>80%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>70%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>60%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>50%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>40%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>30%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>20%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>10%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>0%</cell><cell>Too busy/ not enough time</cell><cell cols="2">Lack of access to nature</cell><cell>Health issues prevent access</cell><cell>Unsure of where to go</cell><cell>Costs of accessing nature</cell><cell>Safety concerns</cell><cell>nature aren't into family Friends and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1st quntile</cell><cell cols="2">2nd quintile</cell><cell>3rd quintile</cell><cell>4th quintile</cell><cell cols="2">5th quintile</cell></row></table><note><p><p>Those in the highest quintiles were substantially more likely to report being too busy or not having enough time to engage with nature. In contrast, most other barriers were faced predominantly by individuals on lower incomes.</p>Figure 2</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 Regression output with barriers as dependent variables Not enough time Lack of access Costs of access Health issues</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Friends</cell><cell>Safety</cell><cell>Unsure</cell></row><row><cell>aren't</cell><cell>concern</cell><cell>of where</cell></row><row><cell>interest</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>to go</cell></row><row><cell>ed</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>Note: *** significant at 1% level ** significant at 5% level * significant at 10% level. Base case is aged 51-70, identifies as male, Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander, does not have a disability, speaks only English at home, highest level of education is high school completion (year 12 certificate), employed full time, is in the third income quintile, currently lives in NSW, lives in a major city, and grew up in a large/capital city.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 5 Sample characteristics</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>National</cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>Percentag e</cell><cell>benchmark (2021</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Census)</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>18-30 years</cell><cell>832</cell><cell>20.8%</cell><cell>21.6%</cell></row><row><cell>31-50 years</cell><cell>1,289</cell><cell>32.1%</cell><cell>35.0%</cell></row><row><cell>51-70 years</cell><cell>1,334</cell><cell>33.3%</cell><cell>29.2%</cell></row><row><cell>&gt;70 years</cell><cell>551</cell><cell>13.8%</cell><cell>14.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Gender 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>1,913</cell><cell>47.8%</cell><cell>49.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>2,074</cell><cell>51.9%</cell><cell>50.7%</cell></row><row><cell>Non-binary</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0.3%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Indigenous status</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Identifies as Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander</cell><cell>79</cell><cell>2.0%</cell><cell>3.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Non-Indigenous</cell><cell>3,883</cell><cell>98.0%</cell><cell>96.6%</cell></row><row><cell>Disability</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Has disability/ies</cell><cell>363</cell><cell>9.1%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>No disability/ies</cell><cell>3,643</cell><cell>90.9%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Linguistic diversity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Speaks a language other than English at home</cell><cell>365</cell><cell>9.1%</cell><cell>22.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Speaks only English</cell><cell>3,641</cell><cell>90.9%</cell><cell>77.7%</cell></row><row><cell>Educational status</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Has not completed Year 12</cell><cell>353</cell><cell>8.8%</cell><cell>8.1%</cell></row><row><cell>Year 12 certificate</cell><cell>561</cell><cell>14%</cell><cell>33.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Certificate/Diploma</cell><cell>1,183</cell><cell>29.5%</cell><cell>31.5%</cell></row><row><cell>Undergraduate</cell><cell>1,052</cell><cell>26.3%</cell><cell>19.6%</cell></row><row><cell>Postgraduate</cell><cell>857</cell><cell>21.4%</cell><cell>7.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Employment status</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Full-time</cell><cell>1,716</cell><cell>42.9%</cell><cell>38.2%</cell></row><row><cell>Part-time</cell><cell>452</cell><cell>11.3%</cell><cell>21.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Casually employed</cell><cell>243</cell><cell>6.1%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Self-employed</cell><cell>258</cell><cell>6.4%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Home duties/volunteer work</cell><cell>208</cell><cell>5.2%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Retired</cell><cell>929</cell><cell>23.2%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Not working or studying</cell><cell>133</cell><cell>3.3%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Student only</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>1.6%</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Income quintile</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lowest income quintile</cell><cell>573</cell><cell>16.2%</cell><cell>20%</cell></row><row><cell>Second-lowest income quintile</cell><cell>813</cell><cell>22.9%</cell><cell>20%</cell></row><row><cell>Middle income quintile</cell><cell>527</cell><cell>14.9%</cell><cell>20%</cell></row><row><cell>Second-highest income quintile</cell><cell>1,015</cell><cell>28.6%</cell><cell>20%</cell></row><row><cell>Highest income quintile</cell><cell>616</cell><cell>17.4%</cell><cell>20%</cell></row><row><cell>State of current location</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>NSW</cell><cell>537</cell><cell>13.4%</cell><cell>31.8%</cell></row><row><cell>Victoria</cell><cell>533</cell><cell>13.3%</cell><cell>25.6%</cell></row><row><cell>Queensland</cell><cell>534</cell><cell>13.3%</cell><cell>20.3%</cell></row><row><cell>South Australia</cell><cell>534</cell><cell>13.3%</cell><cell>7.0%</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>10SECTION C: Nature engagement and environmental behaviours In this section we will ask you about what types of nature you interact with, what you do while you are there and how those interactions relate to other behaviours and values in your life.</figDesc><table><row><cell>If Yes, what are the major barriers to spending more time in nature? (select I vote for people, parties, or policies all that apply) 1. Too busy/not enough time that support nature</cell></row><row><cell>2. Lack of access to nature</cell></row><row><cell>3. Costs of accessing nature</cell></row><row><cell>4. Health issues prevent access 5. Friends and family aren't into nature 11 Section D: Wellbeing</cell></row><row><cell>6. Safety concerns EB1. Over the last year or two, about how often have you generally spent time 7. Unsure of where to go in nature? 1. Never 8. Other:</cell></row><row><cell>2. Less than once a year If no: 3. At least once a year 1. I don't like spending time in nature 4. At least twice a year 5. At least once a month 2. I feel I spend enough time in nature 6. At least once a fortnight 3. I think nature is scary or unsafe 7. At least once a week 8. A couple times a week 4. Other: (specify)</cell></row><row><cell>9. Every day</cell></row><row><cell>EB2. Over the last year or two, how often have you spent time in/at the PEB4: How often do you engage in the following environmental following places? [PROGRAMMER NOTE: Pipe into EC1 and EC2] NA (0) Neve r (1) Less than once a year (2) At least once a year (3) At least twice a year (4 At least once a mont h (5) At least once a fortni ght (6) At least once a week (7) A coupl e behaviours?? [randomize order] Nev Rarely Sometim Ofte Very Every N day er (2) es (3) n (4) often A (9) (1) (5) times I bring up environmental issues in a conversation with my peers week (8) I try to encourage others to change a</cell></row><row><cell>behaviour that I think is harmful to</cell></row><row><cell>the environment 1. A forest (an area filled predominantly with tall trees) I bring up positive nature experiences 2. A grassland/savanna/open woodland (an area with mostly grass or low in a conversation, such as interesting vegetation with occasional trees, not managed for domestical animal facts about wildlife or stories about grazing) things I've seen or done in nature 3. A desert/dry scrubland (a dry area with sand and rock and some hardy I share articles, pictures, or videos on vegetation) social media about nature or 4. A lake, river or other inland waterways environmental issues 5. A wetland, marsh, or estuary (Intermittent fresh water or is I consider environmental impacts regularly flooded with fresh or salt water. They comprise swamps, when making purchasing decisions marshes, billabongs, lakes, lagoons, bogs, fens and peatlands) (e.g. product/service waste, 6. An agricultural area managed for crops or pasture 7. The beach or coastal areas packaging, carbon footprint, 8. On or in the ocean water (as separate to the beach or coast) sustainability, local source etc) 9. A zoo or wildlife park I contact businesses or governments 10.A grassy parkland, botanic garden or playing field (managed, grassy about impacts on environmental lawns, some trees, managed footpaths) 11. issues I'm concerned about A community garden I sign petitions about environmental</cell></row><row><cell>issues I'm concerned about 12.13. Your own garden or yard at home I donate money to organisations that</cell></row><row><cell>protect or support the environment</cell></row><row><cell>EB3. Do you wish you could spend more time in nature? Y/N I attend protests or rallies related to</cell></row><row><cell>environmental issues</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Wel2. For these questions, please tick the box that best describes your situation as it has been over the past week Q1 How much help do you need with jobs around your place of residence (eg preparing food, cleaning, gardening)?</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell> I can do all these tasks very quickly and efficiently without any help</cell></row><row><cell> I can do these tasks relatively easily without help</cell></row><row><cell> I can do these tasks only very slowly without help</cell></row><row><cell> I cannot do most of these tasks unless I have help</cell></row><row><cell> I can do none of these tasks by myself.</cell></row><row><cell>Q2 How</cell></row></table><note><p>1. your life as a whole? 2. your standard of living? 3. your health? 4. what you are achieving in life? 5. your personal relationships? 6. how safe you feel? 7. feeling part of your community? 8. your future security? 9. the quality of your local environment</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>easy or difficult is it for you to get around by yourself outside your place of residence (eg to go shopping, visiting)?</head><label></label><figDesc>On or in the ocean water (i.e. as separate to the beach or coast)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Rest and recov er Rest and recov er Rest and recove r Rest and recov er Rest and reco ver Rest and recov er Rest and recov er Rest and recov er Rest and recov er Rest and recove r Rest and recove r Rest and reco ver</cell><cell> getting around is enjoyable and easy  I have no difficulty getting around outside my place of residence  I have a little difficulty  I have moderate difficulty  I have a lot of difficulty  I cannot get around unless somebody is there to help me. NA/I have never visited this place (0) Not connect ed at all (1) (2) (3) Somewh at connect ed (4) (5) 1. A forest (an area filled predominantly with tall trees) 2. A grassland/savanna/open woodland (an area with mostly grass or low (6) vegetation with occasional trees, not managed for domestical animal place (0) (1) (4) 1. A forest (an area filled predominantly with tall trees) 2. A grassland/savanna/open woodland (an area with mostly grass or low vegetation with occasional trees, not managed for domestical animal grazing) 3. A desert/dry scrubland (a dry area with sand and rock and some hardy vegetation) 4. A lake, river or other inland waterways Disconn ect from daily life Sociali se Accompa ny children to activities Engag e in physic al activiti es Engage in motoris ed leisure activitie s (e.g. dirt-biking, 4-wheelin g, off-roading Experie nce a sense of peace, tranquill ity or awe Engage in cultural activities Enjo y natu re Hav e a picn ic or BBQ Wal k you r pet Pass through to reach your destinati on Engage in Very strongly connect ed (7) (7) activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, conservation) Loo k up at the moo n or star s in the sky Disconn ect from daily life Social ise Accomp any children to activitie s Engag e in physic al activiti es Engage in motoris ed leisure activiti es (e.g. boating , dirt-biking, Experie nce a sense of peace, tranquil lity or awe Engag e in cultur al activiti es Enjo y natu re Hav e a picn ic or BBQ Wal k you r pet Pass through to reach your destinati on Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, conservati on) Loo k up at Go hunti ng G 9. A zoo or wildlife park fi n the moo n or star s in the sky Disconne ct from daily life Socialis e Accompan y children to activities Engage in physica l activiti es Experien ce a sense of peace, tranquilli ty or awe Engage in cultural activiti es Enjoy natur e Have a picni c or BBQ Wal k your pet Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, Look up at the moon or Go hunti ng Go fish g stars in the sky conservation) off-roading ) ) 5. A wetland, marsh, or estuary (Intermittent fresh water or is grazing) regularly flooded with fresh or salt water. They comprise swamps, 3. A desert/dry scrubland (a dry area with sand and rock and some hardy vegetation) marshes, billabongs, lakes, lagoons, bogs, fens and peatlands.) 6. An agricultural area managed for crops or pasture 3. A desert/dry scrubland 6. An agricultural area 10.A botanic garden or urban park with grassy lawns and trees 4. A lake, river or other inland waterways 5. A wetland, marsh, or estuary (Intermittent fresh water or is regularly flooded with fresh or salt water. They comprise swamps, marshes, billabongs, lakes, lagoons, bogs, fens and peatlands.) 6. An agricultural area managed for crops or pasture 7. The beach or coastal areas 8. On or in the ocean water (as separate to the beach or coast) 9. A zoo or wildlife park 10.A grassy parkland, botanic garden or playing field (managed, grassy lawns, some trees, managed footpaths) 11. 7. The beach or coastal areas 8. On or in the ocean water (as separate to the beach or coast) 9. A zoo or wildlife park 10.A grassy parkland, botanic garden or playing field (managed, grassy lawns, some trees, managed footpaths) 11. A community garden 12.Your own garden or yard at home 13.Observing the night sky 14.Other Disconn ect from daily life Sociali se Accompa ny children to activities Engag e in physic al activiti es Engage in motoris ed leisure activitie s (e.g. dirt-biking, 4-wheelin g, off-roading ) Experie nce a sense of peace, tranquill ity or awe Engage in cultural activities Enjo y natu re Hav e a picn ic or BBQ Wal k you r pet Pass through to reach your destinati on Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, conservation) Loo k up at the moo n or star s in the sky Discon nect from daily life Social ise Accomp any children to activitie s Enga ge in physi cal activit ies Engage in motorise d leisure activities (e.g. e.g. dirt-biking, 4-wheeling , off-roading) ) Exper ience a sense of peace , tranq uillity or awe Enga ge in cultur al activit ies Enjo y natu re Hav e a pic nic or BB Q Wa lk yo ur pet Garden ing activiti es Pass through to reach your destina tion Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, conservat ion) Loo k up at the mo on or Go hunti ng Disconn ect from daily life Sociali se Accompa ny children to activities Engag e in physic al activiti es Experien ce a sense of peace, tranquill ity or awe Engag e in cultura l activiti es Enjo y natur e Hav e a picn ic or BBQ Wal k you r pet Pass through to reach your destinati on Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, conservation) Look up at the Go hunti ng Go fis ng moon or stars in the sky star s in the sky A community garden 12.Your own garden or yard at home EC2a. Think about the environment which you feel most benefits your 11. A community garden 7. The beach or coastal areas 13.Observing the night sky 14. 15. Other _____ EC1a. Think about the environment in which you feel most (inter)connected with nature. Can you describe what it is about that place that makes you feel (inter)connected with nature (e.g. are there features of that place or things you do there that help you connect etc)? (optional) [open text] EC1b. Think about the times in which you feel most (inter)connected with nature. Can you describe what it is about that time that makes you feel (inter)connected with nature (e.g. what are you doing, who are you with, what is happening around you)? (optional) [open text] EC2. Please indicate how much you feel each of these places directly benefits your personal health and wellbeing when you visit it: [PROGRAMMER NOTE: DISPLAY ITEMS FROM EC2 =&gt;1] NA/I have never visited this No benefit to my wellbein g (2) (3) Some benefit to my wellbein g (5) (6) A great benefit to my wellbein g health and wellbeing. What kinds of experiences do you have that support your wellbeing when you visit this place? (optional) [open text] EC3. Please think about what you do when you have visited these different types of environments in the last year or two. Select all that apply. [Programmer note: Pipe this from EC1, exclude any marked 'never', or 'NA'] 1. A forest 2. A grassland/savanna/open woodland 58 Disconn ect from daily life Sociali se Accompa ny children to activities Engag e in physic al activiti es Engage in motoris ed leisure activitie s (e.g. dirt-biking, 4-wheelin g, off-roading ) Experie nce a sense of peace, tranquill ity or awe Engage in cultural activities Enjo y natu re Hav e a picn ic or BBQ Wal k you r pet Pass through to reach your destinati on Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, conservation) Loo k up at the moo n or star s in the sky 4. A lake, river or other inland waterway 5. A wetland, marsh, or estuary 59 Disconn ect from daily life Social ise Accomp any children to activitie s Engag e in physic al activiti es Engage in motoris ed leisure activiti es (e.g. boating , dirt-biking, off-Experie nce a sense of peace, tranquil lity or awe Engag e in cultur al activiti es Enjo y natu re Hav e a picn ic or BBQ Wal k you r pet Pass through/ by to reach your destinati on Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, conservati on) Loo k up at the moo n or star s in the sky Go hunti ng G fi n Disconn ect from daily life Social ise Accomp any children to activities Engag e in physic al activiti es Engage in motoris ed leisure activitie s (e.g. e.g. dirt-biking, 4-wheelin Experie nce a sense of peace, tranquil lity or awe Engag e in cultur al activiti es Enjo y natu re Hav e a picn ic or BBQ Wal k you r pet Pass through to reach your destinati on Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. coast care, conservati on, marine Loo k up at the moo n or star s in Go hunti ng G fi n Disconne ct from daily life Socialis e Accompan y children to activities Engage in physica l activiti es Experien ce a sense of peace, tranquillit y or awe Engage in cultural activiti es Enjoy natur e Have a picni c or BBQ Wal k your pet Gardenin g or lawncare activities Pass through to reach your destinatio n Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. landcare, conservatio n) Lo up the mo n o sta in the sky the sky debris cleanup) g, off-12.Your own garden or yard at home roading ) roading ) 61 8. 60 Disconnec t from daily life Socialis e Accompan y children to activities Engage in physica l activitie s Engage in motorise d leisure activities (e.g. boating, Jet skiing) Experienc e a sense of peace, tranquillit y or awe Engage in cultural activitie s Enjoy natur e Have a picni c or BBQ Wal k your pet Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. marine debris cleanup, starfish removal) Look up at the moo n or stars in the sky Go fishi Discon nect from daily life Social ise Accomp any children to activitie s Enga ge in physi cal activit ies Engag e in motori sed leisure activiti es (e.g. dirt-biking, 4-wheeli ng, off-roadin g) Experie nce a sense of peace, tranqui llity or awe Enga ge in cultur al activit ies Enjo y natu re Hav e a pic nic or BB Q Wa lk you r pet Garden ing or lawnca re activiti es Pass through to reach your destina tion Engage in activities to protect or care for nature (e.g. conserva tion, mange wildlife) habitat create ity, biodivers for Loo k up sky the s in star or on mo the at Go hunti ng</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>A common response to the open-ended question was that they are receiving the disability pension. This was recoded to "not working or studying".</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1"><p>The national benchmark figures for gender are based on a question asking the respondent's sex, for which only male and female are options.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>This project is supported with funding from the <rs type="funder">Australian Government</rs> under the <rs type="programName">National Environmental Science Program</rs> through the 1 <rs type="person">Sustainable Communities</rs> and <rs type="person">Waste Hub. Funding</rs> for this work was also provided by the <rs type="funder">University of Tasmania</rs> and the <rs type="funder">Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_zSVaTBx">
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">National Environmental Science Program</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Full survey</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">SECTION A: DEMOGRAPHICS</head><p>Please tell us a little about yourself and your situation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">SECTION B: Human-Nature Connection</head><p>In this section we will ask you questions about how connected you feel with nature and what 'human-nature connection' looks like for you. 1. I think of myself as someone who is very concerned about taking care of nature 2. My relationship to nature is a big part of how I think about myself 3. I feel uneasy if I am away from nature for too long 4. I feel right at home when I am in nature 5. Feeling connected to nature helps me deal with everyday stress 6. I feel a strong emotional connection to nature 7. I enjoy spending time in nature 8. I like to get outdoors whenever I get the chance 9. Being in nature allows me to do the things I like doing most 10.Everything in nature is connected (e.g. animals, plants, humans, water, air, land, fire, etc.) 11.Human beings and nature are connected by the same 'energy' or 'lifeforce' 12.Human wellbeing depends upon living in harmony with nature Q3 How easy or difficult is it for you to move around (using any aids or equipment you need eg a wheelchair, frame or stick)?  I am very mobile  I have no difficulty with mobility  I have some difficulty with mobility (for example, going uphill)  I have difficulty with mobility. I can go short distances only.  I have a lot of difficulty with mobility. I need someone to help me.  I am bedridden.</p><p>Q4 How difficult is it for you to wash, toilet, dress yourself, eat or care for your appearance?  these tasks are very easy for me  I have no real difficulty in carrying out these tasks  I find some of these tasks difficult, but I manage to do them on my own  many of these tasks are difficult, and I need help to do them  I cannot do these tasks by myself at all. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Q5</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="12">SECTION E: Nature Connection and Wellbeing across environments</head><p>In this section, we ask how connected you feel to/at/with different environments and how much you feel those environments contribute to your wellbeing:</p><p>EC1.Please indicate how (inter)connected you feel to nature in/at/with the following places:</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">People on Country: Vital landscapes, Indigenous futures</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kerins</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The Federation Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The empowering variability of affordances of nature: Why do exercisers feel better after performing the same exercise in natural environments than in indoor environments?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Araújo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brymer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Brito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Withagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Davids</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.psychsport.2018.12.020</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychsport.2018.12.020" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology of Sport and Exercise</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biodiversity in the city: Key challenges for urban green space management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aronson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lepczyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goddard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Macivor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nilon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vargo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/fee.1480</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/fee.1480" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/economy/finance/household-income-and-wealth-australia/2019-20" />
		<title level="m">Report on the quality of 2021 Census data</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Australia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Australian Bureau of Statistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019-03-20">2022b. 2019-20. March 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Household income and wealth</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychological and physical connections with nature improve both human well-being and nature conservation: A systematic review of meta-analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Barragan-Jason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Loreau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>De Mazancourt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parmesan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.biocon.2022.109842</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2022.109842" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biological Conservation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">277</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">109842</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Urban versus rural? The effects of residential status on species identification skills and connection to nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bashan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Colléony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/pan3.10176</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/pan3.10176" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">People and Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="347" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Biodivcanada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://publications.gc.ca/collections/collection_2016/eccc/CW66-524-2016-eng.pdf" />
		<title level="m">2020 biodiversity goals and targets for Canada</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The future of social determinants of health: Looking upstream to structural drivers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Homan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1468-0009.12641</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1468-0009.12641" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Milbank Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">S1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring perceptions of how nature recreation benefits mental wellbeing: A qualitative enquiry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brymer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crabtree</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/11745398.2020.1778494</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/11745398.2020.1778494" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Leisure Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="413" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A lower connection to nature is related to lower mental health benefits from nature contact</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>-C</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Astell-Burt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41598-024-56968-5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-56968-5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6705</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Childhood nature connection and constructive hope: A review of research on connecting with nature and coping with environmental loss</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chawla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/pan3.10128</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/pan3.10128" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">People and Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="642" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualising 30 years of population density Change in Australia&apos;s major capital cities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Coffee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00049182.2016.1220901</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00049182.2016.1220901" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Australian Geographer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Incremental demise of urban green spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Colding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Å</forename><surname>Gren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barthel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-445X/9/5/162" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">162</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Land</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Australia&apos;s strategy for nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Australia</forename><surname>Commonwealth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.australiasnaturehub.gov.au/national-strategy" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019-2030</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Web versus other survey modes: An updated and extended meta-analysis comparing response rates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Daikeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bošnjak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Manfreda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/jssam/smz008</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/jssam/smz008" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Survey Statistics and Methodology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is nature relatedness associated with better mental and physical health?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Dean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Shanahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gaston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Barber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Franco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1371</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A green future: Our 25 year plan to improve the environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Defra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/25-year-environment-plan" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Values and principles informing designs for people living With dementia-an emerging international consensus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fleming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zeisel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/26892618.2022.2062806</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/26892618.2022.2062806" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Aging and Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Interactions between people and nature in urban environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Irvine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/CBO9780511778483.008</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511778483.008" />
		<editor>K. J. Gaston</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="171" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Challenges and strategies for urban green-space planning in cities undergoing densification: A review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Haaland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van Den</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ufug.2015.07.009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ufug.2015.07.009" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Urban Forestry &amp; Urban Greening</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="760" to="771" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental affordances: A practical approach for design of nearby outdoor settings in urban residential areas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hadavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C R</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.landurbplan.2014.10.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2014.10.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Landscape and Urban Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nature and health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hartig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>De Vries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Frumkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-032013-182443</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-032013-182443" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Speaking of nature: Relationships between how people think about, connect with, and act to protect nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hatty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mavondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5751/ES-13369-270317</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5751/ES-13369-270317" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecology and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CN-12: A brief, multidimensional connection with nature instrument</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hatty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D G</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mavondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1566">2020. 1566</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human-nature connection: A multidisciplinary review. Current opinion in environmental sustainability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ives</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Giusti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Abson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Klaniecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dorninger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laudan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barthel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Abernethy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Martín-López</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Raymond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kendal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Von Wehrden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cosust.2017.05.005</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cosust.2017.05.005" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How can health promotion address the ecological determinants of health?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1757975917747448</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1757975917747448" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Health Promotion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="4" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The psychological benefits of nearby nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<publisher>Timber Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A scoping review of nature, land, and environmental connectedness and relatedness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Keaulana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kahili-Heede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L N</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Makua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Vegas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C K</forename><surname>Antonio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/18/11/5897" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5897</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What are the benefits of interacting with nature?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Keniger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gaston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Irvine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/10/3/913" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="913" to="935" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Urban green space for health and well-being: Developing an &apos;affordances&apos; framework for planning and design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lennon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13574809.2017.1336058</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13574809.2017.1336058" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Urban Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">22</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A transdisciplinary framework to unlock the potential benefits of green spaces for urban communities under changing contexts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/biosci/biad009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/biosci/biad009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opportunity or orientation? Who uses urban parks and why</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gaston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Shanahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0087422</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0087422" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">87422</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How green is your garden?: Urban form and socio-demographic factors influence yard vegetation, visitation, and ecosystem service benefits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gaston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Shanahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.landurbplan.2016.07.007</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2016.07.007" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Landscape and Urban Planning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Understanding the potential loss and inequities of green space distribution with urban densification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Meyers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Barnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Urban Forestry &amp; Urban Greening</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="952" to="958" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nature contact, nature connectedness and associations with health, wellbeing and pro-environmental behaviours</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jenvp.2020.101389</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvp.2020.101389" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101389</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The connectedness to nature scale: A measure of individuals&apos; feeling in community with nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Frantz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jenvp.2004.10.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvp.2004.10.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="503" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meis-Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Saeri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Boulet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Borg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Faulkner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jorgensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.ari.vic.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0030/443379/Victorians-Value-Nature-survey-results-report-2019.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Victorians Value Nature -Survey results</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of contact with nature on connectedness, environmental identity and evoked contents (Efectos del contacto con la naturaleza en conectividad</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mena-García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Olivos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Loureiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Navarro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/21711976.2019.1643663</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/21711976.2019.1643663" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PsyEcology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>identidad ambiental y contenidos evocados</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Nature Relatedness Scale: Linking individuals&apos; connection with nature to environmental concern and behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Nisbet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zelenski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0013916508318748</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0013916508318748" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environment and Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="715" to="740" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Connection to nature and time spent in gardens predicts social cohesion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R Y</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T P</forename><surname>Nghiem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L Y</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Quazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Shanahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gaston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Carrasco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ufug.2022.127655</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ufug.2022.127655" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>Urban Forestry &amp; Urban Greening</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127655</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between nature connectedness and eudaimonic well-being: A meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pritchard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sheffield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mcewan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10902-019-00118-6</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10902-019-00118-6" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Happiness Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1145" to="1167" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Country-level factors in a failing relationship with nature: Nature connectedness as a key metric for a sustainable future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hamlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Elliott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13280-022-01744-w</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-022-01744-w" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ambio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2201" to="2213" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moments, not minutes: The nature-wellbeing relationship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-A</forename><surname>Passmore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lumber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Wellbeing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Australasian cities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ruming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/9781119316916.ch5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119316916.ch5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Companion to Urban and Regional Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="108" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of capability approach to assess the role of ecosystem services in the well-being of Indigenous Australians</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sangha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Le Brocque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Costanza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cadet-James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.gecco.2015.09.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gecco.2015.09.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Ecology and Conservation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="458" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of environmental concern: Concern for self, other people, and the biosphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/jevp.2001.0227</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1006/jevp.2001.0227" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Challenges in measuring &quot;connectedness to nature&quot; among indigenous children: lessons from the Negev Bedouin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Sedawi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Ben Zvi Assaraf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11422-020-09995-3</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11422-020-09995-3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cultural Studies of Science Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Examining connection to nature at multiple scales provides insights for urban conservation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Selinske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Simmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.biocon.2023.109984</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2023.109984" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biological Conservation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">109984</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond the ecocentric: Diverse values and attitudes influence engagement in proenvironmental behaviours</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sockhill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R Y</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/pan3.10400</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/pan3.10400" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">People and Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1500" to="1512" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global synthesis reveals heterogeneous changes in connection of humans to nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Soga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gaston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.oneear.2023.01.007</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oneear.2023.01.007" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">One Earth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concepts and measures related to connection to nature: Similarities and differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-P</forename><surname>Tam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jenvp.2013.01.004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvp.2013.01.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial and ethnic differences in connectedness to nature and landscape preferences among college students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1089/env.2017.0040</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1089/env.2017.0040" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Justice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increasing biodiversity in urban green spaces through simple vegetation interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Threlfall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mackie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hahs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Stork</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S G</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Livesley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1365-2664.12876</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2664.12876" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1874" to="1883" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural outdoor environments&apos; health effects in gentrifying neighborhoods: Disruptive green landscapes for underprivileged neighborhood residents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Triguero-Mas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Anguelovski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>García-Lamarca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Argüelles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Perez-Del-Pulgar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Shokry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J T</forename><surname>Connolly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">V S</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.113964</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.113964" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science &amp; Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113964</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Demographic and spatial variables associated with spending time in nature during COVID-19 lockdowns</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Van Eeden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Squires</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hames</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bekessy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hatty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ufug.2023.127895</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ufug.2023.127895" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>Urban Forestry &amp; Urban Greening</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">127895</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analysis of human connection to nature and proenvironmental behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Whitburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Linklater</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Abrahamse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/cobi.13381</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/cobi.13381" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Conservation Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Operationalising the capability approach: developing culturally relevant indicators of Indigenous wellbeing -an Australian example</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13600818.2016.1178223</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13600818.2016.1178223" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oxford Development Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding and encouraging greater nature engagement in Australia: results from a national survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wheeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09640568.2015.1054926</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09640568.2015.1054926" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Planning and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1107" to="1125" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Certificate III/IV</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bachelor&apos;s degree</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Graduate diploma / Graduate certificate</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Other: ____ Disab: Do you identify as having a disability?</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Postgraduate degree 10</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">No ATSI: Do you identify as Aboriginal or Torres Strait Islander?</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Torres Strait Islander</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Prefer not to answer LOTE: What is/are the main language(s) you speak at home? 1. Only English</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Other(s) (SPECIFY): COB: In which country were you born?</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Australia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Other</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">*(if Cob=2)</forename><surname>Arr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>what year did you arrive in Australia</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CHE: What sort of environment did you grow up in</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>_________</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to age</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Rural/regional area</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>less than 50,000 people</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Small to medium city</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="250" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>thousand people</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Large or capital city</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>more than 250 thousand people</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PI: What is your approximate HOUSEHOLD income? This refers to the total income from all household occupants, and includes income from wages and salaries, government benefits, pensions, allowances and any other income you usually receive, before deductions for tax, superannuation contributions, health insurance, amounts salary sacrificed, or any other automatic deductions</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A mix of these/other: (SPECIFY) (ALL)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">1-$199 per week ($1-$10</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">$</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>399 per year</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">$200-$299 per week</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="400" to="415" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>599 per year</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">1,500-$1,999 per week</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">$</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="0" to="103" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>999 per year</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Negative or nil income 17. Prefer not to answer MarS: What is your current marital status?</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Separated but not divorced</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Married (in a &apos;de facto&apos; or registered marriage</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Are you a parent or guardian of a child or children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Echs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">No Pcode: And what is the postcode of your main residence?</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>___________</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
