<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">From Flagship to Firm: Gatekeeping, Employer Sorting, and the Returns to College</title>
				<funder ref="#_Uak8C3B">
					<orgName type="full">Harvard Institute for Quantitative Social Science</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_PBX3BU8">
					<orgName type="full">Russell Sage Foundation Dissertation Grant</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-10-16">October 16, 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Aleksei</forename><surname>Opacic</surname></persName>
							<email>aopacic@g.harvard.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Sociology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Clem</forename><surname>Aeppli</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christina</forename><surname>Ciocca Eller</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jessi</forename><surname>Streib</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nathan</forename><surname>Wilmers</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">From Flagship to Firm: Gatekeeping, Employer Sorting, and the Returns to College</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-10-16">October 16, 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">997524DABDDAE4FAD35909E99F364F51</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T14:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Firms increasingly drive college graduates' labor market earnings, yet the vast literature on the value-added of college has largely overlooked their role. Drawing on human capital theory and institutional theories of credentialism, closure, and organizational matching, I argue that college-to-workplace pipelines are a critical driver of college value-added. To test this, I assemble a novel US employeremployee matched dataset merged with postsecondary and high school academic records. Firm placement explains much of the variation in earnings premiums between colleges. Absent firm sorting, the range of counterfactual earnings di!erences across colleges would fall by 56%, and over half of the earnings advantage to attending the state flagship comes from access to higher-paying employers. These sorting e!ects extend broadly across the distribution of high-wage firms, and not merely a handful of elite employers. Crucially, sorting e!ects do not simply reflect skill-based advantages, implying that college quality derives as much from institutional linkages to the labor market as from human capital development. Policies aimed at broadening recruitment pipelines, rather than solely improving instructional inputs, are therefore essential to reducing inequalities in the economic returns to higher education.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Direct pipelines between specific colleges and employers have long been a staple feature of the American school-to-work transition. In the 1950s, the CIA targeted Ivy League college campuses in order to recruit the "best and the brightest",<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> while from the 1970s, select firms in law and management consulting became increasingly desired career destinations for graduates of top colleges <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Granfield, 1992)</ref>. McKinsey founder Marvin Bower was even so committed to recruiting Harvard Business School graduates that he established a fellowship program in his name at the school <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Lemann, 1999)</ref>, and the company soon had full-time employees tasked with recruiting from just this one university. Still today, significant shares of graduates from top colleges land at a remarkably narrow set of employers operating in a narrow set of sectors <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Davis and Binder, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b95">Townsend, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Yet the vast literature on the economic returns to attending specific colleges -or "college value-added" -largely abstracts away from employers themselves. This work convincingly documents sizable earnings payo!s to measures of college quality: attendance at more selective institutions generally yields higher earnings than attendance at less selective ones <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Brand and Halaby, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hoekstra, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Zimmerman, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Goodman et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Witteveen and Attewell, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b82">Smith et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Mountjoy, 2024)</ref>. What remains less understood is why attending di!erent colleges translates into such divergent labor market outcomes.</p><p>Two theoretical perspectives dominate. Human capital explanations for educational returns focus on education's productivity-enhancing e!ects, with workers paid wages corresponding to their marginal contribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Becker, 1962)</ref>. By contrast, longstanding sociological accounts emphasize the ways in which education acts as a sorting device into lucrative segments of the labor market <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Bowles and Gintis, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Parkin, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Bills, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Domina et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Collins, 2019)</ref>, where network advantages and mechanisms of social closure -such as licensing and credentials -bolster the economic value of degrees and certifications <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Weeden, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Weeden and Grusky, 2012)</ref>. While both frameworks highlight important mechanisms, their empirical application to the case of college value-added has been limited. And crucially, neither approach centers the firm as the organizational site through which human capital, credentials, and networks are converted into di!erential economic rewards.</p><p>In this paper, I argue that the college one attends a!ects earnings partly via its e!ects on firm placement. I propose that the sorting of students across employersspecifically, into high-and low-premium firms -is an important yet under-recognized mechanism underpinning the added value of college in the labor market. Through this process of firm refraction, colleges transmit and magnify educational advantage.</p><p>Integrating this mechanism into established human capital and sociological explanations clarifies how educational and employment institutions intersect to construct and sustain labor market inequality.</p><p>To develop this argument, I bridge the literature on college value-added with a growing body of work highlighting the changing structure of American pay inequality. Recent decades have seen rising earnings inequality among workers performing similar tasks within the same occupation. Working at an employer that pays above or below the market return to individual characteristics like human capital or productivity has become an increasingly important driver of earnings di!erences between workers <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Card et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Song et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Wilmers and Aeppli, 2021)</ref>. But while the consequences of firm-level sorting are well documented, the role of the college in sorting individuals into particular firms remains understudied. Prior sociological work emphasizes the role of social closure on the grounds of educational credentials at elite employers <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Ho, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b76">Rivera, 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b77">Rivera, , 2012))</ref>, and documents systematic pipelines between colleges and employers (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Davis and Binder, 2019</ref>). Yet the full extent of this pattern -its reach, e!ects on earnings, and contribution to college value-added -is unknown.</p><p>I address these issues by performing a unique linkage of administrative employeremployee pay records to postsecondary and high school academic records for the population of recent high school graduates in a US state.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> I begin by examining the extent of college-based firm sorting, and its role in explaining college value-added. Next, I examine whether this sorting is confined to elite firms, or extends throughout the broader distribution of high-wage employers. Finally, I assess one possible explanation: mechanical sorting based on worker human capital and productivity.</p><p>I document three findings. First, firm sorting is a powerful mechanism underpinning college value-added. Absent firm sorting, the range of counterfactual earnings di!erences across colleges would fall by 56%. Firm sorting accounts for a full half of the total earnings e!ects of attending the Flagship -the college with the largest earnings returns. Second, firm sorting e!ects are a pervasive form of labor market stratification, wherein the benefits of attending a more selective college are reflected throughout the upper half of the firm pay structure. Finally, firm sorting advantages overwhelmingly reflect non-human capital resources conferred by colleges, implying that a substantial portion of college premiums derives from credential and network, rather than skillbased, advantages. These findings point to college-to-workplace pipelines as a critical, yet so far under-examined, engine of postsecondary inequality. E!orts to close earnings gaps through higher education must attend to how postsecondary institutions connect their graduates to firms. ism, and certifications all contribute to closure <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Weeden, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Weeden and Grusky, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abbott, 2014)</ref>. At the same time, social capital and network resources conferred on students can be activated in job searches via contacts, referrals, and information provision <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">(Stuber, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Armstrong and Hamilton, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b90">Thiele and Gillespie, 2017)</ref>. These networks are institutionalized through Greek life and other exclusive campus organizations, but also through informal peer cultures and interactions that structure everyday interactions on campus <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">(Stevens et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Stuber, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">Ridgeway, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Michelman et al., 2022)</ref>.</p><p>Employers are left implicit in many of these accounts. Human capital models presume a homogeneous labor market in which all firms reward productivity in similar ways. Credentialist accounts recognize education as a closure device, but rarely acknowledge that workplaces themselves are key sites of exclusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Baron and Bielby, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b93">Tomaskovic-Devey and Avent-Holt, 2019)</ref>. And research that highlights collegebased networks does not fully flesh out the implications of facilitating access to specific employers.</p><p>Such an omission would be inconsequential in a purely competitive labor market. When an individual's wage is market-determined independent of any individual employer, certain colleges may produce more skilled graduates or provide them with credentials and network resources, but their graduates should earn more regardless of where they work: jobs, not employers, matter for pay. Yet, where one works is a growing determinant of pay and source of pay inequality in the US <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Groshen, 1991)</ref>. Research has found consistent di!erences in the pay firms o!er to workers, even workers with observationally similar skills <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Abowd et al., 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Card et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Song et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Wilmers and Aeppli, 2021)</ref>. Highly productive "superstar" firms in the technology and professional services sectors o!er exceptionally high compensation, while subcontractors and firms in retail pay substantially less <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Autor et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Krippner, 2012)</ref>. These di!erences in pay across firms are quantitatively important, accounting for up to one third of overall earnings inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">(Song et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Wilmers and Aeppli, 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Education and firm placement</head><p>In the following, I build on these insights to reframe a core assumption of much research on the returns to college. Rather than translating directly into higher wages, college resource advantages -skills, credentials and networks, as summarized in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> -may operate partly through what I term firm refraction. Human capital acquired at more selective colleges may increase productivity but, additionally, facilitate access to higher-paying employers. College credential advantages may operate via informal workplace-level closure by opening doors to resource-rich firms, rather than restricting access to certain occupational groups. And campus cultures may embed advantages by socializing students into expectations, pipelines, and networks tied to specific employers. This perspective conceptualizes colleges and employers as intersecting institutions that jointly structure opportunity, converting educational hierarchies into durable inequalities in employment and pay. By centering the college as a source of firm sorting, it o!ers a fuller account of how colleges generate labor market inequality. Human capital and firm sorting Higher-paying firms hire higher-skilled workers. Earnings bifurcation across employers has coincided with increasing segregation across di!erent types of workers: highlyskilled workers are increasingly employed by firms that pay more, on average <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">(Song et al., 2019)</ref>. Much of this pattern reflects increasing occupation-firm alignment <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">(Wilmers and Aeppli, 2021)</ref>: high paid software engineers work at high-premium firms, while low-paid cooks work at low-premium firms. But could these patterns of sorting partly reflect human capital inputs conferred by colleges?</p><p>If higher-paying firms privilege worker productivity in hiring and recruitment decisions, the answer is yes. Pay di!erences across firms appear, in part, to be driven by organizational di!erences across firms <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(Rosenfeld, 2021)</ref>, from formal structures like firm size and di!erences in production processes like R&amp;D intensity <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Barth et al., 2016)</ref>, to management practices <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Osterman, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Bender et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Bloom et al., 2021)</ref> and job-specific task allocations <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Hackman and Oldham, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Deming and Kahn, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b99">Wilmers, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Oldham and Hackman, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Ranganathan, 2023)</ref>. These di!erences -which translate into pay and productivity di!erences <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Kalleberg et al., 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Card et al., 2018)</ref> -may lead high-paying employers to compete for who they perceive to be the most productive and potentially high-performing workers via intensive skill assessment processes. Meanwhile, assuming that students across colleges have a preference for (and knowledge of) high-paying opportunities, graduates from colleges that bolster their human capital may perform better on employment tests, craft stronger applications, or interview more e!ectively. These colleges tend to be more selective, as the previous section outlined, though important di!erences in skill development may remain even among institutions without a clear rank ordering.</p><p>Just as important is the type of human capital cultivated across colleges. College major is a key form of specific human capital investment, with significant variation in earnings across students with di!erent majors <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Altonji et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Andrews et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Bleemer and Mehta, 2022)</ref>. Colleges that specialize in fields directly valued by high-wage firms -such as engineering, finance, or computer science -could reinforce sorting into high-premium firms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Credentialism and social closure</head><p>Human capital is imperfectly observed by employers: in contexts of imperfect information, managers may rely on signals such as college prestige or selectivity as a filtering criterion in the applicant screening process -even when candidates from di!erent institutions are similarly productive <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">(Thurow, 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Rivera, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Neely, 2022)</ref>. Highpaying employers may be especially likely to do this, due to the premium they place on productivity: degrees from more selective institutions may be seen as evidence of di!erential college value-added <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Deming et al., 2016)</ref>, or as a proxy for underlying ability <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">(Rivera, 2012)</ref>. In particular, <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">Rivera (2011)</ref> found that elite employers largely outsource screening of both hard and soft skills to college admission committees. Importantly, as Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> demonstrates, credentialism channels are not mutually exclusive from human capital mechanisms. At an individual level, students who struggle with college-level coursework are less likely to complete a degree <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Bound and Turner, 2011)</ref>; in aggregate, degree completion itself may serve as evidence of acquired skills at college <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">(Spence, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Deming et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Assessments of skill and competence are important, but likely not the only, drivers of employer decisions: hiring decisions at profitable firms may additionally reflect efforts to protect existing advantages via social exclusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Parkin, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b78">Rivera, 2020)</ref>. More productive, higher-paying firms may be especially likely to practice such exclusion. When incumbents at resource-rich firms are themselves class privileged, managers may select culturally similar workers to facilitate social cohesion and reinforce rent-extraction processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Fligstein and Fernandez, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Burawoy and Wright, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b98">Weeden and Grusky, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b93">Tomaskovic-Devey and Avent-Holt, 2019)</ref>. Over time, these processes generate credential-based segregation across firms, concentrating advantaged workers in resource-rich workplaces while excluding others.</p><p>Employer exclusion could also operate more di!usely through selective recruitment across campuses. Higher-paying employers -both at the very top of the firm pay dis-tribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">(Rivera, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Davis and Binder, 2019)</ref> and more generally <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">(Streib, 2023)</ref> selectively recruit across campuses. Meanwhile, less prestigious employers sometimes avoid the highest-ranked universities altogether, judging such recruitment "not financially sensible" <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">(Streib, 2023)</ref>. These selective recruitment practices provide students with strong cues in the low-information context of the labor market transition <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Deming and Kahn, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b87">Streib, 2023)</ref>. These practices not only constrain information about available opportunities and access to application pipelines, but could also spill over into supply-side behavior: anticipating exclusion, graduates of less selective colleges may deliberately target mid-tier employers rather than risk rejection from elite firms (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Pager and Pedulla, 2015)</ref>. In turn, these selective recruitment practices provide students with strong cues in the low-information context of the labor market transition <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Deming and Kahn, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b87">Streib, 2023)</ref>. Employer exclusion practices could also spill over into supply-side behavior -the targeting of non-elite firms at non-elite collegesin anticipation of exclusion (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Pager and Pedulla, 2015)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Campus foundations of firm sorting</head><p>Although schools may share broad institutional features, individual campuses often develop their own distinctive cultures and social dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Hamilton et al., 2018)</ref> and may themselves amplify patterns of firm sorting. Most directly, colleges di!er in their informal and formal connections with employers <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">(Rosenbaum et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Davis and Binder, 2016)</ref>. Some of these connections are mechanical, through distinct alumni networks resulting from credentialism and employer exclusions, but others may be more actively curated. Colleges with robust career services may actively procure partnerships with prestigious employers in select industries, such as the Corporate Partnership Programs (CPPs) documented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Davis and Binder (2016)</ref>. While especially concentrated at large, research-oriented universities, CPPs are also found across a sizable number of less selective state universities <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Davis and Binder, 2016)</ref>. University career services o!er powerful job search heuristics for students, who often source job leads through university databases and recruiting events <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Manduca, 2024)</ref>.</p><p>In addition to shaping informational environments, colleges influence labor market sorting through more di!use, cultural channels. Scholars writing in the neoinstitutionalist tradition emphasize how organizations shape individual identities and ambitions <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Meyer, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Granfield, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Stevens et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Stuber, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Binder and Wood, 2012)</ref>. Educational institutions are no exception: organizational di!erences across colleges can serve as powerful primers for student identity and career ambitions. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Binder et al. (2016)</ref> note that college freshmen at elite universities arrive on campus largely unaware of potential career paths, but an almost cult-like campus culture soon cements around the elite firms that advertise at campus events (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Granfield, 1992)</ref>. While partly driven by selective employer recruitment across campuses, identity shaping is also likely stoked by what <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Clark (1972)</ref> termed "organizational sagas": colleges vary in the density of their networks, the expectations they project about career success, and the localized status systems that define which jobs are seen as prestigious or appropriate for graduates <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Binder et al., 2016)</ref>. These processes may contribute to a broad prestige hierarchy, funneling students from more selective institutions into higher-premium firms. But, they likely also generate meaningful variation both within tiers of the college hierarchy -insofar as network ties, employer-facing channels, and institutional linkages to high-and low-premium firms develop unevenly across campuses even without clear national prestige. -and across the firm pay distribution -insofar as these processes play out among employers generally.</p><p>In light of the foregoing discussion, I propose three hypotheses regarding the role of firms in explaining college value-added.</p><p>Hypothesis 1: Colleges di!er meaningfully in the extent to which they sort students into high-and low-premium firms, even net of selection into colleges, and di!erences in firm placement account for a substantial share of the overall earnings returns to colleges.</p><p>Hypothesis 2: Attendance at a more selective college provides access to high-premium firms beyond those at the very top of the firm pay distribution.</p><p>Hypothesis 3: Human capital can partly, but not fully, explain college e!ects on firm placement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background and data</head><p>I analyze these questions in the context of one US state's public 4-year college sector. Per the terms of my data use agreement, I keep the identity of the state and institutions anonymous. I therefore refer to the setting as Summit State and use generic institutional labels. The set of seven 4-year universities in Summit State comprise a flagship research university, several branch campuses, a large state (R1) university, and multiple regional universities. The flagship is a large, highly selective public institution; College 4 is also highly ranked nationally, while the remaining institutions primarily serve regional markets. By focusing on a system where most students attend non-elite institutions but where meaningful di!erences in institutional prestige still exist, and therefore o!er a clearer perspective on how firm sorting and wage disparities emerge among a set of colleges which serve a large portion of the college-bound population, outside the context of highly selective private colleges <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Ho, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b76">Rivera, 2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Rivera, , 2015;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Binder et al., 2016)</ref>. 3 Notably, these institutions serve distinct student populations, reflecting the state's stratified pathways into higher education. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S21</ref> shows that the state flagship (the Flagship) and, to a lesser degree, College 4, comprises a more selective, higher-income student body, while regional public universities enroll students from diverse socioeconomic and racial backgrounds. All the 4-year colleges have seen a steady increase in racial-ethnic diversity over time, driven primarily by increasing representation of Hispanic students in the postsecondary sector.</p><p>Linking college students to firms and pay presents a methodological challenge, since traditional survey data typically do not contain employer identifiers, and employeremployee datasets on which firm pay premiums can be established tend to lack granular information on educational credentials or pre-college background characteristics. To overcome this challenge, I perform a unique linkage of three administrative datasets covering recent high school graduates, postsecondary enrollees, and the near full population of employees in Summit State between 2005 and 2022. 4 These data contain two critical components: (1) detailed information on educational attainment and academic records for a large share of Summit state college-goers, and (2) longitudinal records on earnings and employer a"liations for a substantial portion of the state's workforce. Together, repeated observations on both individuals and firms enables a decomposition of earnings into worker and firm-specific pay e!ects and an adjudication of the role of firm sorting in explaining returns to di!erent degrees.</p><p>The employer-employee data come from the state's Unemployment Insurance (UI) program, which requires nearly all employers to submit quarterly reports on employee wages and hours. These reports cover most private, local, and state public-sector workers and include consistent longitudinal employer identifiers, along with basic employer characteristics such as industry (NAICS code), location, and employment counts. Several groups -self-employed, federal employees, and active-duty military -are not covered. Education records come from the State Education Research Center (SERC). Postsecondary files include enrollment, course-level GPA, credits, degree attainment, institution attended, and financial aid filings. High school records provide GPA, school attended, and demographic characteristics (e.g., gender, race/ethnicity, disability status, and FRPL eligibility). Linkages across data sources are performed using Social Security Number (SSN) and full name.</p><p>I construct a school-year panel of 2006-2012 Summit State public high school graduates, 5 linked to their primary employer. Each worker-school-year observation spans fiscal quarter 3 through quarter 2 of the following year. My main outcome is annualized earnings, measured 10 years after high school graduation (with robustness checks at 15 in-state.</p><p>4 For all analyses, I use wages observed up to and including the end of school year 2022, that is, up to financial year 2022:Q2. 5 I define a graduating cohort in terms of the end of the academic school year -that is, the 2006 cohort refers to students graduating high school in 2006.</p><p>years where available), and adjusted to 2022 dollars using the CPI-U. Annual wages are calculated from observed quarterly earnings, and workers with multiple jobs are assigned to the employer where they received the largest share of their compensation, provided they are observed at their primary employer for at least two quarters in any given school year. 6 I link these employer-employee data to postsecondary records from Summit State's public colleges <ref type="bibr">(2005)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2006)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2007)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2008)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2009)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2010)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2011)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2012)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2013)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2014)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2015)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2016)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2017)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2018)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2019)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2020)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2021)</ref>. Postsecondary files provide information on institution attended, GPA, credits, degree attainment, and financial aid. To ensure that education is complete before analyzing wages, I assign to each individual their highest credential attained in the prior school year, prioritizing post-BA, BA, AA, and other degrees. If a student obtains multiple BA credentials in any given year, I attach to that student an in-state public degree if obtained, followed by a public or private 4-year out of state degree. If a student obtains multiple in-state BAs in a given year, I follow a rank ordering (flagship &gt; other public universities &gt; regional colleges) to capture potential institutional signaling e!ects. Students who pursue graduate education are retained in the sample, but their degree attainment is coded to their highest BA institution; in this way, graduate study is treated as endogenous to BA completion. I also use enrollment records to identify first enrollment institution, credits, and cumulative GPA. 7 Finally, I link individuals to high school transcript records, as well as to enrollment and degree certification records from private in-state colleges, as well as public and private out-ofstate colleges via the National Student Clearinghouse.</p><p>My core sample includes all high school cohorts beginning their postsecondary studies at a 4-year institution in Summit State for whom I observe positive UI-covered earnings in the relevant period and for whom I am able to estimate an employer fixed e!ect (see details below). I restrict the sample to 4-year starters for two reasons. First, students who begin at 2-year institutions and later transfer to 4-year colleges di!er systematically from 4-year entrants in both demographics and academic preparation <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Bowen et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Melguizo et al., 2011)</ref>. Restricting treatment e!ects to 4-year starters reduces potential unobserved selection given di!erences across these groups. Second, transfer students typically attend a larger number institutions, complicating the identification of distinct campus e!ects. Given the salience of distinct campus environments as a potential mechanism for firm sorting, restricting the sample to 4-year 6 I drop worker-firm observations with missing information on these attributes, and also assign a unique NAICS and location code to each employer per year. I also exclude from my analyses the small number of students working in firms operating in the Mining, Quarrying, and Oil and Gas Extraction industry (NAICS 21).</p><p>7 I define an individual's first enrollment institution to be that at which they first enrolled in college following the semester in which they graduated high school. Following <ref type="bibr">Mountjoy and Hickman (2021)</ref>, I omit enrollments occurring over the summer. For students enrolled in more than one institution in their first contact with the postsecondary system, I assign their institution to be the institution at which they attempted most credit hours.</p><p>starters o!ers a more focused analysis.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">8</ref> Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> presents descriptive statistics for this core sample (N = 48, 769). Among 4-year starters, there is meaningful heterogeneity by institution attended. For example, freshman admits at the State Flagship have the highest final high school GPA (3.69), while those at Colleges 7 and 6 have the lowest (3.21 and 3.17, respectively). The proportion of freshman admits who were ever on free and reduced price lunches also di!ers considerably across colleges, with the lowest rates at Colleges 4 and 5, as well as the flagship, and the highest at College 7. Among 4-year college entrants, there is notable variation in labor market outcomes by institution. Graduates of the flagship are the most likely to work in large firms (60%), in the Primary Metropolitan Area (62%), and earn the highest wages (log wage of 3.70). In contrast, students from regional colleges such as College 7 and College 6 are more likely to work in smaller firms located outside the Primary Metropolitan Area, and have lower average earnings and wage rates. There are also important di!erences in the likelihood that earnings are observed in administrative data: the probability of observed earnings is highest for Colleges 2, 3 and 6, and is lowest for the state flagship and College 4. Because I only observe earnings for individuals covered by the Summit State UI system (that is, for individuals who are employed in-state), treatment e!ects should be interpreted as local to the population of in-state, UI-covered workers. If certain colleges (e.g., selective 4-year institutions) are more likely to place graduates into jobs out of state, observed earnings may understate the full returns to those institutions. It is also di"cult to ascertain whether out-of-state employment reflects employment at betterpremium employers, or in better jobs at similar firms. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methodology</head><p>My analysis proceeds in two steps. The first step exploits the longitudinal nature of my linked employer-employee earnings data -specifically, fact that I observe workers as they move across di!erent employers over time. I leverage these longitudinal earnings data and tools from labor economics <ref type="bibr">[an AKM model (Abowd et al., 1999)</ref>] to decompose individuals' total earnings into a fixed component ("person e!ects"), as well as a component deriving from firm of employment ("firm e!ects"). The estimated firm e!ects give me a consistent and continuous measure of firms' pay premiums, which I can then use an outcome variable to tease out the firm component of college earnings returns. I treat person e!ects primarily as controls to help estimate the firm e!ects, though I additionally use them as a proxy for human capital in some analyses that follow.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Earnings decomposition</head><p>In the first step, I assume that the (log) earnings paid to worker i in year t is generated by the following model:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ln y it = ω i + Z → it ε + ϑ F (i,t) + ϖ it ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where ω i is an individual fixed e!ect, Z it is a vector of time-varying controls (including year fixed e!ects), F (i, t) is an index function that maps worker i to their employer in year t, ϑ F (i,t) is the firm-specific wage premium, and ϖ it is an error term that captures idiosyncratic shocks. The ϑ F (i,t) terms are my focal parameters. Firm e!ects can be interpreted as capturing the extent to which employer j pays workers a wage premium to their employees, in excess of the wage we would expect on the basis of their own characteristics alone.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">9</ref> Importantly, the firm e!ects in Equation (1) are only identifiable within "connected sets" of workers that are linked by worker mobility across firms <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Abowd et al., 2002)</ref>. A connected set is a network of firms linked together by observed worker mobility: two firms belong to the same set if there is a chain of workers moving between them over time. Because fixed e!ects are only identified relative to one another, estimates from separate sets cannot be compared on the same scale. I therefore restrict estimation of Equation (1) to the "largest connected set", which yields a single, internally consistent scale of firm e!ects. Appendix D provides further details.</p><p>I then apply these estimated firm e!ects to my sample of 2006-2012 Summit State public high school graduates. Specifically, for each individual, I attach the estimated firm e!ect corresponding to the firm at which that individual was employed 10 years following high school graduation. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows that just over 90% of 4-year college attendees are matched to an employer fixed e!ect (that is, 90% of these attendees work at firms in the largest connected set) and that this match rate is consistent across attendees at di!erent colleges. I use this sample for my main empirical analyses estimate causal e!ects of college attendance via and net of firms I use this model to estimate firm e!ects rather than an approach which jointly estimates firm and college e!ects (such as with traditional mediation analysis -see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_28">24</ref> in Appendix E), because it adjusts for patterns of selection into firms that are unobserved by the researcher. If workers di!er in time invariant ways in their productivity in ways not captured by pre-college control variables, the person e!ect (ω i ) parameters absorb this variation. The model does, however, assume away any time-varying unobserved confounders that may predict both firm selection and wages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Estimating the role of firm sorting</head><p>In the second step, I use the firm e!ect attached to each individual to parse out the role of employer sorting in educational returns.</p><p>Let J = {College 7,. . . , College 2, Flagship} denote the set of 4-year public colleges in Summit State; Y denote an individual's earnings 10 years following high school graduation, and let M denote an individual's firm, also at 10 years following high school graduation. I use potential outcomes notation to refer to counterfactual quantities under receipt of a BA from di!erent colleges. Specifically (suppressing subscripts i), I use Y (j) to denote an individual's potential earnings were they to attend college j → J (possibly contrary to fact). I assess the value-added of a attendance at a particular institution relative to attendance at College 7, the college with the lowest raw earnings return in the state. The average treatment e!ect of attending college j relative to attending College 7 can be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ATE Y (j) = E[Y (j) ↑ Y (College 7)].<label>(2)</label></formula><p>To assess the role of firm sorting in mediating the earnings return to a credential from school j (Hypothesis 1), I employ a causal mediation framework. To do so, I make use of the "nested" counterfactual Y (College 7, M(j)). Intuitively, this quantity captures an individual's potential earnings, were they to attend College 7, but worked at the firm that attendance at school j would have directed them to. To assess mediation via firms, we can decompose the ATE of attending school j relative to College 7 as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">ATE Y (j) = E[Y j, M (j) ↑ Y College 7, M(j) ]</formula><p>Explained by earnings gains net of firm sorting</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">+ E[Y College 7, M(j) ↑ Y College 7, M(College 7) ]</formula><p>Explained by between-firm sorting .</p><p>To identify the quantity E[Y College 7, M(j) , I exploit the fact that the earnings decomposition in Equation (1) implies that the value-added to working at a given firm is constant across employees. Under this structural model for earnings, the portion of the total e!ect of attending college j versus College 7 driven by firm sorting is equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">ATE ω (j) = E[ϑ(j) ↑ ϑ(College 7)],</formula><p>(3) that is, the average treatment e!ect of attending college j on a worker's firm premium (see Appendix A). Here, ϑ(j) denotes the potential firm premium of student i if they attended college j → J , corresponding to an individual's employer 10 years after high school graduation. 10 Importantly, the quantity in Equation (3) also captures the the extent to which college j shapes access to high-premium firms, directly addressing Hypothesis 1). Under the assumption of no unobserved confounding for the e!ect of college attendance on within-and between-firm earnings, Equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>) and (3) can be identified via the standard identification formula for the average treatment e!ect (see Appendix B). To make this assumption more plausible, I leverage the administrative registries to compile a large battery of pre-college and college-level covariates. These include basic demographic variables (gender, race, age, high school test scores), precollege characteristics such as FRPL, English language ability, and disability status, as well as high school fixed e!ects. In some analyses, I estimate cumulative e!ects of college attendance and completion on earnings and firm premiums; for these analyses, I use information on first term credit attainment and credit attempts, first term college GPA, and cumulative institution GPA per student at the time of graduation or, if failing to graduate, of dropout. Due to the high-dimensional nature of my control variables, I estimate all quantities using ridge regressions and a double machine learning approach for valid inference. All quantities are estimated for the population of high school graduates who are begin their postsecondary studies at a 4-year college (high school graduating classes <ref type="bibr">[2006]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2007]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2008]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2009]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2010]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2011]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2012]</ref>. Appendix B provides further details.</p><p>10 I assume that the employer fixed e!ects estimated via Equation 1 are measured with negligible error, given the full-population nature of the UI data. Uncertainty estimates then come from uncertainty in estimation of average treatment e!ects. <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Kline (2024)</ref> further shows that downward bias resulting from failing to account for correlation between estimated firm e!ects can outweigh the upward bias attributable to treating firm e!ects as random draws from a super population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>I first document observed gaps in both earnings (teal bars) and firm premiums (orange bars) across 4-year college enrollees. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, top panel, plots mean log earnings gaps between students who first enrolled in each 4-year public college, relative to students first enrolling at College 7, 10 years out from high school graduation. Point estimates are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">16</ref> in Appendix H. There is substantial earnings variation by institution attended. Students who enroll at College 7 have the lowest average earnings (10.738 log points) and lowest mean firm premiums. Students who enroll at the flagship stand out, earning on average .411 log points more than College 7 attendees, and obtaining a firm with a pay premium that is .131 points higher than that attained by College 7 attendees. This is followed by Colleges 2 and 4, with earnings premiums of .258 and .246, and firm premiums of .125 and .073, respectively, and then by Colleges 5 and 6. These raw log earnings gaps are sizable, especially at such an early stage following labor market entry, and in fact exceed the .34 log earnings gap between 4-year starters and the non-4-year starting population (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Do firms mediate the college premium?</head><p>Raw di!erences in earnings and firm premiums across di!erent college attendees may be the result of selection into colleges and the e!ects of college attendance itself. To illustrate the strength of these di!erences even among observationally similar students, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> presents a descriptive view of firm placement by pre-college achievement. Even among students with comparable high school GPAs, institution attended is a strong predictor of the type of firm at which a person works. Flagship and College 2 attendees are employed at markedly higher-premium firms than peers from other colleges, especially those who attended Colleges 5, 6 and 7. Institutional di!erences remain pronounced across the entire GPA distribution: the hierarchy in firm placement is largely preserved even among high-achieving students. For example, students attending the Flagship rather than College 7 with a high school GPA between 2.8 and 3.0 work at firms paying an average premium .11 log points higher (corresponding to a 12% earnings increase). Among students with GPAs between 3.8 and 4.0, this gap rises to .15 log points (implying roughly a 16% earnings increase).</p><p>This simple descriptive comparison underscores how sharply firm sorting tracks institutional a"liation, rather than pre-college academic preparation. To more formally adjust for selection on a broader range of pre-college characteristics, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, bottom panel, plots the treatment e!ects of attending di!erent Summit State colleges relative to College 7 attendance (teal bars), using the large set of control variables described previously. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_16">17</ref> in Appendix H presents corresponding point estimates. Raw earn-ings gaps depreciate significantly after adjusting for selection into college (teal bars). Relative to a baseline of 10.91 log earnings -which captures a person's earnings if they counterfactually attended College 7 -attending the state's flagship campus causes an average increase in earnings by .134 log points (14%).<ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">11</ref> Beyond the flagship, attending College 2 or College 4 corresponds to smaller but still sizable earnings gains, at .06 and .085 log points, respectively. Adjusting for selection into colleges further alters the rank ordering of earnings returns across colleges. Colleges 5 and 6 have raw earnings premiums relative to College 7, but this does not reflect a causal relationship: College 6 attendance provides almost no earnings return, relative to College 7, while attendance at College 5 provides a sizable earnings loss of approximately 5%. These is driven by di!erential selection across colleges. College 7 attendees have significantly lower high school GPAs, and comprise a large Black and Hispanic student population. By contrast, College 5 serves a predominantly White and academically strong student body; the average high school GPA of freshman enrollees stands only behind the Flagship (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). These findings echo those in Ciocca-Eller (2023), who found that colleges' rankings in terms of observed BA completion rates do not necessarily map onto the causal e!ects of each college on BA completion.</p><p>The orange bars in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> show the e!ect of attending college j relative to College 7 on expected firm premiums (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>). Attending the state flagship yields the largest firm premium, amounting to a 7% increase in pay relative to College 7 attendance. This is followed closely by College 2 attendance, and to a lesser extent, Colleges 3 and 4. By contrast, College 5 and 6 attendees work at firms with lower estimated pay premia than those who attended College 7. While college attendance e!ects on firm premiums are smaller than unadjusted raw gaps in firm premiums across colleges, the degree of attenuation is far less pronounced than the attenuation of total overall earnings gaps across colleges. For example, while the flagship log earnings gap (relative to College 7) falls by .277 log points after adjusting for selection, the flagship firm premium gap (relative to College 7) falls by only .73 log points. This implies that characteristics that predict college attendance are more strongly associated with within-firm earnings gains, rather than with earnings gains which result from cross-firm sorting. These patterns suggest that colleges meaningfully a!ect firm assignment, supporting Hypothesis 1. While Flagship or College 2 attendance sorts students into the highest-paying employers, there is still meaningful variation in firm placement among the regional colleges, with College 7 in fact conferring a positive firm advantage relative to College 5 and College 6.</p><p>How significant are these firm sorting patterns for college returns overall? Under the structural model for earnings described in Equation 1, the firm premium returns (orange bars) in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, bottom panel, represent the fraction of college premiums explained by firms (Equation <ref type="formula">3</ref>). Firms account for a full half of the 14% earnings return to Flagship attendance (relative to College 7), and almost entirely account for the earnings advantages of attending Colleges 2 and 3, and negative e!ects of College 6. By contrast, within-firm di!erences appear to matter more for Colleges 4 and 5: firm sorting accounts for approximately one-third and one-fifth, respectively, of these colleges' total earnings return relative to College 7. Importantly, the range of counterfactual earnings di!erences under attendance at di!erent colleges would fall dramatically if firm sorting channels did not exist. The range of total potential earnings between the Flagship and College 5 (the college with the lowest counterfactual earnings returns) is .18 (.134+.046). Absent firm sorting, this would abate to 0.101 (.066+.035), implying a reduction of 56%. Taken together, these results support Hypothesis 1 -that firm placement contributes meaningfully to overall earnings returns to di!erent colleges.  How pervasive is firm sorting?</p><p>Attending the state flagship sorts students into firms that, on average, pay more. But to what extent is driven by access to the highest-paying, elite firms?</p><p>To answer this question, I re-estimate treatment e!ects on firm attainment defined in terms of its percentile rank in the overall firm premium distribution. Specifically, I define a set of binary outcomes indicating whether a student works at a firm at or above the 60th, 70th, 80th, 90th, or 95th percentiles of the firm fixed e!ect distribution. I reestimate Equation (3), replacing the ϑ terms with a set of indicator variables, equal to one if an individual works at a firm at or above percentile p, for p → 60, 70, 80, 90, 95. 12  This percentile-based approach provides insight into whether college e!ects are concentrated at the top of the firm hierarchy, or whether more selective colleges facilitate access to better-premium firms more broadly throughout the distribution.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> shows these estimates, with each point capturing the e!ect of attending a given college (versus College 7) on the probability of working at a firm at or above the indicated percentile. The full set of point estimates is provided in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_18">18</ref> in Appendix H. Attending the Flagship increases the likelihood of working at a firm in the top 95th percentile of the pay distribution by 3.1 percentage points, but increases the probability of working at a firm at or above the 90th percentile by 5.4 percentage points, the 80th percentile by 9.2 percentage points, and the 70th and 60th percentiles by 11.8 and 12.3 percentage points, respectively, relative to College 7. Similar patterns hold for College 2 and, to a lesser extent, Colleges 3 and 4. In contrast, Colleges 5 and 6 show no meaningful firm sorting advantages across the distribution, with College 6 estimates even negative at lower percentiles.</p><p>Firm sorting, then, is not limited to access to only the most elite firms (Hypothesis 2). Rather, more selective colleges such as the Flagship and College 4 appear to systematically expand access to higher-premium employers across the broader distribution of firms. This points to a more di!use but pervasive form of labor market stratification, where the benefits of attending a more selective college are reflected throughout the upper half of the firm pay structure. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human capital mechanisms</head><p>The last sections demonstrated that firms are an important conduit of educational premiums, but did not unpack why. Here, I assess one possible explanation: that human capital gains at certain colleges facilitate access to higher-paying firms.</p><p>I measure human capital in three ways. First, using college GPA at time of graduation or at dropout, for non-completers. Second, using estimated "person e!ects" in Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>, following recent approaches to measuring skill-based matching between workers and firms <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Gerard et al., 2021)</ref>. Third, using field of study. Each of these approaches has its drawbacks. In particular, GPA is not standardized across colleges; person e!ects can only be estimated among the subset of workers who switch firms and reflect a composite of human capital and a variety of other factors, and neither capture how time-varying human capital may unfold for graduates of di!erent colleges. Still, in aggregate this exercise helps assess the utility of human capital as a mechanism for the firm sorting patterns I document.</p><p>To parse out non-human capital channels, I estimate the amount of treatment e!ect that operates net of human capital channels. Letting HC be the measures of human capital listed above, and ϑ be the estimated firm e!ects from Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>, I decompose the firm premium to attending College j relative to College 7 (ATE ω (j)) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">ATE ω (j) = 1 2 r↑{j,College 7} E[Y j, HC(r) ↑ Y College 7, HC(r) ]</formula><p>Explained by non-HC factors</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">+ 1 2 r↑{j,College 7} E[Y r, HC(j) ↑ Y r, HC(College 7) ]</formula><p>Explained by HC-based sorting .</p><p>I estimate these quantities using the mediation estimator described in Appendix B. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref> displays estimates of college firm premium e!ects, juxtaposed against the portion that persists net of each of the three human capital measures. For all but one college (College 5), neither person e!ects nor college GPA explain their firm sorting advantages relative to College 7. The reason for this is explored in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>, which shows the partial e!ect of these two human capital measures on firm premiums (top two rows) and of college GPA on earnings (bottom row). <ref type="foot" target="#foot_8">13</ref> College GPA and person e!ects have only very small e!ects on firm premiums. An increase of a person e!ect by 1 log point corresponds to an firm premium gain of .05. To make sense of this e!ect size, an increase of 1 log point of person e!ects would be equivalent to shifting from the 10th to 93rd percentile in the person e!ects distribution. The e!ect of college GPA on firm sorting advantages is similarly small: increasing college GPA by a full point would yield a firm premium advantage of .03. To put this e!ect size into perspective, the bottom row of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref> shows that increasing college GPA by one point would yield an e!ect on overall earnings that is 7 times as large the e!ect on firm premium.</p><p>Nor do field-of-study di!erences across colleges explain firm sorting advantages. Summit State's colleges do vary markedly in their curricular profiles, with the Flagship school emphasizing STEM and engineering, leading to professions that tend to be clustered in high-premium firms <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">(Wilmers and Aeppli, 2021)</ref>, and the regional colleges emphasizing humanities, education and professional fields (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">14</ref>). These curricular di!erences shape students' fields of study, which in turn could structure the set of firms they might enter, accounting for some of the observed firm premiums. That they do not reflects the fact that colleges convey firm sorting advantages within every field of study (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">S12</ref>). The exceptions are for Colleges 3 and 6, where field of study is an important contributor to firm sorting advantages relative to College 7. While this tentatively suggests that, at less selective colleges, sorting across firms stems from curricular di!erences rather than the interface between employer and college, some caution should be attached to this interpretation, because a student's chosen field of study could be, in part, endogenous to employer behaviors such as campus recruitment.</p><p>Collectively, these analyses suggest that human capital is not a primary -or even substantial driver -of the firm-sorting advantages across colleges that I have documented, partly supporting Hypothesis 3. This is not to say that human capital is not an important driver of college returns overall. In particular, of the 50% of the Flagship premium unexplained by firm sorting, human capital is likely a critical component. Rather, it suggests that the other half on the Flagship premium is driven primarily by non-skill-based resource advantages conferred by the school.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary analyses</head><p>I test the robustness of my findings through several additional analyses. All results are shown in Appendix E. First, I analyze whether firm sorting e!ects vary across race and class background. Absent a measure of family income for all students, I measure class background in two ways: whether a student received free or reduced price lunches in high school, and the family income of students who received financial aid. Across colleges, there is little evidence of heterogeneity in overall e!ects or in the firm sorting advantages conveyed by the college. Similarly, the results for race suggest that college e!ects on firm placement are comparable across racial groups.</p><p>Second, I test whether geographic and industry sorting can account for the observed college-firm premium di!erences. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2</ref> in Appendix D displays average firm premiums across Summit State counties and the locations of each college. Notably, the state flagship is in a county (which I call the "Primary Metropolitan Area") home to some of the highest paying firms in the state. Yet, Figure <ref type="figure">S8</ref> shows that firm placement advantages across colleges do not simply reflect geographic sorting. Flagship attendees obtain access to substantially higher-paying employers, even compared with other college attendees who find work in the same area. Nor do firm-sorting advantages simply stem from industry-based channeling (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">S10</ref>).</p><p>Third, I examine the cumulative or joint e!ects of attendance and completion at a given college. While my main analyses follow prior definitions of college attendance as a treatment (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Hoekstra, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mountjoy and Hickman, 2021)</ref>, this approach conflates attendance e!ects the e!ects of completing a degree -possibly at other campuses. 14 14 Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">14</ref> in Appendix F.2 shows that out-transfer is indeed a common experience: of the 90% of the The results from this exercise (shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6</ref>) are, nevertheless, consistent with my main results.</p><p>Finally, I examine college e!ects on earnings, and their mediation by firms, fifteen years after high school for the subset of cohorts for which I can observe this horizon. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">14</ref> shows that firms remain a central component of college wage premiums, even as the precise pattern of earnings premiums changes (though some e!ects are imprecisely estimated). Notably, the explanatory power of firms for Flagship attendance abates by 20 percent -a decline not driven by erosion of firm sorting advantages, but by the within-firm earnings advantages conferred by Flagship attendance. This shift could reflect several processes, including higher rates of promotion and opportunities for onthe-job skill training among Flagship attendees (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b94">Tomaskovic-Devey et al., 2005)</ref>, or continual human capital investment via graduate education. 15 Graduate education has large labor market returns <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Altonji et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Altonji and Zhong, 2021)</ref>, but may be associated more with within-firm earnings advancement than from between-firm sorting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Colleges do not simply teach; they also act as powerful sorting devices <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Kerckho!, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Domina et al., 2017)</ref>. While it has long been recognized that the relationship between education and earnings may vary across "occupations, communities...and labor markets" <ref type="bibr">(Bills, 2003, p.457)</ref> this variation is often abstracted from employers themselves. In this paper, I have argued that a consequential, yet under-appreciated, dimension of this sorting is across workplaces.</p><p>Drawing on a novel linked employer-employee dataset for high school graduating classes in a US State, I find that firm sorting explains a substantial share of earnings returns across institutions. Half of the earnings premium associated with attending Summit State's flagship public university, relative to a lower-ranked regional university, is explained by di!erences in access to higher-premium firms. Crucially, these patterns persist even after accounting for detailed controls for students' backgrounds and prior academic performance. Firm sorting is also not confined to access to a handful of elite employers. Rather, it is pervasive across the distribution of firms: selective colleges channel graduates into better-premium firms throughout the wage structure, not just Flagship starters earning a BA degree 10 years following high school graduation, 92% completed a degree at the Flagship; by contrast, of the 62% of College 7 starters earning a BA degree 10 years following high school graduation, only 79% completed a degree at College 7.</p><p>15 Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows that, ten years after high school, 17 percent of the Flagship attendees had completed a graduate degree compared with 9 percent of College 7 attendees; fifteen years out, these shares had risen to 22 and 13 percent, respectively.</p><p>into the highest resourced organizations. Further, human capital does not explain the firm sorting advantages conferred by colleges. These findings carry important theoretical and policy implications. Theoretically, they suggest that models of education and inequality must place greater emphasis on employer behavior and organizational sorting. Existing work on school-to-work transitions stresses the role of individual-level skill formation and utilization (Witte and <ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Kalleberg, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Robst, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">DiPrete et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Bol et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Quadlin et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Cassidy and Gaulke, 2024)</ref>, credentialism and social networks. My results show that these processes translate into higher earnings largely when they secure access to higher-paying firms. Moving beyond an exclusive focus on individual-level skills, or on models of social exclusion that abstract away from workplaces, requires recognizing the ways in which educational institutions and employer practices are jointly implicated in the production of inequality.</p><p>From a policy perspective, the results suggest that e!orts to reduce postsecondary wage gaps are likely to be unsuccessful via a sole focus on increasing degree completion or improving instructional quality. I show that a significant portion of the returns to colleges appears to stem from factors that are distinctly non-skill-based. While ensuring that all colleges impart students with skills for the workforce is surely an important goal, such an approach will not fully address earnings disparities if graduates of di!erent institutions continue to face unequal access to higher-paying firms. Colleges thus have a role to play beyond the classroom: strengthening career services, alumni networks and employer partnerships can help ensure that skills students acquire translate into better labor market outcomes. Expanding connections between regional colleges and high-wage employers, investing in career services infrastructure that targets a broader range of firms may materially change the labor market trajectories of their graduates. At the same time, structural constraints -including employers' entrenched preferences for certain credentials and firm-based practices of social closure -limit what colleges can achieve without broader labor market reforms. Narrowing wage gaps will require not only strengthening college inputs, but also encouraging high-paying employers to broaden their hiring pipelines.</p><p>There are several important limitations of my analyses. While the data used provide rare granularity linking students to their educational and employment histories, they are limited to one state's public college system and early career outcomes. Long-term e!ects may di!er, especially as firm-specific networks and career ladders unfold over time. To the extent that between-and within-earnings trajectories evolve di!erently for graduates of di!erent colleges, my analyses could mischaracterize the long-run e!ects of college and the relative importance of firm sorting. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_9">16</ref> Nevertheless, early outcomes may be important: being hired at a higher-premium firm as a labor-market entrant is an important predictor of long-term earnings (Arellano-Bover, 2024). Establishing how common upward firm mobility is across di!erent groups, and its importance for the evolution of earnings inequality across the life-course, remain important and open questions for future research My estimated earnings returns also pertain to the intensive margin of earnings, and exclude a large number individuals who obtain out-of-state employment. To the extent that out-of-state employment is concentrated in better-premium opportunities, and that such employment is more common among more selective college graduates, these patterns could downwardly bias my estimates of firm-based mediation. However, it is di"cult to definitively ascertain the size, or direction, of the bias. Moreover, while I used an extensive set of controls to adjust for selection into colleges, unobserved confounders, such as family social capital or informal job search networks, may still bias estimates to some extent. Finally, my data do not enable me to parse the role of credential advantages versus campus environments in facilitating access to high-paying firms. Distinguishing precisely what matters most for firm sorting -from broader cultural logics, to more direct network e!ects such as referrals and resources by campus career centers -is an important next step.</p><p>Still, the broader implications are clear: firm sorting is a major, under-recognized contributor to the stratified college wage premium. As labor markets grow more unequal and as returns to firm a"liation continue to rise, the stakes of credential-based sorting are only likely to deepen. In the short run, firm assignment shapes wage gaps. In the long run, it likely shapes career trajectories, wealth accumulation, geographic mobility, and even health outcomes. Early access to higher-premium firms compounds advantages over time, while exclusion from such firms constrains upward mobility for graduates of less selective colleges. If policymakers and educators are serious about using higher education as a tool for reducing inequality, they must attend not only to the supply side of skills as taught in colleges, nor solely to the demand side of employer hiring -but to the organizational interface between schools and firms. It is in the everyday logics, practices, and pipelines that link campuses to employers where much of inequality in opportunity is forged. Recognizing this interface -and acting to reshape it -may be a powerful lever to reduce inequalities in the college-to-work transition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Proof of Mediation Under Additive Separability</head><p>In this section, I formally show that, under an additive separability assumption, the mediation of the average treatment e!ect (ATE) of college on earnings is equivalent to the ATE of college on firm pay premiums. As in the main text, let A i = j indicate that individual i attended college j; let X i denote pre-college covariates; let M i denote the firm at which individual i is employed ten years after high school graduation; and let Y i denote log earnings. Assume the following nonparametric structural equation model (NPSEM) with independent errors governs the joint distribution of (X i , A i , L i , M i ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">X i = f X (ϖ X,i ) A i = f A (X i , ϖ A,i ) L i = f A (X i , A i , ϖ Z,i ) M i = f M (X i , A i , L i , ϖ M,i )</formula><p>Additionally, assume that earnings for worker i in year t are generated according to the following model:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">ln y it = ω i + Z → it ε + ϑ F (i,t) + ϖ it ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where ω i is an individual fixed e!ect, Z it is a vector of time-varying controls (including year fixed e!ects), F (i, t) is an index function that maps worker i to their employer in year t, ϑ F (i,t) is the firm-specific wage premium, and ϖ it captures idiosyncratic shocks.</p><p>To link this panel data model to the NPSEM, define Y i to be the logged earnings for individual i ten years after high school graduation as Y i ↔ ln y i,10 years , and let M i ↔ F (i, 10 years). Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">5</ref>) then implies a semi-parametric model for Y i of the form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">Y i = f Y (X i , A i , L i , ϖ Y,i ) + ε → Z i,10 years + g(M i ),<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where g(M i ) = ϑ F (i,10 years) is the firm-specific wage premium faced by individual i, by construction. That is, additive separability in Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">5</ref>) implies that Y i is additively separable in (X i , A i , Z i , ϖ Y,i ) and the firm M i .</p><p>Under ignorability for A i on Y i , the average treatment e!ect of attending college j relative to attending College 7 is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">ATE A↓Y = x [E[Y i | X i = x, A i = j] ↑ E[Y i | X i = x, A i = College 7]] dP (x).</formula><p>I aim to decompose this total e!ect into direct and indirect (mediated) components. Let Y i (a, m) denote the potential outcome under treatment a and mediator value m. Then the ATE can be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">ATE A↓Y = E[Y i (j, M i (j)) ↑ Y i (College 7, M i (j))] Direct e!ect (net of firms) + E[Y i (College 7, M i (j)) ↑ Y i (College 7, M i (College 7))]</formula><p>Indirect e!ect (via firms) .</p><p>Under the above assumptions, we can write</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">E[Y i (College 7, M i (j)) ↑ Y i (College 7, M i (College 7))] = E[f Y (X i , A i (College 7), L i , ϖ Y,i ) + ε → Z i,10 years + g(M i (j))] ↑E[f Y (X i , A i (College 7), L i , ϖ Y,i ) + ε → Z i,10 years + g(M i (College 7))] = E[g(M i (j))] ↑ E[g(M i (College 7))] = E X E[g(M i (j))|A i = j, X] ↑ E X E[g(M i (College 7))|A i = College 7, X] = E X E[g(M i )|A i = j, X] ↑ E X E[g(M i )|A i = College 7, X] = E X E[ϑ F (i,10 years) |A i = j, X] ↑ E X E[ϑ F (i,10 years) |A i = College 7, X].</formula><p>Therefore, under additive separability, the mediated e!ect of college on earnings through firm pay premiums is equivalent to the ATE of college on firm pay premiums. Note further that because of firm e!ect additivity, this decomposition is unique (that is, the reference category does not matter). In other words, </p><formula xml:id="formula_14">E[Y i (College 7, M i (j)) ↑ Y i (College 7, M i (College 7))] = E[Y i (j, M i (j)) ↑ Y i (j, M i (College 7))].</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B Further Details on Estimation Procedures</head><formula xml:id="formula_15">(X) = E[Y | A = College 7, X]</formula><p>. The population-level treatment e!ect is identified (under ignorability) as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">ATE j = µ j ↑ µ College 7 , where µ j = E X [µ j (X)], µ College 7 = E X [µ College 7 (X)].</formula><p>To estimate these target quantities, I use the e"cient influence function (EIF) for the mean outcome under each treatment group. Let μj (X) denote an estimate of µ j (X) obtained from an outcome regression model, and let ρj (X) = Pr(A = j | X) denote the estimated propensity score. Then the EIF-based estimator for µ j is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">μEIF j = 1 n n i=1 μj (X i ) + I(A i = j) ρj (X i ) (Y i ↑ μj (X i )) .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The estimator μEIF</head><p>College 7 is defined analogously. The EIF-based estimator for the average treatment e!ect of attending college j relative to College 7 is then:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">⊋ ATE EIF j = μEIF j ↑ μEIF College 7 .</formula><p>In practice, I estimate μj (X) and ρj (X) (the "nuisance functions") using linear, binomial or multinomial ridge regressions (depending on whether the outcome variable is continuous, binary or categorical, respectively), and implement K-fold cross-fitting. In this procedure, the data is partitioned into K = 5 folds. Cross-fitting preserves the asymptotic e"ciency of the EIF estimator even when using a nonparametric method like ridge regression. Specifically, for each fold k = 1, . . . 5, the nuisance functions are estimated on the training folds (excluding the current fold), and predictions are made on the held-out fold. This process ensures that each observation's EIF term is computed using nuisance estimates that are fit on independent data. The final ATE estimate is computed by aggregating EIF contributions across all folds. Under this procedure, standard errors for ⊋ ATE EIF j can be obtained using the empirical variance of the estimated EIF. Asymptotically valid confidence intervals can then be constructed using the normal approximation. Additionally, in Figures S16, S17 and S18 in Appendix I.2, I display counterfactual probabilities of working in di!erent locations (or in a multi-establishment firm), industries, and firms of di!erent sizes, respectively. These estimates are obtained via μEIF j , where Y i is replaced by a categorical variable denoting the location, industry, or size of an employee's firm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.2 Mediation Quantities</head><p>To assess how firm-based sorting overlaps with other dimensions of stratification (such as industry, location and firm size), I also estimate several mediation-related quantities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Direct E!ects (Figures S8 and S10)</head><p>The first of these is the controlled direct e!ect (CDE) of attending college j relative to College 7 on the firm premium of an individual's firm (FE), net of a mediator m. The CDE isolates the portion of the treatment e!ect that operates not through the mediator, by fixing the mediator at a specific level m. Figures X and Y, for example, display the CDE of attending college j relative to College 7 for industry and location, or firm size.</p><p>To formally define this quantity, let M denote the mediator variable (e.g., industry, location, or size), and let FE(j, m) denote the potential outcome that would be observed if treatment were set to college j and the mediator were fixed to M = m. The controlled direct e!ect (CDE) of treatment j relative to College 7 at mediator level m is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">CDE j (m) = E[FE(j, m)] ↑ E[FE(College 7, m)].</formula><p>To express the CDE as a function of observed data, I invoke an additional no unmeasured confounding for the mediator:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">(FE(j, m) ↗ ↗ A | X) and (FE(j, m) ↗ ↗ M | A = j, X).</formula><p>This assumption rules out any unobserved selection into the mediator (such as location) net of pre-college observed characteristics. As discussed in the main text, this is unlikely to hold. In particular, regionally-based students, for example, who attend College 7, who obtain post-college employment in the Primary Metropolitan Area are likely positively selected, relative to their peers who work elsewhere. In practice, such patterns of selection are likely to downwardly bias my estimates of the CDE. Under this assumption, we can identify E[Y (j, m)] as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">E[Y (j, m)] = E X [E[Y | A = j, M = m, X]] = E X [µ j (m, X)] ,</formula><p>where µ j (m, X) = E[Y | A = j, M = m, X] is the conditional mean outcome under treatment j and mediator level m, given covariates X.</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">Similarly, E[Y (College 7, m)] is identified as: E[Y (College 7, m)] = E X [µ College 7 (m, X)] .</formula><p>Thus, the controlled direct e!ect is identified as the di!erence in these conditional expectations averaged over the distribution of X :</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">CDE j (m) = E X [µ j (m, X) ↑ µ College 7 (m, X)] .</formula><p>This identification result enables estimation using either plug-in estimators (i.e., regression followed by averaging) or doubly robust estimators such as those based on the e"cient influence function (EIF). In practice, I estimate E[Y (j, m)] using the e"cient influence function (EIF) estimator:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">μEIF j (m) = 1 n n i=1 μj (m, X i ) + I(A i = j, M i = m) ρj (m, X i )ρ j (X i ) (FE i ↑ μj (m, X i )) , where μj (m, X i ) is an estimate of E[Y | A = j, M = m, X i ] (obtained from a ridge regression model), ρj (m | X i ) = Pr(M = m | X i , A = j)</formula><p>is the estimated joint propensity of treatment and mediator, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">I(A i = j, M i = m)</formula><p>is the indicator function for the joint treatment-mediator status. The estimated controlled direct e!ect can then be estimated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">⊋ CDE EIF j (m) = μEIF j (m) ↑ μEIF College 7 (m).</formula><p>As in the ATE estimation procedure, cross-fitting is used to mitigate overfitting when estimating nuisance functions the µ j (m, X), ϱ j (X), and ϱ j (m | X). The data is split into K folds; nuisance models are trained on K ↑ 1 folds, and predictions are made on the held-out fold. This ensures that each observation's EIF contribution is based on out-of-fold estimates, preserving the e"ciency and asymptotic normality of the final estimator even when using flexible, high-dimensional learners. Standard errors for ⊋ CDE EIF j (m) are computed using the empirical variance of the estimated EIF terms, analogous to the ATE case.</p><p>Formal Mediation Analyses (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>, and Figures <ref type="figure">S8</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">S10</ref>)</p><p>Overlap between firm-sorting across colleges and geographic-, industry-and size-based sorting can be summarized by an additional mediation quantity, which captures the portion of the treatment e!ect that is not mediated by M (summarizing across levels of M ). Specifically, I estimate the natural direct e!ect (NDE) of attending college j relative to attending College 7, where the mediator M (e.g., industry, location, or firm size) is fixed at the value it would naturally take under treatment j.</p><p>To formally describe this procedure, let FE(a, m) denote the potential outcome under treatment A = a and mediator fixed to M = m, and let M (j) denote the potential value of the mediator under treatment j. Then, the natural direct e!ect is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">NDE j = E[FE(j, M (j))] ↑ E[FE(College 7, M(j))].</formula><p>When estimating direct e!ects, I use school j as the reference group. For example, when comparing the e!ect of attending college j on firm premium net of industry, I ask: to what extent does attending school j relative to College 7 yield access to a higherpremium firm, if College 7 students worked in the same industries as the Flagship students. s</p><p>Under the assumptions mentioned previously, the NDE is identified via:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">NDE j = E X E M |X,A=j [µ(j, M, X) ↑ µ(College 7, M, X)] = E X µ j (X) ↑ E M |X,A=j µ(College 7, M, X) , where µ(a, m, X) = E[FE | A = a, M = m, X].</formula><p>Note that the first term, µ j , can be estimated using the EIF-based estimator as described above. To estimate the second term E[FE(College 7, M(j))], I use its e"cient influence function (EIF), which enables doubly robust estimation. The EIF for this quantity is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">ς i = E M |X i ,A=j [µ(College 7, M, X i )] + I(A i = j) ϱ j (X i ) µ(College 7, M i , X i ) ↑ E M |X i ,A=j [µ(College 7, M, X i )] + I(A i = College 7) ϱ College 7 (X i ) • ϱ j (X i , M i ) ϱ College 7 (X i , M i ) • (FE i ↑ µ(College 7, M i , X i )) ,</formula><p>where ϱ j (X) = Pr(A = j | X) and ϱ College 7 (X) = Pr(A = College 7 | X) are estimated propensity scores, ϱ j (X, M ) = Pr(A = j | X, M ) and ϱ College 7 (X, M ) = Pr(A = College 7 | X, M ) are treatment probabilities conditional on X and M . The EIF-based estimator of E[FE(College 7, M(j))] is then obtained by averaging ςi over the sample, where ςi is estimated by plugging in estimates of nuisance functions in Equation ??. The final estimator of the NDE is therefore:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">⊋ NDE j = 1 n n i=1 θi ↑ ςi , where θ = μij (X i ) + I(A i =j) εj (X i ) (Y i ↑ μj (X i )).</formula><p>Cumulative Treatment E!ects (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_22">S19</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6</ref>)</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_22">S19</ref> in the main text and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6</ref> in Appendix E rely on cumulative treatment e!ects of attendance at college j and BA attainment at college k, relative attendance and completion at College 7. Now, let the observed data consist of units indexed by i = 1, . . . , n, with variables (Y i , A i , X i , Z i , D i ), where as before, X i denotes precollege covariates, A i denotes college attendance, Y i → {FE, lnearn} and, additionally, D i denotes degree completion and Z i denotes a vector of intermediate (post-treatment) covariates. In what follows, Z i include first-term GPA, GPA at graduation or (for noncompleters), at stop-out, number of credits attempted and earned in the first semester, and their squares. I define the cumulative treatment as the joint event (A i = j, D i = k), that is, of attending college j and completing a degree at college k. To estimate the cumulative treatment e!ect of attending college j and completing a BA at college k, I consider the potential outcome Y i (j, k), which represents the firm premium that individual i would face if they both attended and graduated from college k. The target quantity is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">E[Y i (j, k)] ↑ E[Y i (College 7, College 7)],</formula><p>that is, the average outcome under the path of attending college j, completing a degree from college k, relative to attending and completing a degree from College 7. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_22">S19</ref>, j = Flagship and k = J \ Flagship,that is, all colleges bar the Flagship. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6</ref> in Appendix E , j = k.</p><p>Identification of this quantity relies on a sequential ignorability assumption, namely that there is no unobserved confounding for college attendance or for college completion. While in practice this is unlikely to be fully met, my large set of pre-college and post-college covariates makes this assumption more plausible. Under these assumptions, I can estimate E[Y (j, k)] using the e"cient influence function (EIF) estimator:</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">μEIF j,k = 1 n n i=1 μj (X i , Z i ) + I(A i = j) ρj (X i ) (μ j (X i , Z i ) ↑ μj (X i )) + I(A i = j, D i = k) ρj (X i ) • φj (X i , Z i ) (Y i ↑ μj (X i , Z i )) , where • μj (X i , Z i ) = E[Y | A i = j, D i = 1, X i , Z i ] is the outcome regression, • μj (X i ) = E Z|X i ,A i =j [μ j (X i , Z)] is the marginal regression over Z i , • ρj (X i ) = Pr(A i = j | X i )</formula><p>is the treatment (attendance) propensity score, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">• φj (X i , Z i ) = Pr(D i = k | A i = j, X i , Z i )</formula><p>is the probability of BA completion at college k given attendance and post-treatment covariates.</p><p>As in previous sections, I use K-fold cross-fitting to estimate the nuisance functions μj (X, Z), ρj (X), and φj (X, Z) to mitigate overfitting. Each observation's EIF contribution is computed using out-of-fold predictions. Standard errors are obtained from the empirical variance of the EIF terms. has zero reported hours but positive income, I use that individual in the sample (that is, I assume that the employer failed to report the hours of that worker, or that these were wages earned in one quarter but paid in another). If a worker has no reported hours in a given quarter, I classify hours -and therefore the worker's wage rateas missing, but still use the observation to construct annualized earnings. For each calendar quarter, I then identify each worker's primary employer as the firm from which they earned the largest share of their total earnings, and annualize wages from their primary employers, so long as the worker is observed at the firm for at least two consecutive quarters in a given year. These earnings and wage variables, and the corresponding employer, are the basis of my primary analysis. I then annualize the remaining quarterly earnings and hours within each calendar year, conditional on the worker having at least two consecutive quarters of employment with the same primary employer in that year. Annual earnings, hours, and hourly wage rates are computed using this cleaned panel. The resulting unit of observation is the worker-year, defined by the worker's relationship with their primary employer in a given school year. I link these earnings data to individuals' estimated firm premiums, which I obtain from a separate linked employer-employee panel. An employment spell is defined as a sequence of at least five consecutive quarters during which a worker remains employed by the same primary employer. To avoid measurement error from job transitions or partial employment, I drop the first quarter of each spell (which may reflect midquarter job starts) and the last two quarters (which may capture separation-related wage fluctuations). Together with the fact that I keep only an individual's primary employer in a given wage quarter (i.e. that with the largest income share) a record will be dropped if an employer is an individual's primary source of income in one quarter, but if the individual is still observed at that employer in the following quarter but that employer is no longer the individual's primary income source (or if the person skills a quarter at an employer before returning). Essentially, this means that an individual must have begun an employment spell before the second quarter (inclusive) in order for that spell to count as an observation in the year. Similarly, when a given employment spell ends, leaving the employer must occur in the fourth quarter, otherwise that spell will not be counted as an observation for a given wage year. 20  I next impose a series of sample restrictions on this panel. First, I exclude workers who appear with more than nine employers in a calendar year. I also drop workers with annual earnings below $4,270 or with an hourly wage rate less than or equal to $3 (both in 2022 dollars). To eliminate outliers in hours worked, I restrict the sample to 20 For instance, if a person is employed at employer j for 20161, 2, 3,4, 20171, 2, 3. They have over 4 quarters for that spell so part of the spell is kept: <ref type="bibr">20162, 20163, 20164, 20171.</ref> If this is the primary income source in all years, I end up assigning the employer and the total or annualized wages from the employer in 2016, but the person will have no observed wages in 2017 because there is only one quarter observed at the employer (which does not meet the inclusion threshold of two wage quarters in a given year at the primary employe workers with between 400 and 4,800 annual hours, to workers with strictly fewer than 10 employers over the period 2005-2022, and drop employers with fewer than 5 high school graduates observed over the full period.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C Further Details on Sample Construction</head><p>Second, I filter wage observations according to the following exclusion criteria, to determine when an individual completes their education. First, for high school graduates never observed in the postsecondary enrollment or awards files, I take all years following high school graduation (that is, in the school year following high school graduation onwards). If an individual is observed to complete a postsecondary degree (in or out of state), I take all person earnings years following the last credential attained sub BA award (inclusive) that an individual attained, ignoring graduate awards (again, taking wage observations only beginning the school year following award attainment). Finally, for college stop outs (i.e., those that at some point enrolled in college but did not complete it, I define an individual to be stopped out if they are observed as a college enrollee in year 5, and no longer observed as a college enrollee in any subsequent years t, t + 1, ..., T. For individuals who stop out and re-enroll, I only take earnings for that individual following their final enrollment spell. Note that while high school graduates and NSC completers will not feature in my estimation sample for college returns, they can be used to increase precision for estimating the employer e!ects. Together, these restrictions ensure that I make firm inferences from individuals' earnings (i) only once an individual has completed their formal schooling, and (ii) based on either a partial quarter of employment or in the quarters either before or of job loss.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assignment of Employers to Employer Characteristics</head><p>Assigning a consistent location and industry to each firm is essential for analyzing firmlevel variation in wages and outcomes. However, the underlying administrative data present several challenges. Summit State does not require multi-industry and multisite employers to break down their employment and wage data by site and industry. Even when employers do provide these breakouts, it is not clear which employees are working in which locations or industries. While only a very small number of firms in Summit State report data for multiple locations, according to the state's employment department, these firms account for approximately 30% of total employment.. Additionally, location and industry reporting may be inconsistent across workers within the same firm and year. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_11">21</ref>To address these issues, I implement a rule-based procedure to assign each firm a single county and a single NAICS industry code per year (or, when this is not feasible, to explicitly flag the firm as multi-establishment). The procedure begins by determining the modal county and NAICS code for each firm-year. Then, at the firm level, I assign a unique location and industry as follows. If the firm appears in only one unique county (excluding "Multiple Counties"), I assign that county as the firm's location. If a firm is flagged as multi-establishment but consistently reports a single location, I retain that location. If a firm appears in multiple counties or reports both a specific location and "Multiple Counties," I assign it the label "Multiple Counties." I assign a single NAICS code for each firm-year.</p><p>To preserve as many observations as possible, I disregard missing values when more specific information is available. For example, if a firm appears in Jane County and as missing, I assign the firm to Jane County; similarly, if a firm appears with both a valid NAICS code and a missing code, I retain the non-missing value. Firms with no usable location or industry information across all associated workers are excluded from the analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D AKM Model Details</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.1 Model Results</head><p>The first column of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> presents summary statistics for the annualized linked employer-employee panel which I use to fit the AKM model (Equation 1 in the main text) among workers in the years following education completion -that is, after processing the quarterly records imposing the sample restrictions described in Appendix C. The left column shows summary statistics for the full annualized panel, while the right column shows summary statistics for the fully connected set. The employer e!ects are identified only within the "connected set" of employers that are linked by worker transitions between those employers, so the AKM estimation is necessarily restricted to the largest connected set of employers. This consists of 43 percent of employers in the full annualized panel, 70 percent of workers in the panel, and 81 percent of worker-year observations in the panel. Because identification of employer fixed e!ects comes from workers moving between primary employers, it is important to know how much mobility there is in the sample. The table shows that the largest connected set includes over half a million unique workers, and approximately 43 percent of those workers changed primary employer at least once during the panel 2005-2022.</p><p>I estimate the AKM model (Equation 1 in the main text) using the linked employeremployee panel. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">5</ref> shows the resulting model fit (rightmost column) and implied earnings variance decomposition. Logged earnings is decomposed into five components: worker e!ects, firm e!ects, year e!ects, the covariance between worker and employer e!ects (sorting of workers and employers), and a residual. I omit the worker-year and firm-year covariances, which capture, collectively, approximately 3% of the total variance.</p><p>The estimated variance of earnings for workers within 10 years of high school graduation is .36. 47% of Worker fixed e!ects explain the largest share of earnings variation, at 47%. Firm e!ects explain a smaller but still sizable share: approximately 20% of the variation in earnings. These shares are very similar to those estimated by prior authors using UI wage records in Summit State (redacted to keep the state anonymous).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Firm Premium</head><p>Notes: Average and variance of firm pay premiums across industries, normalized relative to the Accommodation and Food Services sector (NAICS 72), which is the lowest-paying sector in terms of both estimated firm e!ects and average worker characteristics. Bars represent the average estimated firm fixed e!ect within each 2-digit NAICS sector, where firm e!ects are estimated using the AKM decomposition described in the main text (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>). Industry-level averages and variances are weighted by the number of person-quarter observations at each establishment. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records. Notes: Average estimated firm wage premium for each Summit State county, based on the location of firms between 2018 and 2022. The array is stylized in order to keep the state and its institutions anonymous. Firm locations are assigned using administrative records from this period, and averages are weighted by the average number of person-year observations at each firm across this same period. Several low-population counties are excluded (white colored) due the low number of firms (under 50) employing high school graduates. Multi-establishment firms are excluded from county-specific averages; their average firm premium, across the full sample, is 0.46 (not shown).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.3 Estimated Firm Premiums across Counties</head><p>Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E Robustness Checks Cited in Main Text</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.1 E!ect Heterogeneity by Socio-Economic Origin</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">S3</ref> compares the ATE of attendance at each college (top panel) and its mediation by firm sorting (bottom panel), comparing students ever eligible for free/reduced-price lunch (FRPL, teal bars) to those who were not (red bars). At the flagship, both FRPL and non-FRPL students earn substantial earnings premiums relative to College 7, with nearly identical magnitudes and similar shares mediated by firm placement. Across Colleges 2-3 and 5-6, the returns for FRPL and non-FRPL students are also closely aligned, and di!erences are not statistically significant. The only meaningful divergence appears at College 4, where non-FRPL students capture somewhat larger gains than their FRPL peers. Taken together, these results suggest that firm sorting contributes comparably to the college earnings premium across socioeconomic groups, with little evidence that class background systematically alters the payo! to selective college attendance. Not FRPL FRPL Notes: The top panel shows estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on log earnings ten years after high school graduation, by FRPL status (colors). The bottom panel shows the portion of the total e!ect mediated through di!erences in employer assignment, by racial-ethnic group (colors). The colleges included are Summit State's Flagship school, and Colleges 2 to 6. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting, and modified to address e!ect heterogeneity. Specifically, I use the EIF-based estimator μEIF</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">j (r) = 1 nr i:R=r μj (X i ) + I(A i =j) ωj (X i ) (Y i ↔ μj (X i ))</formula><p>, where R ↑ {Not FRPL, FRPL} denotes FRPL status, and nr denotes the total number of people in the sample belonging to each R = r group. Grey whiskers denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL).  Family Income Log Earnings Return (versus EWU)</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">A → Y A → M → Y Notes:</formula><p>The top panel shows estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on log earnings ten years after high school graduation, by family income. The bottom panel shows the portion of the total e!ect mediated through di!erences in employer assignment, by racial-ethnic group (colors). The colleges included are Summit State's Flagship school, and Colleges 2 to 6. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting, and modified to address e!ect heterogeneity. Ribbons denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). High school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.2 E!ect Heterogeneity by Race-Ethnicity</head><p>I estimate treatment e!ects across three racial-ethnic groups: White, Hispanic and Black. These models correspond to the conditional average treatment e!ects (CATEs) of college attendance at college j relative to College 7 across racial-gender groups, as well as conditional mediation via firms, and provide insight into whether credentialing and college e!ects apply uniformly across individuals. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">S5</ref> shows that, for White students, college attendance is associated with substantial earnings returns, particularly attendance at the flagship. A sizable portion of these returns is mediated through employer placement. For Hispanic students, flagship attendance also provides a strong, through slightly attenuated e!ect, for which mediation via firms represents a larger component. Among Black students, estimated returns are markedly smaller, though substantially less precise, reflecting the very small number of Black students attending di!erent 4-year colleges, but still indicate meaningful firm-mediated e!ects for several colleges, particularly the Flagship and College 2. Overall, while the magnitude and precision of college e!ects vary across groups, the results suggest that firm sorting plays a substantial role in mediating the college earnings premium across all racial/ethnic groups studied, with especially strong contributions for Hispanic and White students. Notes: The top panel shows estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on log earnings ten years after high school graduation, by racial-ethnic group (colors). The bottom panel shows the portion of the total e!ect mediated through di!erences in employer assignment, by racial-ethnic group (colors). The colleges included are Summit State's Flagship school, and Colleges 2 to 6. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting, and modified to address e!ect heterogeneity. Specifically, I use the EIF-based estimator μEIF</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">j (r) = 1 nr i:R=r μj (X i ) + I(A i =j) ωj (X i ) (Y i ↔ μj (X i ))</formula><p>, where R ↑ {White, Black, Hispanic} denotes racial-ethnic group, and nr denotes the total number of people in the sample belonging to each R = r group. Grey whiskers denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). The red dotted line marks the baseline (College 7) comparison group. Grey whiskers indicate 95% confidence intervals. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.3 Joint E!ect of Attendance and Completion, and Mediation via Firms</head><p>In this section, I examine the cumulative or joint e!ects of attendance and completion at a given college. My main analyses follow prior definitions of college-as-treatment (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Hoekstra, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mountjoy and Hickman, 2021)</ref> by examining the earnings returns to attending di!erent 4-year colleges on earnings, and mediation via firm placement. Nevertheless, such an approach elides an important margin: BA completion. Because the e!ect of attending a particular college partly reflects di!erential likelihoods of degree completion (both any college, and at di!erent colleges), estimated e!ects conflate attendance e!ects (that is, exposure to any given campus) with enrollment and completion e!ects at other campuses. 22 I therefore additionally estimate the cumulative treatment e!ect (CTE) of attendance and completion each of the state's 4-year public colleges, using the DML procedure described in Appendix B. The results from this exercise (shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6</ref>) are consistent with my main results.</p><p>There are two important di!erences compared with my main results. The first is that estimated CTEs are much larger than the estimated ATEs of college attendance as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. The reason for this discrepancy is that counterfactual rates of BA completion are almost identical, at approximately 77% across all colleges (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S15</ref>  22 Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">14</ref> in Appendix F.2 shows that out-transfer is indeed a common experience: of the 90% of the Flagship starters earning a BA degree 10 years following high school graduation, 92% completed a degree at the Flagship; by contrast, of the 62% of College 7 starters earning a BA degree 10 years following high school graduation, only 79% completed a degree at College 7.  Notes: Point estimates and standard errors displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6</ref>. Estimated cumulative treatment e!ects of attending (as a freshman admit) and completing a degree at di!erent colleges on log earnings 10 years following high school graduation, relative to attending (as a freshman admit) and completing a BA at College 7, and mediation via employer placement. Estimates are obtained using the double machine learning (DML) approach described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for all nuisance models. Covariates include those from previous models (demographics, academic background, and high school characteristics), along with additional controls for degree completion selection: GPA at graduation or stop-out, first-term credits attempted and earned, and their squares. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.4 Mediation by Firm Location and Industry</head><p>College-based firm sorting may still emerge even in the absence of employer social exclusion or distinct campus cultures directing students to high-premium firms. Here, I examine two alternative explanations for the observed patterns: geographic-based sorting and industry segregation, Indeed, Figures S16 and S17 in Appendix I.2 show that there is substantial sorting into di!erent locations and industries across colleges.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.4.1 Location</head><p>First, I examine whether the firm premium advantage enjoyed by students attending the Flagship might be driven more mechanically by acting as a gateway to its local (high-wage) labor market. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2</ref>  The natural question then arises of whether the Flagship obtains its firm sorting advantages primarily by anchoring students in the nearby high-wage metropolitan area. 23  To formally assess the role of geographic sorting in explaining the observed firm premium di!erences across colleges, I estimate mediation of college e!ects on firm premia net of location (see Appendix B for methodological details). The results, displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">S7</ref>, show that only a small portion of firm sorting advantages can be accounted for by location. 24  The reasons for this are explored in Figure <ref type="figure">S8</ref>, which presents estimates of controlled direct e!ects (CDEs) of college attendance on firm fixed e!ects, conditioning on firm location. Figure <ref type="figure">S8</ref> presents these estimates, where each panel holds firm location constant -either (1) a single-establishment firm located in the Primary Metropolitan Area (left panel), (2) a multi-establishment firm (middle panel), or (3) a single-establishment 23 In my analyses, I control for high school fixed e!ects, mitigating the related concern that the Flagship students, many of whom may originate from the state's Primary Metropolitan Area or its surrounding areas, are more inclined to remain in the region after graduation even without any college e!ects per se.</p><p>24 Some care should be taken over the causal interpretation of this quantity for two reasons. First, for one's first set of jobs after college, firm and location are in many ways simultaneously determined; "Primary Metropolitan Area" is not a strict mediator for firm as an outcome. Despite not having a strictly causal interpretation, it is nevertheless useful for summarizing the gap in firm premia among workers based in the Primary Metropolitan Area, net of pre-college characteristics. Second, given that College 7 is distant from the Primary Metropolitan Area, College 7 students who do work in the Primary Metropolitan Area may be positively selected on bridging funds and motivation for certain types of work, among other characteristics. I expect that this pattern of selection may downwardly bias my estimates of the direct e!ect, producing a conservative estimate 54 firm located outside the state's Primary Metropolitan Area (right panel).<ref type="foot" target="#foot_12">25</ref> By conditioning on firm location, these estimates capture the portion of the college e!ect on firm wage premiums not attributable to sorting into geographic placement based on person attributes. Intuitively, these quantities capture a person's firm pay premium if they attended college j, relative to College 7, if we fixed their post-college employment location to either the Primary Metropolitan Area, or another area.</p><p>The figure shows that firm placement advantages across colleges do not simply reflect geographic sorting. Attending the Flagship and obtaining employment in the Primary Metropolitan Area, relative to attending College 7 and obtaining employment in the Primary Metropolitan Area, yields access to significantly (.06 log point) higher-premium employers -a figure almost identical to the overall firm premium to the Flagship attendance (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). Notably, College 2 also shows a substantial advantage within the Primary Metropolitan Area, while College 3, despite being located in the Primary Metropolitan Area, does not. The pattern is similar among workers at multi-establishment firms: the Flagship and College 2 attendees are placed at higherpremium employers than comparable students from College 7, largely mirroring the overall firm premia to these schools. By contrast, given employment outside of the Primary Metropolitan Area at a single-establishment employer, firm premium di!erences returns across colleges are far smaller -and in the case of College 4, College 5, and College 6, even negative relative to College 7. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">S7</ref> in Appendix E.4 summarizes the contribution of geographic sorting to the Flagship's firm premium: a full three quarters of its firm-sorting e!ect comes from non-geographic sorting. Note that the importance of geography may work in subtler ways beyond the physical location of graduates to di!erent places. For example, the Flagship may have stronger career center connections to the nearby Primary Metropolitan Area (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Manduca, 2024)</ref>, facilitating high-premium firm attainment compared with College 7 graduates. Log Earnings Return (versus College 7)</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">A → M → Y A → M → Y (net of</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>location)</head><p>Notes: Teal bars show estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on firm pay premiums, ten years after high school graduation. Orange bars show mediation of this e!ect via firm location, defined as a categorical variable denoting whether a firm is a multi-establishment enterprise, located in the state's Primary Metropolitan Area, or located in another county. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Grey whiskers denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL).  Notes: Bars show estimated controlled direct e!ects (CDEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on firm pay premiums. "Primary Metropolitan Area" and "Other Area" denotes working for single-establishment employers in the Primary Metropolitan Area or a non-Primary Metropolitan county, respectively. "Multi-Establishment" denotes working for a firm with multiple establishments; in the administrative UI records, I am unable to locate the specific establishment of employment of workers employed by multi-establishment firms. Each panel holds firm location fixed -to the Primary Metropolitan Area (left panel) multi-establishment firms (middle panel) or other areas (right panel) -and estimates the e!ect of college attendance on the fixed e!ect of a student's employer within that location category, ten years after high school graduation. Estimates reflect the e!ect of college attendance on the average fixed e!ect of a student's employer ten years after high school graduation, adjusting for firm location. By conditioning on firm location, these estimates isolate the portion of the college e!ect that operates net of sorting into geographic or organizational location, and thus adjust for selection into di!erent types of firms. The colleges included are Summit State's Flagship school, and Colleges 2 to 6. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used to estimate both propensity scores and outcome models. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school graduation cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). The red dotted line marks the baseline (College 7) comparison group. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.4.2 Industry</head><p>Second, I examine whether firm sorting stems from industry-based channeling. Industries di!er systematically in their average wage premiums <ref type="bibr">(Yi et al. 2024</ref>). Variation in the types of industries into which di!erent colleges channel their graduates (such as through variation in industry-specific campus targeting) could account for firm premium e!ects. Using the same analytic strategy as for location, I find (in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">S9</ref>) that industry does not explain the observed sorting patterns.</p><p>To show how firm sorting advantages persist even within industry groups, I estimate controlled direct e!ects (CDEs) of college attendance on firm premiums, now controlling for the industry of the employer, and for students' field of study. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">S10</ref> presents these estimates across four major sectors of employment (Finance and Insurance, Health Care and Social Assistance, Information, and Professional, Scientific, and Technical (PST) Services). I fix industry and estimate the average firm premium associated with each college, net of sorting into particular industry sectors (fields of study). Neither industry nor field of study sorting can explain firm premium payo!s to college attendance. Notably, within the Information and PST Services sectors, the Flagship and College 2 graduates enjoy huge firm premiums; within Information, the Flagship attendance sorts workers into firms that pay roughly 0.20 log points more College 7 attendance. Despite a positive payo!, the Flagship firm premium e!ects are significantly smaller in the Finance and Insurance and Health Care Industries. 26  In sum, geographic and industry-based based sorting only partly overlaps with the firm sorting mechanism that I document here. 27 26 This is partly a mechanical artifact of the type of firms within these industries. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref> in Appendix (C) shows that, despite having one of the highest (and lowest) average pay premiums, the variance of pay premiums in the Finance and Insurance (and Health Care) industry is significantly lower than in other sectors. This means that cross-firm sorting e!ects are attenuated relative to other industries. 27 In Appendix E.4, I conduct a formal mediation analysis for the e!ects of college attendance on firm premiums net of location, industry and, additionally size.. I find that these characteristics explain only a small amount of the total flagship firm premium. Log Earnings Return (versus College 7)</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">A → M → Y A → M → Y (net of</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>industry)</head><p>Notes: Teal bars show estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on firm pay premiums, ten years after high school graduation. Orange bars show mediation of this e!ect via the industry in which the firm operates, captured via 2-digits NAICS codes. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Grey whiskers denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL).   Notes: Bars show estimated controlled direct e!ects (CDEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on firm pay premiums, adjusting for industry of employment. Each panel holds industry fixed and estimates the e!ect of college attendance on the fixed e!ect of an individual's employer within that industry, measured ten years after high school graduation. Estimates reflect the e!ect of college attendance on the average fixed e!ect of a student's employer ten years after high school graduation, adjusting for industry sorting. By conditioning on firm industry, these estimates isolate the portion of the college e!ect that operates net of sorting into particular industry sectors, and thus adjust for selection into di!erent types of firms. The colleges included are Summit State's Flagship school, and Colleges 2 to 6. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used to estimate both propensity scores and outcome models. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school graduation cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). The red dotted line marks the baseline (College 7) comparison group. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p><p>E.5 College Attendance E!ects, 15 Years Following High School Graduation State's Flagship school, and Colleges 2 to 6. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Grey whiskers denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). The red dotted line marks the baseline (College 7) comparison group.    Estimates reflect the e!ect of college attendance on the average fixed e!ect of a student's employer ten years after high school graduation, adjusting for field of study sorting. I exclude individuals who did not graduate with a BA, because these students often have an undeclared field of study. The colleges included are Summit State's Flagship school, and Colleges 2 to 6. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used to estimate both propensity scores and outcome models. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school graduation cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL).   Notes: Point estimates and standard errors displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> in the main text. Estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on log earnings ten years after high school graduation, and mediation via employer assignment. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Grey whiskers denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL  Notes: Point estimates and standard errors displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> in the main text. Estimated average treatment e!ect (ATE) of attending a given college (versus College 7) on the probability of working at a firm in the indicated percentile or higher of the firm fixed e!ect (firm premium) distribution, measured ten years after high school graduation. Estimates are computed separately for the 60th, 70th, 80th, 90th, and 95th percentiles of the firm premium distribution, defined within the set of 4-year freshman enrollees. E!ects are estimated using a double machine learning (DML) approach described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both propensity score and outcome models. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school graduation cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL  Notes: Point estimates and standard errors displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> in the main text. Estimated average treatment e!ect (ATE) of attending a given college (versus College 7) on the probability of working at a firm in the indicated percentile or higher of the firm fixed e!ect (firm premium) distribution, measured ten years after high school graduation. Estimates are computed separately for the 60th, 70th, 80th, 90th, and 95th percentiles of the firm premium distribution, defined within the set of 4-year freshman enrollees. E!ects are estimated using a double machine learning (DML) approach described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both propensity score and outcome models. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school graduation cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL).    , that is, a weight equal to 1 divided by the probability of attending the college that they did in fact attend. Pr(A = j | X) is estimated via ridge regression with the following covariates: student race/ethnicity, sex, high school graduation cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), and ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). N = 83, 519; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records, as well as National Student Clearinghouse. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G Supplemental Human Capital Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H.2 College Attendance E!ects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H.3 Quantile Treatment E!ects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H.4 Human Capital Sorting</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I Additional Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I.1 BA Completion and Transfer Students</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BA Completion</head><p>Notes: Bars show counterfactual probabilities of attaining a BA (at any college) within 10 years following high school graduation. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL Notes: Bars show counterfactual probabilities of working in firm that operates in a particular industry. "PST Services" refers to the Professional, Scientific, and Technical Services sector. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL Notes: Bars show counterfactual probabilities of working in firm of a given size. "Small" refers to employers with fewer than 1,000 employees; "Large" refers to employers with 1,000-10,000 employees; "Mega" refers to firms with over 10,000 employees. Size is measured as the average (across months) number of employees working at a firm in the relevant year. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I.3 Screening as a Mechanism</head><p>My theoretical framework highlights several ways in which credentials may sort graduates into di!erent types of firm. In principle, explicit credentialing (that is, employers' screening behaviors -on account of either human capital screening or social closure) could be empirically distinguished from informational network e!ects (which capture job seekers' search behaviors) by observing di!erences in application behavior to firms by credential type, and then in o!er likelihood given application). Unfortunately, in the administrative data, job application information is not observed. Nevertheless, to gain some traction on this issue, I exploit the fact that a non-trivial proportion of individuals who begin their studies at one college attain a BA degree at another. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">S13</ref> in Appendix (I.1) shows that, conditional on attaining a BA degree, some 9% of students who initially attended the Flagship as a freshman admit end up completing their degree elsewhere.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_13">28</ref> I use this variation to examine the e!ect of attaining a BA degree from the Flagship, given that a person starts their postsecondary education at the Flagship, relative to starting college at the Flagship and completing elsewhere (mechanically, at a lower-ranked school). The core intuition here is that a student may still benefit from non-human capital inputs from the Flagship even if they transfer prior to degree completion at the Flagship. By contrast, any purely credentialing advantages are likely reduced, for the simple reason that the Flagship starters but non-completers cannot list a degree from the Flagship on their resumes. In the administrative data, the Flagship starters who finish a degree elsewhere roughly split their time between initial and final college, spending on average 6.6 semesters at the Flagship and 7.7 semesters at the school to which they transfer.</p><p>Exploiting this variation requires overcoming some important selection patterns. In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_21">20</ref> in Appendix I.1, I regress an indicator of out-transfer (from the Flagship) on pre-college as well as college-level covariates such as first-term GPA and credits completed. Column (1) includes student demographic and academic covariates only; column (2) adds high school fixed e!ects to account for unobserved di!erences across sending schools. Interestingly, while Female, Black, and English Language Learner (ELL) students show statistically significant di!erences in transfer rates, the strongest (negative) predictors of out-transfer are college-level covariates; high school GPA e!ects are statistically insignificant. The importance of college-level covariates suggests that more complex estimation strategy is required, in order to properly account for both pre-college, and college-level, covariates -the latter of which may themselves be a!ected by college attended (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Wodtke et al., 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Appendix B details the strategy I employ; in short, I estimate cumulative treatment e!ects (CTEs) of (i) the Flagship attendance and the Flagship completion, and (ii) the Flagship attendance and other school completion, both relative to College 7 attendance and completion. I examine CTEs on three outcomes: (1) the average firm fixed e!ect, (2) the probability of working at a firm in the top 90th percentile of the firm premium distribution, and (3) the probability of working at a firm in the top 80th percentile. These quantities are all estimated using the set of controls described previously, as well as using college-level controls. In particular, high school fixed e!ects adjust for the fact that students may be moving closer to their home.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_22">S19</ref> presents results (point estimates are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_24">21</ref>, Appendix H). The teal bars show the e!ect of attending and graduating from the Flagship, while the orange bars represent the e!ect of attending the Flagship but completing a degree elsewhere. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_14">29</ref> Both the Flagship starters-the Flagship completers and the Flagshipstarters-other completers experience substantial firm premium advantages relative to College 7 graduates. On average, attending and graduating from the Flagship yields a roughly .12 log point firm premium advantage; by contrast, attending the Flagship and completing a degree elsewhere yields no significant loss or gain in firm premium (-0.003, 95% confidence interval [↑.006, .01]) . This lack of gain is reflected in yielding no advantage in gaining access to firms at or above the 80th percentile of firm pay premiums. By contrast, there is a small and significant firm advantage to the Flagship completion when it comes to access to the highest premium firms. Specifically, the Flagship degree completion corresponds to a 2 percentage point increase in the probability of gaining access to a firm at or above the 90th percentile of firm pay (95% confidence interval [.004, .28]), representing a 20% increase on the baseline of 7.9 percentage points. These di!erences, while modest, suggest that holding the the Flagship credential confers an added labor market advantage -above and beyond the benefits of exposure to the the Flagship campus or peer environment -for access to the best paying employers. At the same time, a large portion of the total sorting advantage comes not from the credential itself, but from exposure to a distinct campus environment.  Notes: Point estimates and standard errors displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_22">S19</ref> in the main text. Estimated cumulative treatment e!ects of attending (as a freshman admit) and completing a degree at di!erent colleges, relative to attending (as a freshman admit) and completing a BA at College 7. Cumulative treatment e!ects are defined as the Flagship attendance and the Flagship completion (the Flagship Att., the Flagship BA), and as the Flagship attendance and BA completion at any other in-state, public college (the Flagship Att., Other BA). Outcomes include: (1) the average firm fixed e!ect, (2) the probability of working at a firm in the top 90th percentile of the firm premium distribution, and (3) the probability of working at a firm in the top 80th percentile. Percentiles are defined based on firm assignments among all public four-year college starters in Summit State. Estimates are obtained using the double machine learning (DML) approach described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for all nuisance models. Covariates include those from previous models (demographics, academic background, and high school characteristics), along with additional controls for degree completion selection: GPA at graduation or stop-out, first-term credits attempted and earned, and their squares. Standard errors are in parentheses. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records, as well as National Student Clearinghouse.  Notes: Point estimates and standard errors displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">22</ref>. Column 1 shows estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on log earnings ten years after high school graduation, obtained from a linear regression of log earnings on indicators for attendance at each college, and control variables. Column 2 displays estimates of mediation via firms, based on a linear regression of estimated firm premia on indicators for attendance at each college, and control variables. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending each college (versus College 7) on log earnings ten years after high school graduation, and mediation via employer assignment. Estimates are obtained using a linear modelbased, doubly robust estimator. This doubly robust estimator is equivalent to the EIF-based estimator μEIF j = 1 n n i=1 μj (X i ) +</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I.4 Linear-Based Estimates of ATE</head><formula xml:id="formula_39">I(A i =j) ωj (X i ) (Y i ↔ μj (X i ))</formula><p>as shown in Appendix B, but where μj (X i ) and εj (X i ) are estimated using linear models without cross-fitting, rather than using machine-learning and cross-fitting, Grey whiskers denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I.5 Total E!ect of any 4-Year College Attendance and Mediation via Firms</head><p>In this section, I compare my analyses for di!erent college e!ects relative to the e!ect of attending a 4-year college rather than no college at all. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_26">23</ref> shows results from an analysis of the e!ect of any 4-year college attendance on earnings, relative to no postsecondary exposure. Interestingly, nearly three quarters of the 11% return to any 4-year attendance appears to be driven by within-, rather than-between firm sorting. This suggests that, relative to no postsecondary experience, going to college matters not because of firm placement but because of within-firm productivity and job gains. But, conditional on the decision to attend a 4-year college, further earnings gains derive primarily from the firm at which an individual gains their post-college employment. Notes: Estimated average treatment e!ects (ATEs) of attending a 4-year college (either as a direct admit or as a transfer students) on log earnings ten years after high school graduation, relative to graduating high school but obtaining no postsecondary exposure, and mediation via employer assignment. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Grey whiskers denote 95% confidence intervals. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I.6 Linear Mediation Analysis</head><p>I also estimate a more conventional wage regression that includes firm fixed e!ects directly. This approach follows the empirical strategy of Engbom and Moser (2017) and allows for a simple decomposition of credential e!ects into within-firm and betweenfirm components. Specifically, I estimate the following model:</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">Y i = j ε j I(A i = j) + ϑ F (i) X → i φ + φ t + ϖ i ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where y it denotes the earnings of individual i 10 years following high school graduation; I(C it = j) is an indicator for whether an individual attended college j; and ε j captures the credential-specific earnings premium, relative to a reference group (College 7 attendance). X i denotes control variables which include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school graduation cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). Finally, ϑ F (i) is a firm fixed e!ect for an individual's employer 10 years after high school graduation.</p><p>I estimate this model both with and without the firm fixed e!ects ϑ F (i) to assess the extent to which credential premia reflect sorting into higher-premium firms. If attendance at college j increases earnings regardless of an individual's firm placement, the estimated ε j should remain stable with and without firm controls. Conversely, if college attendance primarily serve to facilitate access to higher-premium firms, then controlling for firm fixed e!ects should substantially attenuate the estimated ε j coefficients.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_28">24</ref> presents results. Column (1) reports estimates from a model without firm fixed e!ects, while column (2) includes firm fixed e!ects to account for variation in wages attributable to employer sorting. In the model without firm fixed e!ects (column 1), I find sizable and statistically significant earnings premiums associated with attending certain four-year public institutions in Summit State. For example, attending the Flagship is associated with a log earnings premium of 0.139, or approximately 15%, relative to College 7 (the omitted category). Similar positive and significant returns are observed for Summit State University (9.3%) and College 2 (7.5%). However, once firm fixed e!ects are included in column (2), these college-specific earnings premiums decline substantially. The estimated premium for Flagship attendance drops to 1.1% and is no longer statistically significant, while the coe"cient for College 2 becomes negative. The premium for Summit State University also falls by more than half, from 9.3% to 3.3%. These results suggest that a substantial portion of the observed earnings advantages for graduates of selective institutions reflects sorting into higher-premium firms, rather than di!erences in pay within firms. It is important to emphasize that this approach does not account for unobserved, time-invariant worker heterogeneity. If individuals with higher unobserved ability are more likely to attend more selective colleges and sort into higher-premium firms, then the firm fixed e!ects model may overstate the extent of mediation through firms. That is, controlling for firm fixed e!ects may "overcontrol" for endogenous sorting, leading to downward-biased estimates of the credential premium and overstated mediation e!ects. When calibrated against my main results, which are based on models that do adjust for selection into firms, this indeed appears to be the case. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Schematic Diagram Linking College Attended to Firm Placement</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Raw Gaps in and Treatment E!ects on Log Earnings and Firm Premiums Among Summit State 4-Year Starters</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: College E!ects on Firm Premium by High School GPA Buckets</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: College Attendance E!ects on Probability of Reaching a Firm with a Premium ↓ pth Percentile</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Firm Sorting E!ects, Isolated from Human Capital Components</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Partial E!ects of Human Capital Measures on Firm Premium and Earnings</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure S2: Mean of Estimated Firm Premiums, by County</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure S3 :</head><label>S3</label><figDesc>Figure S3: College Attendance E!ects and Mediation via Firms, by Free and Reduced Price Lunch (FRPL) Status</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The red dotted line marks the baseline (College 7) comparison group. Grey whiskers indicate 95% confidence intervals. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure S4 :</head><label>S4</label><figDesc>Figure S4: College Attendance E!ects and Mediation via Firms, by Family Income, Among Receivers of Financial Aid</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure S5 :</head><label>S5</label><figDesc>Figure S5: College Attendance E!ects and Mediation via Firms, by Racial-Ethnic Groups</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>in Appendix I.1). Given the positive e!ect of BA completion on earnings, non-completion attenuates ATE estimates of college attendance, relative to CTE estimates of college attendance and completion. Second, the estimated treatment e!ects of College 5 and College 6 attendance and completion are positive, more aligned with the raw earnings gaps displayed in the top panel of Figure 2 than with the negative estimated treatment e!ects presented in the figure's bottom panel. The reason for this is shown in Figure S14 in Appendix I.1: out-transfer (mechanically, to a more selective institution) is a far more common experience among College 7 than among College 5 and 6 attendees (with College 4 a particularly common destination for College 7 attendees). For this reason, CTE estimates of College 7 attendance and completion attenuate the ATE of College 7 relative to College 6 or College 5 attendance, given that College 7 attendance is more likely to lead to a credential from a more selective institution.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure S6: Cumulative Treatment E!ects (CTEs) of Attendance and Completion on Firm Outcomes</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure S7 :</head><label>S7</label><figDesc>Figure S7: College E!ects on Firm Premia, Marginally and Net of Location</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure S9 :</head><label>S9</label><figDesc>Figure S9: College E!ects on Firm Premia, Marginally and Net of Industry</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure S10 :</head><label>S10</label><figDesc>Figure S10: Direct E!ects of College Attendance on Firm Premium, Net of Employer Industry</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure S11: College Attendance E!ects and Mediation via Firms: 15 Years Following High School Graduation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure S12 :</head><label>S12</label><figDesc>Figure S12: Direct E!ects of College Attendance on Firm Premium, Net of Field of Study</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Standard errors are in parentheses. N = 48, 769 (mediation); N = 32, 976 (person e!ects); N = 43, 231 (college GPA), and N = 47, 881 (field of study); high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figure S13 :</head><label>S13</label><figDesc>Figure S13: Observed Conditional Probabilities of Degree Completion Across Colleges, Given First College and Given BA Attained</figDesc><graphic coords="74,190.10,150.72,253.52,239.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure S14 :</head><label>S14</label><figDesc>Figure S14: Counterfactual Conditional Probabilities of Degree Completion Across Colleges, Given First College and Given BA Attained</figDesc><graphic coords="75,176.45,149.47,263.93,251.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure S15: Counterfactual Probabilities of Any BA Attainment by College Attended</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Figure S19 :</head><label>S19</label><figDesc>Figure S19: Cumulative Treatment E!ects (CTEs) of Attendance and Completion on Firm Outcomes</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Figure S20 :</head><label>S20</label><figDesc>Figure S20: College Attendance E!ects and Mediation via Firms: Linear-Based Estimator</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="90,147.89,198.94,316.22,202.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Mean Values of Individual Characteristics, Academic Metrics, and Labor Market Outcomes by College Attainment Status by First College Attendance</figDesc><table><row><cell>College of First Attendance</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>I estimate the average treatment e!ect (ATE) of attending college j relative to College 7 using e"cient influence functions (EIFs). Let the observed data consist of units indexed by i = 1, . . . , n, with variables (Y i , A i , X i ), where Y i → {top10, FE, lnearn} denotes the outcome of interest, A i → {j, College 7} is the treatment assignment indicator, and X i is a vector of observed pre-college covariates.I define the conditional mean outcome under treatment j as µj (X) = E[Y | A = j, X],and similarly for the control group µ College 7</figDesc><table><row><cell>B.1 Average Treatment E!ect of College Attendance (Figure</cell></row><row><cell>2, and Figures S16, S17 and S18)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>DataLinked employer-employee data come from the state's employment department, obtained from employer wage reports filed through the state's Unemployment Insurance (UI) program. Specifically, I obtain quarterly earnings and hours worked from fiscal years 2005:Q1 to 2022:Q2 for nearly all private-sector, nonfederal public, and local government workers covered under the state's Unemployment Insurance (UI) system, representing a substantial share of the state's civilian labor force. 17 Employers submit quarterly wage reports to the employment department on each employees' wages and hours worked, as well as a (quarterly) summary file on employer characteristics including industry (North American Industry Classification System -NAICS -code), location of firm, and total counts of employees for each month. Employers can be either firms or establishments, depending on whether they operate exclusively in Summit State or across multiple states.18 The data are organized at the employee-employer-quarter level, meaning an individual may appear multiple times within a quarter if employed by more than one firm. I discuss the process of attaching a single employer to each person year in detail below. A crucial component of these data is that they contain longitudinal employer identifiers that are consistent across years.19   Data ConstructionIn this section, I provide further details about the construction of my earnings panels. First, for all panels, I begin by imputing missing hours based on an imputed wage rate for the contiguously employed, and drop all observations with negative wage values in a given year-quarter. If the worker has missing, zero, or negative income in a given quarter, I assume the worker is unemployed or working out of state, If the respondent 17 Nearly all employers with employees are required to participate in the UI Program if they pay wages to employees, regardless of the dollar amount. Participation includes registering with the state and submitting quarterly reports, and is not contingent on a worker filing a UI claim. It is these quarterly reports that I use. Several classes of worker are not reported in state UI records. These include self-employed workers and business owners, church employees, as well as federal employees, such as U.S. Postal Service (USPS), federal civilian employees, and active duty and retired military.18 I use the terms "firm" and "employer" interchangeably to refer to a person's place of employment. Technically, within the sample, the employer is the set of establishments operating in Summit State under a given owner. In the event that the company only operates inside Summit State, the employer is the firm; for companies that have registered addresses outside the state, the employer is a an establishment, or set of establishments. For companies operating solely in Summit State and with only one address, the firm is the establishment.19 Mergers, acquisitions, liquidation, changes in ownership and other types of restructuring will result in a new employer identification code.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Summary Statistics for the Full Sample of Workers and the Largest Connected Set (AKM Sample)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Statistic</cell><cell cols="2">Full Sample Connected Set</cell></row><row><cell>Person-year observations</cell><cell>2,913,597</cell><cell>2,355,953</cell></row><row><cell>Unique individuals (SSNs)</cell><cell>744,364</cell><cell>521,605</cell></row><row><cell>Unique firms</cell><cell>127,534</cell><cell>54,811</cell></row><row><cell>Unique movers (2+ firms)</cell><cell>262,674</cell><cell>224,080</cell></row><row><cell>Mover observations</cell><cell>361,497</cell><cell>300,470</cell></row></table><note><p>Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Variance Decomposition of Log Earnings</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variance Component</cell><cell cols="3">Raw Variance Share of Total Adj. R 2</cell></row><row><cell>Person E!ect (Var(ωi))</cell><cell>0 . 1 7</cell><cell>0 . 4 7</cell><cell>. 8 4</cell></row><row><cell>Firm E!ect (Var(εj))</cell><cell>0 . 0 7</cell><cell>0 . 2 0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Person-Firm Sorting (2 • Cov(ωi, εj))</cell><cell>0 . 0 5</cell><cell>0 . 1 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Residual (Var(ϑit))</cell><cell>0 . 0 4</cell><cell>0 . 1 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Total Variance of Log Earnings</cell><cell>0.36</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>Notes: The decompositions also include covariances between worker and employer fixed e!ects and year fixed e!ects. Because these covariances explain only about 3 percent of the variation, they are omitted from the table. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Cumulative Treatment E!ects (CTEs) of Attendance and Completion on Firm Outcomes</figDesc><table><row><cell>College</cell><cell>ATE</cell><cell>Mediation via Firm</cell></row><row><cell>College 7</cell><cell>10.872 (0.0066)*</cell><cell>0.102 (0.003)*</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>0.043 (0.0099)</cell><cell>0.016 (0.0043)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>0.052 (0.0095)</cell><cell>0.04 (0.0042)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.19 (0.0091)</cell><cell>0.08 (0.004)</cell></row><row><cell>College 1</cell><cell>0.221 (0.0087)</cell><cell>0.12 (0.0038)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>in Appendix D displays average firm premiums across Summit State counties and the locations of each college. Notably, the state flagship is in a county (which I call the "Primary Metropolitan Area") with some of the highest firm premiums in the state; Table 1 also showed that Flagship attendees are much more likely than College 7 attendees to work in a firm in the nearby Primary Metropolitan Area.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>College E!ects on Firm Premia, Marginally and Net of Location Point estimates and standard errors shown in Figure S16. See Notes for Figure S16. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.Figure S8: Direct E!ects of College Attendance on Firm Premium, Net of Employer Location</figDesc><table><row><cell>College</cell><cell>Mediation via Firm</cell><cell>Mediation via Firm, Net of Place</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>-0.014 (0.0033)</cell><cell>-0.011 (0.0033)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>-0.011 (0.0034)</cell><cell>-0.012 (0.0033)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.027 (0.0032)</cell><cell>0.025 (0.0032)</cell></row><row><cell>College 2</cell><cell>0.047 (0.0028)</cell><cell>0.038 (0.0026)</cell></row><row><cell>College 3</cell><cell>0.009 (0.0023)</cell><cell>0.002 (0.0022)</cell></row><row><cell>Flagship</cell><cell>0.068 (0.003)</cell><cell>0.051 (0.0028)</cell></row></table><note><p>Notes:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>College E!ects on Firm Premia, Marginally and Net of Industry Point estimates and standard errors shown in Figure S9. See Notes for Figure S9. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc><table><row><cell>College</cell><cell>Mediation via Firm</cell><cell>Mediation via Firm, Net of Industry</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>-0.014 (0.0033)</cell><cell>0.005 (0.0031)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>-0.011 (0.0034)</cell><cell>0.004 (0.0032)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.027 (0.0032)</cell><cell>0.031 (0.003)</cell></row><row><cell>College 2</cell><cell>0.047 (0.0028)</cell><cell>0.047 (0.0027)</cell></row><row><cell>College 3</cell><cell>0.009 (0.0023)</cell><cell>0.016 (0.0023)</cell></row><row><cell>Flagship</cell><cell>0.068 (0.003)</cell><cell>0.072 (0.0028)</cell></row></table><note><p>Notes:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Grey whiskers indicate 95% confidence intervals. N = 23, 289; high school graduating classes of 2006-2007. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records. -year Summit State public college (corresponding to 24% of all high school graduates). The in-state 2-year public college sector enrolls the largest share of Summit State high school graduates, at 54%. By contrast, only 10% (4/(24+4+5+8)) of 4-year starters began at a 4-year private in-state college. Students enrolling in an in-state public 4-year college are broadly similar to those attending a 4-year private or out-ofstate college (though are more likely to be white, and have slightly lower high school GPAs) (Table 12 in Appendix F.1) . High School Graduates' Engagement with the Postsecondary Sector</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">F Descriptive Statistics on Educational Outcomes</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">F.1 Engagement with non-Summit State Public Postsecondary</cell></row><row><cell>System</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">This section shows that the public 4-year postsecondary sector in Summit State is</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">a favored destination for postsecondary goers, and especially for students pursuing</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">postsecondary education in-state. Among 4-year college starters (that is, freshman</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">admits) among the 2006-2012 high school graduating cohorts, 59% (24/(24+4+5+8))</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">began at a 4Proportion of HS Graduates (N = 448,795)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever Attended 4 Year College</cell><cell>0.59</cell></row><row><cell>BA Within 10 Years of HS Completion</cell><cell>0.42</cell></row><row><cell>First College: In-State 4-Year Public</cell><cell>0.24</cell></row><row><cell>First College: In-State 2-Year Public</cell><cell>0.54</cell></row><row><cell>First College: In-State 4-Year Private</cell><cell>0.04</cell></row><row><cell>First College: In-State 2-Year Private</cell><cell>0.01</cell></row><row><cell>First College: OOS 4-Year Public</cell><cell>0.05</cell></row><row><cell>First College: OOS 4-Year Private</cell><cell>0.08</cell></row><row><cell>First College: OOS 2-Year Private</cell><cell>0.00</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Notes: "Ever Attended 4 Year College" denotes whether an individual ever attended a 4-year college with 10 years</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">following high school graduation. High school graduating classes 2006-2012 shown.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records, and National Student Clear-</cell></row><row><cell>inghouse.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Characteristics of High School Graduates by First College Type</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>First College Attended</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">4 Year Summit State Public 4 Year Private or OOS</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>0.54</cell><cell>0.56</cell></row><row><cell>Black</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.04</cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>0.05</cell></row><row><cell>White</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell>0.79</cell></row><row><cell>English Speaking</cell><cell>0.88</cell><cell>0.93</cell></row><row><cell>Final HS GPA</cell><cell>3.44</cell><cell>3.34</cell></row><row><cell>Ever Homeless</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Ever FRPL</cell><cell>0.21</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell>Ever SPED</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.03</cell></row><row><cell>Ever ELL</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Probability of Non-Zero Earnings</cell><cell>0.59</cell><cell>0.38</cell></row><row><cell>N (Individuals)</cell><cell>85,313</cell><cell>63,161</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Notes: Descriptive statistics for students whose first college attended was either a Summit State public four-year</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">institution (or "4 Year Summit State Public") a private or out-of-state four-year institution ("4 Year Summit State or</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">OOS"). High school graduating classes 2006-2012, who were were first-time college enrollees.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records, and National Student Clear-</cell></row><row><cell>inghouse.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 14 :</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Educational Outcomes by College of First Enrollment</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">College Attended</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>College 7</cell><cell>College 6</cell><cell>College 5</cell><cell>College 4</cell><cell>College 3</cell><cell>College 2</cell><cell>Flagship</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The red dotted line marks the baseline (College 7) comparison group. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc><table><row><cell>H Table Outputs: Main Results</cell></row><row><cell>H.1 Raw Earnings Gaps</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Table 16 :</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Raw Log Earnings Gaps Among Summit State 4-Year Starters Point estimates and standard errors displayed in Figure 2 in the main text. Raw log earnings returns, relative to College 7, for students who attended (as a freshman admit) six public 4-year institutions in Summit State. The colleges included are Summit State's Flagship school, and Colleges 2 to 6. Earnings returns are measured ten years after high school graduation, while firm returns correspond to the estimated fixed e!ect of an individual's employer, also ten years after high school graduation. Standard errors are in parentheses. Numbers with asterisks denote means, rather than di!erences in means. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc><table><row><cell>College</cell><cell>Raw Earnings Premium</cell><cell>Raw Firm Premium</cell></row><row><cell>College 7</cell><cell>10.738 (0.0091)</cell><cell>0.089 (0.0036)</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>0.081 (0.0126)</cell><cell>0.023 (0.005)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>0.135 (0.0114)</cell><cell>0.039 (0.0046)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.245 (0.0109)</cell><cell>0.073 (0.0043)</cell></row><row><cell>College 2</cell><cell>0.256 (0.021)</cell><cell>0.124 (0.0083)</cell></row><row><cell>College 3</cell><cell>0.136 (0.0236)</cell><cell>0.058 (0.0094)</cell></row><row><cell>Flagship</cell><cell>0.411 (0.0106)</cell><cell>0.141 (0.0042)</cell></row></table><note><p>Notes:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Table 17 :</head><label>17</label><figDesc>College Attendance E!ects and Mediation via Firms</figDesc><table><row><cell>College</cell><cell>ATE</cell><cell>Mediation via Firm</cell></row><row><cell>College 7</cell><cell>10.91 (0.0052)</cell><cell>NA</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>-0.017 (0.0079)</cell><cell>-0.014 (0.0033)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>-0.046 (0.0081)</cell><cell>-0.011 (0.0034)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.085 (0.0076)</cell><cell>0.027 (0.0032)</cell></row><row><cell>College 2</cell><cell>0.06 (0.0063)</cell><cell>0.047 (0.0028)</cell></row><row><cell>College 3</cell><cell>0.015 (0.0052)</cell><cell>0.009 (0.0023)</cell></row><row><cell>Flagship</cell><cell>0.134 (0.0071)</cell><cell>0.068 (0.003)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). Standard errors are in parentheses. Numbers with asterisks denote counterfactual means, rather than treatment e!ects. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Table 18 :</head><label>18</label><figDesc>College Attendance E!ects on Probability of Reaching a Firm with a Premium ↓ pth Percentile</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Percentile (p) of Firm Premium</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>College</cell><cell>95th</cell><cell>90th</cell><cell>80th</cell><cell>70th</cell><cell>60th</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>-0.01 (0.0021)</cell><cell>-0.006 (0.0032)</cell><cell>-0.009 (0.0045)</cell><cell>-0.01 (0.0054)</cell><cell>-0.018 (0.0061)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>0 (0.0024)</cell><cell>0.001 (0.0033)</cell><cell>-0.001 (0.0046)</cell><cell>-0.002 (0.0055)</cell><cell>-0.004 (0.0061)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.009 (0.0024)</cell><cell>0.022 (0.0033)</cell><cell>0.045 (0.0046)</cell><cell>0.058 (0.0054)</cell><cell>0.065 (0.0059)</cell></row><row><cell>College 2</cell><cell>0.025 (0.0022)</cell><cell>0.041 (0.0029)</cell><cell>0.071 (0.0039)</cell><cell>0.083 (0.0046)</cell><cell>0.091 (0.005)</cell></row><row><cell>College 3</cell><cell>0.003 (0.0016)</cell><cell>0.01 (0.0021)</cell><cell>0.03 (0.003)</cell><cell>0.047 (0.0037)</cell><cell>0.021 (0.0041)</cell></row><row><cell>Flagship</cell><cell>0.031 (0.0024)</cell><cell>0.054 (0.0032)</cell><cell>0.092 (0.0043)</cell><cell>0.118 (0.005)</cell><cell>0.123 (0.0054)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). Standard errors are in parentheses. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table 19 :</head><label>19</label><figDesc>College Attendance E!ects on Firm Premium, Isolated from Human Capital</figDesc><table><row><cell>College</cell><cell>Firm Sorting E!ect</cell><cell>Net of PE</cell><cell>Net of GPA</cell><cell>Net of FOS</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>-0.014 (0.0023)</cell><cell>-0.007 (0.0027)</cell><cell>-0.012 (0.0025)</cell><cell>-0.004 (0.0023)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>-0.011 (0.0024)</cell><cell>-0.002 (0.0028)</cell><cell>-0.006 (0.0025)</cell><cell>-0.006 (0.0024)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.027 (0.0023)</cell><cell>0.033 (0.0027)</cell><cell>0.035 (0.0024)</cell><cell>0.024 (0.0022)</cell></row><row><cell>College 2</cell><cell>0.047 (0.0019)</cell><cell>0.047 (0.0023)</cell><cell>0.055 (0.002)</cell><cell>0.044 (0.0019)</cell></row><row><cell>College 3</cell><cell>0.009 (0.0016)</cell><cell>0.017 (0.0019)</cell><cell>0.014 (0.0017)</cell><cell>-0.003 (0.0016)</cell></row><row><cell>Flagship</cell><cell>0.068 (0.0021)</cell><cell>0.069 (0.0025)</cell><cell>0.077 (0.0022)</cell><cell>0.065 (0.0021)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head>Table 20 :</head><label>20</label><figDesc>Predictors of Transferring out of the state's Flagship Linear probability model estimates of the likelihood that a student transfers from the state's Flagship, given that they began their postsecondary studies at the Flagship. The outcome variable equals one if the student completes a BA at a di!erent institution than where they initially enrolled. Column (1) includes student demographic and academic covariates only; column (2) adds high school fixed e!ects to account for unobserved di!erences across sending schools. Key predictors include first-term GPA and first-term credits, both of which are strongly negatively associated with transfer likelihood. Female, Black, and English Language Learner (ELL) students show statistically significant di!erences in transfer rates. Standard errors are clustered at the individual level in column (1) and at the high school level in column (2). Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records, as well as National Student Clearinghouse.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Transfer</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell></row><row><cell>Constant</cell><cell>0.1810 →→→</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0193)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>-0.0094 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0104 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0028)</cell><cell>(0.0028)</cell></row><row><cell>Black</cell><cell>-0.0290 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0329 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0088)</cell><cell>(0.0064)</cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic</cell><cell>0.0063</cell><cell>-0.0097</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0068)</cell><cell>(0.0076)</cell></row><row><cell>white</cell><cell>0.0147 →→→</cell><cell>0.0086 →→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0031)</cell><cell>(0.0035)</cell></row><row><cell>finalgpa</cell><cell>0.0057</cell><cell>0.0014</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0051)</cell><cell>(0.0046)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever Homeless</cell><cell>0.0212</cell><cell>0.0130</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0218)</cell><cell>(0.0265)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever FRPL</cell><cell>0.0034</cell><cell>-0.0038</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0037)</cell><cell>(0.0042)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever SPED</cell><cell>0.0021</cell><cell>0.0047</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0202)</cell><cell>(0.0218)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever ELL</cell><cell>0.0219 →→</cell><cell>0.0269 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0085)</cell><cell>(0.0099)</cell></row><row><cell>first_term_gpa</cell><cell>-0.0435 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0407 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0028)</cell><cell>(0.0041)</cell></row><row><cell>first_term_cred</cell><cell>-0.0016 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0016 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0005)</cell><cell>(0.0005)</cell></row><row><cell>Standard-Errors</cell><cell>IID</cell><cell>HS</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>19,720</cell><cell>19,720</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.01765</cell><cell>0.04986</cell></row><row><cell>Within R 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.01574</cell></row><row><cell>HS fixed e!ects</cell><cell></cell><cell>↭</cell></row><row><cell>Notes:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records. Bars show counterfactual probabilities of working in a firm located in either the state's Primary Metropolitan Area, a multi-establishment firm, or in a non-Primary Metropolitan Area county. "Primary Metropolitan Area" and "Other Area" denotes working for single-establishment employers in the state's Primary Metropolitan Area or a non-Primary Metropolitan Area, respectively. S "Multi-Establishment" denotes working for a firm with multiple establishments; in the administrative UI records, I am unable to locate the specific establishment of employment of workers employed by multi-establishment firms. Estimates are obtained using a double machine learning (DML) approach, as described in Appendix B, with ridge regression used for both the propensity score and outcome models, estimated with five-fold cross fitting. Control variables include student race/ethnicity, sex, high school cohort, high school GPA and GPA squared, high school fixed e!ects, and indicators for whether the student was ever homeless, ever eligible for free or reduced-price lunch (FRPL), ever received special education services (SPED), or ever classified as an English language learner (ELL). N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">I.2 Counterfactual Firm Location, Industry and Size Figure S17: Counterfactual Probabilities of Working in Select Industries, by College</cell></row><row><cell>Attended</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Figure S16: Counterfactual Probabilities of Working in the Primary Metropolitan Area, a Multi-Establishment Firm, or Outside the Primary Metropolitan Area, by College Attended 0.2 0.4 0.6 Counterfactual Probability of College 5 College 4 College 3 College 2 Flagship E d u c a t i o n a l S e r v i c e s F i n a n c e a n d I n s u r a n c e H e a l t h C a r e I n f o r m a t i o n P S T S e r v i c e s Working at Location College 7 College 6 0.00 0.05 0.10 0.15 0.20 0.25 Counterfactual Probability of College 7 College 6 College 5 College 4 College 3 College 2 Working in Industry Flagship</cell></row><row><cell>0.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P r i m a r y M e t r o p o l i t a n A r e a</cell><cell>M u l t i -E s t a b l i s h m e n t</cell><cell>O t h e r A r e a</cell></row></table><note><p>Notes:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_23"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="5">Figure S18: Counterfactual Probabilities of Working in Firm of Given Size, by College</cell></row><row><cell>Attended</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.6</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Counterfactual Probability of</cell><cell>Working in Firm of Size</cell><cell>0.0 0.2 0.4</cell><cell></cell><cell>College 7 College 6 College 5 College 4 College 3 College 2 Flagship</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Small</cell><cell>Large</cell><cell>Mega</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_24"><head>Table 21 :</head><label>21</label><figDesc>Cumulative Treatment E!ects (CTEs) of Attendance and Completion on Firm Outcomes</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Flagship Att., Flagship BA Flagship Att., Other BA</cell><cell>Di!erence</cell></row><row><cell>Mean Firm Premium</cell><cell>0.12 (0.0038)</cell><cell>0.123 (0.0049)</cell><cell>-0.003 (0.0044)</cell></row><row><cell>&gt; 90th Percentile of Firm Premium</cell><cell>0.095 (0.0041)</cell><cell>0.079 (0.0061)</cell><cell>0.016 (0.006)</cell></row><row><cell>&gt; 80th Percentile of Firm Premium</cell><cell>0.161 (0.0055)</cell><cell>0.164 (0.0082)</cell><cell>-0.004 (0.0079)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head>Table 22 :</head><label>22</label><figDesc>College Attendance E!ects and Mediation via Firms: Linear-Based Estimator</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Log Earnings Firm Premium</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>0.0111</cell><cell>-0.0029</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0124)</cell><cell>(0.0058)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>-0.0424 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>-0.0063</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0118)</cell><cell>(0.0056)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.0927 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>0.0332 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0113)</cell><cell>(0.0051)</cell></row><row><cell>College 3</cell><cell>0.0733 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>0.0579 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0192)</cell><cell>(0.0100)</cell></row><row><cell>College 2</cell><cell>0.0318</cell><cell>0.0136</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0237)</cell><cell>(0.0093)</cell></row><row><cell>Flagship</cell><cell>0.1393 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>0.0767 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0131)</cell><cell>(0.0059)</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>-0.1798 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>-0.0731 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0067)</cell><cell>(0.0028)</cell></row><row><cell>Black</cell><cell>-0.0658 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>0.0089</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0174)</cell><cell>(0.0063)</cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic</cell><cell>-0.0059</cell><cell>-0.0089</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0156)</cell><cell>(0.0055)</cell></row><row><cell>Asian</cell><cell>0.0189 ↗</cell><cell>0.0132 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0105)</cell><cell>(0.0038)</cell></row><row><cell>Has GED</cell><cell>0.2026 ↗</cell><cell>0.0332</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1214)</cell><cell>(0.0631)</cell></row><row><cell>HS Graduation Year</cell><cell>0.0208 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>0.0065 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0018)</cell><cell>(0.0007)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever Homeless</cell><cell>-0.0485</cell><cell>-0.0435 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0341)</cell><cell>(0.0165)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever FRPL</cell><cell>-0.0482 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>-0.0060 ↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0095)</cell><cell>(0.0035)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever SPED</cell><cell>-0.2262 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>-0.0539 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0285)</cell><cell>(0.0100)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever ELL</cell><cell>-0.0081</cell><cell>0.0031</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0244)</cell><cell>(0.0089)</cell></row><row><cell>HS GPA</cell><cell>-0.3849 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>-0.0672 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0348)</cell><cell>(0.0187)</cell></row><row><cell>HS GPA, Squared</cell><cell>0.1034 ↗↗↗</cell><cell>0.0148 ↗↗↗</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0058)</cell><cell>(0.0030)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>48,808</cell><cell>48,808</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.11097</cell><cell>0.08110</cell></row><row><cell>Within R 2</cell><cell>0.07267</cell><cell>0.04355</cell></row><row><cell>HS fixed e!ects</cell><cell>↭</cell><cell>↭</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_26"><head>Table 23 :</head><label>23</label><figDesc>E!ect of Any 4-year Exposure, and Mediation via Firms</figDesc><table><row><cell>College</cell><cell>ATE</cell><cell>Mediation via Firm</cell></row><row><cell>High School Only</cell><cell>10.622 (0.003)*</cell><cell>0.093 (0.0011)*</cell></row><row><cell>4-Year Attendance</cell><cell>0.108 (0.0037)</cell><cell>0.028 (0.0014)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_27"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). Standard errors are in parentheses. Numbers with stars denote counterfactual means, rather than treatment e!ects. N = 227, 114; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head>Table 24 :</head><label>24</label><figDesc>Linear Mediation AnalysisNotes: Results from linear regressions of log earnings ten years after high school graduation on college attended and student characteristics, estimated with and without firm fixed e!ects. Column (1) includes controls for high school fixed e!ects, student demographics, and academic background, but omits firm controls. Column (2) adds firm fixed e!ects to account for wage variation attributable to employer assignment. The coe"cients on college indicators represent earnings di!erences relative to College 7, the omitted category. Comparing columns shows how much of the college earnings premium is accounted for by di!erences in the types of firms students work for. Standard errors in parentheses.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Log Earnings</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">M1: No Firm E!ects M2: With Firm E!ects</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell></row><row><cell>College 6</cell><cell>0.0111</cell><cell>0.0148</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0124)</cell><cell>(0.0143)</cell></row><row><cell>College 5</cell><cell>-0.0424 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0407 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0118)</cell><cell>(0.0143)</cell></row><row><cell>College 4</cell><cell>0.0927 →→→</cell><cell>0.0318 →→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0113)</cell><cell>(0.0135)</cell></row><row><cell>College 3</cell><cell>0.0733 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0368 →</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0192)</cell><cell>(0.0216)</cell></row><row><cell>College 2</cell><cell>0.0318</cell><cell>-0.0160</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0237)</cell><cell>(0.0275)</cell></row><row><cell>Flagship</cell><cell>0.1393 →→→</cell><cell>0.0103</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0131)</cell><cell>(0.0148)</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>-0.1798 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0729 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0067)</cell><cell>(0.0070)</cell></row><row><cell>Black</cell><cell>-0.0658 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0722 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0174)</cell><cell>(0.0198)</cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic</cell><cell>-0.0059</cell><cell>0.0014</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0156)</cell><cell>(0.0150)</cell></row><row><cell>Asian</cell><cell>0.0189 →</cell><cell>-0.0099</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0105)</cell><cell>(0.0098)</cell></row><row><cell>Has GED</cell><cell>0.2026 →</cell><cell>0.2254 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1214)</cell><cell>(0.0721)</cell></row><row><cell>HS Graduation Year</cell><cell>0.0208 →→→</cell><cell>0.0122 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0018)</cell><cell>(0.0017)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever Homeless</cell><cell>-0.0485</cell><cell>0.0135</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0341)</cell><cell>(0.0390)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever FRPL</cell><cell>-0.0482 →→→</cell><cell>-0.0219 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0095)</cell><cell>(0.0079)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever SPED</cell><cell>-0.2262 →→→</cell><cell>-0.1416 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0285)</cell><cell>(0.0320)</cell></row><row><cell>Ever ELL</cell><cell>-0.0081</cell><cell>-0.0398</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0244)</cell><cell>(0.0253)</cell></row><row><cell>HS GPA</cell><cell>-0.3849 →→→</cell><cell>-0.2134 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0348)</cell><cell>(0.0473)</cell></row><row><cell>HS GPA, Squared</cell><cell>0.1034 →→→</cell><cell>0.0647 →→→</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0058)</cell><cell>(0.0075)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>48,808</cell><cell>48,808</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.11097</cell><cell>0.59102</cell></row><row><cell>Within R 2</cell><cell>0.07267</cell><cell>0.03244</cell></row><row><cell>HS fixed e!ects</cell><cell>↭</cell><cell>↭</cell></row><row><cell>Firm fixed e!ects</cell><cell></cell><cell>↭</cell></row></table><note><p>*** p &lt; 0.01, ** p &lt; 0.05, * p &lt; 0.1. N = 48, 769; high school graduating classes of 2006-2012. Source: Summit State administrative UI earnings, postsecondary and high school records.</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://www.muckrock.com/news/archives/2018/jan/26/cia-college-tour-campus-protest/.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>I anonymize the focal state throughout this paper to comply with my data use agreement governing my use of the state's administrative data.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Table 10 in Appendix F.1 confirms that the public</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_3"><p>4-year postsecondary sector in Summit State is a favored destination for postsecondary goers, and especially for students pursuing postsecondary education</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_4"><p>In order to ensure comparability across analyses that require non-missing industry, firm size, and firm location information, I define an individual to have observed earnings only if the individual has non-missing information on these employer attributes. In practice, this reduces the sample trivially, by just over 200 individuals.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_5"><p>Note that in all analyses that follow, I normalize firm fixed e!ects with respect to the average firm e!ect in the retail sector.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="11" xml:id="foot_6"><p>Qualitatively, my estimate of flagship attendance on earnings is broadly similar to, albeit somewhat smaller than, to those presented by Hoekstra (2009), who uses a regression discontinuity design to estimate the economic return to attending the flagship relative to students' fallback options as between 19% and 24%. That my estimates are smaller could reflect either cross-college variation in institutional impact, or larger treatment e!ects among the set of compliers whose admission or enrollment decisions were determined by the admission cuto! studied</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_7"><p>I define percentiles of pay premiums with respect to the population of 4-year college attendees, rather the full sample of high school graduates, to capture sorting e!ects for the types of firms college graduates are likely to work at. There is considerable employer segregation between college goers and graduates and those without postsecondary experience.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_8"><p>These are all estimated net of the same covariates used for the main analyses, in addition to first college attended.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="16" xml:id="foot_9"><p>Preliminary analyses in this direction suggest some waning of the importance of firm sorting 15 years after high school graduation (Figure (S11), Appendix (E)), driven by an increased within-firm returns to flagship</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_10"><p>attendance over time, rather than by waning firm sorting patterns over time. Parsing out to what extent this pattern results within-firm progression on the basis of educational credentials per se, as opposed to graduate education returns, is an important direction for future work.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="21" xml:id="foot_11"><p>Note in addition that the UI wage data reports only the location of the employer, and not where an individual employee is located.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="25" xml:id="foot_12"><p>As discussed in detail in Appendix (C), I am unable to discern the location of employment for employers with multiple establishments. I therefore categorize single establishment firms into whether they are located in the "Primary Metropolitan Area" or another county ("Other Area"), or whether the employer has multiple establishments.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="28" xml:id="foot_13"><p>Of the 7.5% of the Flagship starters who transfer out of the Flagship, 56% transfer to an in-state college.Of those, just under half transfer to College 3 or College 2.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="29" xml:id="foot_14"><p>Note that the Flagship attendance and completion yields a significantly higher firm premium, relative to the Flagship attendance e!ects shown in Figure(??). The reason for this discrepancy is that counterfactual rates of BA completion are almost identical, at approximately 77% across all colleges (Figure (S15) in Appendix (I.1)). Given the positive e!ect of BA completion on earnings, non-completion attenuates ATE estimates of college attendance, relative to CTE estimates of college attendance and completion.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>The analyses and conclusions presented in this work are solely those of the author and do not reflect the views or opinions of the state's Employment or Education Departments. This research was partly supported by a <rs type="funder">Russell Sage Foundation Dissertation Grant</rs> (RSF Grant#: <rs type="grantNumber">2401-47047</rs>), grants from the <rs type="funder">Harvard Institute for Quantitative Social Science</rs>, the <rs type="institution">Harvard Center for Population Studies</rs>, as well as a <rs type="grantName">Linda G. Hammett Ory Fellowship</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PBX3BU8">
					<idno type="grant-number">2401-47047</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Uak8C3B">
					<orgName type="grant-name">Linda G. Hammett Ory Fellowship</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I.7 Trends in Pell Grant and Minority Students at Summit</head><p>State Public College </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The system of professions: An essay on the division of expert labor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>University of Chicago press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High wage workers and high wage firms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Francis</forename><surname>John M Abowd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kramarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Margolis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0012-9682</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computing person and firm e!ects using linked longitudinal employer-employee data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>John M Abowd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Francis</forename><surname>Creecy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kramarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The labor market returns to advanced degrees</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ling</forename><surname>Altonji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0734-306X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heterogeneity in human capital investments: High school curriculum, college major, and careers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erica</forename><surname>Joseph G Altonji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Costas</forename><surname>Blom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Meghir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Econ</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1941-1383</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The analysis of field choice in college and graduate school: Determinants and wage e!ects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Joseph G Altonji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arnaud</forename><surname>Arcidiacono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Maurel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="396" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The returns to college major choice: Average and distributional e!ects, career trajectories, and earnings variability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rodney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Scott</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Imberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lovenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Stange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Career consequences of firm heterogeneity for young workers: First job and firm size</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jaime</forename><surname>Arellano-Bover</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0734- 306X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="549" to="589" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Paying for the Party</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Elizabeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laura</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extending the race between education and technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Autor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claudia</forename><surname>Goldin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AEA papers and proceedings</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Nashville, TN</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Economic Association 2014 Broadway</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="347" to="351" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suite 305</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bringing the firms back in: Stratification, segmentation, and the organization of work</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bielby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American sociological review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0003-1224</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="737" to="765" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">It&apos;s where you work: Increases in the dispersion of earnings across establishments and individuals in the united states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erling</forename><surname>Barth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alex</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0734-306X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">S. human capital: A theoretical and empirical analysis, with special reference to education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
			<publisher>University of Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investment in human capital: A theoretical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of political economy</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-3808</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">College choice and wages: Estimates using data on female twins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jere R Behrman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Mark R Rosenzweig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Taubman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6535</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="672" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Management practices, workforce selection, and productivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Bender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Van Reenen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefanie</forename><surname>Wolter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0734-306X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The education-innovation gap</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename><surname>Biasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Song</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Credentials, signals, and screens: Explaining the relationship between schooling and job assignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of educational research</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6543</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="469" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Becoming right: How campuses shape young conservatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Binder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kate</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Career funneling: How elite students learn to define and desire &quot;prestigious&quot;jobs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Binder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nick</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociology of Education</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0038-0407</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How robust is the evidence on the e!ects of college quality? evidence from matching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dan</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Je!rey A</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of econometrics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-4076</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A&quot;rmative action and its race-neutral alternatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zachary</forename><surname>Bleemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpubeco.2023.104839</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpubeco.2023.104839" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">220</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104839</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Will studying economics make you rich? a regression discontinuity analysis of the returns to college major</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zachary</forename><surname>Bleemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aashish</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/APP.20200447</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Journal: Applied Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-22</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pay, productivity and management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Scott</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ohlmacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cristina</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tello-Trillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Melanie</forename><surname>Wallskog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">School-to-work linkages, educational mismatches, and labor market outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thijs</forename><surname>Bol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christina</forename><forename type="middle">Ciocca</forename><surname>Eller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Herman</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Van De Werfhorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Diprete</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0003-1224</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="307" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dropouts and diplomas: The divergence in collegiate outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Bound</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sarah</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="613" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Shape of the River. Long-Term Consequences of Considering Race in College and University Admissions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>William</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Derek</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bok</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ERIC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Crossing the finish line</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>William G Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chingos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mcpherson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Schooling in capitalist America</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Samuel</forename><surname>Bowles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Herbert</forename><surname>Gintis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regression and matching estimates of the e!ects of elite college attendance on educational and career achievement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jennie</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Charles</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Halaby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science Research</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0049-089X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="749" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coercion and consent in contested exchange</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Burawoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erik</forename><surname>Olin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wright</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Politics &amp; Society</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0032-3292</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Workplace heterogeneity and the rise of west german wage inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jörg</forename><surname>Heining</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly journal of economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0033-5533</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="967" to="1015" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Firms and labor market inequality: Evidence and some theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ana</forename><forename type="middle">Rute</forename><surname>Cardoso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joerg</forename><surname>Heining</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0734-306X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The increasing penalty to occupation-education mismatch</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hugh</forename><surname>Cassidy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amanda</forename><surname>Gaulke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economic Inquiry</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0095-2583</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="607" to="632" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diversifying society&apos;s leaders? the causal e!ects of admission to highly selective private colleges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Raj</forename><surname>Chetty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What makes a quality college? re-examining the equalizing potential of higher education in the united states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christina</forename><surname>Ciocca-Eller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/727891</idno>
		<idno>doi: 10.1086/727891</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1086/727891" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9602</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-09">9 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The organizational saga in higher education. Administrative science quarterly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Burton R Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="184" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The credential society: An historical sociology of education and stratification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Randall</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Estimating the return to college selectivity over the career using administrative earnings data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stacy</forename><surname>Dale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the payo! to attending a more selective college: An application of selection on observables and unobservables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stacy</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dale</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1531-4650</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1491" to="1527" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Selling students: The rise of corporate partnership programs in university career centers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Binder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Emerald Group Publishing Limited</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="422" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Industry, firm, job title: The layered nature of early-career advantage for graduates of elite private universities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Binder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Socius</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2378-0231</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2378023119859711</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Skill requirements across firms and labor markets: Evidence from job postings for professionals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0734-306X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The value of postsecondary credentials in the labor market: An experimental study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Noam</forename><surname>David J Deming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amira</forename><surname>Yuchtman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claudia</forename><surname>Abulafi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Goldin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="778" to="806" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">School-to-work linkages in the united states, germany, and france</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christina</forename><forename type="middle">Ciocca</forename><surname>Thomas A Diprete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thijs</forename><surname>Eller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Herman</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van De Werfhorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9602</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1869" to="1938" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Categorical inequality: Schools as sorting machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thurston</forename><surname>Domina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Penner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emily</forename><surname>Penner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual review of sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0360-0572</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Worker power, firm power, and the structure of labor markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><surname>Fligstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roberto</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Quarterly</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0038-0253</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Institutional selectivity and institutional expenditures: Examining organizational factors that contribute to retention and graduation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ann</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gansemer-Topf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schuh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="642" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Research in higher education</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assortative matching or exclusionary hiring? the impact of employment and pay policies on racial wage di!erences in brazil</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">François</forename><surname>Gerard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lorenzo</forename><surname>Lagos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edson</forename><surname>Severnini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002- 8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3418" to="3457" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Access to 4-year public colleges and degree completion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joshua</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Hurwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0734-306X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="867" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Making elite lawyers: Visions of law at harvard and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Granfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of the female/male wage di!erential: Is it who you are, what you do, or where you work</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Erica L Groshen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Human Resources</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-166X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="472" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motivation through the design of work: Test of a theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Hackman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Greg</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Oldham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational behavior and human performance</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0030-5073</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="279" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Providing a &quot;leg up&quot;: Parental involvement and opportunity hoarding in college</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laura</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Josipa</forename><surname>Roksa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kelly</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociology of Education</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0038-0407</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mark Hoekstra. The e!ect of attending the flagship state university on earnings: A discontinuity-based approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Karen</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6535</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="717" to="724" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2009</date>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Liquidated: An Ethnography of Wall Street</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Economic segmentation, worker power, and income inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arne</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kalleberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Althauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9602</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="651" to="683" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The status attainment process: socialization or allocation?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kerckho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">!</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social forces</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1534-7605</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="368" to="381" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Firm wage e!ects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Handbook of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1573-4463</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Capitalizing on crisis: The political origins of the rise of finance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Greta</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Krippner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The kids in the conference room</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Lemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">10 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">i was open to anywhere, it&apos;s just this was easier:&quot; social structure, location preferences, and the geographic concentration of elite college graduates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Manduca</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qualitative Sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0162-0436</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing the educational attainment of community college transfer students and four-year college rising juniors using propensity score matching methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tatiana</forename><surname>Melguizo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gregory</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kienzl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mariana</forename><surname>Alfonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Higher Education</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-1546</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The e!ects of education as an institution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of Sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9602</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Old boys&apos; clubs and upward mobility among the educational elite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Valerie</forename><surname>Michelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Seth</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zimmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0033-5533</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="909" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Jack Mountjoy and Brent R Hickman. The returns to college (s): Relative value-added and match e!ects in higher education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Mountjoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2024. 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
	<note>Marginal returns to public universities</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Megan</forename><surname>Tobias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neely</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Hedged out: Inequality and insecurity on Wall Street</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Univ of California Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Not what it was and not what it will be: The future of job design research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Greg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Oldham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Richard Hackman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of organizational behavior</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0894-3796</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="463" to="479" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The wage e!ects of high performance work organization in manufacturing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Osterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ilr Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0019-7939</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Race, self-selection, and the job search process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Devah</forename><surname>Pager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pedulla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9602</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1005" to="1054" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Marxism and class theory: A bourgeois critique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Parkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Strategies of social closure in class formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Parkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Same major, same economic returns? college selectivity and earnings inequality in young adulthood</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Natasha</forename><surname>Quadlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emma</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tom</forename><surname>Vanheuvelen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Social Stratification and Mobility</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0276-5624</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100647</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When the tasks line up: How the nature of supplementary tasks a!ects worker productivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aruna</forename><surname>Ranganathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ilr Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0019-7939</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="556" to="585" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Race, income, and enrollment patterns in highly selective colleges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rachel</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Sean F Reardon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Klasik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982-2004. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why status matters for inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cecilia</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ridgeway</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American sociological review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0003-1224</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pedigree: Elite reproduction in hiring</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lauren</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ivies, extracurriculars, and exclusion: Elite employers&apos; use of educational credentials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lauren</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Social Stratification and Mobility</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0276-5624</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hiring as cultural matching: The case of elite professional service firms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lauren</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American sociological review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0003-1224</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1022" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Employer decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lauren</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual review of sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0360-0572</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Education and job match: The relatedness of college major and work</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Robst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economics of Education review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0272-7757</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">After admission: From college access to college success</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Regina</forename><surname>James E Rosenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ann</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Deil-Amen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Person</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Russell Sage Foundation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">You&apos;re paid what you&apos;re worth: And other myths of the modern economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jake</forename><surname>Rosenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The economic impact of access to public four-year colleges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joshua</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Hurwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Firming up inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jae</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fatih</forename><surname>Guvenen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Till</forename><surname>Von</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wachter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly journal of economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0033-5533</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Job market signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Spence</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sieve, incubator, temple, hub: Empirical and theoretical advances in the sociology of higher education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mitchell L Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Arum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev.soc.34.040507.134737</idno>
		<idno>doi: 10.1146/annurev.soc.34.040507.134737</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.soc.34.040507.134737" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0360-0572</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">7 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The theory of&quot; screening,&quot; education, and the distribution of income</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Stiglitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American economic review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Accidental Equalizer: How Luck Determines Pay after College</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jessi</forename><surname>Streib</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Talk of class: The discursive repertoires of white working-and uppermiddle-class college students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jenny</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stuber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="318" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inside the college gates: How class and culture matter in higher education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jenny</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stuber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Lexington Books</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social stratification at the top rung: Classed reports of students&apos; social experiences on a selective university campus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Megan</forename><surname>Thiele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brian</forename><forename type="middle">Joseph</forename><surname>Gillespie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Perspectives</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0731-1214</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Post-baccalaureate wage growth within four years of graduation: The e!ects of college quality and college major</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Liang</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Higher Education</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0361-0365</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="459" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Generating inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Thurow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Relational inequalities: An organizational approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Donald</forename><surname>Tomaskovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-Devey</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dustin</forename><surname>Robert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Avent-</forename><surname>Holt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Race and the accumulation of human capital across the career: A theoretical model and fixed-e!ects application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Donald</forename><surname>Tomaskovic-Devey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Melvin</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kecia</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9602</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Which company employs the most college graduates in your state?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bill</forename><surname>Townsend</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">8 2023. 98</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do some occupations pay more than others? social closure and earnings inequality in the united states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kim A Weeden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9602</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The three worlds of inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Weeden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Grusky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Sociology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9602</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1723" to="1785" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inequality and market failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Weeden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Grusky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Behavioral Scientist</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-7642</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="491" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Job turf or variety: Task structure as a source of organizational inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nathan</forename><surname>Wilmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administrative Science Quarterly</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0001-8392</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1018" to="1057" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consolidated advantage: new organizational dynamics of wage inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nathan</forename><surname>Wilmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Clem</forename><surname>Aeppli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0003-1224</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1100" to="1130" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matching training and jobs: The fit between vocational education and employment in the german labour market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arne</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Witte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kalleberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Sociological Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1468-2672</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The earnings payo! from attending a selective college</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dirk</forename><surname>Witteveen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Attewell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science Research</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0049-089X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neighborhood e!ects in temporal perspective: The impact of long-term exposure to concentrated disadvantage on high school graduation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Geo!rey T Wodtke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Felix</forename><surname>Harding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Elwert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American sociological review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0003-1224</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="736" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Does quality pay?: Benefits of attending a high-cost, prestigious college</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Liang</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The returns to college admission for academically marginal students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Seth</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zimmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0734-306X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="711" to="754" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
