<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Systematic review: The reliability of indicators that may differentiate between suicidal, homicidal, and accidental sharp force wounds</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jason</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
							<email>jason.chin@anu.edu.au</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stephanie</forename><surname>Clayton</surname></persName>
							<email>stephanie.clayton1@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><surname>Cordner</surname></persName>
							<email>stephen.cordner@vifm.org</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bethany</forename><surname>Growns</surname></persName>
							<email>bethany.growns@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kylie</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
							<email>kylie.hunter@sydney.edu.au</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>ORCID</roleName><forename type="first">Kristy</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Martire</surname></persName>
							<email>k.martire@unsw.edu.au</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gianni</forename><surname>Ribeiro</surname></persName>
							<email>gianni.riberio@unisq.edu.au</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stephanie</forename><surname>Summerby</surname></persName>
							<email>stephanie.summersby@police.vic.gov.au</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Law</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>5 Fellows Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>2601</postCode>
									<settlement>Acton</settlement>
									<region>ACT</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Law &amp; Justice</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Psychology, Speech, and Hearing</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">National Health and Medical Research Council Clinical Trials Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep4">School of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep5">Criminology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">New South Wales Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">The Victorian Institute of Forensic Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University of New South Wales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">University of Sydney Bernard</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit6">University of New South Wales</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit7">University of Southern Queensland</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Systematic review: The reliability of indicators that may differentiate between suicidal, homicidal, and accidental sharp force wounds</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4C2D087B449591F0DA62A67BC620DD51</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>sharp force wound</term>
					<term>sharp force injury</term>
					<term>sharp force fatality</term>
					<term>manner of death</term>
					<term>forensic pathology</term>
					<term>homicide</term>
					<term>suicide</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This protocol aims to address two metaresearch questions: what do we know about the science underlying impactful legal decisions and how can we assess this evidence efficiently and accurately, such that it is usable for courts? To do so, this protocol describes our plan for a systematic review of the literature underlying whether there are reliable indicators of the manner of death in stab wound cases. Evidence of nature was recently found admissible at the High Court of Australia in Lang v The Queen. However, despite the High Court uncritically accepting this evidence, there has never been a systematic review that critically appraises the relevant literature. Beyond the review itself, we will fully document our process and all of the timesaving tools we rely on to provide knowledge about whether systematic reviews of this nature can be efficiently deployed in legal proceedings.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rationale</head><p>This systematic review will identify and synthesise research that examines indicators that may be used to distinguish between suicidal and homicidal sharp force wounds (e.g., presence of defensive injuries, anatomical site of the wound). <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">1</ref> It will also preliminarily assess the quality of this research. Although our search strategy (see below) is focused on homicidal and suicidal wounds, we will also include literature we find about fatal accidental sharp force wounds and cases where the manner of death was undetermined. We do this to provide a more complete resource for users.</p><p>We have undertaken this review in response to expert opinion evidence admitted in a murder trial (R v Lang), where a forensic pathologist opined that a stab wound to the torso was more likely homicide than suicide. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">2</ref> The testimony and several factors advanced in favour of the opinion were supported by oral references to experience and research. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">3</ref> This review is an attempt to determine what support there is in the biomedical research literature for the expert opinion in Lang regarding factors that may reliably distinguish between stab wounds that are self-inflicted or inflicted by others.</p><p>Moreover, the broader question of whether admissible expert opinion is supported by mainstream biomedical research might cast light on admissibility rules and legal practice. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">1</ref> 'Commonly used characteristics for differentiation between self-inflicted and third-party-inflicted injuries are the anatomical site, the number and arrangement of injuries, damage of clothing, the presence of hesitation or defense wounds, and the direction of the stabbing wound canal.': Julia Schädler et al, 'Singular stab wounds to the trunk: Is this suicidal or homicidal?' (2024) 68 Legal Medicine 102430. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">2</ref> Lang v The Queen [2023] HCA 29. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">3</ref> Ibid [21], [456], [466].</p><p>Specifically, there are ongoing discussions about whether forensic pathologists and medical examiners should be permitted to provide manner of death conclusions for legal proceedings (as opposed to only making such conclusions for statistical purposes, which has not attracted critique). <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">4</ref> In short, external commentators <ref type="bibr">5</ref> and forensic professionals <ref type="bibr">6</ref> have argued that manner of death determinations, in many cases, are not reliable enough to be presented in court. Some have also argued that these determinations go beyond the expertise of forensic medical practitioners and encroach on the role of the judge or jury (i.e., the factfinder). <ref type="bibr">7</ref> Therefore, a systematic review evaluating the research basis for manner of death determinations in sharp force wound cases may provide broader insights into the risks and benefits of forensic pathology in the legal system. As we discuss below, existing systematic reviews on this topic made no attempt to assess the quality of the underlying research. <ref type="bibr">8</ref> Finally, we aim to provide practical guidance about conducting systematic reviews for legal proceedings. To help assess the practicality of such work, we will conduct this review with time-saving tools and carefully document the time this review takes, as well as any hurdles we encounter. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">9</ref> Indeed, and as discussed below, previous reviews in forensic pathology have noted challenges in reviewing the literature due to a lack of guidance 10 and reporting standards. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">11</ref> Prior reviews of research on manner of death in sharp force injury cases Preliminary searches found two systematic reviews of the relevant literature (Appendix A). First, De-Giorgio and colleagues performed a systematic review that included 78 articles (672 cases) describing purported suicidal sharp force injuries and 52 articles (2,670 cases) describing purported homicidal sharp force injuries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">12</ref> Their review covered both English and non-English language articles. The review authors noted their efforts to review the literature were hindered by poor reporting: the data available in the literature are often not detailed, clear, or homogenous enough to perform a meaningful comparison between different studies. Thus, it was not possible to identify one or more parameters that are sufficient for making an absolute differential diagnosis between suicide and homicide.' <ref type="bibr">13</ref> For example, only about a fifth of the cases provided the localisation of the injuries and their number. <ref type="bibr">14</ref> While De-Giorgio and colleagues were critical of the reporting of the articles included in their sample, they did not comment on other aspects that may increase risk of bias. For instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">9</ref> Justin Clark et al 'A full systematic review was completed in 2 weeks using automation tools: a case study' (2020) 121 Journal of Clinical Epidemiology 81. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">10</ref> Cordner et al (n 8). <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">11</ref> Fabio De-Giogio et al, 'Suicidal or Homicidal Sharp Force Injuries? A Review and Critical Analysis of the Heterogeneity in the Forensic Literature' (2015) 60(S1) Journal of Forensic Sciences S97, S105: 'Nevertheless, the data available in the literature are often not detailed, clear, or homogenous enough to perform a meaningful comparison between different studies. Thus, it was not possible to identify one or more parameters that are sufficient for making an absolute differential diagnosis between suicide and homicide.'. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">12</ref> Ibid. <ref type="bibr">13</ref> Ibid S105. 14 Ibid S100. they did not scrutinise or themselves provide any detail about how the manner of death was determined in the included cases (e.g., through eyewitness accounts, video footage). Considering that they set out to provide a critical analysis of the literature, this was surprising.</p><p>The second review is a scoping review performed by AlGheryafi and colleagues. <ref type="bibr">15</ref> This review included six studies because, unlike Di-Giorgio et al, it included only retrospective studies (excluding case reports and case series). This review also set out to be a critical review <ref type="bibr">16</ref> but did not appraise the methodology of included studies. Its conclusions about indicators of suicidal versus homicidal sharp force wounds were:</p><p>According to the results, these parameters ranged from being strongly predictive to less predictive, and no single parameter was conclusive in differentiating suicide from homicide. Some of the important predictors of the homicidal manner of death in sharp-force fatalities include clothing damage, presence of defense injuries, presence of injuries caused by another type of violence other than sharp-force, vertically oriented chest stabs, and sharp-force injuries in the head and back anatomical sites. Some of the important predictors of the suicidal manner of death in sharp-force fatalities include the presence of tentative injuries, sharp-force injuries to the wrist, and the presence of a suicide note […] the findings related to individual parameters should be integrated with findings related to other parameters and collectively the manner of death should be determined for a more accurate diagnosis of the manner of death. <ref type="bibr">17</ref> AlGheryafi and colleagues listed some limitations. <ref type="bibr">18</ref> This included heterogeneity in the included cases (i.e., variance in their factual circumstances) and the restrictiveness of their own search strategy.</p><p>19 15 Zainab Fathi AlGheryafi et al, 'Differentiating suicide from homicide in sharp-force fatalities with stab and/or incised wounds: A scoping review' (2024) 67 Legal Medicine 102388. 16 Ibid 3. 17 Ibid 8 [emphasis added]. 18 Ibid 8. 19 Ibid 8.</p><p>Both previous reviews were helpful in allowing us to identify a variety of research relevant to our research question (see Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). They include a spread of article types (case studies, case series, retrospective studies). These articles helped us develop our methodology, as described below.</p><p>Table 1. Known articles Authors Year Title Type Note AlGheryafi et al 2024 Differentiating suicide from homicide in sharp-force fatalities with stab and/or incised wounds: A scoping review Scoping review Not to be included in eventual review, but title includes useful keywords Brunel et al 2010 Homicidal and suicidal sharp force fatalities: Autopsy parameters in relation to the manner of death Retrospective study De-Giorgio et al 2015 Suicidal or homicidal sharp force injuries? A review and critical analysis of the heterogeneity in the forensic literature Systematic review Not to be included in eventual review, but title includes useful keywords Di Nunno 2001 Suicide by hara-kiri: a series of four cases Case series Ito et al 2009 Traumatic ventricular septal defect following a stab wound to the chest Case study Karlsson 1998 Homicidal and suicidal sharp force fatalities in Stockholm, Sweden. Orientation of entrance wounds in stabs gives information in the classification Retrospective study Racette et al 2008 Suicidal and homicidal sharp force injury: a 5-year retrospective comparative study of hesitation marks and defense wounds Retrospective study Schädler et al 2024 Singular stab wounds to the trunk: Is this suicidal or homicidal? Retrospective study Scolan et al 2004 Homicide-Suicide by Stabbing Study Over 10 Years in the Toulouse Region Retrospective study Terranova et al 2020 Criminological and Medico-legal Aspects in Homicidal and Suicidal Sharp Force Fatalities Retrospective study Thomsen et al 2020 Sharp Force Homicide in Denmark 1992-2016 Retrospective study Von linde et al 2024 A Swedish nationwide forensic study of the manner of death in single stab injuries to the trunk Retrospective study See Appendix B for full citations to these articles Objectives Our primary objective is to systematically review and critically appraise the literature identifying indicators of fatal self versus other-inflicted (i.e., suicidal versus homicidal) sharp force wounds (including stabbed and incised wounds). If there is literature regarding accidental sharp force wounds, we will also include that research. Secondarily, we will describe other aspects of this literature, such as the proportion of case reports following reporting guidelines (e.g., CARE)<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">foot_1</ref> and the proportion of studies that are open access.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overview of methodology and description of preliminary searches</head><p>We identified two prior systematic reviews (those reviewed above). These reviews helped reveal further articles within the present review's scope (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). We used these articles to refine the search strategy described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transparency of this review</head><p>The final version of this protocol will be prospectively registered on the Open Science Framework (link: XXX). Our PRISMA-P checklist is openly available (<ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/efhzn">https://osf.io/efhzn</ref>). Any data we extract from articles will also made openly available on the Open Science Framework (<ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/">https://osf.io</ref>). Deviations from this protocol will be explicitly acknowledged in the final manuscript. We did not seek ethics board approval because this is a review of existing research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Eligibility criteria</head><p>Inclusion criteria: We will include case studies, case series, and retrospective studies of participants of any age and sex. The primary outcome of interest is whether the fatal wound(s) was or were inflicted by the person themself (i.e., suicidal), another party (i.e., homicidal), or by accident. As a result, we will only include articles that record a fatal outcome in which a determination of manner of death was attempted. We will also only include cases in which the cause of death appears to be a sharp force wound (including stabbed and incised injuries). We will not restrict based on date.</p><p>Exclusion criteria: We will exclude non-English language articles due to a lack of non-English language proficiency among the review team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Search strategy and information sources</head><p>Review author JC designed the search strategy and will perform the search (Appendix A).</p><p>We will search MEDLINE via Ovid, Scopus, and Web of Science with no date restriction. We will record the date of the search. JC will perform backwards and forwards citation analysis using SpiderCite (<ref type="url" target="https://sr-accelerator.com/#/help/spidercite">https://sr-accelerator.com/#/help/spidercite</ref>). For articles that SpiderCite is not able to search, we will generate those citations manually. JC will also deduplicate the result using Endnote.</p><p>The search string was generated using reference articles from preliminary searches (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>) and the search strings of two prior systematic reviews (see Appendix A). An information specialist (KH) and subject matter specialists (BI, SC) helped in the design of the search.</p><p>In terms of grey literature, the authors will contact the mailing lists for the U.S. National</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Association of Medical Examiners and the Medicolegal Death Investigation Subcommittee of the</head><p>Organization of Scientific Area Committees (OSAC) for Forensic Science.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study records</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Selection process</head><p>Search results (title and abstract) will be screened for eligibility by two authors independently. One review author (JC) will retrieve full-text articles. Two authors will screen full texts for inclusion. The forward and backwards citation search will be screened by one author (JC). Discrepancies will be recorded and resolved through discussion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Article variables -general</head><p>• Full name of corresponding author</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">• DOI • Article title • Year of publication • Journal title</formula><p>• Country of corresponding author</p><p>• Email address of the corresponding author</p><p>• Affiliations of all authors (e.g., university, law enforcement) -select all that apply</p><p>• Type of article (case study, case series, retrospective study, systematic review)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Article variables -transparency and openness</head><p>• Data available and, if so, where?</p><p>• Code available and, if so, where?</p><p>• Prospectively registered and if so where?</p><p>• Purports to follow a reporting guideline (e.g., CARE)?</p><p>• Open access with publisher (gold open access)?</p><p>• Open access elsewhere (i.e., green open access) (e.g., ResearchGate)?</p><p>• Funding sources declared or no statement</p><p>• Conflicts of interest declared or no statement Case(s) -Background variables • Number of cases • Date or date range of included cases (or for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Geographic location of cases (as specific as possible, City, State, Nation)</p><p>• Reported gender/sex of deceased (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Age of deceased (for each case if reported indivdually)</p><p>• Was there a formal recording of the death scene by a forensic pathologist or medical examiner? (for each case if reported indivdually)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case(s) -Focal Injury/Injuries</head><p>• Number of wounds</p><p>• Type of wound (for each wound)</p><p>o If bone or cartilage wounds, method of determining this (visual, VT, Xray)</p><p>• Site of wound (for each wound)</p><p>• Orientation of wound (for each wound)</p><p>• Severity of wound (for each wound)</p><p>o Using Injury severity score</p><p>• Track marks within single wound? (for each wound)</p><p>• Turn and reinsertion? (for each wound)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case(s) -Other injury/injuries (number, location, healing/fresh)</head><p>• Hesitation/tentative injuries and description (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Defensive injuries and description (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Bruises and description (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Lacerations and description (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Abrasions and description (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Other (e.g., post mortem injuries, associated injuries, including petechiae in neck compression cases which might have occurred alongside the sharp force injury)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case(s) -Other variables</head><p>• Toxicology (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Psychiatric history, including source of history (e.g., deceased's general practitioner) (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Other pre-existing illnesses (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Damage to clothing (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Suicide note (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>• Weapon found (for each case if reported individually)</p><p>o Weapon type (if found)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk of Bias</head><p>• Risk of bias will be assessed as described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overall quality of evidence</head><p>• Overall quality of evidence will be assessed as described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes and prioritization</head><p>The primary outcome we will assess is the conclusion that the fatal wound(s) were homicidal or suicidal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data synthesis -Exploratory</head><p>We will attempt to quantitively synthesise cases by first separating them into four groups:</p><p>those classified by study authors as suicides, homicides, accidents or inconclusives. <ref type="bibr">21</ref> Then, we will list the frequency with which the case variables listed above appear in each group. If we calculate a percentage for that variable, we will calculate that against the number of cases in which the authors specifically stated whether the variable was measured (e.g., the proportion of suicides with positive toxicology results will be calculated only on cases where it is explicitly stated that toxicology was taken). We may also provide separate tables for studies with high versus low risk of bias. The quantitative synthesis should be considered exploratory.</p><p>We will also perform article-level quantitative summaries, such as the frequency and percentage of that articles that are open access. For quantitative syntheses, we may apply a measure of uncertainty, such as confidence intervals.</p><p>Again, any conclusions drawn from this synthesis should be treated with caution and considered exploratory. This is because there is no existing guidance on meta-analysis for the type of research included in this review. Much of our analysis will be contingent on the data we can extract and the quality of that data, both of which are difficult to forecast.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk of bias assessment -exploratory</head><p>We will adapt existing risk-of-bias tools <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">22</ref> used for assessing medical interventions because we are not aware of any tools designed for forensic pathology. Indeed, in an earlier systematic review of the suicidal strangulation literature, Cordner and colleagues remarked on this lacuna: 'As far as we are aware there is no critical appraisal instrument available to determine the quality of a medico-legal death investigation as presented in a case report'. <ref type="bibr">23</ref> To begin to develop such an instrument, we identified three items from Cochrane's risk of bias approach and tool, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">24</ref> and will adapted them. However, we may also develop other methods once we have read and reviewed the literature we identify.</p><p>First, we can adapt two sources of bias from Cochrane's 'information bias' 25 category.</p><p>Cochrane notes that information biases (also referred to as measurement bias) can occur when intervention:</p><p>cases may be more likely than controls to recall potentially important events or report exposure to risk factors they believe to be responsible for their disease. Differential misclassification of intervention status can occur in cohort studies if it is obtained retrospectively. This can happen if information (or availability of information) on intervention status is influenced by outcomes: for example a cohort study in elderly people in which the outcome is dementia, and participants' recall of past intervention status at study inception was affected by pre-existing mild cognitive impairment. <ref type="bibr">26</ref> In manner of death cases, some indicators may be recorded differently or only be recorded in cases where homicide or suicide is expected. Accordingly, studies should take steps to engage in some blinding or systematization when recording indicators of homicide or suicide (e.g., an author unaware of the determination is in charge of collecting and quantifying information about the number of wounds and their severity or there are standard items to record).</p><p>Another source of information bias is bias in the measurement of the outcome. For instance, there is a risk of circularity: indicators manners of death are taken to be reliable because they were used to determine manner of death in included cases. As a result, some independent and relatively objective assessment of ground truth is preferable. A priori, we can only speculate as to the safeguards studies may put into place. Therefore, bias in the measurement of the outcome will be done after assessing the included studies. Before fully viewing the literature, we can speculate that risk of bias may vary, with some cases including very clear manners of death (e.g., the deceased is found in a room locked from the inside or the death is veiwed by several eyewitnesses) or very unclear manners of death (e.g., the manner of death is determined based on the same indicators recorded in the case).</p><p>Note that in their systematic review of shaken baby research, Lynøe et al used a similar approach:</p><p>Studies were assessed as having a low risk of bias when the study cases, namely shaken babies, were unequivocally confirmed as having been violently shaken and when the shaking preceded the symptoms associated with the triad, for example by a video recording or independent witness information.</p><p>[…] Studies were assessed as having a moderate risk of bias when the shaken baby study cases were identified as the result of a detailed confession by the suspected perpetrator… 27 27 Lynøe et al (n 8) 23.</p><p>Finally, both observational studies and randomised trials are at risk of reporting biases. <ref type="bibr">28</ref> For instance, Cochrane notes that 'it is difficult to imagine that [reporting biases] are any less serious' 29 for observational studies because many observational studies 'do not have written protocols, and many are exploratory so -by design -involve inspecting many associations between intervention and outcome'. <ref type="bibr">30</ref> A major way in which reporting biases are assessed is considering 'Whether the trial was analysed in accordance with a pre-specified plan that was finalized before unblinded outcome data were available for analysis'. Accordingly, when available, we will record any divergences between pre-specified plans and the ultimate reporting.</p><p>If the prespecified plan is not available, we will note this. We will also note whether articles purported to follow a reporting guideline (e.g., CARE).</p><p>To summarise, we will assess:</p><p>• Blinding</p><p>• Ground truth assessment</p><p>• Methods to control reporting biases Using our assessment on those three criteria, we will provide a holistic risk of bias judgment for each article based on the levels of risk of bias in ROBINS-I. <ref type="bibr">31</ref> Once again, given the lack of work in this area, this should be considered exploratory. Two members of the review teams will make these assessments independently, with disagreements adjudicated by discussion.</p><p>28 Ibid 25-2-4. 29 Ibid 25-2-4. 30 Ibid 25-2-4. 31 Sterne et al (n 22). These are helpful, but appear to be missing some notation (quotation marks and parentheses).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>This review's search strategy</head><p>We combined many of the terms in these searches with keywords identified in our reference set using the WordFreq tool (<ref type="url" target="https://sr-accelerator.com/#/wordfreq">https://sr-accelerator.com/#/wordfreq</ref>). We refined the search string using the SearchRefinery tool (<ref type="url" target="https://sr-accelerator.com/#/searchrefinery">https://sr-accelerator.com/#/searchrefinery</ref>), which helps identify terms that increase the total number of search results without finding relevant citations. The result of the process is the following search string (PubMed): This results in 1587 total PubMed results on September 27, 2024, finding 10/10 reference articles.</p><p>We will search MEDLINE via Ovid, Scopus, and Web of Science. Those strings have been generated based the above PubMed string using Polyglot (<ref type="url" target="https://sr-accelerator.com/#/polyglot">https://sr-accelerator.com/#/polyglot</ref>): MEDLINE via Ovid (suicid*.tw. OR "self harm*".ti. OR "self inflict*".ti. OR "self injury".ti. OR herself.tw. OR himself.tw. OR homicid*.tw. OR murder*.tw. OR kill.ti. OR manner.ti. OR assault.tw. OR</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Homicides(</head><figDesc>stab wound* OR stab injur* OR cut wound* OR cut injur* OR sharp injur* OR sharp wound* AND murder) OR (stab wound* OR stab injur* OR cut wound* OR cut injur* OR sharp injur* OR sharp wound* AND murder*) OR (stab wound* OR stab injur* OR cut wound* OR cut injur* OR sharp injur* OR sharp wound* AND homicid*)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>(</head><figDesc>suicid*[tiab] OR "self harm*"[ti] OR "self inflict*"[ti] OR "self injury"[ti] OR herself[tiab] OR himself[tiab] OR homicid*[tiab] OR murder*[tiab] OR kill[ti] OR manner[ti] OR assault[tiab] OR accident*[tiab]) AND ("sharp force"[tiab] OR "sharp wound*"[tiab] OR "sharp injur*"[tiab] OR "sharp weapon"[ti] OR stab[tiab] OR "stab wound*"[tiab] OR stabbing[tiab] OR stabbed[tiab] OR "stab injur*"[tiab] OR "cut wound*"[tiab] OR cutting[ti] OR "cut injur*"[tiab] OR incis*[ti] OR knife[ti] OR scalpel[ti])</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Note that such practices vary by jurisdiction.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="20" xml:id="foot_1"><p>https://www.care-statement.org/.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="21" xml:id="foot_2"><p>See Table5in Thore Karlsson, 'Homicidal and suicidal sharp force fatalities in Stockholm, Sweden. Orientation of entrance wounds in stabs gives information in the classification' (1998) 93 Forensic Science International 21, 28.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>Thank you to <rs type="person">Justin Clark</rs> for providing methodological guidance.</p></div>
			</div>
			
			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>declare no funding sources.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data management</head><p>We will use Endnote to manage the library of articles. Data will be extracted into spreadsheets, which will be made openly available on the Open Science Framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data collection process</head><p>A standardised form (initially piloted on five included studies) will be used for data extraction of characteristics of studies, key variables, outcomes, and risk of bias. Two review authors will independently extract and code these items, with discrepancies recorded and resolved through discussion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data items</head><p>We will record the following variables. Article-level variables will be recorded using a Google form. Case-level variables will be recorded in spreadsheets (one spreadsheet for case studies and one spreadsheet for articles describing multiple cases).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Confidence in cumulative evidence -exploratory</head><p>We will adapt GRADE (Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation) <ref type="bibr">32</ref> to provide an estimate of the general level of confidence in the evidence that there are reliable indicators of suicidal and homicidal sharp force wounds. GRADE consists of five factors: limits in study design or execution (risk of bias), inconsistency of results, indirectness of evidence, imprecision, and publication bias. Not all of these factors are applicable or will be easy to estimate concerning our research question and literature. However, we will be able to provide an assessment of the following factors:</p><p>• Study design by appraising the included studies as a whole by providing a holistic synthesis of the individual risk of bias assessments of included studies.</p><p>• Imprecision by considering the total number of included cases and associated measures of uncertainty (e.g., confidence intervals).</p><p>Two review authors will make these determinations independently and resolve disagreements through discussion. As with risk of bias, our confidence in cumulative evidence assessment should be considered exploratory due to the lack of existing guidance and protocols for this determination in forensic pathology. We will also provide comments and discussion about any other overall strengths and limits in the found literature. <ref type="bibr">32</ref> Gordon Guyatt et al, 'GRADE guidelines: 1. Introduction -GRADE evidence profiles and summary of findings tables' (2011) 64 Journal of Clinical Epidemiology 383.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Background on search strategy development</head><p>This appendix provides some background on how we developed our search strategy. In particular, we built off the strategies used by two previous systematic reviews: AlGheryafi  This returns 25 articles as of July 24, 2024 (consistent with their reporting of 23) and catches 5/10 of the reference articles in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. A major limitation is the lack of root expanders (e.g., substituting stab wound* for stab wounds would catch an additional article) and a lack of the term 'manner'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>De-Giorgio et al</head><p>De-Giorgio et al conducted two searches (in Medline), one for homicides and one for suicides. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Suicides</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimizing Error and Bias in Death Investigations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dan</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Seton Hall Law Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ending Manner-of-Death Testimony and Other Opinion Determinations of Crime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Keith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dean</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Findley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Strang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Duquesne Law Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognitive Bias in Medicolegal Death Investigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">William</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academic Forensic Pathology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">552</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>it is a matter of weighing information for which there may not be much certainty</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>William R Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manner Determination in Forensic Pathology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Academic Forensic Pathology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Findley and Strang</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suicidal ligature strangulation: a systematic review of the published literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><surname>Cordner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Forensic Science, Medicine and Pathology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1023</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Systematic reviews that seek to appraise quality As far as we are aware there is no critical appraisal instrument available to determine the quality of a medico-legal death investigation as presented in a case report.&apos;; However, we are aware of one attempt to adapt an existing appraisal tool: Niels Lynøe et al, &apos;Insufficient evidence for &apos;shaken baby syndrome&apos; -a systematic review&apos; (2017) 106 Acta Paediatrica</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RoB 2: a revised tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Ac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sterne</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ l</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">4898</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ROBINS-I: a tool for assessing risk of bias in non-randomised studies of interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Ac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sterne</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cordner et al</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">130</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 4919</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>BMJ i</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions (version 6,3</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Julian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Higgins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://training.cochrane.org/handbook.25Ibid25-2.26Ibid25-" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-02-03">2023. 2-3</date>
			<publisher>Cochrane</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">(&quot;sharp force&quot;) OR TITLE-ABS(&quot;sharp wound*&quot;) OR TITLE-ABS(&quot;sharp injur*&quot;) OR TITLE(&quot;sharp weapon&quot;) OR TITLE-ABS(stab) OR TITLE-ABS(&quot;stab wound*&quot;) OR TITLE-ABS(stabbing) OR TITLE-ABS(stabbed) OR TITLE-ABS(&quot;stab injur*&quot;) OR TITLE-ABS(&quot;cut wound*&quot;) OR TITLE(cutting) OR TITLE-ABS(&quot;cut injur*&quot;) OR TITLE(incis*) OR TITLE(knife) OR TITLE(scalpel)) Web of Science ((TI=suicid* OR AB=suicid*) OR TI=&quot;self harm*&quot; OR TI=&quot;self inflict*&quot; OR TI=</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>TITLE-ABS(assault) OR TITLE-ABS(accident*)) AND (TITLE-ABS</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>tw. OR &quot;sharp injur* tw. OR &quot;sharp weapon&quot;.ti. OR stab.tw. OR &quot;stab wound*&quot;.tw. OR stabbing.tw. OR stabbed.tw. OR &quot;stab injur*&quot;.tw. OR &quot;cut wound*&quot;.tw. OR cutting.ti. OR &quot;cut injur*&quot;.tw. OR incis AND (&quot;sharp force&quot;.tw. OR &quot;sharp wound* *.ti. OR knife.ti. OR scalpel.ti.) Scopus (TITLE-ABS(suicid*) OR TITLE(&quot;self harm*&quot;) OR TITLE(&quot;self inflict*&quot;) OR TITLE(&quot;self injury&quot;) OR TITLE-ABS(herself) OR TITLE-ABS(himself) OR TITLE-ABS(homicid*)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differentiating suicide from homicide in sharp-force fatalities with stab and/or incised wounds: A scoping review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zainab</forename><surname>Fathi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Algheryafi</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Legal Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102388</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homicidal and suicidal sharp force fatalities: Autopsy parameters in relation to the manner of death</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christophe</forename><surname>Brunel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Forensic Science International</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">150</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suicidal or Homicidal Sharp Force Injuries? A Review and Critical Analysis of the Heterogeneity in the Forensic Literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fabio</forename><surname>De-Giogio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Forensic Sciences S</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suicide by Hara-kiri</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nunzio</forename><surname>Di</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nunno</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Journal of Forensic Medicine and Pathology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Traumatic ventricular septal defect following a stab wound to the chest</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hideki</forename><surname>Ito</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">General Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homicidal and suicidal sharp force fatalities in Stockholm, Sweden. Orientation of entrance wounds in stabs gives information in the classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thore</forename><surname>Karlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Forensic Science International</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suicidal and homicidal sharp force injury: a 5-year retrospective comparative study of hesitation marks and defense wounds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stéphanie</forename><surname>Racette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Forensic Science, Medicine, and Pathology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Singular stab wounds to the trunk: Is this suicidal or homicidal?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julia</forename><surname>Schädler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Legal Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102430</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homicide-Suicide by Stabbing Study Over 10 Years in the Toulouse Region</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>V Scolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Journal of Forensic Medicine and Pathology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Criminological and Medico-legal Aspects in Homicidal and Suicidal Sharp Force Fatalities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cladio</forename><surname>Terranova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Forensic Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1184</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sharp Force Homicide in Denmark 1992-2016</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Asser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Thomsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Forensic Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Swedish nationwide forensic study of the manner of death in single stab injuries to the trunk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Berg Von Linde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Forensic Science International</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">111910</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
