<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Rights, Capabilities, and Critical Pedagogy: Assessing Empowerment in INGO-led Non-formal Education for Refugees &amp; Migrants in Libya</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Waed</forename><surname>Altireeki</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Political and International Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leeds</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Leeds</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Rights, Capabilities, and Critical Pedagogy: Assessing Empowerment in INGO-led Non-formal Education for Refugees &amp; Migrants in Libya</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D10A204AE3FB63C14E8091E92BE04DD2</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T14:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Education in Emergencies</term>
					<term>Refugee education</term>
					<term>Mixed Migration</term>
					<term>Capabilities</term>
					<term>quality education</term>
					<term>Empowerment prolonged stays in transit countries (GGH-EiE, n.d.</term>
					<term>UNESCO, 2019b</term>
					<term>MMC, 2024a</term>
					<term>2024c)</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study investigates how INGO-led NFE programmes for children and youth on the move seek to empower learners amid the complexities of mixed migration. It takes Libya as a case study, given its position as a central route to the Mediterranean and its high influx of refugees and migrants. The study proposes an integrated conceptual lens-combining the 4As rightsbased framework, the capability approach, and critical pedagogy-to examine the empowering dimensions within INGO practices. Based on qualitative interviews with 12 staff from five INGOs, findings reaffirm critiques of Education in Emergencies' short-term approach, highlighting its emphasis on provision over impact. Education's empowering potential is found to be constrained by the absence of progressive learning pathways and the limited efforts to enhance learners' agency.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>While education has long been enshrined as a fundamental right in international treaties and reasserted through the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs)-particularly SDG4 <ref type="bibr">(UNESCO, 2019a;</ref><ref type="bibr">2019b)</ref>, it remains an unfulfilled promise for many children and young people caught in the uncertainties of mixed migration 1 (Geneva Global Hub for Education in Emergencies <ref type="bibr">[GGH-EiE]</ref>, n.d.; <ref type="bibr">UNESCO, 2019b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mixed Migration Centre [MMC], 2024b;</ref><ref type="bibr">2024c)</ref>. The magnitude of people moving through mixed migration flows-especially children-highlights the urgent need to examine how education systems respond to their rights and needs. UNHCR (2025c) reports over 123 million forcibly displaced people worldwide, including more than 45 million children. In parallel, the number of international migrants has risen to over 281 million <ref type="bibr">(IOM, 2024)</ref> with mid-2024 figures from the Migration Data <ref type="bibr">Portal (2025)</ref> showing a total of 304 million. However, data on children and young people in irregular migration remains difficult to capture due to the informal and often undocumented nature of such movements. Nevertheless, the increasing number of children-reported as 28 million in 2020 (IOM, 2024)-arriving in destination countries highlights their growing significance within global mobility <ref type="bibr">(UNESCO, 2019b;</ref><ref type="bibr">IOM, 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">MMC, 2025)</ref>.</p><p>Whether people move to escape conflict or persecution, or to pursue better economic opportunities, their journeys are often non-linear, involving irregular routes and multiple border crossings (UNHCR UK, n.d.; <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sharpe, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">MMC, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr">MDP, 2022)</ref>. This complexity is reflected in the educational experiences of children and youth, not only during their journeys but also throughout 1 There is no widely agreed definition of mixed migration; it can refer to mixed motivations for moving among individuals or the varied legal statuses within migration flows, often highlighting the complexity of population movements <ref type="bibr">(MMC, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>The aim of this research is twofold. First, it seeks to make a theoretical contribution by proposing an integrated conceptual lens-combining the rights-based approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Tomaševski, 2001)</ref>, the capability approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Sen, 1999)</ref>, and critical pedagogy <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Freire, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">hooks, 1994)</ref>. This</p><p>contribution involves exploring the conceptual intersections between the three frameworksparticularly around agency and empowerment-to propose a more coherent lens for analysing the impact of educational provision in humanitarian contexts. This analytical lens carries possibilities for reimagining NFE practice in ways that better respond to learners' realities and aspirations, while also contributing to the literature on the operationalisation of the capabilities approach in education.</p><p>Second, the research examines how INGO-led education programmes seek to empower learners in mixed migration settings, offering novel empirical insights from Libya through qualitative interviews with 12 staff from five INGOs. In doing so, it highlights the challenges embedded in the design and delivery of these programmes-as well as the structural and operational constraints facing INGOs-that weaken their potential to empower learners.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conceptual framework</head><p>While the Rights-based 4 As Framework, the Capability Approach, and Critical Pedagogy each offers distinct contributions, this analysis proposes that when these three frameworks are used in combination, they offer a more comprehensive lens to understanding what it means for education to be both transformative and rights-fulfilling. The study unpacks each of the three frameworks and synthesises the ways in which they mutually reinforce one another. To translate abstract theoretical concepts into observable elements of programme design, the study identifies indicators that reflect alignment with the empowerment dimensions demanded by the integrated conceptual framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The 4 As framework</head><p>This rights-grounded framework establishes a normative structure for the provision of the right to education. Availability, Accessibility, Acceptability, and Adaptability represent the four fundamental and interdependent conditions under which this right must be fulfilled <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Tomaševski, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tikly and</ref><ref type="bibr">Barrett, 2011, UNESCO, 2019a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Shah and Lopes Cardozo, 2019)</ref>. Each of the four dimensions carries specific implications for the design of humanitarian education programmes. Availability refers to the adequate provision of educational resources. Accessibility involves the removal of barriers-whether physical, economic, or sociocultural-that prevent learners from accessing educational activities. Acceptability focuses on the quality and cultural relevance of education, including respect for learners' dignity and values, while guaranteeing safety within the learning environment. Finally, Adaptability refers to the flexibility of educational provision to respond to learners' circumstances.</p><p>Rights to, in, and through education <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Tomaševski (2001)</ref> explains that the four As serve to fulfil rights to, in and through education.</p><p>Availability and accessibility address rights to education, while acceptability and adaptability fulfil rights in education. Directly linked to the focus of this study, adaptability fulfils rights through education-where education's empowering potential lies.</p><p>However, although Tomaševski does not present any of the four elements as standalone or more significant, availability is often prioritised in humanitarian settings, justified by the imperative to ensure rapid access <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Mustafa, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Shah and Lopes Cardozo, 2019)</ref>. The study argues that such prioritisation risks weakening education's acceptability and adaptability and the mechanisms through which they are implemented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A social justice response to rights-based gaps</head><p>The top-down orientation commonly adopted by EiE interventions <ref type="bibr">(Novelli and Kutan, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr">ElAsad, 2025)</ref> could mirror the dynamics through which human rights were originally formulated, often at a high international level, and thus at risk of remaining disconnected from the lived realities of politically marginalised communities <ref type="bibr">(Robeyns, 2006b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tikly and Barret, 2011)</ref>. To address this limitation, scholars like <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tikly and Barrett (2011)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Shah and Lopes Cardozo (2019)</ref> argue that the rights-based approach should be supplemented with a social justice perspective.</p><p>Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Thorsen (2020)</ref> argues that the social justice lens helps inform education in migration settings because it encourages looking beyond basic enrolment to understand how migration, gender, class, and ethnicity shape educational opportunities, constraints, and empowerment.</p><p>Building on this, this study undertakes such an integration by drawing on the capability approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Sen, 1999)</ref>-particularly for its emphasis on agency, voice, and contextual relevance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The capability approach</head><p>The capability approach views freedom as both the means and the end of development <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Sen, 1999)</ref>.</p><p>At its core are the interrelated concepts of functionings, capabilities, resources, and unfreedoms.</p><p>Functionings refer to the actual achievements or states of being-such as being literate.</p><p>Capabilities, on the other hand, represent the real opportunities or freedoms individuals have to attain those functionings-often not explicitly measurable or visible. Resources constitute the means-such as income, services, or institutional support-through which individuals may pursue valued functionings. In contrast, unfreedoms refer to constraints that prevent individuals from living a life they value while also limiting their ability to convert resources and capabilities-such as that of education-into desired achievements and capabilities. It encompasses various barriers, including economic disparities, social inequalities, and structural constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Saito, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Robeyns, 2006a;</ref><ref type="bibr">2006b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tikly and Barrett, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Buzzelli, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Aoun Barakat et al., 2025)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Synergies between the capabilities and rights-based approaches</head><p>Both the capability approach and the rights-based approach are grounded in a commitment to human dignity and a multifaceted understanding of development. While the rights-based approach frames individuals as rights-holders entitled to legal and moral claims <ref type="bibr">(Tomasevki, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Robeyns, 2006b)</ref>, the capability approach emphasises the real freedoms people have to achieve well-being focusing on agency and dignity <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Sen, 1999)</ref>. Both share a multifaceted view of developmentencompassing economic, social, and political dimensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Sen, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Tomaševski, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Robeyns, 2006b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tikly and Barret, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">UNESCO, 2019a)</ref>. The rights-based approach focuses on securing education rights (to, in, and through education), while the Capability Approach complements this by assessing how these rights translate into meaningful opportunities and functionings <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Shah and Lopes Cardozo, 2019)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Capabilities and education</head><p>Although Sen did not explicitly develop the capability approach in relation to education, he recognised education as a capability in its own right and as a vital expander of other capabilities.</p><p>The approach recognises education's intrinsic and instrumental value, acknowledging both the importance of education for skill development and the role it plays in fostering a deep understanding of the world, cultivating freedom, reasoning, and meaningful relationships <ref type="bibr">(Robeyns, 2006b;</ref><ref type="bibr">UNESCO, 2003)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Addressing critiques of the capability approach</head><p>While I argue that the openness of the capability approach-particularly not defining a list of essential capabilities <ref type="bibr">(Robeyns, 2006b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tikly and Barret, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Trezi, 2014)</ref>-is strategically important to maintain contextual sensitivity. I argue that the openness of this approach presents a limitation-specifically, the absence of ethical grounds to govern the use of capabilities. This is one reason why this research combines the capability approach with the rights-based approach, which, despite its own limitations, offers a legal and moral reference for exercising freedom. This critical reflection was inspired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Saito (2003)</ref>, who argued that education should teach values to guide the exercise of capabilities.</p><p>Additionally, a central debate in the capability approach concerns how the expansion of capabilities is reflected in empirical indicators, and whether measurement should focus on capabilities or functionings <ref type="bibr">(Robeyns, 2006a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tikly and Barrett, 2011)</ref>. Nonetheless, I would argue that the primary concern should not be the outcomes measurement per se, but rather the extent to which education programmes align with the principles of agency and freedom. Cary Buzzelli's interpretation of the capability approach in early education reinforces this perspective: 'When education enhances freedom and agency it allows for expanded capabilities in the future' <ref type="bibr">(2015, p. 207)</ref>. Therefore, this study focuses on identifying indicators within INGO education programming that reflect alignment with the capability approach. The emphasis is on how to achieve empowerment through education, rather than on measuring programme outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Deepening acceptability and adaptability</head><p>By centring agency and relevance, this approach supports recognising the forms of knowledge, skills, and learning most relevant to their lived realities. In this way, it is useful in identifying critical gaps in acceptability and adaptability dimensions within humanitarian education interventions, such as weaknesses in community engagement and participation.</p><p>A central alignment indicator with the capability approach is the (1) meaningful community participation throughout the lifecycle of education projects, facilitated through structured channels that ensure relevance and timely adaptation to learners' evolving needs. This includes shaping content, modalities, and outcomes, and informing the programme's strategies and theory of change. In parallel, to reflect accountability and a genuine commitment to respecting the agency and dignity of the people served, this participation should be accompanied by (2) structured mechanisms through which learners and their caregivers can voice feedback and satisfaction regarding the educational experiences. Their satisfaction with the relevance of the programmes to their needs and aspirations should be an indicator of the effectiveness of these programmes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Holistic perspective</head><p>Sen asserts that 'Development consists of the removal of various types of unfreedoms that leave people with little choice and little opportunity of exercising their reasoned agency' <ref type="bibr">(Sen, 1999, p. xii)</ref>. This perspective shifts the focus from merely equalising provision-availability within the four As framework-to the need to interrogate and address the constraints that hinder learners from utilising education to achieve valued functionings and capabilities. This perspective points to a critical aspect: the heterogeneity of learners. In Sen's terms, individuals have different capability sets based on personal characteristics-conversion factors-such as gender, disability, ethnicity, and shaped by broader social power dynamics and structural inequalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Walker, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tikly and Barrett, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Buzzelli, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Aoun Barakat et al., 2025)</ref>.</p><p>Building on this, the perspective of unfreedoms can be applied to interrogate the barriers to achieving empowerment through INGO-led NFE in two key ways: first, by interrogating how NFE programmes engage with conversion factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Walker, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tikly and Barrett, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Buzzelli, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Aoun Barakat et al., 2025)</ref>; and second, by applying the concept of unfreedoms to examine the structural and institutional constraints imposed on INGOs that undermine their efforts to empower learners.</p><p>A humanitarian education programme aligned with the capability approach would reflect its holistic nature by (3) identifying and addressing these conversion factors. This could be reflected in the proactive integration of complementary services-either internally at the INGO level or externally through coordination and partnerships with other actors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Critical pedagogy</head><p>Critical pedagogy positions learning as a means for emancipation and social transformation. This emancipatory aim is pursued by cultivating critical consciousness-an awareness of social, political, and economic injustices and one's position within these structures-and linking this awareness to praxis-understood as reflective and transformative action, thereby enhancing learners' agency <ref type="bibr">(hooks, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Thomas, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Biesta, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Luter et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Magee, A. and Pherali, T. , 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cubeddu and Mangone, 2024)</ref>.</p><p>The methods central to this approach focus on making education a collaborative work, where students are viewed as active participants in knowledge production rather than passive recipients <ref type="bibr">(hooks, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Thomas, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Biesta, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Luter et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Magee, A. and Pherali, T. , 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cubeddu and Mangone, 2024)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Synergies between the capability approach and critical pedagogy</head><p>Synergies between the capability approach and critical pedagogy emerge from their shared goal of advancing freedom and social justice. Empirical applications of critical pedagogy in educational programmes reveal strong synergies with the capability approach, offering meaningful routes for its operationalisation through pedagogy. For example, outcomes from the Community as Classroom programme-a Freirean-inspired academic support programme implemented at a K-8</p><p>school in an under-resourced neighbourhood in Buffalo, New York-demonstrate increased learner engagement, not only in heightened awareness of social and environmental issues within their communities but also through fostering agency and collective action to address such problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Luter et al., 2017)</ref>. Notably, participation in this project correlated with measurable improvements in academic outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Luter et al., 2017)</ref>. These findings align education's dual role: as intrinsically valuable in expanding individuals' capacity for critical reflection and agency, and as instrumentally valuable in improving outcomes such as academic achievement and skill development <ref type="bibr">(UNESCO, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Robeyns, 2006a)</ref>.</p><p>To align with critical pedagogy, NFE programmes should create spaces for learners to critically reflect on their lived experiences-such as displacement, legal status, marginalisation, or limited access to rights-and actively take a role in shaping their educational experiences. Such alignment could be observed in the (4) use of problem-posing and dialogue-based methods, alongside (5) participatory approaches that involve learners in shaping the content. These practices align with the adaptability and acceptability of the rights-based approach, as they respond to the specific needs and priorities of affected populations. At the same time, they reinforce the capability approach by enhancing learners' agency and the relevance of education. Alignment with critical pedagogy could also be evident when programmes link critical awareness with meaningful action, for instance, through student-led projects or community-based learning initiatives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Educators' role</head><p>Building on Friere's foundation, bell hooks' highlights in her concept of Engaged Pedagogy educators' central role in fostering critical reflection and awareness-not only in their students, but also within themselves. hooks argues that an educator's wellbeing, including their pursuit of self-actualisation and personal growth, is essential to fulfilling their role <ref type="bibr">(hooks, 1994)</ref>. In humanitarian contexts, teachers may be affected by displacement, insecurity, or other forms of hardship, which can impact their wellbeing and, in turn, their ability to support their learners.</p><p>Therefore, the analysis will consider the different challenges and the internal working conditions that may challenge teachers in enacting their pedagogical roles. In doing so, the analysis will also explore the extent to which INGOs offer support to teachers. Such support can include (6) institutional support for teachers' wellbeing, professional development opportunities, and efforts to raise awareness about the importance of holistic care.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conceptualising the empowerment space</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> illustrates the interconnections between the three frameworks discussed in this section.</p><p>Acceptability and adaptability are central to fulfilling rights in and through education, representing the empowerment space within the rights-based approach. Extended by the capability approach, empowerment-capability expansion-can occur both through skill development and the cultivation of critical reasoning and freedom.</p><p>On the skill development side, rights in education are essential to ensuring that education is of quality and relevance to learners' language, cultures, needs, values, and aspirations. Crucially, such relevance cannot be realised without meaningful community participation. This relevance also strengthens the agency of learners and the broader population served, allowing them to act as agents shaping their own educational experiences. Finally, as indicated earlier, the cultivation of critical consciousness and agency through critical pedagogy further enhances academic outcomes, which in turn reinforces skill development. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methodology</head><p>The study employs a qualitative approach to examine how INGO NFE programmes act to empower learners within mixed migration flows. Firstly, the theoretical section of the research explores the empowerment dimensions embedded within the rights-based approach and the capability approach, and as operationalised by critical pedagogies. Secondly, the empirical component of the research consisted of 12 semi-structured interviews with staff from five INGOs implementing education programmes for children and youth within mixed migration flows in Libya. Participants held a range of technical, managerial, and field-based roles (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p><p>Purposive sampling was used to select participants with firsthand experience designing, managing, or implementing NFE activities. Effort was made to include diverse perspectives across international and local staff, a range of organisational roles, and varied operational areas within Libya, allowing for a broader understanding of practices across different organisational contexts.</p><p>All interviews were conducted via Microsoft Teams between 13 June and 20 June 2025 in Arabic or English depending on participants' preference. Interviews lasted between one and one and a half hours. All interviews were audio-recorded with consent, transcribed using Microsoft Teams and supplemented by manual transcription. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings</head><p>In exploring the research questions, seven themes were identified from the empirical data collected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Populations served</head><p>The responses reflected an operational adoption of a refugee-migrant distinction as it is commonly applied within humanitarian practice in Libya. In the absence of a formal asylum system, respondents often referred to individuals originating from countries listed by UNHCR as experiencing conflict or persecution-such as Sudan, Syria, Eritrea, and Somalia-as 'refugees', regardless of their actual legal status or documentation. Conversely, individuals from other countries within the broader mixed migration flows were generally referred to as migrants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Unfreedoms and conversion factors</head><p>The distinction within mixed migration populations includes the degree of empathy extended towards different groups, reflecting differentiated experiences of unfreedoms.</p><p>Respondents consistently noted that refugees and migrants of Arab origin receive more empathy from both host communities and authorities. This distinction in empathy has implications for access to essential services provided by the government and by humanitarian actors, including access to education-formal and non-formal.</p><p>A secondary differentiation layer concerns migration aspirations. Some refugees and migrants view Libya as a place to settle and integrate-often engaging in informal work and establishing a degree of stability-while others see it as a transit point, staying temporarily to secure funds for onward movement to Europe. These differing aspirations shape how families decide to invest in education and how they navigate access to it. While more settled families may enrol children in private, community-run schools or INGO-run NFE programmes, newly arrived or those in transit often lack the financial means or the stability to do so.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Goals of NFE programmes</head><p>INGO staff narratives emphasise that the primary goal of their programmes is to uphold the right to education, while providing protection and safeguarding to children who otherwise 'will be on the streets, begging, stealing, exploited.' (Interviewee1). However, the narratives reflect not only the lifesaving value of EiE in humanitarian settings but also its long-term, capability-expanding function-aligning with Sen's capability approach. Education was framed as enabling autonomy and future agency, equipping children and youth with capabilities that would serve them regardless of where their futures unfold. Interviewee9:</p><p>It's empowerment for them, for the children. Even if they don't stay in Libya for long, it's for their future. Whether they return home or reach another country, they carry that knowledge with them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Access vs Impact</head><p>Although programme narratives suggest an intention to promote the rights to, in, and through education, the findings reveal notable gaps in the alignment with the acceptability and adaptability dimensions through which rights in and through education should be realised in practice <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Tomaševski, 2001)</ref>.</p><p>The narratives notably highlight a stronger focus on increasing access and enrolment in NFE compared to attention to its acceptability and adaptability. Yet persistent gaps in availability and accessibility continue to undermine the realisation of rights in and through education. A disconnect between needs-persistent barriers to education-and INGOs' temporary non-formal education interventions is underscored by respondents who explained that after completing a short coursetypically two weeks to a few months, with one INGO offering access for up to a year-participants become ineligible as programmes shift to new 'unique beneficiaries.' This approach was largely attributed to donor pressures with only one actor reported flexibility in enrolment by their donors.</p><p>The implications of this approach for capability expansion are observed in two ways: it limits learners' ability to develop skills progressively and limits learners' and caregivers' decisionmaking power to pursue further educational levels, undermining empowerment through the cultivation of agency. We can say we provided supplementary education or catch-up activities to this beneficiary, but we're basically rushing through everything. We're rushing to meet deadlines and meet indicator targets, not necessarily focusing on real learning impact. (Interviewee12) It's just such a short period of time. You try to at least teach them the Arabic alphabet and how to make words, like first graders. The teachers make a great effort, but once they feel they will fulfil the objective, that's it. We end with them and bring in a new group. We don't take them to level 2 or 3 or 4. After six weeks, we move on, this is the policy. (Interviewee8)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Agency restriction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I see that at the end of each cycle when the children get sad because they think it's something wrong they did that is stopping the cycle. (Interviewee1)</head><p>We have some parents, they ask for more, for example my child has been coming here, you have taught him a lot and why don't they continue taking them because they haven't been accepted in schools yet. (Interviewee8)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Language of numbers</head><p>Another implication of higher focus on increasing numbers of children and youth reached with NFE is creating a culture of numbers and quantitative indicators that ultimately sidelines the overarching goal of making transformative impacts-in favour of meeting donor requirements.</p><p>Notably, this donor-implementer relationship was replicated between INGOs and their local implementing partners, reinforcing upward reporting. Interviewee7: Sometimes they don't care. They care about the figures, the numbers, …that there are these number of migrants in needs when they have to use in in <ref type="bibr">[sic]</ref> speech or whatever. In contrast, one example that stood out was a basic literacy and numeracy programme offering one year of progressive learning, demonstrating greater impact, not limited to literacy and numeracy but also social skills. Interviewee6:</p><p>We felt the impact through the appreciation expressed by parents and the visible improvements in the children. This impact isn't just educational…, it also affects the child's social development. The children were able to integrate into the school environment, make friends, and become part of a community. This had a broader positive impact on the students, their sense of belonging, their mindset, and even their outlook on the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Rights in and through education</head><p>The narratives highlight INGOs' efforts to improve the acceptability and adaptability of education, particularly their focus on enhancing teaching quality. Examples include the recognition and response to learners' psychological needs-particularly through efforts to create safe learning environments and provide psychosocial support-alongside attempts to address language barriers. However, INGOs' efforts to ensure acceptability and adaptability are not underpinned by robust participatory mechanisms throughout the educational experience. As the findings indicate, these programmes lack structured involvement of learners and caregivers through all stages of the project life cycle. Interviewees indicate that cultural sensitivity is often mediated through teachers' personal capacities over structured community consultation mechanisms. This was highlighted by Interviewee6 who stated,' the success of these efforts depends heavily on the capacity of the volunteers.' While communities are often involved in initial needs assessments during the project initiation phase, this early engagement is unsustained in subsequent project phases. During the planning phase, community participation is largely confined to caregiver induction sessions, with limited consultation on logistical matters such as activity scheduling, and, in some cases, input on selecting from a set of pre-defined life skills topics.</p><p>The implementation and monitoring phases lack structured and consistent mechanisms for participants to voice their evolving needs or provide real-time feedback-aside from the general Complaint and Feedback Mechanisms (CFMs) established at the organisational level. However, despite the presence of CFMs, the feedback that is gathered generally influences future initiatives instead of adjusting current interventions. This is particularly problematic given that children and youth are often not targeted with further services once they are no longer classified as 'unique beneficiaries.' Interviewee12:</p><p>At the beginning of the cycle, we do a session for our beneficiaries and introduce the specific approach of cycle for them and what's the followed curriculum exactly and the timeline for the cycle, the session takes about 2-3 hours, and in about 4 weeks we do an evaluation session with the parents to hear their feedback in order to improve our implementation in the next cycle.</p><p>In the evaluation phase, success is typically measured through short-term, quantifiable indicators aligned with donor commitments. In contrast, less emphasis is placed on participants' satisfaction. This suggests accountability is primarily directed toward donors over the people served.</p><p>Furthermore, the prevailing exclusionary reporting practices weaken the efficiency of existing feedback mechanisms; once learners are deemed 'reached' and no longer eligible for further NFE, they have little incentive to offer genuine feedback to improve services from which they no longer benefit.</p><p>Notably, stronger alignment with the principles of adaptability and acceptability was evident in interventions with increased participation and agency of local education providers through partnerships, where they had more agency in decision-making and planning. These collaborations supported existing educational structures, strengthening what already exists instead of operating in isolation. Such partnerships often bore fruit in the form of pathways to accredit children's learning, thereby enhancing its potential for recognition and transferability. Interviewee5:</p><p>Our clearest successes were <ref type="bibr">[sic]</ref> in the remedial education program. Around 90% of those who participated were able to obtain a certificate of completion for their educational level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Empowerment through critical pedagogies</head><p>When asked whether life skills and critical thinking sessions support learners in engaging with real-life projects that link critical reflection with action-in line with Freirean pedagogy-staff largely acknowledged that such practices are limited. While some programmes include sessions about child rights to raise awareness, it was noted that life skills sessions tend to remain more theoretical.</p><p>In relation to teachers, interviewees repeatedly highlighted challenges impacting their wellbeing, which in turn, constrain the enactment of critical pedagogies. While internal advocacy secured limited benefits-such as health insurance and paid leave in two cases-these remained exceptions. Challenges included insufficient compensation and persistent payment delays, which caused financial instability for teachers. Interviewee6:</p><p>The biggest challenge in working with volunteers is the organization's own policy regarding their engagement and management. This situation often leads to a high turnover of volunteers…, they are treated almost like full-time staff but contracted as casual workers.</p><p>Additionally, teachers often share traumas or personal hardships of migration and displacement, creating additional emotional burdens. Yet, psychological and mental health support for teachers remains limited, as do opportunities for professional development, contributing to sustained stress and burnout among educators. Interviewee12 highlighted the limited training opportunities caused by busy work schedules:</p><p>Another challenge faced by our teachers is the limited number of training opportunities we are currently able to provide. This has become especially difficult recently due to the large number of ongoing activities and the already packed schedules of the staff. It's hard to pause activities just to conduct training sessions</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Holistic Programming</head><p>A single example of integrated programming emerged where an INGO integrated vocational training and livelihoods support, supporting youth with business skills and start-up materials.</p><p>However, the majority of responses indicated that service integration was often reactive rather than proactive, occurring through referrals upon raising concerns instead of proactively integrating complementary services to address learners' broader needs. However, referral mechanisms themselves are marked by significant gaps. Interviewee6:</p><p>There's no pre-defined pathway, no established steps or designated partners to refer to. Instead, when a case arises, we scramble to figure out who can take it on, and this leads to delays and inefficiency.</p><p>INGOs with case management units demonstrated relatively stronger referral mechanisms, primarily in responding to protection needs such as psychosocial support. However, this often follows the same ad hoc approach.</p><p>At the broader humanitarian coordination level, coordination was described as fragmented despite the presence of sectoral task forces. This fragmentation was critically expressed as a hindrance to joint advocacy efforts. Interviewee7 stated, 'But we never go as a community. We are a community.</p><p>We have the same interest, we are supposed to.' Notably, although many of these INGOs were implementing projects funded by UN agencies, respondents reported receiving limited support or advocacy from those agencies, leaving them to navigate security pressures alone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Unfreedoms of INGOs</head><p>Compounding these restrictions is the persistent lack of acceptance by host communities that respondents attributed to shortcomings in community engagement strategies and the low visibility of INGOs. Interviewee2 described this as the 'number one challenge':</p><p>There have been significant social media waves and public discourse in recent months around migration issues and the reintegration of migrants. The reactions have been intense....So, I would say the number one challenge is the limited community acceptance of migrants and refugees.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>While INGOs aim to empower children and young people within mixed migration patterns by providing access to education and training, the approach through which they seek this empowerment falls short in operationalising the transformative dimensions within the intersecting frameworks of rights-based, capabilities, and critical pedagogies. INGOs mainly seek learner's empowerment through facilitating recovery from the traumas of displacement and migration. This is reflected in the integration of psychosocial support activities across all aspects of NFE programming.</p><p>In contrast, capability expansion through skill development is often narrowed by the prevalent short-term model-characterised by a focus on provision, resulting in tightly framed courses to meet large enrollment targets. This model offers limited scope for meaningful skill development, lacking gradual progression pathways. Given the persistent lack of educational alternatives for learners to transition into after completing INGO-provided NFE, the current programme model appears disconnected from the realities of the context. It delivers one-off educational support, premised on the assumption that the emergency of limited access to education is a short-term condition.</p><p>While restricted agency was mainly expressed in the limited decision-making power to pursue further levels of education, the issue is deeper. The limited community participation as well as weak downward accountability limits the ability of learners and their caregivers to shape the education they receive, rendering them passive recipients of aid rather than agents shaping how it is delivered. These gaps constrain the agency among the populations served, an outcome that works against the very aim of empowerment <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Sen, 1999)</ref>.</p><p>Capability expansion is further hindered by the limited implementation of critical pedagogies, with educators' constrained role emerging as a major gap. Drawing on the perspectives of <ref type="bibr">Freire and hooks (2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">1994)</ref>, internal INGOs challenges-such as delayed teachers' payments, lack of institutional support, and the precarious nature of teachers' contracts-create significant barriers for teachers. This reveals a fundamental disconnect in programme design: educators are tasked with fostering empowerment among learners while remaining unsupported and disempowered within the very systems they serve.</p><p>Another factor contributing to the uneven expansion of capabilities is the absence of holistic and </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>This research makes a theoretical contribution by proposing an integrated analytical lens that combines the rights-based approach, the capability approach, and critical pedagogy to examine INGOs practices. It demonstrates how these perspectives reinforce each other to deepen understanding of empowerment through education in humanitarian settings, with particular attention to acceptability and adaptability. The study highlights links between the capability approach and critical pedagogy, showing how the latter can operationalise the former by embedding agency, relevance, and critical reflection into pedagogy. This lens was applied to analyse qualitative interviews with 12 INGO education staff from five organisations delivering NFE across Libya, providing insights into how these programmes contribute to learner empowerment in ways aligned with the theoretical dimensions of empowerment.</p><p>While the narratives described INGO programmes as aiming to fulfil the three components of the right to education-rights to, in, and through education-the findings suggest limitations in the dimensions of empowerment, which undermine the fulfilment of rights through education, where the transformative potential of education lies.</p><p>INGO-led NFE programmes aim to empower learners through trauma recovery and skills development, by integrating PSS and offering education and training opportunities such as basic literacy, numeracy, vocational training, and life skills. However, these efforts are undermined by the programmes' own approach. Findings suggest a problematic prioritisation of provisionevident in high enrolment targets-at the expense of ensuring acceptability and adaptability, which are essential for genuine empowerment.</p><p>The focus on increasing enrolment was reinforced by exclusionary donor reporting mechanisms, which rendered learners ineligible for further education once they had been reported as 'unique beneficiaries'. Additionally, the lack of structured community participation throughout the project cycle restricts the space for learners to shape or influence the education they receive, thereby undermining empowerment through agency enhancement. Additionally, any capability expansion appears uneven due to insufficient attention to conversion factors, which are attributed to weak holistic programming, and limited coordination between actors. Furthermore, the cultivation of freedoms and agency through critical pedagogy is constrained by limited opportunities for reflective awareness and learner participation in co-creating knowledge, as well as by factors limiting teachers' roles, including emotional and financial burdens, lack of institutional support, and insecure contracts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research implications</head><p>The findings underscore the need for a nuanced understanding of how the dimensions of empowerment-as framed by this research's theoretical frameworks-can be embedded in NFE to align with the three components of the right to education-rights to, in, and through educationparticularly through upholding community agency and the meaningful support and enactment of teachers' roles. Additionally, donor pressures that risk shifting focus from impact to donor compliance, prompt interrogating the dynamics between donors and implementers and its implications on NFE's transformative potential. Similarly, limited acceptance by host communities invites inquiry into the social, political, and cultural factors shaping such responses.</p><p>Finally, the constrained support and coordination from UN agencies highlights the need to investigate relationships between INGOs and multilateral actors within Libya, including how shared goals are negotiated and operationalised in complex humanitarian settings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclosure statement</head><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Notes on contributor</head><p>Waed Altireeki is an education specialist with over five years of experience in the humanitarian field. Her last position was within an INGO leading education in emergencies programmes. She recently completed an MA in Global Development and Education and conducted this research as part of her dissertation. Her primary interests lie in exploring the transformative role of education across diverse contexts and philosophical perspectives.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Links between rights, capabilities, and critical pedagogy within the empowerment space.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,80.00,72.00,451.68,513.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Findings</head><label></label><figDesc>reveal a complex and often unpredictable operating environment, severely impeding INGOs' ability to deliver transformative, rights-fulfilling NFE. INGOs experience significant access restrictions and heightened scrutiny, exacerbated by ongoing political fragmentation in Libya. Since March 2025 (up to data collection in mid-June), the majority of INGOs providing aid to refugees and migrants have been suspended by authorities in the western region, who claimed that such aid encourages the settlement of irregular migrants. This suspension disrupted essential services, including education and protection.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>interdisciplinary planning within education programmes to respond to conversion factors. As a result, capability expansion through NFE becomes dependent on the existing capability sets of individual learners. The limitations in addressing conversion factors are further compounded by the fragmented coordination between actors across sectors, which weakens support services, referral pathways, and collective advocacy efforts to negotiate access to rights for refugee and migrant populations-efforts that could reduce dependency on INGO-led NFE provision. Despite these challenges, certain interventions-albeit not always embedded in systemic approachesstood out for their stronger alignment with empowerment dimensions. These include vocational training for youth that enhance employability across the formal and informal economy, literacy and numeracy classes offering year-long enrolment, and partnerships with local education providers enabling the certification of learning.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . participant profiles</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Participant ID</cell><cell>Functional Role</cell></row><row><cell>Interviewee1</cell><cell>Technical Staff</cell></row><row><cell>Interviewee2</cell><cell>Management Role</cell></row><row><cell>Interviewee3</cell><cell>Field Staff</cell></row></table><note><p>Thematic analysis was used to explore the interview narratives. Transcripts were imported into NVivo 15 and analysed using a combination of deductive and inductive coding. Deductive codes were informed by the conceptual framework and included categories such as availability, unfreedoms, agency, acceptability, capability expansion, critical pedagogies, and holistic programming. Inductive codes, by contrast, emerged organically from participants' own language and the issues they raised during interviews. These included themes such as access vs quality, and internal challenges within INGOs.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . INGO staff quotes on access vs impact Prioritisation</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>project continues</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>of availability I understand that with the with the [sic] organisation such as</p>[INGO]  </p>or any other organisation, they don't want to leave children without education. So they want to reach as many children as they can, which I understand. But at the same time, we hope that we can continue to do more, we don't stop, especially for those who were unlucky enough to be accepted [in formal education]. (Interviewee8) keeping the same student will leave us way behind in our targets, each ... so for us to reach the 4,000 we will have to reach new children or as we call them unique beneficiaries, these targets that the donors put for us, puts us in another pressure which is keep getting funded [sic] so the</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Acknowledgement My heartfelt thanks go as well to the humanitarian aid practitioners who were generous with their time, expertise, and experiences; this research would not have been possible without their invaluable contributions</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.linkedin.com/in/waad-treki/" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The use of mobile learning: a pathway towards refugees&apos; inclusion&apos;, Information Technology for Development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aoun</forename><surname>Barakat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dabbous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Accessed On</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02681102.2025.2502419</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02681102.2025.2502419" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-05-25">25 May 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Don&apos;t be fooled by ignorant schoolmasters: On the role of the teacher in emancipatory education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Biesta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1478210316681202</idno>
		<ptr target="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1478210316681202" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Policy Futures in Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-05-25">2017. 25 May 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The capabilities approach: Rethinking agency, freedom, and capital in early education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buzzelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1463949115600030</idno>
		<ptr target="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1463949115600030" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Contemporary Issues in Early Childhood</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-06-05">2015. 5 June 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="213" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Social Justice Education Approach: Towards a New Cultural Model of Education?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cubeddu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mangone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://ijse.padovauniversitypress.it/2024/1/6" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Italian Journal of Sociology of Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2024-07-21">2024. 21 July 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International Organization for Migration</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.educationcannotwait.org/sites/default/files/2022-03/21_MYRP_LIBYA_Programme%20Document_20211201.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">57_Migrant_Repo rt%20-%20Final.pdf?iframe=true Education Cannot Wait. 2021. Multi-Year Resilience Programme: Libya programme document</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Displacement Tracking Matrix (DTM)</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025-03">2025. March-April 2025. August 2025. June 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>DTM Libya Round 57 Migrant Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pedagogy of the oppressed (30th anniversary ed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Freire</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Newyork: Continuum</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Acting ahead to protect education investments</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Geneva Global Hub for Education in Emergencies</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://eiehub.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/EiE-Hub-2025-Flagship-Report-FINAL.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-08">2025. August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Children on the move: The missing piece in education in emergencies</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Geneva Global Education in Emergencies Hub</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://eiehub.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/EiE-Migration.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-05">2024. May 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">EiE and mental health and psychosocial support</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Geneva Global Education in Emergencies Hub</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://eiehub.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/EiE-MHPSS" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-08">2024. August 2025</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>pdf hooks, B. 1994. Teaching to Transgress: Education as the Practice of Freedom</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">INEE guidance note on psychosocial support</title>
		<ptr target="https://inee.org/resources/inee-guidance-note-psychosocial-support" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Network for Education in Emergencies (INEE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-08">2018. August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<ptr target="https://dtm.iom.int/terms-and-conditions" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Organization for Migration (IOM). 2025. DTM Libya migrant report</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-04-10">April 2025. 10 May 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">International Organization for Migration</title>
		<ptr target="https://mena.iom.int/sites/g/files/tmzbdl686/files/documents/2024-05/pub2023-047-l-world-migration-report-2024_1.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-08">2024. 2024. August 2025</date>
			<publisher>International Organization for Migration (IOM)</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">World Migration Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Critical consciousness and schooling: The impact of the community as a classroom program on academic indicators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Luter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Education Sciences</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcauliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Oucho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://publications.iom.int/books/world-migration-report-2024" />
		<title level="m">International Organization for Migration (IOM)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Geneva</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-08">2024. 2024. August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">World Migration Report</note>
	<note>Online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.migrationdataportal.org/themes/mixed-migration" />
		<title level="m">Migration Data Portal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-08">2022. August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International migration data: Groups overview</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Migration Data Portal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.migrationdataportal.org/international-data?i=groups&amp;t=2024" />
		<title level="m">Accessed 16</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-08">August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Understanding of mixed migration and smuggling</title>
		<ptr target="https://mixedmigration.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/MMC-understanding-of-mixed-migration-and-smuggling.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-08">August 2025</date>
			<publisher>Mixed Migration Centre</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Rethinking mixed migration: What about internal migration and displacement?</title>
		<ptr target="https://mixedmigration.org/rethinking-mixed-migration-what-about-internal-migration-and-displacement/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-08">2021. August 2025</date>
			<publisher>Mixed Migration Centre</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What changes over the course of the migration journey? Results from piloting longitudinal 4Mi</title>
		<ptr target="https://mixedmigration.org/resource/economic-lives-migrants-in-libya" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mixed Migration Centre (2024a) Crossing borders, building livelihoods: The insecure economic lives of migrants in Libya</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Mixed Migration Centre</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022-08">2022. August 2025. August 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Educational realities and needs of migrant children and youth in West and North Africa</title>
		<ptr target="https://mixedmigration.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/335_Education_children_WANA_EN.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-08">August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Mixed Migration Centre. 2024b</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixed Migration Review</title>
		<ptr target="https://mixedmigration.org/resource/quarterly-mixed-migration-update-na-q2-2025/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mixed Migration Centre (2025) Quarterly Mixed Migration Update: North Africa</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-08">2024. August 2025. 2025. August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Migration politics, migration narratives and public opinions</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Education in Emergencies: Humanitarian-Development Nexus country analysis -Final</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mustafa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Inter-Agency Network for Education in Emergencies (INEE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-10">2019. October 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Online</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://inee.org/sites/default/files/resources/EiE%20Hum" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-08">August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Dev%20Nexus%20Country%20Analysis%20-%20Final%20%28Oct%202019%29.pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Education in Emergencies&apos;: from saving souls to saving schools?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Novelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kutan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14767724.2023.2236566</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/14767724.2023.2236566" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-07-21">2024. 21 July 2025</date>
			<publisher>Globalisation, Societies and Education</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="419" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The imperial entanglements of</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Women and human development: The capability approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Nussbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://genderbudgeting.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/nussbaum_women_capabilityapproach2000.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-05">2000. May 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multi-Sector Needs Assessment (MSNA): Migrants and refugees in Libya -Education and Child Protection component</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Unhcr</forename><surname>Reach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://inee.org/sites/default/files/resources/REACH_LBY_Factsheet_Education-and-Child-Protection_LBY2105b_March_2022.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-03">2022. March 2022. August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Capability Approach in Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Robeyns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.hd-ca.org" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-07-21">2006. 21 July 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Three models of education: Rights, capabilities and human capital. Theory and Research in Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Robeyns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1477878506060683</idno>
		<ptr target="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1477878506060683" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-07-21">2006. 21 July 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="84" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Amartya Sen&apos;s Capability Approach to Education: A Critical Exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Saito</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Philosophy of Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-07-21">2003. 21 July 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-9752.3701002</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-9752.3701002" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Development as Freedom</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Achieving educational rights and justice in conflictaffected contexts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lopes Cardozo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/id/eprint/10081587/1/Shah_Article_10_Shah.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Education and Conflict Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixed up: International law and the meaning(s) of &apos;mixed migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sharpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/rsq/hdx021</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Refugee Survey Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Education in emergencies: challenges of providing education for Rohingya children living in refugee camps in Bangladesh</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M C</forename><surname>Shohel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/20004508.2020.1823121</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/20004508.2020.1823121" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-07-21">2022. 21 July 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="126" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Education Inquiry</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reframing inclusive education: educational equality as capability equality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Terzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cambridge Journal of Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="479" to="493" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-07-21">2014. 21 July 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/0305764X.2014.960911</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/0305764X.2014.960911" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Revisiting Pedagogy of the oppressed: Paulo Freire and contemporary African studies. Review of African Political Economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/27756265" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-07-21">2009. 21 July 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="269" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Independent child migration: mobilities and life course transitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Thorsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9781315276908/routledge-handbook-migration-development-tanja-bastia-ronald-skeldon</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/books/edit/10.4324/9781315276908/routledge-handbook-migration-development-tanja-bastia-ronald-skeldon" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Routledge Handbook of Migration and Development. 1st ed. Abingdon: Routledge</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bastia</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Skeldon</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-07-21">2020. 21 July 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="210" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social justice, capabilities and the quality of education in low income countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tikly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijedudev.2010.06.001.</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijedudev.2010.06.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Educational Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-07-21">2011. 21 July 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human rights obligations: Making education available, accessible, acceptable and adaptable. Right to Education Primer No. 3. Stockholm: Right to Education Project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tomaševski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.right-to-education.org/sites/right-to-education.org/files/resource-attachments/Tomasevski_Primer%203.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-06">2001. June 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A handbook on the right to education: A rights-based approach to education 2030</title>
		<ptr target="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000366556" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-06-19">2019. 19 June 2025</date>
			<publisher>UNESCO</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Global Education Monitoring Report 2019: Migration, displacement and education -Building bridges, not walls</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Paris</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>UNESCO</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019-08">2019. August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000131823" />
		<title level="m">Literacy as freedom: a UNESCO round-table</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>UNESCO</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003-08">2003. August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.unhcr.org/sites/default/files/2025-06/libya-operational-update-may-2025.pdf" />
		<title level="m">UNHCR. 2025b. Libya Operational Update</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>UNHCR</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025-05-17">May 2025. 17 August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Refugee statistics</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.unhcr.org/refugee-statistics" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-08">August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Education solutions for migrant and displaced children and their host communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Unicef N.D</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.unicef.org/media/83561/file/Education-solutions-for-migrant-and-displaced-children-and-their-host-communities.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-08">August 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is equity in education? Reflections from the capability approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Unterhalter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Studies in Philosophy and Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-07-21">2009. 21 July 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="415" to="424" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11217-009-9125-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11217-009-9125-7" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Amartya Sen&apos;s capability approach and education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09650790500200279</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/09650790500200279" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Educational Action Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-07-21">2005. 21 July 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
