<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 1 Trauma-Informed &amp; Culturally Responsive Practices for the Care and Support of Refugees: The Case of Middle East and North Africa</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Afana</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_JHYDDd3">
					<orgName type="full">of Immigrant and Minority Health</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_dmVUA8a">
					<orgName type="full">informed systems of care</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_p7WdmS6">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_nxuqgTZ #_9QEkRc7">
					<orgName type="full">CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_DPKsvun">
					<orgName type="full">Middle East</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Eid</roleName><forename type="first">Abo</forename><surname>Hamza</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">College of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Humanities, and Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Al Ain University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Al Ain</settlement>
									<country key="AE">UAE</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Mental Health Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tanta University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="EG">Egypt</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><surname>Al-Krenawi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty of Humanities</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Social Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Cross-Cultural Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Algoma University</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><surname>Elbedour</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Human Development and Psychoeducational Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Education in</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Howard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>D.C</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><surname>Hamid</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Clinical Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medicine and Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Emirates University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United Arab UAE</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><surname>Moustafa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">School of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Society and Design</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Bond University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Gold Coast</addrLine>
									<region>Queensland</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Eid</forename><forename type="middle">G Abo</forename><surname>Hamza</surname></persName>
							<email>eidhamza@edu.tanta.edu.eg</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Mental Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tanta University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tanta</settlement>
									<country key="EG">Egypt</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 1 Trauma-Informed &amp; Culturally Responsive Practices for the Care and Support of Refugees: The Case of Middle East and North Africa</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">54FEB87C10E1F24DAC4FC32CA85C8BC8</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>refugees</term>
					<term>Middle East</term>
					<term>mental health</term>
					<term>trauma-informed care</term>
					<term>trauma TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Most refugee research is done in the West. Few research focuses on refugees abroad. To fill this information vacuum, this study investigates Middle Eastern refugees' problems. Conflict and instability in the region have led to enormous numbers of refugees seeking protection in adjacent nations. Due to social isolation, lack of basic amenities, and sexual and gender-based psychological abuse, these refugees typically struggle to find relief. Trauma, separation, and loss affect many refugees' mental health.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Refugees in the Middle East face different challenges than those in the</head><p>West, but trauma-informed care should be used by care providers to improve mental health outcomes and give refugees hope and security. This study aims to define a trauma-informed treatment system for Middle Eastern clinicians to help displaced people restore self-esteem and empowerment. Our goal is to help refugees cope with the psychological and mental strains of relocation and forced migration, not physical injuries.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p>The issue of refugees cannot and should not be ignored. Their sheer numbers have the potential to destabilize governments around the region. Afghans are now living in Iran, which marks the eastern border of the Middle East.</p><p>On the northern border of the Middle East, Turkey is currently hosting almost four million refugees, with the majority being Syrian nationals <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Zaccara &amp; Conçalves, 2021)</ref>. Many of these Syrians are trying to enter the European Union, which has raised concerns about the stability of Greece, according to its prime minister <ref type="bibr">(Fargues &amp; Fandrich, 2012)</ref>. The millions of Syrians fleeing the civil war have also placed a significant social and financial burden on Lebanon, Jordan, Iraq, and, to a lesser extent, Egypt. Lebanon, already one of the poorest countries in the region, is struggling to provide basic water, sanitation, food, healthcare, housing, and electrical services to the influx of refugees. Despite dealing with internal chaos since 2019, Lebanon has recently recorded the highest per capita rate of refugees worldwide.</p><p>Further, Lebanon is currently facing a major challenge in meeting the demands on its infrastructure, as it far exceeds its capacity to meet the needs <ref type="bibr">(Ostrand, 2015, p. 262)</ref>. Similarly, Jordan is also struggling to provide necessities to approximately 0.75 million Syrian refugees <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Zaccara &amp; Conçalves, 2021)</ref>. These refugees, both registered and unregistered, make up about 10% of Jordan's population <ref type="bibr">(Al-Krenawi &amp; Bell, 2023)</ref>. Additionally, one-sixth of the Syrian refugees living outside official camps survive on less than USD 96 per month and almost half of them do not have access to</p><p>TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 7</p><p>heating. Iraq, which has nearly 2 million internally displaced people, is also hosting around a quarter million Syrian refugees, which has led to competition for resources. Egypt initially welcomed refugees, but this changed after a change in political leadership <ref type="bibr">(Ostrand, 2015)</ref>. Despite this, more than 380,000 refugees have crossed into neighboring countries, such as Egypt, South Sudan, Chad, Ethiopia, and the Central African Republic (UNHCR, 2023b).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Challenges Faced by Refugees</head><p>Refugees from the Middle East, like refugees from other parts of the world, face a range of challenges. These include a lack of access to necessities such as food, clean water, and shelter. The COVID-19 pandemic has further exacerbated the hardships experienced by refugees. This includes the suspension of travel and other services associated with seeking asylum, economic difficulties (with refugees being 60% more likely to lose their jobs or income due to COVID-19), and a higher vulnerability to disease (particularly in low-income settings where many resettled refugees live) <ref type="bibr">(Brickhill-Atkinson &amp; Hauck, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>In addition to facing challenges related to their physical well-being and health, refugees also deal with multiple mental health concerns and emotional reactions to victimization such as confusion, hopelessness, anxiety, fear, and depression. After TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 8 (PTSD) among over 5,100 refugees in 15 countries was 31.46% (95% CI 24.43-38.5). The prevalence of depression was 31.5% (95% CI 22.64-40.38), while the prevalence of anxiety disorders was 11% (95% CI 6.75-15.43). The prevalence of psychosis was 1.51% (95% CI 0.63-2.40). According to the authors, these numbers highlight the need for ongoing, long-term mental health care. Similar numbers were found in a 2009 study, which showed a prevalence rate of 30.6% for PTSD and 30.8% for depression among 82,000 refugees (Rodriguez &amp; Grumbine, 2020). Although younger age appears to serve as a protective factor against mental health crises (Al-Krenawi &amp; Bell, 2023), children and adolescent refugees are not immune. A meta-analysis of eight studies of child and adolescent refugees and asylum seekers by Bürgin (2022) indicated a 22.7% prevalence of PTSD, 13.8% of depression, and 15.8% of anxiety disorders (p. 847). According to a study carried out by Sirin and Rogers-Sirin (2015), in a Turkish refugee camp named Islahiye, 45% of Syrian refugee children experienced PTSD symptoms, 20% had clinically diagnosable levels of depression, and many experienced daily psychosomatic symptoms such as pain in the arms and legs (25%) or headaches (20%) (Hadfield et al., 2017). However, for refugees resettled in the Middle East, finding mental health care can be more challenging than for their counterparts in other parts of the world. Mental health expenditures in Arab countries, as a percentage of total government health budgets, already tend to be low: from just 2% in Syria and Egypt to 5% in Lebanon, compared to, for example, 11% in TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 9</p><p>Germany and the Netherlands <ref type="bibr">(Sijbrandij, 2017)</ref>. This suggests that it is more difficult for refugees living in the Middle East to receive the mental health care they need to manage the trauma they have experienced. In addition, many, if not most, of the refugees from Iraq and Syria do not live in refugee camps; this makes it even more challenging to provide mental health care <ref type="bibr">(Sassoon, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sijbrandij et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Apart from a lack of and limited access to mental health services, refugees from the Middle East also face some additional risks. For example, hypertension caused by increased salt intake, physical inactivity, and smoking "represents a major burden among refugees" in the Middle East <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Zibara et al., 2021)</ref>. In addition to hypertension, Syrian refugees are more afflicted by chronic and costly diseases, such as diabetes, heart disease, and cancer when compared to their refugee counterparts from Africa, who suffer more from endemic and epidemic infectious diseases and malnutrition <ref type="bibr">(El Saghir et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Two issues exacerbate the problem for Syrian refugees with cancer. First, according to a 2018 report, "only 23% of functional public hospitals in Syria provided cancer treatment services" (El Saghir, 2018, p. 434). This suggests that several Syrian refugees with cancer have not been receiving treatment. In addition, cancer patients among refugees often have poor outcomes due to "poor hygiene and living conditions, as well as the limited health education, limited access to care, and limited resources" (El Saghir, 2018, p. 434). TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 10 Based on a study conducted in Norway, oral health also appears to be of greater concern to Middle Eastern refugees, who had more extensive oral challenges than refugees from Africa (Høyvik et al., 2019). Another concern that cannot be ignored is the link between mental health and heat. In a systematic review of connections between heat and mental health outcomes, Thompson et al. (2018) established the links between high ambient temperatures and increased risk of suicide and mental-health-related admissions. In a later systematic review and metaanalysis, Liu et al. (2021) detected a positive relationship between elevated temperatures and negative mental health outcomes. In another 2021 study, researchers found that as temperatures rose above 79 degrees Fahrenheit, "activity in the parasympathetic nervous system, the anti-stress system that can help us stay calm and relaxed, was lowered" (Aubrey, 2023). Unfortunately, projections by Lelieveld et al. (2016) have suggested that heat extremes in the Middle East will accelerate with global climate change, possibly reaching 46 degrees Celsius (114.8 Fahrenheit) on the hottest days. Since Kuwait hit 53.2 degrees Celsius in 2021, making it the hottest place on the earth that year (Haddad, 2021), 46 degrees Celsius might seem like a cold front. Three other countries in the Middle East also joined the 50 degrees Celsius club in June 2021: the U.A.E., Iran, and Oman (Cappucci, 2021). The only country outside the Middle East to reach 50 degrees Celsius was Pakistan. TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 11</p><p>Negative health consequences among refugees can also be attributed to the rise in child marriages (defined as the marriage of a girl under 18) and child pregnancies. In a study on refugees conducted in Djibouti, Yemen, Lebanon, Iraq, Bangladesh, and Nepal, the average number of child marriages was found to be significantly higher among the displaced when compared to the host population <ref type="bibr">(Elnakib et al., 2023)</ref>. In Jordan, the number of females under 18, who were being impregnated, increased from 5% at the beginning of 2013 to 8.5% in 2014 <ref type="bibr">(Sahbani et al., 2016)</ref>. For the most part, researchers have agreed that child marriage is a health <ref type="bibr">(Hampton, 2010</ref><ref type="bibr">), economic (Parsons et al., 2015)</ref>, and quality of life issue <ref type="bibr">(Mim, 2017)</ref>. In particular, girls who got married below the age of 18 were found to be at an increased risk for sexually transmitted diseases <ref type="bibr">(Bartels et al., 2018</ref><ref type="bibr">), spousal violence (Mourtada et al., 2017)</ref>, "cervical cancer, malaria, death during childbirth, and obstetric fistulas," and their offspring were "at increased risk for premature birth and death as neonates, infants, or children" <ref type="bibr">(Nour, 2006</ref><ref type="bibr">(Nour, , p. 1644))</ref>. In addition, girls who married young were often prevented from receiving a proper education, thereby limiting their career potential and economic independence <ref type="bibr">(Bartels et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>While it is true that when people are hungry, thirsty, or sick, mental health is not a priority <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Wells et al., 2020)</ref>, it is also true that Middle Eastern refugees have suffered the kind of trauma that can have a negative impact.</p><p>For example, over 34% of Syrian refugees in Jordan have been separated</p><p>from a member of their family <ref type="bibr">(Al-Krenawi &amp; Bell, 2023)</ref>. Family separation</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 12</formula><p>is a major source of distress for refugees, related to depression, PTSD, and psychological quality of life. This reflects only one type of trauma in a list of 26 types covering all three measures of mental health <ref type="bibr">(Miller et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>For example, children from Syria -and other countries -might have experienced war-associated stressors, bombings, torture, poverty, and malnutrition, the adverse effects of which could last up to 9 years <ref type="bibr">(Hadfield et al., 2017)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Butler et al. (2011)</ref> estimate that between 5% and 35% of the world's refugees have been tortured.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Service Plan</head><p>Given the turbulent history of the Middle East, countries in the region likely to host refugees should make plans for future influxes of displaced persons. These plans should be guided by some form of trauma-informed mental health care, to help victims and survivors manage the psychological distress they suffer as a result of forced displacement.</p><p>Initial efforts to care for refugees must focus on providing basic services <ref type="bibr">(Bürgin et al., 2022)</ref>. These include food, shelter, water, and Regarding pre-emigration status, one study found that higher levels of education may be linked to greater mental health challenges among refugees <ref type="bibr">(Al-Krenawi &amp; Bell, 2023)</ref>. Healthcare providers also have to understand that neighbors and trusted adults before the forced relocation may have turned into enemies <ref type="bibr">(Björn &amp; Björn, 2004</ref>). An important aspect of the healing process is to support refugees in their search for meaning, in finding some purpose in their forced displacement and relocation, and in redefining themselves from victims to survivors, thereby re-establishing trust and a sense of self-coherence and control over their environment that is a crucial element of any refugee mental health plan.</p><p>While considering sub-populations, Al-Krenawi and Bell (2023) found that marital satisfaction, self-esteem, and life satisfaction were significantly TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 15 better for male Syrian refugees in Jordan than their female counterparts. The authors concluded that Syrian female refugees face unique factors that "place them at increased risk of mental health problems" (p. 714). Regarding the resettled community, researchers in Canada found that Syrian refugees were more likely to access government resources; therefore, they might not need as much incentive as other nationalities to seek care (Pandalangat &amp; Kanagaratnam, 2021). Care providers also need to honor refugee concerns about repatriation (Björn &amp; Björn, 2004). However, regional refugee programs need to be established to re-establish family reunification (Fargues &amp; Fandrich, 2012). The more family reunification refugees have, the sooner and better they cope with the posttraumatic stress of victimization. The next step towards adaptive adjustment is managing the mental health needs/stressors of individuals by implementing a TIC framework. According to the U.S. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA, 2014), "Individual trauma results from an event, series of events, or set of circumstances that is experienced by an individual as physically or emotionally harmful or life-threatening and that has lasting adverse effects on the individual's functioning and mental, physical, social, emotional, or spiritual well-being" (p. 7). SAMHSA outlines the four dimensions or Rs of TIC. Service providers must realize that there is a widespread impact of trauma on refugees and that there are different paths toward healing and recovery (Ford-Paz et al., 2021). Next, they must TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 16 recognize the signs and symptoms of trauma in both their clients and staff. Third, they must respond with policies, procedures, and practices that integrate knowledge about trauma. Finally, they must actively resist "traumatization" (Butler et al., 2011; Ford-Paz et al., 2021). As Ellis et al. (2008) have reported discrimination in host countries intensifies initial PTSD associated with war and displacement, a safe environment not only provides physical security but freedom from xenophobia and racism (Miller et al. 2019). SAMHSA (2014) goes on to recommend that TIC programs are implemented by designating a leader, screening for trauma, providing written policies that are transparent and a safe physical environment, engaging clients with peers and family members, providing culturally sensitive training to staff and partners, monitoring progress, and evaluating results. Available screening measures, such as the Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item scale, can be used to screen for trauma (Miller et al., 2019). Cultural humility or honoring the client's culture (Adams &amp; Kivlighan III, 2019; Loomis et al., 2018; Wells et al., 2020), for example, by learning about and respecting family hierarchy (Björn &amp; Björn, 2004) or by asking permission to discuss difficult subjects (Miller et al., 2019) is a highly recommended therapeutic skill. In addition, Clervil et al. (2013) note that disorders such as PTSD may be expressed differently across cultures. Without knowledge of cultural variations, professional mental health providers may miss critical information. TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 17 Adams and Kivlighan III (2019) expanded the concept of cultural knowledge by suggesting that besides cultural humility, service providers learn to take advantage of cultural opportunities: they should not miss the chance to discuss a client's cultural values. Providers also need to develop cultural comfort, which details the ease with which the therapist can engage with the culture of the client. Dorado et al. (2016) posited that the most important training when dealing with the traumatized is to get providers to ask, "What has happened to you?" instead of "What is wrong with you?" Thus, refugees need to know that traumatic reactions are normal reactions to an abnormal situation.</p><p>In addition, clinics should integrate and co-locate medical, legal, socioeconomic, and mental health services, which are culturally affirmative and holistic <ref type="bibr">(Harlow et al., 2023)</ref>. This form of muti-expert integration is easier to achieve in refugee camps, especially when large numbers of refugees make it practically impossible to deliver to individuals dispersed across urban areas.</p><p>Taking a similar approach, Im, Rodriguez, and Grumbine (2020) add that mental health service providers should make a distinction between the average traumatized individual and the relatively small percentage of refugee populations with severe problems. They also warn that service</p><p>providers need to consider linguistic problems. since some languages do not have words available for mental health diagnoses. Apart from finding ways to translate Western terms for mental health diagnoses and care, Miller et TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 18 al. (2019) noted the need to sometimes destigmatize the use of appropriate medications and cognitive behavioral therapies. In addition to the TIC practices mentioned above, Butler, Reinfrette, and Critelli (2011) emphasized the strength-based service delivery orientation and the utilization of an empowerment model that strives to maximize client choices and control of their recovery and emphasizes the client's strengths, assets, and resilience. According to the authors, choice and control for refugees may mean walk-in appointments and evening hours for mental health clinics. Cordes (2021) added that language barriers might have to be addressed by providing longer appointment times. Clervil et al. (2013) outlined a similar empowerment model to Butler, Reinfrette, and Critelli's (2011), suggesting that TIC integrates consumers' voices in treatment, identifies their strengths, and rebuilds social support systems in a safe environment. Miller et al. (2019) noted that consumers' strengths include sports, household tasks, and reading. Lack of training in culturally adaptive cognitive behavior therapy can be a barrier to serving traumatized victims (Wells et al., 2020). One effective approach to dealing with a paucity of trained service providers is to provide consultation services and recruit non-professional helpers within the community. For example, Sijbrandij et al. (2017) recommended a Problems Management Plus (PM+) intervention that can enable these helpers to develop the required skills and techniques following 10 days of training. Here, participants are taught breathing relaxation techniques and TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 19 problem-solving skills along with ways of strengthening social support, to re-engage with positive activities in individual or group settings. Individual versions are delivered over five weekly sessions of 90 minutes each for individuals or 120 minutes for groups. A pilot program in Pakistan was shown to be effective in reducing anxiety, depression, and post-traumatic stress. Group interventions for Syrian refugees were slated for Jordan and Turkey, and a smartphone-based program was set for Egypt. Not all researchers are enamored by a TIC approach. Westoby and Ingamells (2010) contend that trauma work is "overemphasized and overlegitimized" because refugees who learn that identifying themselves as traumatized can gain resources might get trapped in an approach that does not help (p. 1766). The authors added that TIC forces a "Western therapeutic model on other societies" (p. 1768). They also argued that it places heavy emphasis on individual needs. Terrana et al. (2022) provided evidence for such a viewpoint in a study on Somalis living in San Diego. The authors found that community-based interventions are more effective than individual coping mechanisms. Murray, Davidson, and Schweitzer (2010) stressed the need to develop culturally responsive intervention programs that "rely less on medical models of psychological distress that unduly emphasize stress-related trauma and more on psychosocial models that develop a sense of stability, safety, and trust" (p. 582). Westoby and Ingamells (2010) concluded: TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 20 Anthropological tradition requires that intervention programs build on local resources and strategies so that the community's existing abilities to deal with difficulties, illness, suffering, and stress are strengthened. The starting point is to establish what these resources are, identify where they have been disrupted, and facilitate the reestablishment of these resources and processes for strengthening them. (p. 1766). that shape the experiences of psychological distress as also its symptomatic expression and sequelae.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conceptualization of Trauma in the Arab</head><p>The conceptualization of trauma within the Arab world focuses solely on problems located within the individual and lacks a developed conceptual vocabulary for relational, social, communal, and cultural problems. Yet, remembering and forgetting traumatic events depends on memory systems that carve trauma not only on the body and brain but also on the social and political processes that aim to regulate public and private recollection.</p><p>Some studies have aimed to investigate PTSD solely using standardized Western-based tools. On the other hand, four studies looked at culturally relevant idioms of trauma-related distress. In these studies, "context" included both cultural and socio-ecological or structural aspects (for instance, economic, political, and gender-related aspects of living). The question explored was not the presence of symptoms or features of PTSD or other comorbid disorders, but the cultural competence in the conceptualization of such symptoms. The question was as follows: How did participants from the Arab Region make meaning of and express traumarelated distress? One study found that while there was a symptom overlap between PTSD and depression symptoms, idioms of distress were</p><p>TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 22 significantly different statistically (Rasmussen et al. 2011). Two studies included the terms feeling 'broken' ‫محطمة(‬ muḥaṭṭima) or 'destroyed' (… ‫مدمرة‬ mudammira). Feeling broken or destroyed conveys suffering in terms of a broken spirit, morale, or hopes for the future. These cultural idioms were used in response to not just traumatic exposure but also protracted violence and oppression and were validated by Barber et al. 2016. The authors explored connections among structural violence, psychological</p><p>distress, trauma exposure, and chronic non-communicable diseases. They reported that participants could not separate the social and political context responsible for their trauma, poverty, and powerlessness from their physical health. Trauma was depicted as integral to social suffering. Consequently, help-seeking was also social and communal rather than an action of an "individual." Two studies reported that Palestinian cultural idioms of trauma -"blow" (sadma ‫,)صدم‬ "tragedy" (faji'ah ‫,)فاجعة‬ "calamity" (musiba ‫,)مصيبة‬</p><p>and "catastrophe" (nakba ‫)نكبة‬ -were not always diagnostic entities requiring treatment, but rather a vocabulary through which distress is expressed and social support mobilized. While some of these idioms require professional attention, others may not. Their consequences may self-resolve or become normalized as part of the collective experience of violence and its related distress. A few studies highlighted that these distress reactions to occupation and political violence are part of an adaptive response to an extraordinary predicament. They should not be overmedicalized <ref type="bibr">(Afana et al. 2010</ref><ref type="bibr">(Afana et al. , 2020;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Barber et al. 2016b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hammad &amp; Tribe, 2020)</ref>. ……………</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 23</head><p>presented two idioms of distress: "deep sadness" (Hozun ‫)حزن‬ and "madness" (Majnun ‫,)مجنون‬ in a Darfuri sample. The two idioms included multiple symptoms. When symptoms were cross-listed against Western PTSD and depression symptoms, there was an overlap, but the differences were significant.</p><p>Studies looking at variations within the concepts of psychopathology and resilience documented interrelated themes integrating sociocultural, historical, structural, political, and, at times, religious contextual aspects.</p><p>They presented idioms of resilience such as (a) muqawam ‫مقاومة‬ / resistance to military siege and occupation; (b) awda ‫عودة‬ / return to cultural roots despite historical and ongoing settler colonialism; and (c) sumud ‫صمود‬ / perseverance through daily adversities and trauma accumulation. All these concepts are integrated within the social fabric of the context of trauma.</p><p>They are vital to the process of understanding and expressing/resolving distress. They also presented religious idioms of resilience, for example, "perseverance" (sumud ‫)صمود‬ and "surrender to God's will" (taslim ‫)تسليم‬ that attribute meaning to ongoing traumatic and violent exposure and past historical and transgenerational trauma. Such meaning-making processes contextualize trauma in a wider context and ascribe meaning to suffering.</p><p>The studies concluded that, in this context, categories of distress, for example, PTSD, do not hold much meaning. Associated symptoms are viewed as part of the overall state of being. It is important to note that in seven of these articles, traumatic exposure was not conceptualized as a TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 24</p><p>single event that posed a threat to self, but rather as an ongoing part of a local setting.</p><p>It is important to gain an understanding of Arab culture-specific expressions of distress, traditional and religious healing practices, and coping strategies. For example, there is a need for community initiatives to promote resilience and increase the use of positive coping mechanisms such as cultural, religious, and traditional healing rituals, skills, and strategies <ref type="bibr">(Al-Krenawi, 2016)</ref>. Arab clients in the mental health service may express their distress through metaphors and proverbs. Culture-specific idioms of distress and explanatory models of illness and health are crucial to understanding this process of meaning-making <ref type="bibr">(Kleinman, 1988)</ref>, as well as the considerations of social context and power structures <ref type="bibr">(Kirmayer, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>Individuals and practitioners need to co-construct a shared understanding of the focus of treatment. Among Arab persons, common idioms of distress may include the sorrow of one's whole life or being tired, an unbearable sense of pressure, or the world closing all doors on the face <ref type="bibr">(Al-Krenawi, 2000)</ref>. Somatic therapy aims to treat mental and emotional health issues through a connection among mind, body, and spirit. This body-and spiritcentric approach works by helping to release stress, tension, and trauma from the body. Unlike global mental health treatment, such as cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT), which focuses prominently on the mind, somatic therapy incorporates body-oriented modalities such as breathwork and meditation to support mental healing. In addition, somatic therapy sessions</p><p>TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 25 include healing rituals and mind-body-spirit exercises. Mental health practitioners in the primary health center should come up with cultural projects, such as embroidery, through which women can talk about their psychosocial, emotional, and familial problems. For instance, the term fadfada means the creation of a safe environment to express their emotional problems through storytelling, while working on embroidery or another cultural project. Oral storytelling is very much used and acceptable in Middle Eastern society, not just to preserve history and culture. Additionally, Arab people use storytelling as a way of coping with distress and collective trauma. Arab cultural healing practices of hikaya (oral storytelling) are used to cope with collective trauma and loss (Atallah, 2017) as well as other emotional pains and difficulties. Oral storytelling involves people sharing tales of joys, sorrows, life, and memories of sacred places, linking the past to the future; it involves people bearing witness to each other's stories in a supportive environment (Zarifi, 2015). Given the stigma attached to the mental health systems in Arab society (Fahoum &amp; Al-Krenawi, 2023), mental health workers can initiate group work in the public health center (PHC) in collaboration with the general practitioner (GP) at least in the first session. This process will provide the women with a good opportunity to speak about their emotional and familial problems using the cultural strategy of fadfada, wherein the group leader needs to bring a cultural and religious context to the group dynamic (Al-Krenawi, 1996; Banawi &amp; Stockton, 2008). As stated by the prophet Muhammad, "Those TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 26 who interact with people and tolerate their hardships are better than those who do not interact with people and do not tolerate their pains" (Mohammad, 570-622 C.E., cited in Ibn Majah, 1975). Another strategy that may be used with the Arab clients in the PHC is the photovoice strategy. As part of this intervention, patients discuss their problems as in other forms of mental wellness therapies (Wang &amp; Burris, 1994). Rather than just talking about them, somatic intervention guides patients to focus on their underlying physical sensations. It is essential to incorporate Islamic principles into the treatment of Arab individuals. Western models of treatment often refer to meditation, philosophy, and poetry to enhance well-being (Kabat-Zinn, 1990; McMahan &amp; Braun, 2017). Likewise, visualization, meditation, and mindfulness are also basic approaches constituting Islamic spirituality and wellness. Islamic ritual prayer or salah involves principles of meditation. Salah incorporates Qur'anic recitations with different physical postures, such as standing, bowing (ruku), sitting (tashahud), and prostration (sujud). Muslims are enjoined to perform salah five times a day, with each salah being divided into repeated units of prayer (rakahs) that vary slightly based on the salah being performed. The first step is to make the intention (niyah) to pray. While standing for prayer, Muslims are taught to visualize Allah in front of them and to take account of the angels who join them. To facilitate visualization, Muslims pray in the direction of the Kaaba, ending each set of rakahs by acknowledging angels, others present in the congregation, and TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 27 the one leading the prayer. Prayer rugs often contain a picture of the Kaaba to help Muslims center their intentions. The acknowledgment of the self, others who are present, and intentions to a higher deity, connect the physical, relational, and spiritual aspects of each person. Additional Islamic mindfulness practices include the use of the words in shaa Allah (God willing) as part of daily vernacular when speaking of intentions, as well as utilizing the tasbeeh or prayer beads. Other Arabic terms, such as subhan Allah (glory to God) and Alhamdulillah (praise be to God), also acknowledge and express mindfulness of self, actions, intentions, and gratitude as one engages in daily affairs. Islam's practices of ritual prayer, Qur'anic imagery, dhikr (rhythmic devotions), dua (supplication, request, gratitude, prayer), hadith (traditions and saying of the Prophet Muhammad), as well as Islamic poetry, can be used to enhance behavioral therapies, specifically, mindfulness practices and cognitive frameworks found in ACT and DBT (Ahmed &amp; Amer, 2013). In summary, it is hard to maintain a positive outlook on the future in the Middle East, especially considering how global climate change is impacting the region. Given the existing conflicts based on geography, religion, ethnicity, and politics, scarcity of water leading to food insecurity is only going to make things worse. It is difficult to be kind to others when you are hungry, thirsty, and hot. Hence, governments worldwide must plan for an influx of refugees who will cross borders in search of a better life. It TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 28 would be a smart strategy to prepare for the physical and mental health needs of refugees, should they be forcibly displaced in the future. It is the responsibility of Middle Eastern and Western governments, international organizations, civil society, and the community at large to work together to prevent the Middle Eastern refugee crisis by addressing the underlying causes of displacement. If that fails, everyone must take responsibility for providing essential services and creating a more inclusive and welcoming environment for refugees in the Middle East.</p><p>Providing food, water, and shelter for large numbers of refugees is challenging but possible. However, providing necessary mental health care is a more complex issue. Trauma often leads to negative self-images, making refugees feel helpless, frightened, and powerless. By providing trauma-informed practices that are culturally sensitive to refugees from the Middle East, we can help them regain self-coherence, self-equilibrium, strength, and a sense of control and resiliency. More research is needed, however, as refugee studies are still relatively unfamiliar to Middle East area specialists <ref type="bibr">(Fábos, 2015)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>This study highlights the substantial beneficial effects of group </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>According to Iranian authorities, around one million refugees have crossed the border from Afghanistan since the Taliban regained control in the late summer of 2021. The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) reports that over 3.6 million documented and undocumented TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 6</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>reviewing numerous studies published between 2003 and 2020, Blackmore et al. (2020) concluded that the prevalence of post-traumatic stress disorder</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>security. The latter two deserve special mention. Given the consequences of global climate change and the lack of water in several parts of the Middle East, having enough water for simple hydration, let alone cooking and cleaning, is a matter of basic survival as well as mental health. Current findings related to the relationship between hydration status and cognitive performance and mood "suggest that particular cognitive abilities and mood TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 13 states are positively influenced by water consumption" (Masento, 2014, p.1841).Refugees' mindsets are often consumed by fear, danger, and insecurity. Thus, safety is an essential component of the healing process for refugees. Further, avoiding re-traumatization is an integral aspect of trauma-informed care (TIC). Post-emigration violence/abuse can exacerbate mental health problems. As young women raped in post-emigration settings are often unable to find suitable husbands, their guardians may seek to marry them off as soon as possible. Child brides are also motivated by a desire to escape poor family conditions or feelings of confinement(Bartels   et al., 2018). Although logistically it is easier to get services to refugees in camps rather than to those integrated into communities(Ostrand, 2015), refugees in camps are placed at greater risk for poor sanitary conditions, lack of privacy, and intense heat(Shearlaw, 2013). As a compromise solution,Bartels et al. (2018)  suggested the creation of a "safe place," a location where girls and their families can find security. Sponsored by NGOs, these centers can also raise awareness about sexual and reproductive health and autonomy.Due to forced displacement, refugees are likely to perceive that they are socially isolated. Therefore, once the basic needs of the refugees are met, host countries can begin to look at various forms of community support to invalidate the victim's assumption that the world is now a threatening place(Bürgin et al., 2022; Im et al., 2020). For example, athletic fields can TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 14 be created for both physical and mental health. Schools can also be established, although instructors need to recognize that trauma can impair cognitive development and create challenges for displaced youth(Hadfield   et al., 2017).Once service providers have a handle on necessities and have created spaces for the community's mental health, they can focus on the mental health needs of the community and individuals by becoming informed about their pre-emigration status, their lives while on the run (the loss of their homes; treatment of sub-populations, such as women and children; and separation of families), and the "resettled community"(Pandalangat &amp;   Kanagaratnam, 2021).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>Word: Implications for Practice with Refugees in the Middle East A large body of literature uses Western-based diagnostic frameworks (for example, the International Classification of Diseases: ICD-11 or the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual: DSM-5) and tools to assess for universal symptoms and expression of PTSD. A growing yet confined body of literature is questioning the appropriateness of such frameworks and tools to conceptualize the etiology and the phenomenology of traumatic stress for Arab refugees or in other non-Western contexts. The decontextualization of traumatic experiences from cultural contexts results in a limited and categorical understanding of traumatic distress across the world (Kleinman, 1987). The literature often includes a set of pre-determined assumptions defined by Western psychiatric nosology of a traumatic event as a single event or a string of single events that happen to a single individual, ignoring a wider understanding of how TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 21trauma is experienced across diverse communities and cultures. Given the fluid use of the term 'culture', it is important to note that the term 'cultural' is deeply intertwined with several social factors (for example, socioeconomic conditions, gender, generation gaps, and political settings)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc>counselling on emotional regulation, self-esteem, stress management, and assertiveness among female refugees who have experienced Sexual and Gender-Based Violence (SGBV). The results of our research highlight the crucial importance of employing counselling methods that are culturally TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 29 sensitive and trauma-informed when addressing the distinct difficulties experienced by female refugees from various cultural backgrounds. The study highlights the significance of group counselling that combines selfcentered rational emotive behavioural therapy and art therapy in improving self-awareness, emotional effectiveness, and overall psychological wellbeing among this vulnerable population. The study's results emphasize the need for more focused and comprehensive support networks for female refugees experiencing SGBV, promoting the wider adoption of such programs in comparable situations. The findings have significant consequences, underscoring the necessity of ongoing advocacy, policy formulation, and allocation of resources to promote the mental well-being and successful integration of refugees, especially women, into host communities. Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration ICD-11: International Classification of Diseases, 11th Revision</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head></div>
<div><head>Not applicable</head></div>
<div><head>References</head><p><rs type="person">Afana</rs>, <rs type="person">A. J.</rs>, <rs type="person">Tremblay</rs>, <rs type="person">J.</rs>, <rs type="person">Ghannam</rs>, <rs type="person">J.</rs>, Ronsbo, H., &amp; Veronese G. (2020).</p><p>Coping with trauma and adversity among <rs type="projectName">Palestinians in the Gaza Strip: A qualitative, culture-informed analysis. Journal of Health Psychology</rs>, 25(12), 2031-2048. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1359105318785697">https://doi.org/10.1177/1359105318785697</ref> TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; <rs type="funder">CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">AND SUPPORT 31</rs> <rs type="funder">Afana</rs>, A. H., <rs type="person">Duncan P</rs>., Rønsbo, H., &amp; Kirmayer, L. J. (2010). Endurance is to be shown at the first blow: Social representations and reactions to traumatic experiences in the Gaza Strip. Traumatology, 16(4), <rs type="person">73-84. Barber</rs>, <rs type="person">B. K.</rs>, <rs type="person">McNeely</rs>, <rs type="person">C. A.</rs>, <rs type="person">Sarraj</rs>, <rs type="person">E. E.</rs>, <rs type="person">Daher</rs>, <rs type="person">M.</rs>, <rs type="person">Giacaman</rs>, <rs type="person">R.</rs>, Arafat, <rs type="person">C.</rs>, <rs type="person">Barnes</rs>, W., &amp; Mallouh, M. A. (2016). Mental suffering in protracted political conflict: Feeling broken or destroyed. PLoS One, 11(5), Article e0156216. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0156216">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0156216</ref> Al-Krenawi, A. (In Progress). Syrian Refugees in Jordan and Mental Health: Challenges and Culturally Sensitive Practice. <rs type="person">Brill Publisher</rs>. Al-Krenawi, A., &amp; Bell, M. M. (2023). Gender differences in Syrian refugees in Jordan: Psychological, self-esteem, family function, marital satisfaction, and life satisfaction. International Journal of Social Psychiatry, 69(3), 714-723. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1177/00207640221140286">https://doi.org/10.1177/00207640221140286</ref> Aratani, L. (2019, June 27). 'I feel lucky': Millions have fled war-torn Yemen -the U.S. has accepted 50. The Guardian (Manchester, England). <ref type="url" target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jun/27/yemen-refugees-usa-">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jun/27/yemen-refugees-usa-</ref>trump-asylum Aubrey, A. (2023, July 31). Yes, heat can affect your brain and mood. Here's why. MPR News. <ref type="url" target="https://www.mprnews.org/story/2023/07/31/npr-heat-">https://www.mprnews.org/story/2023/07/31/npr-heat-</ref>wave-brain-mood-anxiety Bartels, <rs type="person">S. A.</rs>, <rs type="person">Michael</rs>, <rs type="person">S.</rs>, <rs type="person">Roupetz</rs>, <rs type="person">S.</rs>, <rs type="person">Garbern</rs>, <rs type="person">S.</rs>, <rs type="person">Kilzar</rs>, <rs type="person">L.</rs>, <rs type="person">Bergquist</rs>, <rs type="person">H.</rs>, <rs type="person">Bakhache</rs>, <rs type="person">N.</rs>, <rs type="person">Davison</rs>, <rs type="person">C.</rs>, &amp; <rs type="person">Bunting</rs>, A. (2018). Making sense of TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; <rs type="affiliation">CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT</rs> 32 child, early and forced marriage among Syrian refugee girls: A mixed methods study in Lebanon. BMJ Global Health, 3(1), Article e000509. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2017-000509">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2017-000509</ref> Blackmore, <rs type="person">R.</rs>, <rs type="person">Boyle</rs>, <rs type="person">J. A.</rs>, <rs type="person">Fazel</rs>, <rs type="person">M.</rs>, <rs type="person">Ranasinha</rs>, <rs type="person">S.</rs>, <rs type="person">Gray</rs>, <rs type="person">K. M.</rs>, <rs type="person">Fitzgerald</rs>, <rs type="person">G.</rs>, <rs type="person">Misso</rs>, M., &amp; <rs type="person">Gibson-Helm</rs>, M. (2020). The prevalence of mental illness in refugees and asylum seekers: A systematic review and metaanalysis. PLoS Medicine, 17(9), Article e1003337. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1003337">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1003337</ref> Björn, G. J., &amp; Björn, Å. (2004). Ethical aspects when treating traumatized refugee children and their families. Nordic Journal of Psychiatry, 58, 193-198. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1080/08039480410006223">https://doi.org/10.1080/08039480410006223</ref> Brickhill-Atkinson, M., &amp; Hauck, F. R. (2021). Impact of COVID-19 on resettled refugees. Primary Care, 48(1), 57-66. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pop.2020.10.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pop.2020.10.001</ref> Bürgin, <rs type="person">D.</rs>, <rs type="person">Anagnostopoulos</rs>, <rs type="person">D.</rs>, Board and <rs type="institution">Policy Division of ESCAP</rs>, <rs type="person">Vitiello</rs>, <rs type="person">B.</rs>, <rs type="person">Sukale</rs>, <rs type="person">T.</rs>, <rs type="person">Schmid</rs>, M., &amp; Fegert, J. M. (2022). Impact of war and forced displacement on children's mental health-multilevel, needs-oriented, and trauma-informed approaches. European Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, 31(6), 845-853. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00787-022-01974-z">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00787-022-01974-z</ref> Butler, L. D., Rinfrette, E. S., &amp; Critelli, F. M. (2011). Trauma-informed care and mental health. Directions in Psychiatry, 31, 197-210. TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 33 Cappucci, M. (2021, June 7) Record heat bakes Middle East as temperatures top 125 degrees. The Washington Post. <ref type="url" target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/weather/2021/06/07/record-june-">https://www.washingtonpost.com/weather/2021/06/07/record-june-</ref>heat-wave-middle-east/ Clervil, R., Guarino, K., DeCandia, C. J., &amp; Beach, C. A. (2013). Traumainformed care for displaced populations: A guide for community-based service providers. The National Center on Family Homelessness. Cordes, C. C. (2021). Culturally responsive refugee and migrant health. Families, Systems, &amp; Health, 39(4), 670-673. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1037/fsh0000666">https://doi.org/10.1037/fsh0000666</ref> Dorado, J. S., Martinez, M., McArthur, L. E., &amp; Leibovitz, T. (2016). Healthy environments and response to trauma in schools (HEARTS): A wholeschool, multi-level, prevention and intervention program for creating trauma-informed, safe, and supportive schools. School Mental Health, 8, 163-176. <ref type="url" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12310-016-9177-0">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12310-016-9177-0</ref> Ellis, B. H., Lincoln, A. K., MacDonald, H. Z., &amp; Cabral, H. J. (2008). Mental health of Somali adolescent refugees: The role of trauma, stress, and perceived discrimination. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 76(2), 184-193. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-">https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-</ref>006X.76.2.184 Elnakib, S., Paina, L., Attal, B., Akter, R., Khoury, G., Karim, L., Barkat, H. H., Tamang, A., Yenokyan, G., Metzler, J., &amp; Robinson, C. (2023). Incidence of child marriage among refugees and internally displaced TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 34 persons in the Middle East and South Asia: Evidence from six crosssectional surveys. BMJ Open, 13(6), Article e070056. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2022-070056">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2022-070056</ref> El Saghir, N. S., Soto Pérez de Celis, E., Fares, J. E., &amp; Sullivan, R. (2018). Cancer care for refugees and displaced populations: Middle East conflicts and global natural disasters. American Society of Clinical Oncology Educational book. American Society of Clinical Oncology. Annual Meeting, 38, 433-440. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1200/EDBK_201365">https://doi.org/10.1200/EDBK_201365</ref> Fargues, P., &amp; Fandrich, C. (2012). The European response to the Syrian refugee crisis. What next? MPC RR 2012/14, Robert Schuman Center for Advanced Studies, San Domenico di Fiesole (FI): European University Institute.</p><p><rs type="person">Ford-Paz</rs>, <rs type="person">R. E.</rs>, <rs type="person">DeCarlo Santiago</rs>, <rs type="person">C.</rs>, <rs type="person">Bustos</rs>, <rs type="person">Y.</rs>, <rs type="person">Uriarte</rs>, <rs type="person">J. J.</rs>, <rs type="person">Distel</rs>, <rs type="person">L. M. L.</rs>, <rs type="person">Ros</rs>, <rs type="person">A. M.</rs>, <rs type="person">Coyne</rs>, <rs type="person">C. A.</rs>, <rs type="person">Rivera</rs>, <rs type="person">C.</rs>, <rs type="person">Guo</rs>, <rs type="person">S.</rs>, <rs type="person">Rusch</rs>, <rs type="person">D.</rs>, <rs type="person">St Jean</rs>, <rs type="person">N.</rs>, <rs type="person">Hilado</rs>, <rs type="person">A.</rs>, <rs type="person">Zarzour</rs>, <rs type="person">H.</rs>, <rs type="person">Gomez</rs>, <rs type="person">R.</rs>, &amp; Cicchetti, C. (2023). Acceptability and initial promise of trainings for community stakeholders serving refugee and immigrant families. Psychological Services, 20(1), 188-201. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1037/ser0000457">https://doi.org/10.1037/ser0000457</ref> Frontline World. (2002-2011). Sudan: The quick and the terrible. <ref type="url" target="https://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/sudan/facts.html">https://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/sudan/facts.html</ref> Haddad, M. (2021, July 1). Mapping the hottest temperatures around the world. Aljazeera. TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; <rs type="funder">CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">AND SUPPORT 35</rs> <ref type="url" target="https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/7/1/interactive-mapping-hottest-">https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/7/1/interactive-mapping-hottest-</ref>temperatures-around-world Hadfield, <rs type="person">K.</rs>, <rs type="person">Ostrowski</rs>, A., &amp; Ungar, M. (2017). What can we expect of the mental health and well-being of Syrian refugee children and adolescents in Canada? Canadian Psychology, 58(2), 194-201. <ref type="url" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/cap0000102">http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/cap0000102</ref> Hampton, T. (2010). Child marriage threatens girls' health. JAMA, 304(5), <rs type="grantNumber">509-510</rs>. <ref type="url" target="https://doi:10.1001/jama.2010.1009">https://doi:10.1001/jama.2010.1009</ref> Hammad, J., &amp; Rachel T. (2020). Social suffering and the <rs type="projectName">psychological impact of structural violence and economic oppression in an ongoing conflict setting: The Gaza Strip. Journal of Community Psychology</rs>, 48(6), <rs type="grantNumber">1791-810</rs>. Harlow, <rs type="person">J.</rs>, <rs type="person">Cruz</rs>, <rs type="person">N. C.</rs>, <rs type="person">Celada-Dalton</rs>, <rs type="person">T.</rs>, &amp; Cederbaum, J. A. (2023). La Linterna: Clinical model for trauma-exposed, migrant children. Psychological Trauma: Theory, Research, Practice, and Policy. Advance online publication. <ref type="url" target="https://dx.doi.org/10.1037/tra0001415">https://dx.doi.org/10.1037/tra0001415</ref> Høyvik, A. C., Lie, <rs type="person">B.</rs>, <rs type="person">Grjibovski</rs>, A. M., &amp; Willumsen, T. (2019). Oral health challenges in refugees from the <rs type="funder">Middle East</rs> and Africa: A comparative study. Journal <rs type="funder">of Immigrant and Minority Health</rs>, 21(3), 443-450. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-018-0781-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-018-0781-y</ref> Im, <rs type="person">H.</rs>, <rs type="person">Rodriguez</rs>, <rs type="person">C.</rs>, &amp; Grumbine, J.M. (2020). A multitier model of refugee mental health and psychosocial support in resettlement: Toward <rs type="projectName">TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 36 trauma-</rs>formed and culture-<rs type="funder">informed systems of care</rs>. Psychological Services, 18(3), <rs type="grantNumber">345-364</rs>. <ref type="url" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/ser0000412">http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/ser0000412</ref> Kleinman, A., Das V., Lock, M., &amp; Lock, M. M. (1997). Social suffering. University of California Press. Laub, Z. (2015, April 29). Yemen in crisis. Council on Foreign Relations. <ref type="url" target="https://www.files.ethz.ch/isn/190632/Backgrounder_%20Yemen">https://www.files.ethz.ch/isn/190632/Backgrounder_%20Yemen</ref>'s%20C i...pdf <rs type="person">Liu J.</rs>, <rs type="person">Varghese B. M.</rs>, <rs type="person">Hansen A.</rs>, <rs type="person">Xiang</rs>, <rs type="person">J.</rs>, <rs type="person">Zhang Y.</rs>, <rs type="person">Dear</rs>, <rs type="person">K.</rs>, <rs type="person">Gourley</rs>, <rs type="person">M.</rs>, <rs type="person">Driscoll T.</rs>, <rs type="person">Morgan</rs>, <rs type="person">G.</rs>, <rs type="person">Capon</rs>, A., &amp; Bi, P. (2021). Is there an association between hot weather and poor mental health outcomes? A systematic review and meta-analysis. Environmental International, 153. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2021.106533">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2021.106533</ref> Loomis, B., Epstein, K., Dauria, E. F., &amp; Dolce, L. (2018). Implementing a trauma-informed public health system in San Francisco, California. Health Education &amp; Behavior, 1-9. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1090198118806942">https://doi.org/10.1177/1090198118806942</ref> Masento, N., Golightly, M., Field, D., Butler, L., &amp; Van Reekum, C. (2014). Effects of hydration status on cognitive performance and mood. British Journal of Nutrition, 111(10), 1841-1852. doi:10.1017/S0007114513004455 Miller, A., Hess, J. M., Bybee, D., &amp; Goodkind, J. R. (2017). Understanding the mental health consequences of family separation for refugees: TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 37 Implications for policy and practice. American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 88(1), 26-37. <ref type="url" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/ort0000272">http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/ort0000272</ref> Miller, K. K., Brown, C. R., Shramko, M., &amp; Svetaz, M. V. (2019). Applying trauma-informed practices to the care of refugee and immigrant youth: 10 clinical pearls. Children, 6(94), 1-11. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.3390/children6080094">https://doi.org/10.3390/children6080094</ref> Mim, S. A. (2017). Effects of child marriage on girls' education and empowerment. Journal of Education and Learning, 11(1). <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.11591/edulearn.v11i1.5130">https://doi.org/10.11591/edulearn.v11i1.5130</ref> Mourtada, R., Schlecht, J., &amp; Dejong, J. (2017). A qualitative study exploring child marriage practices among Syrian conflict-affected populations in Lebanon. Conflict and Health, 11(S1). <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13031-">https://doi.org/10.1186/s13031-</ref>017-0131-z Murray, K. E., Davidson, G. R., &amp; Schweitzer, R. D. (2010). Review of refugee mental health interventions following resettlement: Best practices and recommendations. American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 80(4), 576-585. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org">https://doi.org</ref> /10.1111/j.1939-0025.2010.01062.x Nour, N. M. (2006). Health consequences of child marriage in Africa. Emerging Infectious Disease, 12(11), 1644-1649. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org">https://doi.org</ref> /10.3201/eid1211.060510 Ostrand, N. (2015). The Syrian refugee crisis: A comparison of responses by Germany, Sweden, the United Kingdom, and the United States. Journal on Migration and Human Security, 3(3), 255-279. TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 38 Pandalangat, N., &amp; Kanagaratnam, P. (2021). Refugee mental health framework: A systematic tool and approach that optimizes outcomes. Asian American Journal of Psychology, 12(3), 241-249. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1037/aap0000194">https://doi.org/10.1037/aap0000194</ref> Parsons, J., Edmeades, J. D., Kes, A., Petroni, S., Sexton, M. W., &amp; Wodon, Q. (2015). Economic impacts of child marriage: A review of the literature. The Review of Faith &amp; International Affairs, 13(3). <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1080/15570274.2015.1075757">https://doi.org/10.1080/15570274.2015.1075757</ref> Peretz, D. (1996). Palestinians, refugees, and the Middle East peace process. United States Institute of Peace Press. Rasmussen, A., Katoni, B., Keller A.S., &amp; Wilkinson, J. (2011). Posttraumatic idioms of distress among Darfur refugees: Hozun and Majnun. Transcultural Psychiatry, 48(4), 392-415. Sahbani, S., Al-Khateeb, M., &amp; Hikmat, R. (2016). Early marriage and pregnancy among Syrian adolescent girls in Jordan; do they have a choice? Pathogens and Global Health, 110(6), 217-218. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1080/20477724.2016.1231834">https://doi.org/10.1080/20477724.2016.1231834</ref> Sassoon, J. (2009). The Iraqi refugees: The new crisis in the Middle East. I.B. Tauris &amp; Co. Ltd. Shearlaw, M. (2013, July 25). Are refugee camps the best solution for people fleeing a crisis? Guardian (Manchester, England). TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 39 <ref type="url" target="https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2013/jul/25/refugee">https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2013/jul/25/refugee</ref> -camps-solution-people-fleeing-crisis Sijbrandij, M. et al. (2017). Strengthening mental health care systems for Syrian refugees in Europe and the Middle East: Integrating scalable psychological interventions in eight countries. European Journal of Psychotraumatology, 8(2). <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1080/20008198.2017.1388102">https://doi.org/10.1080/20008198.2017.1388102</ref> Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. (2014). SAMHSA's Concept of Trauma and Guidance for a Trauma-Informed Approach. HHS Publication No. (SMA) 14-4884. Rockville, MD. Terrana, A., Ibrahim, N., Kaiser, B., &amp; Al-Delaimy, W. K. (2022). Foundations of Somali resilience: Collective identity, faith, and community. Cultural Diversity and Ethnic Minority Psychology, 28(4), 533-543. <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1037/cdp0000536">https://doi.org/10.1037/cdp0000536</ref> Thompson, R., Hornigold, R., Page, L., &amp; Waite, T. (2018). Associations between high ambient temperatures and heat waves with mental health outcomes: A systematic review. Public Health, 161, 171-191. https//doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2018.06.008 UNHCR. (2022). Self-reliance and entrepreneurship. <ref type="url" target="https://www.unhcr.org/self-reliance-and-entrepreneurship.html">https://www.unhcr.org/self-reliance-and-entrepreneurship.html</ref> UNHCR. (2023a). Sudan. <ref type="url" target="https://www.unhcr.org//countries/sudan">https://www.unhcr.org//countries/sudan</ref> TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR</p></div>
			</div>
			
			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p>The authors did not receive support from any organization for the submitted work. manuscript as submitted.</p></div>
			</div>


			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_nxuqgTZ">
					<idno type="grant-number">AND SUPPORT 31</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Palestinians in the Gaza Strip: A qualitative, culture-informed analysis. Journal of Health Psychology</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_9QEkRc7">
					<idno type="grant-number">AND SUPPORT 35</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_p7WdmS6">
					<idno type="grant-number">509-510</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">psychological impact of structural violence and economic oppression in an ongoing conflict setting: The Gaza Strip. Journal of Community Psychology</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_DPKsvun">
					<idno type="grant-number">1791-810</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_JHYDDd3">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 36 trauma-</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_dmVUA8a">
					<idno type="grant-number">345-364</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of data and material</head><p>Not applicable</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethics approval and consent to participate</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Not applicable</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent for publication</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Not applicable</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sudan emergency</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.unhcr.org/eg/sudanemergency" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023b</date>
			<publisher>UNHCR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community readiness in the Syrian refugee community in Jordan: A rapid ecological assessment tool to build psychosocial service capacity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abo-Hilal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Steel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Plested</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lawsin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/ort0000404Wikipedia</idno>
		<ptr target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2023_Sudanese_refugee_crisis" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Orthopsychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="212" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 2023. August 29, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A critically informed perspective of working with resettling refugee groups in Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Westoby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ingamells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bjsw/bcp084</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi:10.1093/bjsw/bcp084" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Social Work</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1759" to="1776" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Migrants, refugees, and displaced persons in the Middle East and North Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zaccara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Conçalves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1590/1980-85852503880006302</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1590/1980-85852503880006302" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Revista Interdisciplinar Mobilidade Humana</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dealing with non-Palestinian refugees in the Middle East: Policies and practices in an uncertain environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zaiotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ijrl/eel006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ijrl/eel006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Refugee Law</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemiology and management of hypertension TRAUMA-INFORMED &amp; CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE PRACTICES FOR REFUGEE CARE AND SUPPORT 41 among refugees in the Middle East: A review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Zibara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Costanian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Al Haddad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kilani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tohme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aoun Bahous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41371-021-00508-5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41371-021-00508-5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Human Hypertension</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="666" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
