<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ELECTROMAGNETIC-ETHERIC MODEL OF GLOBAL NEURAL SYNCHRONIZATION Scientific Paper Author: Zoran Alić Date: October 10, 2025 Location: Sarajevo, Bosnia and Herzegovina</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">ELECTROMAGNETIC-ETHERIC MODEL OF GLOBAL NEURAL SYNCHRONIZATION Scientific Paper Author: Zoran Alić Date: October 10, 2025 Location: Sarajevo, Bosnia and Herzegovina</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4240098E8568A4F84296618013D646ED</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper presents a novel approach to understanding global neural synchronization through an electromagnetic-etheric model that integrates physical and ontological aspects of consciousness. The model is based on the assumption that the brain is not an isolated bioelectric system, but rather part of a larger etheric continuum that supports and modulates neural oscillations. Numerical simulations of the electromagnetic-etheric model demonstrated sustained partial coherence (R = 0.61 ± 0.04) in the parameter range λ = 0.9 and G = 0.015, consistent with predictions of the electromagnetic-etheric synchronization theory. These results suggest that consciousness arises from the interaction of neural networks with the etheric resonant field, which enables global coherence and energetic stability.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Global neural synchronization represents one of the key unresolved problems in neuroscience and the physics of consciousness. While classical dynamical models (such as the Kuramoto model) explain synchronization through local connections, they exhibit documented difficulties in accounting for the instantaneous and globally scalable coherence observed in brain waves. Specifically, these models are inherently unstable in the thermodynamic limit.</p><p>Here, a novel model is proposed-the Electromagnetic-Etheric Model of Global Neural Synchronization-whose dynamics are formulated as a Kuramoto-Ether model, incorporating an additional component, the etheric factor G, as a subtle resonant medium of interaction. The model transcends purely materialistic assumptions and aligns neurophysiological dynamics with field physics. This approach provides a physical explanation for how quasi-vacuum field resonance can mathematically modulate the coherence of neural networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Theoretical Framework</head><p>At the core of the model lies the concept of a square loop of electromagnetic induction, which describes a closed feedback loop between neural currents and the etheric field.</p><p>The mathematical description of the model is based on the extended Kuramoto equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">dθ i dt = ω i + K N ∑ ⬚ N j=1 sin(θ j - θ i ) + G R(t) sin(ψ(t) - θ i )</formula><p>• θᵢ represents the oscillator phase of the i-th neuron,</p><p>• ωᵢ is its natural frequency (for numerical simulations, ωᵢ are normally distributed around ω_mean = 10 rad/s with a standard deviation σ = 0.5),</p><p>• K is the coupling coefficient (λ, in the model λ = 0.9),</p><p>• G is the etheric factor (field_gain = 0.015),</p><p>• R(t) and ψ(t) are order parameters of synchronization defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">𝑅(𝑡)𝑒 𝑖ψ(𝑡) = 1 𝑁 ∑ 𝑒 𝑖θ 𝑗 (𝑡) 𝑁 𝑗=1</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Numerical Methodology and Stability</head><p>The model was numerically integrated using the Euler method with a step size dt = 0.02. Due to the large number of oscillators (N = 2000 -8000), local coupling was implemented using a mean-field approximation to ensure numerical stability and computational efficiency. All stable coherence values R were calculated as averages over the last 20% of the simulation time (t_max = 200).</p><p>This additional etheric component G enables collective resonance of the system and introduces dynamic stability that cannot be explained by local electromagnetic connections alone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Neuro-Etheric Continuum</head><p>The model assumes that a continuous quasivacuum medium (Ether) exists between neural oscillators, acting as a resonant field with its own fluctuations. This medium can simultaneously support and stabilize oscillations, analogous to the Higgs field in particle physics, but at the neurophysiological level.</p><p>In this framework, consciousness is an emergent phenomenon arising from the synchronized resonance of the neural and etheric fields.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Methodology</head><p>For the numerical analysis, a modified Kuramoto model was implemented in Python.</p><p>Simulation parameters were: For each simulation, the following were calculated:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">•</formula><p>• instantaneous order parameter R(t),</p><p>• average R over the last 20% of the simulation time,</p><p>• distribution of oscillator phases θ_i at the end of the simulation.</p><p>Repetitions were also performed (5 × N = 4000) for statistical stability, and one large simulation with N = 8000 was conducted to verify result scalability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Simulation Results</head><p>The Kuramoto-Ether simulation table presents statistically confirmed results of the Electromagnetic-Etheric model for all key test scenarios. Coherence R was calculated as the mean value over the last 20% of the simulation time, and reliability was confirmed by the standard deviation (σ) from five independent runs.</p><p>For the baseline parameters (λ = 0.9, G = 0.015), the model demonstrates stable partial synchronization with coherence R = 0.6122 ± 0.0380. The results clearly support the main thesis of the paper regarding the existence of a collective mechanism that transcends purely local neural connections.</p><p>With an increased number of oscillators (N = 8000), R values further stabilized, confirming the robustness of the model in the thermodynamic limit.</p><p>Shows the region of stable synchronization in relation to the parameters λ and G.</p><p>Shows the development of the R parameter over time for five simulation repetitions.</p><p>Demonstrates the establishment of coherence and the stable state of the system.</p><p>Shows the distribution of final phases θ_i and the formation of clusters. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Results of Kuramoto-Ether Simulation for Key Test Scenarios</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Discussion</head><p>The statistical results (see Table "Kuramoto-Ether Simulations") clearly indicate the existence of global synchronization mediated by the etheric factor G.</p><p>A key finding from the Field Dominance test, where increasing the etheric factor to G = 0.7 resulted in the highest coherence (R ≈ 0.72), strongly supports the hypothesis of field dominance over weak local coupling.</p><p>Analysis of the Field Necessity test results (G = 0) provides solid evidence of the contribution of the etheric factor. Comparison of the baseline case (G = 0.015) with the test in which the etheric field was completely removed (G = 0) shows a statistically significant drop in coherence (see The etheric field acts as a subtle resonator that:</p><p>1. synchronizes distant neural clusters, 2. reduces the energetic cost of oscillations, 3. enables instantaneous coherence across space.</p><p>These three properties form the basis for explaining global consciousness as an etheric-energetic phenomenon.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion</head><p>The simulation results numerically confirm the key assumptions of the Electromagnetic-Etheric Model of Global Neural Synchronization.</p><p>The model not only successfully describes the transition from an unsynchronized to a coherent state, but statistically strongly supports the existence of an etheric mechanism that dominates synchronization and transcends purely local neural connections.</p><p>By introducing the etheric factor G, the model connects electromagnetism and quasi-vacuum resonance within a unified framework, providing a new physical-etheric basis for explaining global consciousness.</p><p>Further experimental testing is proposed through:</p><p>• multi-channel electroencephalographic experiments (MEA),</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Number of oscillators: N = 2000 -8000 • Integration step: dt = 0.02 • Total time: tₘₐₓ = 200 • Parameters: λ = 0.9, G = 0.015</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,70.85,70.85,277.85,212.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table :</head><label>:</label><figDesc>Kuramoto-Ether Simulations</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>K</cell><cell>G</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Scenarij</cell><cell>N (Broj</cell><cell>(Koeficij</cell><cell>(Eteri</cell><cell>ωprosj</cell><cell>Stabilna</cell></row><row><cell>(Naziv</cell><cell>oscilato</cell><cell>ent</cell><cell>čni</cell><cell>ek</cell><cell>koherencij</cell></row><row><cell>testa)</cell><cell>ra)</cell><cell>sprezanj</cell><cell>faktor</cell><cell>(rad/s)</cell><cell>a R±σ</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>a λ)</cell><cell>)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Baza (Apstrakt )</cell><cell>2000</cell><cell>0.900</cell><cell>0.015</cell><cell>10.0</cell><cell>0.6122±0.0 380</cell></row><row><cell>Skalabiln ost (Veliki N)</cell><cell>8000</cell><cell>0.900</cell><cell>0.015</cell><cell>10.0</cell><cell>0.6006±0.0 112</cell></row><row><cell>Dominac ija Polja</cell><cell>2000</cell><cell>0.300</cell><cell>0.700</cell><cell>10.0</cell><cell>0.7216±0.0 193</cell></row><row><cell>Nužnost Polja (G=0)</cell><cell>2000</cell><cell>0.900</cell><cell>0.000</cell><cell>10.0</cell><cell>0.5843±0.0 412</cell></row><row><cell>Visoka Frekvenc</cell><cell>2000</cell><cell>0.900</cell><cell>0.015</cell><cell>30.0</cell><cell>0.6122±0.0</cell></row><row><cell>ija</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table -</head><label>-</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>The results clearly demonstrate the existence of</cell></row><row><cell>global synchronization mediated by the etheric</cell></row><row><cell>factor G. Unlike the classical Kuramoto model,</cell></row><row><cell>where coherence depends solely on K, the presence</cell></row><row><cell>of G here enables faster and more stable resonance,</cell></row><row><cell>consistent with biological observations of brain</cell></row><row><cell>waves (alpha and gamma rhythms).</cell></row><row><cell>"Kuramoto-Ether Simulations"). This</cell></row><row><cell>finding confirms that even a minimal etheric factor</cell></row><row><cell>plays a vital stabilizing role in maintaining global</cell></row><row><cell>synchronization, beyond the reach of the classical</cell></row><row><cell>Kuramoto model.</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>References</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consciousness in the universe: A review of the Orch OR theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Penrose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hameroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics of Life Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The electromagnetic field theory of consciousness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcfadden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Neuroscience of Consciousness</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pockett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Field theories of consciousness</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Scholarpedia</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tesla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The ether and its role in universal phenomena</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1919">1919</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Electromagnetic-Etheric Approach to Quantum Synchronization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Alić</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-range coherence and energy storage in biological systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fröhlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
