<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Inequality in Child Mortality Persists Between Genera ons in the Netherlands, 1835-1919</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Van Dijk Ins</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">onal affilia ons</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centre for Economic Demography</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Department of Economic History</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lund University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Affiliated resesacher</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Radboud Centre for Historical Demography and Family History</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nijmegen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Inequality in Child Mortality Persists Between Genera ons in the Netherlands, 1835-1919</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">99C485C03CFB83C7E362C01F62427FCB</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Death clustering</term>
					<term>social inequality in child mortality</term>
					<term>death clustering</term>
					<term>health inequality</term>
					<term>intergenera onal persistence</term>
					<term>health mobility</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In historical the Netherlands, child mortality was distributed unequally between families and this inequality persisted across genera ons. Using family recons tu on data for the province of Zeeland (LINKS) containing over 200.000 children born 1835-1914, I show that mortality was higher among children under age 5 whose parents lost siblings before age 5. This intergenera onal persistence of child mortality existed independently from socioeconomic differences in child mortality. Inequali es accumulated, as child mortality was highest for low-SES children whose parents originated from highmortality, low-socioeconomic status families. Intergenera onal transmission in child mortality persisted even when child mortality had declined in the early 20 th century.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduc on</head><p>Child mortality is commonly considered a key indicator of well-being and the popula on living standard and its level is used for compara ve purposes of inequality in the living standard in the world <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Sen 1998)</ref>. Young children are highly dependent on their families to survive, and child mortality and characteris cs that contribute to the risk of early death concentrate in families ( <ref type="bibr">van Dijk 2019b)</ref>. Inequali es between families in their likelihood of child loss capture broad inequality in sociodemographic, behavioral and spa al characteris cs that shape living condi ons and affect the likelihood of child death. Moreover, intergenera onal persistence of high child mortality shows how some families face such unfavorable condi ons over more than one genera on. By examining the magnitude of intergenera onal persistence of child mortality, the accumula on of risk factors for early-life mortality in a specific group of families can be addressed.</p><p>The me-trend in intergenera onal persistence of child mortality is of par cular interest to understand the long-term development of inequality in living standards in the popula on. Inequali es in child mortality may have changed during the demographic transi on, when child mortality declined. Improvements in child survival may par cularly have benefited the most disadvantaged families. On the other hand, when child deaths declined, child deaths could have increasingly been concentrated in a small set of deprived families. In this paper, I address long-term trends in intergenera onal persistence of child mortality in the Netherlands between <ref type="bibr">1835-1919.</ref> In this period, levels of child mortality fell from around 365 to 117 deaths per 1000 live-born infants (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). Changes in the degree of intergenera onal persistence in child mortality throws light on a crucial indicator of the popula on's living standard, the capacity of families to keep their children alive and inequality therein over me.</p><p>Across genera ons, parents and children face similar challenges in taking care of their families and helping their children survive. Poverty and low socioeconomic status, behavioral pa erns including breas eeding and weaning of children, and other social factors are o en similar between parents and children. Intergenera onal persistence of such characteris cs could therefore make an important contribu on to increased child mortality in more than one genera on. For contemporary <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Hajizadeh, Nandi, and Heymann 2014)</ref> and historical popula ons (Antonovsky and Bernstein 1967; Dribe and Karlsson 2022; <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Van Poppel, Jonker, and Mandemakers 2005)</ref>, it is well established that child mortality is higher among lower social class groups. At the same me, previous research has shown that intergenera onal persistence of infant mortality exists even a er taking into account social class of mothers and grandmothers ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">van Dijk and Mandemakers 2018)</ref>. Other social, behavioral, spa al, and biological factors that are shared between genera ons through processes of social reproduc on, socializa on, shared living condi ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Preston, Hill, and Drevenstedt 1998)</ref> and gene c inheritance <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Vandezande and Ma hijs 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">van Dijk 2019a)</ref> likely also contribute to these inequali es.</p><p>Earlier studies have documented the intergenera onal transmission of child and infant mortality from mother to daughter. Two studies using sibling and offspring surveys established a strong intergenera onal persistence in child mortality in developing countries 2004-2017 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Lu and Vogl 2023</ref><ref type="bibr">) and 1970</ref><ref type="bibr">-2000</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Bhalotra and Rawlings 2011)</ref>. For historical popula ons, Quaranta and Sommerseth <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Quaranta and Sommerseth 2018)</ref> show that intergenera onal transmission of infant mortality from mother to daughter is found in a number of historical popula ons in Western Europe, including Zeeland ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">van Dijk and Mandemakers 2018)</ref>. There has been surprisingly li le a en on for intergenera onal persistence of child mortality from fathers to their surviving sons. In contrast, for the intergenera onal persistence of social status, an overwhelming majority of work focuses on persistence from fathers to sons. Intergenera onal transmission of child mortality, a broader indicator of early-life mortality than infant mortality, has not been studied for historical Europe, and finally, interac ons with socioeconomic factors have been neglected. This paper has two main aims. First, I show the extent to which social class inequali es existed between families in young-age child mortality in historical the Netherlands over this period. Second, I show the intergenera onal persistence of inequali es in child mortality across me. Did grandparents and parents have similar pa erns of child loss in mes of declining child mortality when child deaths became less common? I show that child mortality was distributed unequally between families and that this inequality persisted across genera ons. Parents, both fathers and mothers, with elevated sibling child mortality had increased risk of deaths among their own young children. Intergenera onally high risk of child death exists next to a social class gradient in mortality but cannot be explained by it. Both in high and low social class families, intergenera onal similari es in high child mortality existed. Among parents that grew up in high mortality, low-SES families with low adulthood SES had the highest under-five mortality among their children, so that inequali es in child mortality accumulate in families. Further, intergenera onal transmission is found even for a period when child mortality had declined strongly. Inequali es in child mortality persist across genera ons in families, over and above the social gradient in mortality. Panel A: Yearly child and infant mortality rate and the stillbirth rate in the province of Zeeland, the Netherlands, 1835-1913. Panel B: Number of mother's sibling deaths in childhood, by mother's birth year, 1812-1892. Source: Author calculations, LINKS Zeeland (R. J. Mourits et al. 2022)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Intergenera onal inequali es in child mortality: Earlier literature</head><p>Studying inequality in mortality is fundamental to understanding overall inequality in the popula on's living standard ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">van Raalte, Sasson, and Mar kainen 2018)</ref>. Inequality in the distribu on of child mortality has been studied largely in rela on to measurable social factors of specific individuals, such as family socioeconomic status, maternal age and child sex. In another approach, maternal bereavement has been studied using indicators of child mortality levels and survey data <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Smith-Greenaway et al. 2021)</ref>. In this paper I use a third approach and study the extent to which inequality in child mortality persists between genera ons. Strong intergenera onal persistence of child mortality flags low equality of opportunity and high inequality in the distribu on of the length of life, already at the start of life. The degree to which the risk of death before age 5 is related to the experience of the previous genera on shows the concentra on of child mortality in a specific subset of families and the extent to which mothers and fathers have a similar experience as their own parents regarding child loss. Reversely, if mothers and fathers are more successful in keeping their infants and children alive than their own parents this illustrates progress, at least in that family. Intergenera onal persistence in child mortality thus captures the overall inequality between families in their possibili es to keep young children alive, and flags crucial inequality between children already at the start of life. Socioeconomic factors could be an important reason that parents and children are similar in their likelihood of experiencing death among their infants and young children. Socioeconomic status has been argued to be a fundamental cause of mortality, as regardless of place, me and the dominant disease environment, resources could contribute to disease preven on, treatment, and in handling the consequences of exposure to health risks <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Link and Phelan 1995)</ref>. Depending on the period and the disease environment, socioeconomic inequali es in child mortality could emerge through a range of characteris cs in which social classes differ and that directly affect mortality <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Dribe and Karlsson 2022)</ref>. The large literature on infant and child mortality shows the importance of nutri on, sanita on, immuniza on, breas eeding and care taking prac ces for child survival and improvements therein in the 19 th and 20 th century. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Mosley and Chen (1984)</ref> provide a framework regarding socioeconomic status and proximate determinants of child mortality. They argue that socioeconomic factors indirectly contribute to child mortality through a set of proximate determinants that consist of maternal factors, nutri on, health care, injuries and environmental contamina on. Socioeconomic factors can put children at an increased risk of exposure to disease pathogens, weaken children's health through insufficient nutri on or care, access to health care a er injury or disease, and increasing risk of death due to external factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Mosley and Chen 1984)</ref>. Overall, such factors could increase risk of child death for a subset of mothers <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Das Gupta 1990)</ref>. Socioeconomic status may affect these proximate determinants through mechanisms rela ng to economic resources, cultural factors and the place of residence. More resources may improve quality of nutri on, reduce crowding in the home and improve access to health care, and reduce harmful exposures to pathogens in the environment, with be er hygiene and access to clean water.</p><p>While this framework usefully links socioeconomic factors to more direct determinants of mortality, broader social inequali es than inequali es based on social class of the household alone also contributed to the survival chances of young children in the past. As a result, SES of families may only capture part of the social stra fica on in child mortality ( <ref type="bibr">van Dijk 2019b)</ref>. Moreover, the extent to which these mechanisms affec ng child mortality were linked to SES of families could have changed over me, so that socioeconomic status could be a poor indicator of the risk of child mortality in some periods. Earlier research has shown that infant and child mortality were rela vely equally distributed between the social classes in 19 th century Sweden, before the demographic transi on, but that inequali es grew over me <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Dribe and Karlsson 2022)</ref>. Similarly, in 19 th century the Netherlands the social gradient in child survival was small in comparison to regional differences in child mortality ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Van Poppel, Jonker, and Mandemakers 2005)</ref>, even if children of unskilled workers had a higher likelihood of death before the fi h birthday. A social disadvantage in child mortality for the underprivileged persisted into the 20 th century. For Amsterdam, such differences were related to sociodemographic characteris cs, residen al environment, water supply, and religious groups. Housing and neighborhood characteris cs were especially related to mortality in late infancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Ekamper and van Poppel 2019)</ref>. Moreover, the absence of a social welfare system and the generally lower standard of living implied that parental death o en had catastrophic consequences for the survival chances of young children <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Quanjer, van Dijk, and Rosenbaum-Feldbrügge 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Taken together, these findings imply that although socioeconomic status ma ered for child survival, a range of other social factors also could have been important, and part of these mechanisms can affect individuals across genera ons. Surviving children may have faced similar challenges as their parents in keeping their children alive, in rela on to shared living condi ons or behavioral features. Detrimental events in the family, for example, illegi macy of the birth of a child in Sweden at a me that this was not socially acceptable <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Modin, Koupil, and Vågerö 2009)</ref> has previously been shown to be associated with intergenera onal persistence of mortality and ill health. Learned behavior (Vandezande and Ma hijs 2013) including feeding, weaning and nursing children may have affected the likelihood of infec on with disease, especially during the summer months <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Walhout 2010)</ref>, which could have affected mortality across genera ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Vandezande and Ma hijs 2013)</ref>.</p><p>It should be noted that intergenera onal persistence of child mortality is an indicator of the overall level of inequality between families in their abili es to keep their young children alive, regardless of whether they are related to socioeconomic, spa al, or behavioral factors. Measuring intergenera onal persistence of child deaths is therefore a dis nct approach from earlier studies on social inequali es in child mortality in that it does not necessarily set out to study a specific factor that contributes to child mortality but addresses the extent to which mortality concentrates in a specific subset of the popula on. This makes it possible to look at developments in the overall level of inequality in child mortality between families, even if the mechanisms that contribute to these inequali es change over me. Analy cally, there are parallels to studying the intergenera onal persistence of social status or poverty. Like intergenera onal persistence in socioeconomic status, similari es between grandparents and parents in offspring loss capture mobility or lack thereof from one genera on to the next. Importantly, intergenera onal persistence in child mortality also captures the extent to which the second genera on manages to escape the disadvantage of the first genera on in survival of young children.</p><p>Over me, child mortality rates fell sharply. Knowledge about the origins of disease became common, treatment op ons more widespread, improvements in public infrastructure benefited the whole popula on, and the nutri onal standard of the popula on improved. Social differences in mortality can especially be expected once the origins of disease are known and resources can be used to guard oneself against disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Clouston et al. 2016)</ref>, although social differences in mortality can also relate to the living standard itself (nutri on, housing and the ability to care for sick rela ves). With improvements in knowledge and how well diseases could be treated, it is possible that the intergenera onal similari es in mortality declined. Improved rou nes in taking care of infants and children and knowledge about hygiene may have resulted in smaller inequali es in how well children were cared for. Improvements in the living standard and increases in social mobility over me may have benefited especially the most vulnerable families. A previous study on intergenera onal persistence of health has shown that maternal indicators of poor health in childhood and adulthood both contribute to increased mortality and stun ng among their children, and that inequali es in Africa grew between 1970 and 2000 <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Bhalotra and Rawlings 2011)</ref>. Moreover, intergenera onal persistence of mortality in low-and middle income countries 2004-2017 fell with aggregate child mortality <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Lu and Vogl 2023)</ref>.</p><p>In this paper, I study both the socioeconomic gradient in child mortality and intergenera onal persistence of high child mortality. I contrast es mates of the role of SES in child survival with es mates of the intergenera onal persistence in child mortality, to show what part of the persistence of mortality can be explained by intergenera onal depriva on. This is only one social factor of many possible sources of varia on in child mortality, but it is an important one, and widely studied in almost all literature on inequality in child mortality. The paper contributes to the exis ng literature on social inequali es in child mortality by addressing how, in a period of declining child mortality, high child mortality was related across genera ons -and what part, if any, of the social gap in child mortality was related to socioeconomic resources. I document the trend in intergenera onal transmission of high mortality, as well as the trend in SES and child mortality in the Netherlands. The long-term development in such inequality is important as evidence for overall inequali es in the popula on living standard. I include not only SES of the household in which the child grows up (measured using father's SES based on his occupa on), but also SES of the grandparental households using maternal grandfather and paternal grandfather's occupa on and contrast the influence of the household of origin of the mother and the father.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Data</head><p>Analyses are based on a large-scale historical demographic dataset for the historical province of Zeeland, Netherlands (LINKS). LINKS (Linking System for historical family reconstruc on) Zeeland links together indexed civil cer ficates to historical individuals, reconstruc ng vital events during their life course, and linking individuals to their parents, partners, and children across many genera ons. LINKS has been used extensively for historical demographic research on the Netherlands and has been subject to thorough checks of quality and reliability (van den <ref type="bibr">Berg et al. 2021)</ref>.</p><p>The largely Protestant province of Zeeland is situated in the southwestern corner of The Netherlands and consists largely of islands. The popula on had very high fer lity throughout the study period, with a mean number of children of around 8 for married couples (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> for descrip ve sta s cs). A lack of potable water existed due to problems with salinity and especially in dry summers diarrhea-related mortality among young children peaked. Life expectancy was low, both at birth and for infants and children, with child mortality reaching 50% before the fi h birthday in some years, with high levels of epidemic disease in par cularly affected communi es <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Hoogerhuis 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Poppel and Mandemakers 2002)</ref>.</p><p>The LINKS data consists of linked digi zed indexes of civil cer ficates. These originate from obligatory vital event registra on, which was introduced in The Netherlands in 1812. The cer ficates include informa on on the names of born, married and deceased persons, the municipality of the vital event, the individuals' place of birth, age, occupa onal tles, and names of parents. Life course events of the same individuals have been linked together through name-based linkage of cer ficates pertaining to the same individuals, using first and last names of the ego and his or her parents, spouses, and children. The full database contains informa on on 1,930,189 individuals from Zeeland who experienced a vital event in that province between 1812 and 1914 for births, 1812 and 1927 for marriages, and 1812 and 1957 for deaths. For the analysis, 217,330 children are selected, born between 1834 and 1914, whose parents and grandparents are known and whose parents both have at least one sibling. They are the descendants of more than 40 thousand mothers and fathers and more than 26 thousand maternal and paternal grandmothers and grandfathers. For a full overview of selec on criteria, see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">A1</ref>. The data structure allows us to follow individuals through their life course and also contains informa on on their siblings, parents, aunts, uncles, and grandparents, plus the children of these rela ves. The birth cohorts 1833-1913 are included, following children's survival un l 1918.</p><p>A death date or observa on a er age 5 is available for 75.3% of the children. A death date is available for 49.1% of the index persons included in the analyses. For a further 26.2% of the index persons a civil record is linked a er childhood which is not their death cer ficate (e.g. their own marriage or their child's birth, marriage, or death). It is assumed that children for whom no further cer ficates are linked (24.6%) survived un l age 5<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> . For a minority of the cases, a cer ficate of death may not have been indexed or linked although the child died before the age of five. These cases likely weaken associa ons between our variables of interest. Child mortality in the sample was somewhat lower than in the popula on (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Appendix 2</ref>).</p><p>Children who were lifeless upon registra on are excluded from the analysis. These cases encompass both s llbirths and births of infants who died before they were reported to the municipality, which had to be completed within 3 working days a er birth <ref type="bibr">(Vulsma 1988)</ref>. Es mates suggest that 71% of lifeless reported infants concern s llbirths and 29% concern live births of infants who died before municipal registra on of birth ( <ref type="bibr">Van Poppel et al. 2012</ref>). As it is unclear which children were born alive and for how long they lived a er birth, lifeless registered children are excluded from the analyses of child death, which will lead to a slight underes ma on of infant deaths in the neonatal period and to conserva ve es mates of the intergenera onal rela on in child mortality risk. Descrip ve sta s cs may be found in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. I include characteris cs of the observed children, their family of origin, and childhood circumstances of their parents. Demographic characteris cs of the children include birth order and if the child has a twin. For both fathers and mothers, an indicator is included for first birth at a young age (before age 21). Other characteris cs of interest concern whether the birth interval to the previous child was short (&lt; 18 months) and if the father or mother died before the child's fi h birthday. Young children are highly dependent on family members for survival in their early life, and the death of a parent can therefore detrimentally affect the chances of survival of infants and young children <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Quanjer, van Dijk, and Rosenbaum-Feldbrügge 2023)</ref>. For some children, there is no known date of death of one or both of their parents and there is no observa on a er their fi h birthday (for 12.4% of the children, the mother has no death date, and she is not observed a er the child's fi h birthday or death date. For 12.9% of the children, this applies to their father). In these cases, it is assumed that the parents survived un l the fi h birthday or -in case the child died before the fi h birthday -un l death.</p><p>Due to high childhood mortality in the province of Zeeland in the research period, it is common that parents lost at least one sibling in childhood (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, panel B). I include separately the number of child deaths in the sibling group of the parent (0, 1, 2 or more deaths). In a robustness check that produces largely the same findings, the number of sibling deaths is expressed as a propor on of the number of siblings of the parent. Socioeconomic status (SES) of children's families of origin, and the socioeconomic status of the family of origin of their parents are included. SES was measured using the highest known occupa onal tle of the father and the grandfathers using HISCLASS scores across all indexed civil cer ficates linked to one person. HISCLASS is a system that groups historical occupa onal tles into broad occupa onal classes. This broad status indicator is recoded into 6 occupa onal groups:</p><p>Higher occupa ons, higher skilled workers, medium skilled workers, lower skilled workers, unskilled workers, farmers and fisherman, and a separate category for missing observa ons (Van Leeuwen and Maas 2011). Occupa onal tles from the Netherlands have been standardized in previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Mandemakers et al. 2020</ref>). In the research period, men were usually the primary breadwinner. Female labor market par cipa on was severely under registered <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Janssens 1997)</ref>. In line with previous research, I therefore rely on the occupa on of the husband. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results</head><p>In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, the concentra on of child deaths in families in historical the Netherlands is shown. There are more mothers observed (filled line) that escape deaths among infants and children altogether than expected (do ed line) based on total child mortality rate in the popula on. Thus, there are more women without deaths than expected, and a higher number of women experiencing several deaths than expected based on the total child mortality rate. This implies a concentra on of sibling deaths in a subset of the families. Perhaps this finding is unsurprising, as this concentra on of child deaths in certain families suggests that it is not just chance that determined which children survived their childhood; other factors, opera ng at the level of the family or the communi es in which these families lived, also determined the likelihood of survival of children.</p><p>In Panel B the concentra on of child deaths in families by SES is shown. SES is grouped into the two main categories: White collar workers (higher and lower managers and professionals), and blue-collar workers (medium skilled workers, lower skilled workers, and unskilled workers). The figures show that the concentra on of deaths in families is stronger among blue collar workers (red filled line) than in white collar families (blue filled line). There are more women who do not experience any child deaths at all, but this propor on is larger among white collar women. There are also more women that experiencing many child deaths, among both white-and blue-collar women, but the propor on of blue-collar women that experience high numbers of deaths is higher than among white collar women.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the rela onship between parental SES (HISCLASS-5) and the risk of child death (lower panel) in Zeeland, the Netherlands, 1835-1918. The figure shows the hazard rate of mortality before the fi h birthyear for SES groups indicated in the panel heading in comparison to the children of unskilled workers (lower managers, professionals, and clergy). Analyses are separated by children's birth cohort. I include five socioeconomic status groups, in reference to children from unskilled workers: Higher managers and professionals, lower managers, medium skilled workers, farmers and lower skilled workers. A large difference in the mortality hazard becomes apparent already for the birth cohort 1835-1859. Children from all SES groups have significantly lower mortality than children of unskilled workers, except children from lower skilled workers' families, where the difference is not significant 1835-1879 and from 1880, mortality is significantly higher than among children of unskilled workers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Intergenera onal transmission of inequality in infant and child mortality</head><p>Next, I show the overall intergenera onal correla on in child mortality in families, using clustered Cox propor onal hazard models of survival between birth and the fi h birthday. Observa ons are censored at age five. The main independent variables are sibling deaths of the mother and the father and SES of the households of origin of mother and father. Analyses are clustered on the mother level to es mate standard errors that are robust for the fact that the same parents can have mul ple observed children in the sample. In Model 1 (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>), only sibling deaths of the father and the mother are included, next to a range of control variables: sex and birth year of the child, birth order and birth interval, age of the mother, death of the father and mother before the child's fi h birthday or death.</p><p>The results show that the hazard ra o of child mortality is higher if parents are from sibling groups with several child deaths before age 5. Especially if there were three or more deaths among the siblings, the risk of death of the child is higher. Mother's sibling deaths are more strongly related to child mortality than father's sibling deaths before age 5. In Model 2, SES of the household of origin is included, as well as SES of the household of origin of the father and the mother. I find that the rela on between child mortality among parents' siblings persists, but effect es mates are smaller than previously, although the differences are not significant. Thus, the intergenera onal persistence in child mortality is not explained by the socioeconomic status of the parents. I include SES of the grandparents (maternal and paternal) and the children's households of origin, using father's social class based on his recorded occupa on. While in the analyses presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> a finer SES-scale was used, here the dis nc on between white collar (higher and lower managers and professionals), and blue-collar workers (medium skilled workers, lower skilled workers, and unskilled workers) is reported. Farmers and individuals with missing values are reported separately. Results are shown in Supplementary Material Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">S2</ref>. Model 1 shows the effects of the dichotomized parental siblings' child mortality on the hazard ra o of mortality before age 5 among their children. I control for a range of characteris cs including parental and grandparental SES. As before, the HR of mortality for children whose parents had elevated child mortality among their own siblings is higher. For the interac on with SES of the household of origin, I expected that children at the greatest risk of before-5 mortality would be children who are from a deprived household, whereas more resources (a higher SES) could ameliorate the risk of high child loss in previous genera ons. However, the findings show that while parental SES again explains part of the intergenera onal persistence in child loss, there is no evidence for an interac on between intergenera onal persistence in child loss and SES. Intergenera onal persistence of child mortality is thus not stronger for blue collar workers than for white collar workers.  Figure notes: HR is hazard ra o from Cox Propor onal Hazard (survival) models, in reference to children of unskilled workers.</p><p>Analyses are by birth cohort and control for sex, birth year, birth order, mother age at birth, short interval to preceding birth, and father and mother's death before the child's fi h birthday or own death. Source: LINKS Zeeland. For the es mates, see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S1</ref>. Number of individuals (deaths) by birth cohort; Birth cohort 1835-1859 19,302 (6,787); Birth cohort 1860-1879 61,588 (18,444); Birth cohort 1880-1899 76,470 (16,734); Birth cohort <ref type="bibr">1900-1914 59,970 (9,685)</ref>. Source: Author calcula ons, LINKS Zeeland</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Time-trend in intergenera onal persistence of child mortality</head><p>In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>, the intergenera onal persistence of child mortality over me is shown for four birth cohorts: <ref type="bibr">1835-1859, 1860-1879, 1880-1899 and 1900-1914.</ref> Mother's and father's sibling deaths before age 5 are included simultaneously and in Model 2, a control is added for socioeconomic status as well as for socioeconomic status of the household of origin (uncontrolled effects can be found in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">S3A</ref> and <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">S3B</ref> for fathers and mothers, respec vely). Between the first and the last birth cohort, profound change occurred in the survival chances of young children. The child mortality rate (before the fi h birthday) was almost halved, and year-to-year varia on strongly reduced given declining impact of epidemic disease on child mortality in this period (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). As discussed above, socioeconomic factors remained an important predictor of child mortality (see Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>). I find that the same applies for intergenera onal persistence of child mortality: Over me, whether mothers and fathers originated from a family in which several children died before age 5 remains a significant predictor of child mortality among their own children.</p><p>Especially child mortality among the mother's siblings is consistently a strong predictor of child mortality. Par cularly if child mortality was high (more than two child deaths among mother's siblings), the hazard ra o of mortality among her children was high. For sibling deaths among father's siblings, a reduc on in the effect is observed over me, whereby less high child mortality among his siblings is no longer a significant predictor for the birth cohort 1860 -1879. If there were more than two childhood deaths among his siblings, the hazard ra o of mortality among his children is significantly higher over the en re period studied here, but the effect decreases with me and is significantly less strong for the birth cohorts <ref type="bibr">1880-1899 and 1900-1914. 4.4</ref> Change in the role of intergenera onal persistence of child loss and SES over me Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows intergenera onal persistence of child mortality and the intergenera onal persistence of child mortality over me a er controlling for SES for the four birth cohorts. Although effects are somewhat a enuated for each birth cohort a er controlling for SES, socioeconomic status of the parents' family of origin and the family in which the child grows up do not significantly reduce the intergenera onal transmission of child mortality. Thus, inequali es accumulate. The highest child mortality is found with families carrying the dual burden of low SES and high child mortality in previous genera ons. At the same me, I did not find evidence for a sta s cally significant interac on effect between social status and high mortality in the previous genera on (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">S2</ref>). Moreover, the hazard ra o of child mortality in rela on to child mortality in the family of origin is rela vely stable between periods (see Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>), except for fathers, for whom the effect appears stronger in the first birth cohort included than for later birth cohorts.  9,685 HR is hazard ra o from Cox Propor onal Hazard (survival) models. Analyses are by birth cohort and control for sex, birth order, mother age at birth, short interval to preceding birth, father and mother's death before the child's fi h birthday or own death, HISCLASS of the parents of the child, and HISCLASS of the parents' families of origin. The models are clustered at the mother level to provide robust standard errors. Source: LINKS Zeeland.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 4. Effect of intergenera onal transmission of child mortality over me</head><p>Source: LINKS Zeeland. Es mates of the effect of parents' sibling deaths before age 5 on the hazard of child death before age 5. Filled lines are bivariate es mates, do ed lines are controlled for socioeconomic status (HISCLASS) of the parents of the child, of the parents' families of origin, sex, birth interval, birth order, parental death before age 5 or death of the child, and mother age at birth. Uncontrolled effects can be found in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">S3A</ref> (mothers) and S3B (fathers). Controlled effects can be found above in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.</p><p>To show changes in the absolute effect over me, I compute the average marginal effect on a child death over me, by mother and father's number of sibling deaths before age 5. Average marginal effects are based on a logis c regression analysis of the likelihood of death before age 5. The chance of a child death before age 5 increases with around 4 percentage points on average over the study period if the mother's family of origin experienced two or more child deaths before age 5. In the first study period, the increase is 7 percentage points if the mother lost two siblings under age 5. The effect size decreases somewhat over me but in the final period remains significant at 3 percentage points by the final period (see Table <ref type="table">4</ref>). For fathers, like before, effects are somewhat weaker and not always significant for the loss of one sibling before age 5. The average marginal effect of two or more sibling deaths remains linked most consistently to an increase in the likelihood of death before age 5 of about 2 percentage points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Predicted probabili es</head><p>Regarding absolute chances of a child death, predicted probabili es based on the average marginal effects shown in Table <ref type="table">4</ref> illustrate the differences between different types of families. For a boy with an average-aged mother, a birth interval to the previous child that's not par cularly short, with birth order 3, and whose father is a low-skilled worker, the probability of death before age 5 is 22.8% if the mother had no sibling deaths. This figure increases to 27.4% if she had two or more sibling deaths. Both es mates are for a boy whose father had no sibling deaths. For fathers, the probability rises from 22.8% to 25.1% if the father's family of origin experienced two or more sibling deaths. If neither parent had had a sibling death before age 5, and they came from a high socioeconomic status group and maintained this status in adulthood, the predicted probability of a child death was only 17.8%. The differences between families in the chance of a child death were large, both between the poor and the rich, and between families with a history of increased child deaths and without such a family history. Table <ref type="table">4</ref>. Average marginal effects from logit models of child death before age 5 by parental sibling child mortality under age 5, in Zeeland, the Netherlands,  Analyses are by birth cohort and control for sex, parents' HISCLASS, HISCLASS of the families of origin of the parents, birth order, short birth interval, and mother age at first birth. Source: LINKS Zeeland.</p><p>Any birth cohort Cohort 1835-1859 Cohort 1860-1879 Cohort 1880-1899 Cohort 1900-1914 95% CI 95% CI 95% CI 95% CI 95% CI AME Low Upp AME Low Upp AME Low Upp AME Low Upp AME Low Upp Mother's sibling mortality: None Ref Ref Ref Ref Ref 1 sibling death .014 .009 .019 .022 .002 .041 .016 .005 .027 .010 .001 .019 .010 .001 .018 2 sibling deaths .018 .013 .024 .026 .005 .047 .018 .006 .030 .014 .005 .023 .016 .007 .025 &gt; 2 sibling deaths .045 .041 .050 .069 .051 .087 .052 .042 .062 .035 .027 .043 .030 .022 .038 Father's sibling mortality: None Ref Ref Ref Ref Ref 1 sibling death .005 .000 .010 .025 .006 .044 .003 -.008 .014 .004 -.005 .013 .000 -.008 .009 2 sibling deaths .010 .005 .016 .043 .022 .064 .006 -.005 .018 .010 .001 .020 .005 -.004 .014 &gt; 2 sibling deaths .023 .018 .027 .056 .038 .074 .023 .013 .033 .014 .006 .022 .018 .010 .026 HISCLASS: Unskilled workers Ref Ref Ref Ref Ref Higher occ. -.032 -.042 -.023 -.032 -.063 -.002 -.042 -.060 -.024 -.025 -.041 -.009 -.019 -.037 .000 Skilled workers -.031 -.037 -.025 -.031 -.055 -.007 -.018 -.030 -.005 -.007 -.017 .003 -.010 -.020 .000 Medium skilled -.035 -.042 -.028 -.050 -.075 -.025 -.024 -.038 -.010 -.015 -.027 -.004 -.007 -.018 .005 Lower skilled -.057 -.063 -.051 -.055 -.078 -.031 -.059 -.071 -.046 -.040 -.050 -.030 -.018 -.028 -.008 Farmers -.011 -.018 -.004 -.009 -.039 .022 .007 -.009 .023 .009 -.004 .021 .019 .007 .030 Missing -.035 -.041 -.029 -.030 -.053 -.008 -.033 -.045 -.022 -.019 -.028 -.009 -.003 -.013 .006 N mothers 43,312 5,186 14,762 20,074 19,938 N fathers 42,418 5,118 14,495 19,852 19,859 N children 217,330 19,302 61,588 76,470 59,970 Deaths age 0-5 51,650 6,787 18,444 16,743 9,685</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Robustness checks</head><p>The main results are tested for robustness using a somewhat different selec on of families from the data by selec ng only selected children whose parents have two or more known siblings (are from families of at least three children), so that all parents in the analyses are at risk for having at least 2 sibling deaths. This results in the selec on of 199,060 children (a reduc on of 18,249 children or about 8 percent).</p><p>Results can be found in the Supplementary Material (Table <ref type="table">S4</ref>) and are almost iden cal to the analyses presented here. Next, I include sibling mortality as a propor on of the number of children in the family of origin of the parents. Results are in Table <ref type="table">S5</ref>. Effects are somewhat stronger in this single indicator of childhood mortality among the siblings of the parents, but results are similar: increased mortality for children whose mothers and fathers came from a high-childhood-mortality family, with stronger effects for mothers than fathers, and effects that persist over me. These models are not chosen as the main model as they are less ve in their interpreta on and the propor on of child deaths depends on the number of siblings that mothers and fathers have.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion and discussion</head><p>Child mortality was distributed unequally between families, and this inequality persisted between genera ons in historical the Netherlands. Analyses based on full popula on family recons tu on data (LINKS) for a province in the Netherlands, Zeeland, 1835-1919 show that both socioeconomic status and parents' families' level of child mortality contribute to the risk of child death before age 5. Children of mothers and fathers who experienced a larger number of sibling child deaths had an increased risk of death before their own fi h birthday. Importantly, intergenera onal persistence of child mortality is not driven by social class of parents or grandparents. Inequali es accumulate, as low-SES families of which both parents originated from high mortality families had the highest level of mortality.</p><p>Like earlier authors, I show that there is a social gradient in child mortality in the period studied. Higher socioeconomic status groups had lower child mortality than unskilled and lower-skilled workers. Effects are largely similar over me, except for lower skilled workers, among whom mortality becomes even higher than among unskilled workers in the last two periods studied here. In historical the Netherlands, social mobility was low <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Knigge 2016</ref>) so that low SES across genera ons could contribute to the intergenera onal persistence of child mortality. Yet, high risk of child death is not explained by socioeconomic characteris cs of the family in which a child grows up, nor their grandparents' socioeconomic status.</p><p>However, there is a correla on between grandparental socioeconomic status and grandchild hazard of mortality before age 5, even a er controlling for socioeconomic status of the household in which the child grows up, using occupa on of the father. Grandparental effects on grandchildren, for example social status a ainment of grandchildren, have in the past been interpreted as a broad effect of grandparental resources and social networks on grandchildren <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Mare and Song 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Knigge 2016)</ref>. Such studies have shown that socioeconomic factors affect social status a ainment not just over one genera on -father to child -but also over several genera ons of rela ves -grandfather to grandchild <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Dribe and Helgertz 2016)</ref>. Such effects persist even if grandparents and children never met nor if the compe on grandparental resources is larger, so that such residual effects of socioeconomic status can point to imprecisely measured socioeconomic status effects that work through resources of the family of origin of the child <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Helgertz and Dribe 2022)</ref>. If only the occupa on of the father is included, unexplained variance because of measurement error could be captured by grandparental measurements of social status <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Engzell, Mood, and Jonsson 2020)</ref>. Similarly, the contribu on of grandparents' social status to grandchild survival, a er considering the socioeconomic status of the parents, may be related to imprecise measurements of parents' SES. Yet, grandparents could also have contributed resources, knowledge and help in mes of need. Further research should establish what drives this rela onship.</p><p>Over me, child mortality declined strongly in the Netherlands. Intergenera onal transmission effects are found even when child mortality had declined strongly, par cularly for women. For mothers to children, effects remained largely similar over me, with increased mortality par cularly for children of mothers origina ng from families where several child deaths occurred among their siblings. This finding implies that even among women with the strongest disadvantage -in terms of both a low socioeconomic status and elevated mortality in their household of origin -the absolute risk of losing their young children decreased over me. Yet, compared to other families in the popula on, these women and their children remained at the strongest disadvantage over me. For fathers, the magnitude of the intergenera onal effect declined when child mortality rates decreased, par cularly for more average experiences of sibling mortality (e.g. loss of one or two siblings in childhood).</p><p>It is unclear why the intergenera onal persistence of child mortality is stronger from mother to her children than from father to his children. Commonly, studies inves ga ng persistence of social status find the opposite: a stronger intergenera onal persistence from father to son or daughter than from mother to son or daughter <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Dribe and Helgertz 2016)</ref>, although some work has shown a stronger influence of maternal economic par cipa on on her daughter's than sons' status a ainment (Brea-Mar nez 2023). In this work, a higher hazard ra o of mortality is observed for children whose mothers came from high-mortality households than for children whose fathers originated from high mortality households. A possible reason is the larger role for women in caretaking of children in this period <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Janssens 1997)</ref>, and possibly, girls learned child-care prac ces such as unsuitable feeding prac ces in the household of origin and used these for their own children (Das Gupta 1990). The possible help of grandmothers, for example a er childbirth or when children were sick, could be gendered, and a previous literature has established that in some contexts the help of a mother's own mother could make a crucial difference for child survival in historical Europe <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Sear and Mace 2008)</ref>. In families where grandmothers raised their children in unfavorable condi ons, indicated by her own high child loss, they may neither have had the health nor knowledge to assist their daughters and daughters in law with the care of their grandchildren -and instead, their outdated knowledge or own need of help may have been a burden on their daughters and daughters in law.</p><p>Studying the me-trend in intergenera onal persistence of high mortality shows the long-term development in equality of opportunity. Over me, high mortality in the families of origin of the mother and father show a persistent correla on to the mortality hazard of young children, despite sibling child deaths becoming less common. Thus, intergenera onal persistence of high child mortality is a clear marker of inequality in historical the Netherlands. To study such intergenera onal inequali es in other contexts, such as contemporarily developed socie es, it is essen al to study mortality over a broader age range as mortality at young ages contemporarily tends to be mercifully low. In children's health, however, broader pa erns of intergenera onal persistence may s ll be a key indicator of inequality in the standard of living.</p><p>There are some drawbacks to this study. First, the sta s cal analysis relied on data origina ng from linked indexes of civil cer ficates. Individuals are not con nuously observed in registers, as they would with, for example, a church or state popula on register. Although earlier work has shown that for this area and period the resul ng life course and family reconstruc ons generally reflect the result from con nuous popula on register data (van den <ref type="bibr">Berg et al. 2021)</ref>, important characteris cs of individuals and their families are not included in these linked vital event data, including religion, migra on movements, and household income. Second, families across Zeeland have been included, so that regional migrants -who moved for marriage or work opportuni es, but not over long distances -can be tracked. Spa al and geographic differences in inequality in child deaths over me were not included in this work. The local condi ons for children to grow up in could have been quite different between places of residence, given that Zeeland consists of islands with somewhat different economic opportuni es and physical limita ons such as access to safe drinking water. Together, the reasons for accumula on of high child mortality across genera ons beyond poverty and socioeconomic status remain therefore somewhat of a black box. Yet, as was argued previously, the overall accumula on of inequali es in the likelihood of early child death across me is an important indicator of families' rela ve standard of being and inequality in opportunity in socie es.</p><p>In a previous study of intergenera onal persistence in child mortality, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Lu and Vogl (Lu and Vogl 2023)</ref> argue that studying the topic of child concentra on in mortality is important to study inequality in bereavement. I argue here that it is important to study intergenera onal persistence as an indicator of inequality in mortality itself. Some families are more likely to experience child mortality and to have poor health. This phenomenon should not solely be inves gated from a socioeconomic perspec ve (the social gradient in mortality) or in rela on to other social and socioeconomic indicators but is worthy of a en on and a measurement of inequality in the living standard and the distribu on of mortality in itself. Addressing the trend in intergenera onal persistence in mortality, and differences between contexts, serves as a measurement of inequality between places and over me.</p><p>In conclusion, intergenera onal persistence of (high) mortality, as shown in this work, highlights the lack of opportunity for children to achieve a long life already at the me of their birth, given in which family they were born. Intergenera onal persistence in young age mortality is of pressing importance as it eradicates opportuni es for individuals to live a long and healthy life before their lives have even fully started. This paper shows evidence that there was inequality of opportunity in young-age survival which persisted over me in 19 th and early 20 th century the Netherlands. Whether this trend con nued later in the 20 th and 21 st century and whether it generalizes to mortality at older ages or health of children are important avenues for future research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Acknowledgements</head><p>The author gratefully acknowledges funding by Riksbankens Jubileumsfonden (An Age Old Advantage, P21-0139). The data set is freely available from HSN, see: (R. J. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Mourits et al. 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr">R. Mourits, Van Dijk, and Mandemakers 2020)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Data availability statement</head><p>Data is available from the Ins tute of Social History, Amsterdam, Netherlands, here:</p><p>h ps://hdl.handle.net/10622/QUJNCD. Code and replica on files available upon request. 8. References Antonovsky, Aaron, and Judith Bernstein. 1967. "Social Class and Infant Mortality." Social Science &amp; Medicine 11 (8): 453-70. h ps://doi.org/10.1016/0037-7856(77)90022-1. Berg, Niels van den, Ingrid K. van Dijk, Rick J. Mourits, P. Eline Slagboom, Angelique A. P. O. Janssens, and Kees Mandemakers. 2021. "Families in Comparison: An Individual-Level Comparison of Figure A2. CMR in the popula on of Zeeland and in the selected sample, birth cohorts 1835-1914 Child mortality rate per 1000 liveborn children in the year of observation. Source: author calculations, LINKS Zeeland</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Infant and child mortality and s llbirth rates 1835-1913 (top panel) and frequency of sibling deaths over me (bo om panel)</figDesc><graphic coords="3,92.52,297.60,327.96,196.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Expected and observed child loss clustering in families (Panel A) and observed child loss by SES (Panel B) for all birth cohorts.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,92.52,231.60,399.48,199.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Filled</head><figDesc>Figure 3. Socioeconomic status and HR of child mortality across birth cohorts</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure A1 .</head><label>A1</label><figDesc>Figure A1. Selec on of index persons</figDesc><graphic coords="21,92.28,80.16,297.12,314.76" type="vector_box" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="22,92.52,80.28,426.48,255.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Descrip ve sta s cs</figDesc><table><row><cell>All</cell><cell cols="3">Index persons Fathers Mothers</cell></row><row><cell>Year of birth</cell><cell>1886</cell><cell>1853</cell><cell>1855</cell></row><row><cell>HISCLASS family of origin</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Higher occupa ons</cell><cell>4.27</cell><cell>7.70</cell><cell>7.52</cell></row><row><cell>Higher skilled workers</cell><cell>16.20</cell><cell>12,00</cell><cell>11.81</cell></row><row><cell>Medium skilled workers</cell><cell>11.96</cell><cell>10.79</cell><cell>9.77</cell></row><row><cell>Lower skilled workers</cell><cell>8.81</cell><cell>18.33</cell><cell>18.24</cell></row><row><cell>Farmers</cell><cell>17.12</cell><cell>7.20</cell><cell>6.86</cell></row><row><cell>Missing</cell><cell>16.20</cell><cell>28.71</cell><cell>29.97</cell></row><row><cell>Unskilled workers</cell><cell>25.45</cell><cell>15.27</cell><cell>15.83</cell></row><row><cell>Parent variables</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sibship size</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>8.08</cell><cell>8.11</cell></row><row><cell>Sibling child deaths (age 0-5)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>None</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>21.29</cell><cell>20.46</cell></row><row><cell>1 sibling child death</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>24.68</cell><cell>24.20</cell></row><row><cell>2 sibling child deaths</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>18.75</cell><cell>18.71</cell></row><row><cell>More than 2 sibling child deaths</cell><cell></cell><cell>35.28</cell><cell>36.63</cell></row><row><cell>Child variables</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex: Girl</cell><cell>48.83</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Birth order</cell><cell>4.36</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Twin birth</cell><cell>2.58</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Birth cohort</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1835-1859</cell><cell>28.34</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>1860-1879</cell><cell>35.19</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>1880-1899</cell><cell>27.59</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>1900-1914</cell><cell>28.34</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Mother age at birth</cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Age 13-20</cell><cell>2.82</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Age 21-29</cell><cell>47.39</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Age 30-34</cell><cell>25.86</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Age 35-50</cell><cell>23.93</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Short interval to preceding birth</cell><cell>34.56</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Father death before age 5</cell><cell>2.28</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Mother death before age 5</cell><cell>2.60</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Unique individuals</cell><cell cols="2">217,330 42,418</cell><cell>43,312</cell></row><row><cell>Deaths before age 5</cell><cell>23.76</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: Author calcula ons, LINKS Zeeland</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Cox propor onal hazard models of child mortality age 0-5 by parental sibling child mortality age 0-5 in Zeeland, theNetherlands, 1834Netherlands,  -1918       HR is hazard ra o from Cox Propor onal Hazard (survival) models. Analyses by birth cohort and control for sex, birth order, mother age at birth, short interval to preceding birth, and father and mother's death before the child's fi h or own death. The models are clustered at the level of the mother to provide robust standard errors. Source: LINKS Zeeland.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Model 1 95% CI</cell><cell cols="2">Model 2 95% CI</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>HR</cell><cell cols="2">Lower Upper HR</cell><cell cols="2">Lower Upper</cell></row><row><cell>Mother's sibling mortality: None</cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 sibling death 1.074</cell><cell>1.041</cell><cell>1.109 1.069</cell><cell>1.036</cell><cell>1.103</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2 sibling deaths 1.105</cell><cell>1.068</cell><cell>1.143 1.092</cell><cell>1.056</cell><cell>1.129</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">More than 2 sibling deaths 1.257</cell><cell>1.221</cell><cell>1.293 1.235</cell><cell>1.200</cell><cell>1.270</cell></row><row><cell>Mother's childhood SES: Unskilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Higher occupa ons</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.954</cell><cell>0.913</cell><cell>0.996</cell></row><row><cell>Skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.957</cell><cell>0.922</cell><cell>0.992</cell></row><row><cell>Medium skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.002</cell><cell>0.964</cell><cell>1.040</cell></row><row><cell>Lower skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.939</cell><cell>0.908</cell><cell>0.971</cell></row><row><cell>Farmers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.064</cell><cell>1.019</cell><cell>1.111</cell></row><row><cell>Missing</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.983</cell><cell>0.952</cell><cell>1.015</cell></row><row><cell>Father's sibling mortality: None</cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 sibling death 1.034</cell><cell>1.002</cell><cell>1.066 1.027</cell><cell>0.996</cell><cell>1.059</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2 sibling deaths 1.066</cell><cell>1.031</cell><cell>1.102 1.057</cell><cell>1.022</cell><cell>1.092</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">More than 2 sibling deaths 1.133</cell><cell>1.101</cell><cell>1.166 1.116</cell><cell>1.085</cell><cell>1.148</cell></row><row><cell>Father's childhood SES: Unskilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Higher occupa ons</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.863</cell><cell>0.826</cell><cell>0.902</cell></row><row><cell>Skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.929</cell><cell>0.894</cell><cell>0.965</cell></row><row><cell>Medium skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.951</cell><cell>0.914</cell><cell>0.990</cell></row><row><cell>Lower skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.937</cell><cell>0.905</cell><cell>0.969</cell></row><row><cell>Farmers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.023</cell><cell>0.980</cell><cell>1.067</cell></row><row><cell>Missing</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.962</cell><cell>0.931</cell><cell>0.995</cell></row><row><cell>HISCLASS: Unskilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Higher occupa ons</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.864</cell><cell>0.818</cell><cell>0.912</cell></row><row><cell>Skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.945</cell><cell>0.913</cell><cell>0.978</cell></row><row><cell>Medium skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.910</cell><cell>0.875</cell><cell>0.947</cell></row><row><cell>Lower skilled workers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.819</cell><cell>0.789</cell><cell>0.849</cell></row><row><cell>Farmers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.049</cell><cell>1.009</cell><cell>1.091</cell></row><row><cell>Missing</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.913</cell><cell>0.883</cell><cell>0.944</cell></row><row><cell>N mothers</cell><cell>43,312</cell><cell></cell><cell>43,312</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>N fathers</cell><cell>42,418</cell><cell></cell><cell>42,418</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>N children</cell><cell>217,330</cell><cell></cell><cell>217,330</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Deaths age 0-5</cell><cell>51,650</cell><cell></cell><cell>51,650</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Cox propor onal hazard models of child mortality age 0-5 by parental sibling child mortality age 0-5 in Zeeland, theNetherlands, 1834Netherlands,  -1914       </figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Birth cohort 1835-1859</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Birth cohort 1860-1879</cell><cell cols="3">Birth cohort 1880-1899</cell><cell cols="3">Birth cohort 1900-1914</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>95% CI</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>HR</cell><cell>Low</cell><cell>Upp</cell><cell>HR</cell><cell>Low</cell><cell>Upp</cell><cell>HR</cell><cell>Low</cell><cell>Upp</cell><cell>HR</cell><cell>Low</cell><cell>Upp</cell></row><row><cell>Mother's sibling mortality:</cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>None</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 sibling death 1.086</cell><cell>1.002</cell><cell>1.177</cell><cell>1.066</cell><cell>1.012</cell><cell>1.124</cell><cell>1.051</cell><cell>0.996</cell><cell>1.109</cell><cell>1.074</cell><cell>1.005</cell><cell>1.147</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2 sibling deaths 1.100</cell><cell>1.009</cell><cell>1.199</cell><cell>1.078</cell><cell>1.020</cell><cell>1.139</cell><cell>1.076</cell><cell>1.017</cell><cell>1.138</cell><cell>1.119</cell><cell>1.042</cell><cell>1.202</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">&gt; 2 sibling deaths 1.276</cell><cell>1.186</cell><cell>1.372</cell><cell>1.238</cell><cell>1.181</cell><cell>1.297</cell><cell>1.199</cell><cell>1.142</cell><cell>1.258</cell><cell>1.223</cell><cell>1.150</cell><cell>1.300</cell></row><row><cell>Father's sibling mortality:</cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>None</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 sibling death 1.099</cell><cell>1.018</cell><cell>1.187</cell><cell>1.013</cell><cell>0.963</cell><cell>1.065</cell><cell>1.013</cell><cell>0.962</cell><cell>1.067</cell><cell>0.999</cell><cell>0.935</cell><cell>1.066</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2 sibling deaths 1.165</cell><cell>1.073</cell><cell>1.264</cell><cell>1.021</cell><cell>0.967</cell><cell>1.079</cell><cell>1.054</cell><cell>0.996</cell><cell>1.114</cell><cell>1.026</cell><cell>0.957</cell><cell>1.101</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">&gt; 2 sibling deaths 1.217</cell><cell>1.130</cell><cell>1.310</cell><cell>1.099</cell><cell>1.050</cell><cell>1.150</cell><cell>1.069</cell><cell>1.019</cell><cell>1.122</cell><cell>1.122</cell><cell>1.056</cell><cell>1.192</cell></row><row><cell>HISCLASS: Unskilled workers</cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ref</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Higher occupa ons 0.982</cell><cell>0.892</cell><cell>1.081</cell><cell>0.853</cell><cell>0.78</cell><cell>0.933</cell><cell>0.874</cell><cell>0.793</cell><cell>0.964</cell><cell>0.878</cell><cell>0.751</cell><cell>1.025</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Skilled workers 0.941</cell><cell>0.848</cell><cell>1.045</cell><cell>0.957</cell><cell>0.904</cell><cell>1.013</cell><cell>0.970</cell><cell>0.916</cell><cell>1.028</cell><cell>0.930</cell><cell>0.863</cell><cell>1.002</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Medium skilled workers 0.957</cell><cell>0.862</cell><cell>1.063</cell><cell>0.918</cell><cell>0.861</cell><cell>0.978</cell><cell>0.930</cell><cell>0.869</cell><cell>0.996</cell><cell>0.954</cell><cell>0.877</cell><cell>1.038</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Lower skilled workers 0.961</cell><cell>0.883</cell><cell>1.045</cell><cell>0.801</cell><cell>0.755</cell><cell>0.850</cell><cell>0.814</cell><cell>0.764</cell><cell>0.867</cell><cell>0.882</cell><cell>0.814</cell><cell>0.955</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Farmers 1.059</cell><cell>0.940</cell><cell>1.192</cell><cell>1.039</cell><cell>0.972</cell><cell>1.110</cell><cell>1.058</cell><cell>0.989</cell><cell>1.131</cell><cell>1.129</cell><cell>1.043</cell><cell>1.221</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Missing 0.938</cell><cell>0.863</cell><cell>1.019</cell><cell>0.891</cell><cell>0.844</cell><cell>0.940</cell><cell>0.914</cell><cell>0.865</cell><cell>0.967</cell><cell>0.980</cell><cell>0.910</cell><cell>1.055</cell></row><row><cell>N mothers</cell><cell>5,186</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>14,762</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>20,074</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>19,938</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>N fathers</cell><cell>5,118</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>14,495</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>19,852</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>19,859</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>N children</cell><cell>19,302</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>61,588</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>76,470</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>59,970</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Deaths age 0-5</cell><cell>6,787</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>18,444</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>16,734</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>The percentage of index persons without a known death date or other civil event linked increases from 15.0% in the birth cohort 1835-1860 to 36.8% for index persons born a er 1900. This is expected, as follow-up is shorter for the last-born birth cohorts, and increases our confidence that a large majority of the individuals for whom no date of death is available survived their early childhood.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>available here: h ps://hdl.handle.net/10622/QUJNCD Code and replica on files available upon request</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>9. Appendix A1. Figure <ref type="figure">A1</ref>. Selec on of index persons A2. Figure <ref type="figure">A2</ref>. CMR in the popula on of Zeeland and in the selected sample, birth cohorts 1835-1914 10. Supplementary material S1: Cox propor onal hazard models of child mortality age 0-5 by parental SES, age 0-5 in Zeeland, the Netherlands, 1834-1919 S2: Cox propor onal hazard models of child mortality age 0-5 by parental sibling child mortality and SES, age 0-5 in Zeeland, the Netherlands, 1834-1919 S3: Table <ref type="table">S3A</ref>: Mothers' sibling mortality and child mortality over me with and without controls in Zeeland, Netherlands. Table <ref type="table">S3B</ref>: Fathers' sibling mortality and child mortality over me with and without controls in Zeeland, Netherlands S4: Cox propor onal hazard models of child mortality age 0-5 by parental sibling child mortality age 0-5 in Zeeland, the Netherlands, 1834-1914 for children of parents with more than two siblings S5: Cox propor onal hazard models of child mortality age 0-5 by parental sibling child mortality age 0-5 in Zeeland, the Netherlands, 1834-1914 with the number of sibling deaths of parents as a propor on of the number of siblings</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Life-Course and Family Reconstruc ons between Popula on and Vital Event Registers</title>
		<idno type="DOI">hps://doi.org/10.1080/00324728.2020.1718186</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Popula on Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="110" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intergenera onal Persistence in Health in Developing Countries: The Penalty of Gender Inequality?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sonia</forename><surname>Bhalotra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Samantha</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rawlings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">.org/10.1016/j.jpubeco.2010.10.016</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics, New Direc ons in the Economics of Welfare: Special Issue Celebra ng Nobel Laureate Amartya Sen&apos;s 75th Birthday</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Materfamilias: The Associa on of Mother&apos;s Work on Children&apos;s Absolute Income Mobility, Southern Sweden (1947-2015)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brea-Mar</forename><surname>Nez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gabriel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ereh/heac010</idno>
		<ptr target="//doi.org/10.1093/ereh/heac010" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Review of Economic History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Social History of Disease: Contextualizing the Rise and Fall of Social Inequali es in Cause-Specific Mortality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sean</forename><forename type="middle">A P</forename><surname>Clouston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marcie</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jo</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Phelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bruce</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Link</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13524-016-0495-5</idno>
		<ptr target="//doi.org/10.1007/s13524-016-0495-5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1631" to="1656" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Death Clustering, Mothers&apos; Educa on and the Determinants of Child Mortality in Rural Punjab, India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Das</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monica</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Popula Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Dijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Death and the Family</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Enschede</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early-Life Mortality Clustering in Families: A Literature Review</title>
		<idno type="DOI">hps://doi.org/10.1080/00324728.2018.1448434</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Popula on Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Like Mother, Like Daughter. Intergenera onal Transmission of Infant Mortality Clustering in Zeeland, the Netherlands, 1833-1912</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Dijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kees</forename><surname>Van</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mandemakers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.51964/hlcs9286</idno>
		<ptr target="//doi.org/10.51964/hlcs9286" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Historical Life Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-02">2018. February</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Las ng Impact of Grandfathers: Class, Occupa onal Status, and Earnings over Three Genera ons in Sweden 1815-2011</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mar</forename><surname>Dribe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>Helgertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Economic History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="969" to="1000" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inequality in Early Life: Social Class Differences in Childhood Mortality in Southern Sweden, 1815-1967</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mar</forename><surname>Dribe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Omar</forename><surname>Karlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/ehr.13089</idno>
		<ptr target="//doi.org/10.1111/ehr.13089" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic History Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="502" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infant Mortality in Mid-19th Century Amsterdam: Religion, Social Class, and Space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Ekamper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frans</forename><surname>Van Poppel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Popula Space and Place</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e2232</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">It&apos;s All about the Parents: Inequality Transmission across Three Genera ons in Sweden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Engzell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carina</forename><surname>Per</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Mood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jonsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Inequality in Infant Mortality: What Explains Varia on across Low and Middle Income Countries?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohammad</forename><surname>Hajizadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arijit</forename><surname>Nandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jody</forename><surname>Heymann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science &amp; Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do Grandfathers Ma er for Occupa onal and Earnings A ainment? Evidence from Swedish Register Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>Helgertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mar</forename><surname>Dribe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/esr/jcab029</idno>
		<ptr target="//doi.org/10.1093/esr/jcab029" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Baren Op Beveland: Vruchtbaarheid En Zuigelingenster e in Goes En Dorpen Gedurende de 19 e Eeuw</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hoogerhuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Wageningen University and Research</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Rise and Decline of the Male Breadwinner Family? An Overview of the Debate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Angélique</forename><surname>Janssens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">.org/10.1017/S0020859000114774</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Interna onal Review of Social History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond the Parental Genera on: The Influence of Grandfathers and Great-Grandfathers on Status A ainment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antonie</forename><surname>Knigge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13524-016-0486-6</idno>
		<ptr target="//doi.org/10.1007/s13524-016-0486-6" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1219" to="1244" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Condi ons As Fundamental Causes of Disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bruce</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Link</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jo</forename><surname>Phelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health and Social Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intergenera onal Persistence in Child Mortality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frances</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tom</forename><surname>Vogl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review: Insights</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HSNDB Occupa ons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kees</forename><surname>Mandemakers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Hornix</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rick</forename><surname>Mourits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sanne</forename><surname>Muurling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Corinne</forename><surname>Boter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Van Dijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ineke</forename><surname>Maas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="ps://hdl.handle.net/10622/88ZXD8" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IISH Data Collec on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Mobility in Mul ple Genera ons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Xi</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.rssm.2023.100806</idno>
		<ptr target="ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.rssm.2023.100806" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Social Stra fica on and Mobility, Robert D. Mare&apos;s Legacy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100806</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023-12">2023. December</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early life effects on socioeconomic performance and mortality in later life: full life course approach using contemporary and historical sources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bi</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Modin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ilona</forename><surname>Koupil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Denny</forename><surname>Vågerö</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.socscimed.2009.02.019</idno>
		<ptr target="//doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2009.02.019" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science &amp; Medicine, Part Special Issue</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1633" to="1640" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Impact of Early Twen eth Century Illegi macy across Three Genera ons. Longevity and Intergenera onal Health Correlates</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Analy cal Framework for the Study of Child Survival in Developing Countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mosley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lincoln</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Popula on and Development Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linked Civil Registry, Zeeland, Release 2017_01</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rick</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mourits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kees</forename><surname>Mandemakers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fons</forename><surname>Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zijdeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="ps://hdl.handle.net/10622/QUJNCD" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">IISH Data Collec on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">From Matched Cer ficates to Related Persons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mourits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Van Dijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kees</forename><surname>Mandemakers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sociaal-economische verschillen in zuigelingen-en kinderster e in Nederland, 1812-1912</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frans</forename><surname>Poppel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kees</forename><surname>Van</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mandemakers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bevolking &amp; Gezin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Childhood Condi ons That Predict Survival to Advanced Ages among African-Americans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Samuel</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Preston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Greg</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Drevenstedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science &amp; Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1246" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Short Lives: The Impact of Parental Death on Early-Life Mortality and Height in the Netherlands, 1850-1940</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Quanjer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Björn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ma</forename><surname>Van Dijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hias Rosenbaum-Feldbrügge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-01">2023. January, 10421550</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduc on: Intergenera onal Transmissions of Infant Mortality Using the Intermediate Data Structure (IDS)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luciana</forename><surname>Quaranta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hilde</forename><forename type="middle">Leikny</forename><surname>Sommerseth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Historical Life Course Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Case for Monitoring Life-Span Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alyson</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Raalte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Isaac</forename><surname>Van</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pekka</forename><surname>Sasson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mar Kainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6418</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1002" to="1004" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who Keeps Children Alive? A Review of the Effects of Kin on Child Survival</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rebecca</forename><surname>Sear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ruth</forename><surname>Mace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2007.10.001</idno>
		<ptr target=".org/10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2007.10.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolu on and Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mortality as an Indicator of Economic Success and Failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amartya</forename><surname>Sen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global Burden of Maternal Bereavement: Indicators of the Cumula ve Prevalence of Child Loss</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emily</forename><surname>Smith-Greenaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diego</forename><surname>Alburez-Gu Errez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jenny</forename><surname>Trinitapoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emilio</forename><surname>Zagheni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Global Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4837</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differen al Infant and Child Mortality in Three Dutch Regions, 1812-1909 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van Poppel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marianne</forename><surname>Frans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kees</forename><surname>Jonker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mandemakers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic History Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="272" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inherited Dimensions of Infant Mortality. Detec ng Signs of Dispropor onate Mortality Risks in Successive Genera ons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ma</forename><surname>Vandezande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Koenraad</forename><surname>Ma Hijs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The History of the Family</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is Breast Best? Evalua ng Breas eeding Pa erns and Causes of Infant Death in a Dutch Province in the Period 1875-1900</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Evelien</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Walhout</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The History of the Family</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
