<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">their Links to Prosociality Across the World</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Lusine</forename><surname>Grigoryan</surname></persName>
							<email>lusine.grigoryan@york.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of York</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">their Links to Prosociality Across the World</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4F38AD3EA62B3A090CA906D8F083B2A5</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>dignity culture</term>
					<term>honor culture</term>
					<term>face culture</term>
					<term>prosocial behavior</term>
					<term>reciprocity</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Cultural logic is a set of cultural scripts and patterns organized around a central theme. The cultural logics of dignity, honor, and face describe different ways of evaluating a person's worth and maintaining cooperation. These cultural logics vary in prevalence across cultures. In this study, we collaboratively develop and validate a measure capturing these cultural logics, which will allow us to map world cultures based on the prevalence of these logics. We will further explore the interrelations of dignity, honor, and face with prosocial behavior, values, moral beliefs, and religiosity as well as examine the generalizability of these relationships across cultures. Finally, we will explore historical antecedents (e.g., resource scarcity) and current correlates (e.g., inequality) of the country-level prevalence of these cultural logics. This study will generate a new dataset of country scores for dignity, honor, and face that will be available for future comparative research. It will also provide theoretical insights for researchers and practitioners interested in cooperation and social behavior within and between cultures.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>(In)Alienable Worth? Cultural Logics of Dignity, Honor, and Face and their Links to</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prosociality Across the World</head><p>Humans are an obligatorily interdependent species, meaning that, to survive, we must cooperate with other humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Brewer &amp; Caporael, 2006)</ref>. How do we ensure that others cooperate? Many researchers have argued that we developed morality as an answer to the problem of cooperation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Curry, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Curry et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Rai &amp; Fiske, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b77">Tomasello &amp; Vaish, 2013)</ref>. A large-scale study of the ethnographic records of 60 societies, varying from hunter-gatherer societies to modern states, found that certain forms of cooperation, such as group loyalty, reciprocity, or bravery, have a universally positive moral valence <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Curry et al., 2019)</ref>. Although people in different societies might generally agree on which kinds of behaviors are morally virtuous, the mechanisms of enforcing these behaviors vary <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Leung &amp; Cohen, 2011)</ref>. The cultural logics of dignity, honor, and face offer three different mechanisms for ensuring moral conduct and cooperation in societies.</p><p>The distinction between the cultural logics of dignity, honor, and face is a relatively new one <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Leung &amp; Cohen, 2011)</ref>, although each of these concepts has been studied independently for a long time, such as the Chinese concepts of "face" <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Hu, 1944)</ref>, honor and shame <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Peristiany, 1966)</ref>, or Kant's conceptualization of dignity <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Kant, 1785)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Leung and Cohen (2011)</ref> described a cultural logic as a "constellation of shared beliefs, values, behaviors, practices, and so on, that are organized around a central theme <ref type="bibr">" (p. 508)</ref>. They differentiated between the logics of dignity, honor, and face as alternative pathways to solve two main problems that all societies must address: the problem of a person's worth and the problem of cooperation, or social order. In the cultural logic of dignity, a person's worth is considered inalienable, and cooperation is governed by a set of internalized universal rules or principles. In the cultural logic of honor, a person's worth has an internal and an external component: "Honor must be claimed, and honor must be paid by others." <ref type="bibr">(Leung and Cohen, 2011, p. 509)</ref>. The cultural logic of honor typically prevails in environments where external authorities, such as governments, are not trusted to enforce universal rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Nowak et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Uskul &amp; Cross, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Here, individuals must prove that they are worthy of respect and cooperation by demonstrating both strong positive reciprocity (e.g., consistently fulfilling obligations such as paying one's debts) and strong negative reciprocity (e.g., retaliating against insults). In the cultural logic of face, a person's worth is largely ascribed to them by others. The focus is on how much respect one can claim based on the position they occupy in the societal hierarchy and how well they fulfill the requirements of that position <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Ho, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Kim &amp; Cohen, 2010)</ref>. In face cultures, cooperation is ensured by strong positive reciprocity norms. However, unlike in honor cultures, the group or the superior administers punishment, and direct negative reciprocity is disfavored as being disruptive to group harmony <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Leung &amp; Cohen, 2011)</ref>.</p><p>This study has three main goals. First, despite the potential value of these constructs as descriptors of cultural differences, their conceptualization and operationalization are still underdeveloped -there is no single broadly accepted definition of these cultural logics or a measure that would perform well across cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(van Osch et al., 2020)</ref>. Our first goal is to clarify the conceptualization and validate a measure of Dignity, Honor, and Face (DHF) logics across cultural contexts. Second, the lack of a cross-culturally validated measure also means that there are no country-level scores available for these cultural logics which could be used in cross-cultural research, similar to such scores for other dimensions of cultural difference, such as individualism-collectivism <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Hofstede, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Minkov &amp; Kaasa, 2022)</ref> or tightness-looseness <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Gelfand et al., 2011)</ref>. Our second goal is to collect data across a large number of countries and create an open database of the prevalence of DHF logics across world societies. Finally, cultural logics are theorized to be predictive of a range of values, behaviors, and beliefs relevant to human prosociality and cooperation, but these links have been sparsely studied. Our third goal is to identify both country-level and individual-level correlates and behavioral manifestations of these cultural logics. This study will contribute to the efforts to move beyond dichotomized conceptualizations of cultural differences (individualism vs. collectivism, East vs. West) and advance our understanding of human cooperation by describing and explaining the variation in strategies people across the world use to promote cooperation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theoretical Background</head><p>We will briefly outline different conceptualizations and measures of honor, dignity, and face as cultural logics proposed in earlier studies. We will begin with honor, which has been studied the most, continue with face, and end with dignity, which, as a cultural logic, has been studied the least.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Honor</head><p>Honor has been conceptualized as a value that comprises an individual's self-worth and their reputation in the community <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Pitt-Rivers, 1966)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Cross et al. (2014)</ref> asked participants in Türkiye and northern USA open-ended questions about the meaning of honor and identified three dimensions that described honor in both countries: self-respect, moral behavior, and social status/respect. Honor is a highly gendered construct: The set of standards to which men and women must conform are quite different, therefore a distinction can be made between masculine and feminine honor <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Guerra et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Mosquera, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Pomerantz et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Rodriguez Mosquera et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Vandello et al., 2009)</ref>. More recent research suggests that despite these different expectations, men and women in honor cultures have a shared understanding of what these standards are for each group, which makes it possible to capture honor culture norms with the same measure across genders <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Pomerantz et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Vignoles et al., 2024)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Figueredo et al. (2004)</ref> also distinguished between positive and negative reciprocity (revenge) and developed a measure to capture these two facets of honor. Finally, a number of studies suggest a distinction between individual and group-based honor <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Guerra et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Rodriguez Mosquera et al., 2002)</ref>. A recent literature review suggests that while individual honor predicts interpersonal outcomes, such as positive reciprocity or retaliation, group-based honor predicts intergroup outcomes, such as defensiveness and support for intergroup aggression <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">(Uskul et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Cultures of the Middle East and the Mediterranean region (e.g., Türkiye, Iran) have typically been described as honor cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">(Vignoles et al., 2024)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Ho (1976)</ref> defined face as "the respectability and/or deference which a person can claim for himself <ref type="bibr">[sic]</ref> from others, by virtue of the relative position he <ref type="bibr">[sic]</ref> occupies in his social network and the degree to which he <ref type="bibr">[sic]</ref> is judged to have functioned adequately in that position as well as acceptably in his <ref type="bibr">[sic]</ref> general conduct" (p. 883). According to Ho, the concept of face is Chinese in origin and is a literal translation of Chinese 臉 (liǎn) and 面子 (miànzi). Although both words can be translated as face, liǎn is more closely linked to moral conduct and character virtue, whereas miànzi is more closely linked to status and prestige. This distinction parallels <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Cross et al.'s (2014)</ref> distinction between moral behavior and social status. Another important distinction is made in face negotiation theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">(Ting-Toomey, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Ting-Toomey &amp; Kurogi, 1998)</ref>: Facework can be self-directed or other-directed, either aimed at preserving one's own or the other person's face and status. Similarly, drawing on <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Takata's (2000)</ref> work on self-construal, <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Park et al. (2017)</ref> differentiate between self-focused and other-focused relational selves. This distinction between self-face and other-face is similar to the distinction between individual and group-based honor, where the focus is either on the self or on the other. Cultures of the East Asian region (e.g., China, Japan) have typically been described as face cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Ho, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Lin &amp; Yamaguchi, 2008)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Face</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dignity</head><p>The Oxford English Dictionary defines dignity simply as "the quality of being worthy or honourable". However, the distinctive feature of dignity cultures is the belief that self-worth is inalienable and does not depend on others <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Leung &amp; Cohen, 2011)</ref>. This idea of the "inherent dignity of the human person" <ref type="bibr">(UN, 1966, p. 5)</ref> is foundational to the entirety of international human rights law (O'Mahony, 2012). However, dignity does not exist in isolation, nor is it asocial. Expressions such as being "treated with dignity" or "denied dignity" suggest that dignity has a social component, the same as honor and face. It, too, has the component of morality (if someone tries to give or take a bribe, they might be described as having no dignity) and status/respect (to treat someone with dignity is to treat them with respect). A recent set of studies conducted in Armenia <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Grigoryan &amp; Khachatryan, 2023)</ref> found two facets of dignity that parallel the distinction between self-concern and other-concern in honor and face studies. Self-oriented dignity reflects the autonomy component of this cultural logic (i.e., being guided by one's own moral standards of behavior), whereas other-oriented dignity reflects the focus on treating others with dignity. Cultures of the Western European region (e.g. the U.K. and Germany) have typically been described as dignity cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Maitner et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Smith et al., 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Integrated Conceptualization of the Cultural Logics</head><p>These three constructs have much in common. All three are concerned with moral conduct and character virtue. They all assume a certain set of standards to which individuals must conform. In the case of honor, these standards are gendered, in the case of face, they strongly depend on the status relations between the interaction partners, and in the case of dignity, these standards are internal rather than external. However, the presence of moral standards and the need to live up to them is a common element of all three. Each is also linked to status: Someone who has dignity, honor, or face can respect themselves and deserves respect from others (i.e., has higher status than someone who does not). The unique feature of dignity culture is the notion of inalienable worth and the focus on internal standards of moral behavior; for honor cultures, the unique feature is the strong norm of reciprocity, both positive and negative; and for face, it is the focus on how one fulfills the requirements of their social role and preserves group harmony. Each of these cultural logics has two facets, one self-oriented and one other-oriented. The two facets can have different consequences for interpersonal and intergroup behavior; for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Lun et al. (2023)</ref> found that across 24 nations, other-face concern was associated with positive outcomes, and self-face concern with negative outcomes in interpersonal conflicts.</p><p>At the individual level, throughout this paper, we conceptualize dignity, honor, and face as belief systems and operationalize them through the personal endorsement of beliefs and behaviors constituting each. At the societal level, we conceptualize dignity, honor, and face as cultural logics and operationalize them as perceptions of one's society's endorsement of beliefs and behaviors associated with each. Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Leung and Cohen (2011)</ref>, we describe these cultural logics as "ideal types".</p><p>Despite the recognition that certain regions or cultures are typically considered to align with one of the three logics, we assume that members of any given cultural or national group will endorse all three logics to some extent, and that any given culture will have high between-individual variability in personal endorsement of each of these logics. We provide descriptions of core beliefs and behaviors associated with each of the six constructs proposed here in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Present Research</head><p>In this section, we outline the hypotheses and research questions we aim to address in this study. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref> clarifies some key terms to facilitate understanding of the proposed hypotheses and proposed analysis. The hypotheses and analysis plan are summarized in the "Analysis Plan Summary" table in the Supplementary Materials (SM). Level 2 [between or cluster] Refers to a level of analysis in multilevel models where sample/country-level scores and variances are used for modeling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Two Facets of Dignity, Honor, and Face (H1)</head><p>Consistent with the literature, we propose that each of the cultural logics of dignity, honor, and face can be described either through a single latent factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">(Smith et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Vignoles et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b86">Yao et al., 2017)</ref>, each represented by two facets of self-concern and other-concern <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Grigoryan &amp; Khachatryan, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Lun et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b80">Uskul et al., 2023)</ref>. We therefore hypothesize that a hierarchical model with three higher-order factors of dignity, honor, and face, each represented by two facets of self-concern and other-concern, will appropriately describe the data (H1a). We also expect that this model will fit the data better than a 3-factor model that does not differentiate between the two facets of self-concern and other-concern (H1b). We will alternatively test a six-factor model in case the hierarchical model does not converge. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows the three alternative models. Additionally, we will test if the same factor structure holds at the individual and the sample level of analysis, and whether this factor structure is appropriate for both individual endorsement and perceived norms measures. Finally, we will use the alignment optimization procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Asparouhov &amp; Muthén, 2023)</ref> to establish the degree of invariance of this measure across countries. A. Proposed model B. Competing model </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cultural Logics and Prosocial Behavior (H2)</head><p>The proposed integrative view of dignity, honor, and face cultural logics suggests that all three serve the same function: regulating social behavior. Because prosociality is the cornerstone of group living and one of the most important areas where social behavior needs to be regulated, we would expect that the endorsement of the cultural logics of dignity, honor, and face is predictive of prosociality, but only if the focus is on the others rather than on the self. We therefore predict that the individual endorsement of the other-concern facet of all three cultural logics will predict higher prosociality towards strangers (H2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cross-Country Differences in Prosociality (H3)</head><p>An important question to consider when it comes to predicting prosociality across cultures is towards whom we are prosocial: A stranger whom we are unlikely to meet again, or someone who can potentially reciprocate (e.g., ingroup member; <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Levine et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Romano et al., 2021)</ref>? In this study, we will capture three types of social behavior: prosociality towards strangers in one-shot interactions, that is, universal prosociality, and positive and negative reciprocity towards strangers in repeated interactions. The rules-based, de-contextualized view of morality that is prevalent in dignity cultures is likely to be most beneficial for universal prosociality. However, dignity cultures are assumed to be individualistic <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Leung &amp; Cohen, 2011)</ref> and the evidence so far suggests that interdependent or collectivistic cultures might be more prosocial, although it is less clear when this prosociality extends beyond the ingroup and when it does not <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Feygina &amp; Henry, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Luria et al., 2015)</ref>. We therefore do not have a prediction for the prevalence of universal prosociality but will explore whether the cultural logics can explain differences in it. We expect positive reciprocity to be most prevalent in face and honor cultures, both of which can be described as collectivistic <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Feygina &amp; Henry, 2015)</ref>. Finally, negative reciprocity, or punishment of non-cooperation, is likely to be most prevalent in honor cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Jackson et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Nisbett &amp; Cohen, 1996</ref>; but see <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Gächter &amp; Herrmann, 2009)</ref>. We therefore predict that higher country-level honor and face logic scores will predict higher positive reciprocity (H3a and H3b) and higher country-level honor scores will predict higher negative reciprocity (H3c).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Criterion Validity (H4-H5)</head><p>As a validation check for our newly proposed measure, we will attempt to replicate some earlier findings from the literature regarding the association of each cultural logic with other variables of interest. Honor concerns, particularly masculine honor, have been linked to violence and hostility at intrapersonal (e.g., suicide; <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Osterman &amp; Brown, 2011)</ref>, interpersonal <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Brown et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Nisbett &amp; Cohen, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">van Osch et al., 2013)</ref>, and intergroup levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Barnes et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Saucier et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>We expect that endorsement of honor culture will predict more positive attitudes toward violence (H4a). Relations of dignity and face cultural logics with other psychological constructs have been studied much less. Some initial evidence suggests that face culture predicts more concern for maintaining the reputation (face) of the other person in an interpersonal conflict ("other-face concern" in face negotiation theory; <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Oetzel &amp; Ting-Toomey, 2003)</ref>, while dignity culture predicts lower other-face concern, both at individual <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Smith et al., 2021)</ref> and cultural levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Lun et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Smith et al., 2021)</ref>. We will include a measure of how strongly people are concerned about preserving their own (self-face) or the other person's face (other-face) in a situation of interpersonal conflict and expect to find a positive link between face endorsement and other-face concern in interpersonal conflict (H4b)</p><p>and a negative link between dignity endorsement and other-face concern in interpersonal conflict (H4c). We will also test the predictive power of the newly developed measure by attempting to replicate findings that suggest people endorsing different cultural logics react differently to provocation: that honor is associated with retaliatory reactions, face with withdrawal, and dignity with the use of humor <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Krys et al., 2017)</ref>. Although <ref type="bibr">Krys et al.'s (2017)</ref> study found the expected effects only for honor and dignity cultures, we will test all three predictions as initially theorized. Therefore, we expect that honor will predict retaliation (H5a), face will predict withdrawal (H5b), and dignity will predict humor (H5c) as reactions to provocation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploratory Research Questions</head><p>We will also include other well-established measures of values <ref type="bibr">(Schwartz Portrait Values Questionnaire;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Schwartz, 2021)</ref> and morality (Moral Foundations Questionnaire-2; <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Atari et al., 2023)</ref> that will allow us to position the newly developed measures vis-à-vis other widely used constructs in the field. Although there is no sufficient evidence to propose formal hypotheses, we do have some expectations about how these constructs might be related. For the self-transcendence versus self-enhancement dimension of Schwartz values, we expect all three other-concern facets of cultural logics to correlate positively with self-transcendence, and honor-self and dignity-self to correlate positively with self-enhancement. For the conservation versus openness dimension, we expect both dignity facets to correlate positively with openness, and both face and honor facets to correlate positively with conservation. For moral foundations, we expect the other-concern facet of all three cultural logics to relate positively to care, dignity-self to relate positively to proportionality and dignity-other -to equality, and both facets of honor and face to relate positively to loyalty, authority, and purity. Short measures of religiosity and wellbeing will be included as exploratory measures.</p><p>Finally, we will gather country-level secondary data to position the newly developed measures vis-à-vis historical data and current economic and societal indicators. We expect honor cultures to score higher on historical threats (e.g., pathogen prevalence and territorial conflicts) and dignity cultures to score lower on historical threats and higher on current levels of economic and societal development (e.g., GDP per capita and human development index). We do not make predictions about face cultures but will explore these relationships for the first time in this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>We will conduct a cross-cultural survey to (1) test the factor structure of the proposed scales of dignity, honor, and face cultural logics (henceforth -DHF, H1), (2) map the world cultures on the prevalence of these logics, and (3) identify both country-level and individual-level correlates and behavioral manifestations of these cultural logics, including prosocial behavior (H2-H5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample</head><p>For all power calculations involving significance testing (see "Analysis plan summary" in the SM) we use an alpha level of .05, as we consider 5% probability of Type I error acceptable, given the relatively low risk of consequences of this type of error. We aim to collect data from at least 50 countries representing various world regions to provide valuable descriptive data and have sufficient power for testing country-level correlates of DHF. With a country level sample size of 50, we will be able to detect a medium-sized correlation of r = .38 in country-level analyses with 80% power. This sample size will also be sufficient for multilevel analyses <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Maas &amp; Hox, 2005)</ref> to explore potential person-environment interactions. Establishing a measurement model that adequately describes the data in all countries is a necessary precondition for providing valid cross-cultural data on the prevalence of DHF across the world. We will use the alignment optimization procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Asparouhov &amp; Muthén, 2023)</ref> to identify the degree of comparability of the scores across all samples. A simulation study of the alignment optimization procedure suggests that with a high number of groups (&gt;15), a group size of 250 would be sufficient for a model that contains non-invariant parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">(Wen &amp; Hu, 2022)</ref>. Based on power analysis for all other hypotheses we plan to test (see "Analysis plan summary" in the SM), a sample size of n = 300 per country should be sufficient to detect all the effects of interest. We will aim to recruit 300 participants per country. If the sample size in a country is lower than 300 but higher than 100 after making all reasonable efforts to recruit more participants, the sample will still be included in the main analysis. If the sample size is between 50 and 100 participants, the sample will only be included in multilevel analyses testing associations across all samples, but not in the alignment optimization procedure. If the sample size is below 50, the sample will be dropped from all analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria</head><p>Only data from participants who are 18 years or older and were born and currently reside in the country of data collection will be included in the analyses<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> . Both student samples and local community samples will be included, and participants of all ethnic and religious backgrounds can take part. When sufficient data (at least n = 100) are available for student versus community samples or for different ethnic, religious, or regional groups in a country, we may further explore within-country variability in the endorsement of cultural logics. The questionnaire will include three attention checks and participants who fail two or three of them will be excluded. Each attention check will be embedded at the end of a questionnaire block (block 2 -DHF norms, block 5 -attitudes toward violence, and block 9 -moral foundations), and will read "Hello, are you still paying attention? If you are reading this question, please choose the option [scale label consistent with the scale in that block]". For tests including the dictator and ultimatum games, we will additionally exclude participants who failed the comprehension questions for the respective game.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical Considerations and Open Science</head><p>The study has been approved by the ethics committee of the University of York. We will obtain necessary ethical approvals, or alternatively, documentation of ethics waivers or exemptions from all participating institutions. All participants will give informed consent to participate (the lead institution's consent form will be used as the default and will be adapted for local use when necessary). The local data collection teams will decide on participant compensation in accordance with local norms and requirements. This study is low-risk since it does not involve any risks to participants, deception, or collection of personal data as defined by GDPR. The study is preregistered (<ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/2eygt">https://osf.io/2eygt</ref>). All study materials, data, and code will be shared via the Open Science Framework (<ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/ygv2h/?view_only=e7936670774c4fcbb9d65bdce0f6e7b9">https://osf.io/ygv2h/?view_only=e7936670774c4fcbb9d65bdce0f6e7b9</ref>) and made public as soon as this manuscript is published. We also aim to create a world map demonstrating the distribution of dignity, honor, and face logics across countries. This map and the underlying data will be available openly to other researchers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design and Procedure</head><p>Data will be collected online via the survey platform Qualtrics. All data will be stored on Qualtrics servers located in Germany in accordance with the GDPR standards. Most scales included in the study are already available in multiple languages. For each language used in the study, we will gather the available measures and the local labs will (1) check the quality of available translations and adjust when necessary and (2) translate all the remaining measures and instructions using a combination of collaborative and iterative translation with back-translation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Douglas &amp; Craig, 2007)</ref>.</p><p>The questionnaire will include measures of dignity, honor, and face cultural logics, behavioral measures of prosociality, and self-reported measures of potential correlates of DHF. The order of the measures will be as follows: DHF endorsement, DHF norms, prosocial behavior, self-reported positive and negative reciprocity, face negotiation in interpersonal conflict, attitudes toward violence, reactions to provocation, values, moral foundations, religiosity, subjective well-being; socio-demographic variables, including age, gender, country of residence, migration background, place of upbringing and current residence (urban/rural), ethnicity, religious denomination, education, and subjective income (see SM for the full questionnaire).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dignity, Honor, and Face Cultural Logics</head><p>Based on the existing measures of dignity, honor, and face cultural logics <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Grigoryan &amp; Khachatryan, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Smith et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Vignoles et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b86">Yao et al., 2017)</ref>, we developed a version of the questionnaire that differentiates between the self-concern and other-concern facets of each cultural logic (see Table <ref type="table">S1</ref> in the SM for the item list). Each facet was measured with 5 items, 30 items total. Out of 30 items, 18 have been tested in earlier cross-cultural studies (60%) and 12 were new or have only been tested in one country (40%). We pretested this questionnaire in two states in the USA (New York and Texas) and additionally received feedback on the face validity of the items from three anonymous reviewers. The item list was revised and expanded based on this feedback (see Table <ref type="table">S5</ref> for a revised item list).</p><p>To make sure that the DHF measure is culturally sensitive and captures relevant beliefs and behaviors across cultures, we started the present cross-cultural study with questionnaire review and refinement. In the onboarding questionnaire, each collaborator received the operational definitions of each of the constructs and a list of 18 items randomly selected from the full list of 36 items shown in Table <ref type="table">S5</ref>. For each item, they were asked to first guess which of the six facets the item was supposed to measure. Then, they rated how well that item represents the construct on a 5-point scale. Finally, they rated how difficult it would be to translate this item to the language of data collection (if not English) on a 5-point scale. At the end, the full list of potential items for each subscale was shown and each collaborator could suggest replacements for existing items or new items to add.</p><p>Overall, 141 collaborators representing 50 countries of planned data collection provided feedback. About 70% of those who provided feedback planned to collect data in languages other than English. We revised the item list based on collaborator feedback; the findings from this feedback survey are presented in the SM. The revised item list was pilot tested again (see SM for more details)</p><p>and Table <ref type="table">S6</ref> presents the final item list. The items within each scale (norms and endorsement) will be presented to the participants in a random order, to minimize order effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prosocial Behavior</head><p>Universal prosociality will be measured using the dictator game, which is a common measure of altruistic behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Edele et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Kahneman et al., 1986)</ref>. We adapted the instructions for the non-incentivized version of the game from <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Romano et al. (2021)</ref>, which allows for asynchronous pairing of the participants. Participants will be asked to distribute an endowment of 10 Monetary Units (MU) between themselves and another participant. The amount that the participant decides to transfer to the other person is a measure of universal prosociality as this is a one-shot interaction with a stranger, where the participant will not gain anything from sharing their hypothetical resources.</p><p>The ultimatum game <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Güth et al., 1982)</ref> is traditionally used to measure negative reciprocity:</p><p>the willingness to incur costs to punish non-cooperators (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Yamagishi et al., 2012)</ref>. We adapted the non-incentivized version of the game to assess both positive and negative reciprocity in a repeated interaction with a stranger. We operationalize positive reciprocity here as the willingness to return favors. After the dictator game, participants will be informed that they will be matched with a new person and will play the following two rounds with that same person. First, participants will be assigned to the role of the Receiver. This round measures negative reciprocity. Following adapted instructions from <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Columbus et al. (2021)</ref>, participants will be asked to indicate whether they accept or reject each proposal made by another player, with proposals ranging from 0 to 10 MUs. Rejecting the proposal results in both players getting nothing. In this version of the game, the lowest value of the proposal that the participant would accept (or in other words -the highest cost that they would want to bear to punish the other player) is the measure of negative reciprocity. In the last round, participants will be in the role of the Proposer and decide how much they would propose for each value (0-10) that the other person could have proposed in the previous round. In this last round, we will use modified instructions, telling the participant that the other person will not be able to reject their proposal. This approach allows us to measure positive reciprocity without it being confounded by concerns about retaliation or rejection.</p><p>We will also measure participants' expectations on whether they think their proposal (conditional, from 0 to 10) would have been accepted or rejected to capture expectations of reciprocity. At the end of data collection, we will randomly pair each participant with another participant from the same country to calculate how many monetary units they hypothetically earned.</p><p>The results of our pretest suggest that the behavioral patterns observed in this procedure are comparable to those observed in incentivised versions of these games. This finding falls in line with a growing body of literature indicating that designs using imaginary and real rewards produce very consistent findings <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Balliet et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Romano et al., 2017</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Romano et al., , 2021))</ref>. Additionally, we observed significant correlations between the behavioral measures of positive and negative reciprocity from this adaptation of the ultimatum game and their corresponding self-reported measures, which supports the construct validity of our approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Self-Reported Measures</head><p>Positive and negative reciprocity. We will use six items from the German Socio-Economic Panel (SOEP) to assess positive and negative reciprocity <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Egloff et al., 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Attitudes toward violence. We will use the short version of the Velicer Attitudes toward</p><p>Violence Scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">(Velicer et al., 1989)</ref>. Based on the adaptation of the scale by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Anderson et al. (2006)</ref>,</p><p>we selected three items to measure each of the four domains of violence acceptance: acceptance of war (intergroup violence), intimate violence, penal code violence, and corporal punishment for children.</p><p>Self-face and other-face concern. Face concerns in interpersonal conflict will be measured by the short, 10-item version <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Lun et al., 2023)</ref> of the Face Concerns Scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Oetzel et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ting-Toomey &amp; Oetzel, 2001)</ref>. Participants are asked to recall a conflict they recently had with someone and to describe that interaction through a series of multiple-choice questions. Self-face concern is measured by 4 items (e.g., "I was concerned with protecting my self-image") and other-face concern -by 6 items (e.g., "I tried to be sensitive to the other person's self-worth").</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reactions to provocation. We will use the shortened version of the Reactions to Provocation</head><p>Scale developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Krys et al. (2017)</ref>. The original measure includes 7 scenarios describing various insults. After each scenario, participants are asked how they would behave in that situation, with three options: retaliation ("return the insult"), withdrawal ("do nothing and expect others to intervene"), and humor ("humorously comment on that person's behavior"). In this study, we will use three out of seven scenarios with minor modifications (scenarios can be found in the SM).</p><p>Values. The short version of the Schwartz Portrait Value Questionnaire (PVQ-21; Schwartz, 2021) will be included to measure basic human values. The PVQ-21 measures ten values that are organized into a motivational continuum by two dimensions: conservation vs. openness to change and self-enhancement vs. self-transcendence. The scale is available in multiple languages and has been validated cross-culturally (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bilsky et al., 2011)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Moral foundations. We will use the 36-item version of the revised Moral Foundations</head><p>Questionnaire (MFQ-2; <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Atari et al., 2023)</ref> to capture six moral foundations: care, equality, proportionality, loyalty, authority, and purity. The scale is available in multiple languages and has been validated cross-culturally <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Atari et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Religiosity. The Duke University Religion Index (DUREL; <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Koenig &amp; Büssing, 2010</ref>) is a 5-item measure of religiosity that includes one item capturing organizational religious participation, one item capturing non-organizational participation, and three items capturing intrinsic religiosity. The scale is available in multiple languages and has been validated cross-culturally <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">(Toscanelli et al., 2022)</ref>.</p><p>Well-being. We will use the 5-item Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS; <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Diener et al., 1985)</ref>.</p><p>The measure is available in multiple languages and has been validated cross-culturally <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Jang et al., 2017)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Country (Sample)-Level Indicators</head><p>Country performance. We will use the World Bank data on GDP per capita and economic inequality (Gini index), the United Nations' Human Development Index (HDI) and Gender Inequality Index (GII), and the Freedom House "Global Freedom" scores.</p><p>Historical data. We will use historical data on population density data from the World Bank for the years 1961 (fewer countries available) and 2000 (more countries available). We will also include historical data on territorial threats from the International Crisis Behavior project (ICB, 2022), an index of historical disease prevalence from <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Murray and Schaller (2010)</ref>, vulnerability to natural disasters from the World Risk Index (World Risk Report, 2011), and resource scarcity measured as the prevalence of food insecurity and access to safe drinking water in the year 2000 from the Food and Agriculture Organization of the UN (FAOSTAT, 2024).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cultural indicators.</head><p>We will use available secondary data, including the individualism-collectivism and flexibility-monumentalism indices from <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Minkov and Kaasa (2022)</ref>;</p><p>the most recent data on cultural tightness-looseness <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Eriksson et al., 2021)</ref>, and the relational mobility index <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Thomson et al., 2018)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis Plan</head><p>All data analysis will be conducted in R. We will use all available data from the participants who have consented to take part in the study, even if they did not complete the questionnaire, unless an ethics approval for a specific sample prevents this. We will calculate indices for each construct as the mean score of all items that comprise each scale or subscale, if their reliability is acceptable (Cronbach's α &gt; .50). We will only remove items if the scale's reliability is α &lt; .50 in more than 40% of the samples and item removal improves the reliability by at least α = .10 in at least half of the samples where it was initially poor. When calculating indices, the mean will be calculated based on non-missing items. We will test the robustness of our findings on a subsample of participants with no missing values. Each analysis will be run only on a subsample of participants who have no missing values on the variables involved in that analysis. Unlike all other indices, scores for the DHF constructs will be calculated based on the results of the confirmatory factor analysis and the alignment procedure. The alignment procedure will be initially performed in R, unless limitations to the sirt package necessitate using Mplus for broader feature implementations. See Analysis Plan Summary and Analysis Pipeline in the SM for details. We will use a p &lt; .05 significance threshold for all tests unless otherwise specified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Factor structure (H1).</head><p>To test the factor structure of the DHF questionnaire, we will conduct a multilevel confirmatory factor analysis (MCFA), specifying a hierarchical model with three higher-order latent factors representing dignity, honor, and face, each further represented by the two facets of self-concern and other-concern (H1a, see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>). For comparison, we will test a multilevel </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overall model plans.</head><p>Each structural equation model is described below and in the SM. We expect that models may not converge or present improbable parameter estimates (i.e., a Heywood case of negative variance or correlations estimated over one). We will consider combining factors with extremely high correlations (i.e., &gt; .95) if they are theoretically plausible, and negative variances will be controlled for by setting the variance to a small positive number based on the variances of other items or latent variables. For model non-convergence, we will try to find the convergence issue to modify the model. If samples do not have variability (i.e., all countries show the same effect), we will consider removing the Level 2 structure for each model. For all models, we may test the Level 1 and Level 2 structures separately to identify any model misspecifications and address convergence issues.</p><p>We will also consider testing each sample separately to determine if a specific country leads to convergence issues. Finally, if the hierarchical model with higher-order latent constructs does not converge, we will alternatively test a six-factor model (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref> above) that would still provide supporting evidence for the differentiation between the two facets of each cultural logic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Model comparison.</head><p>To compare the models, we will use AIC and BIC (lower values indicate better fit) in combination with the criteria proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chen (2007)</ref>: a difference between models of ΔCFI &gt; .010 and ΔRMSEA &gt; .015 would indicate that one model is significantly better fit to the data than the other (i.e., higher CFI and lower RMSEA would indicate better fit). The final model will then be modified for improvement. Model assessment will include evaluation of item loadings on both individual and sample level. If a given item does not significantly load on the respective factor and the model fit improves after removing the item, or the item loads in the opposite to the expected direction, the item will be removed. Otherwise, the item will be retained. If modification indices suggest a strong residual correlation between items, and this correlation is theoretically justified, a residual correlation will be added.</p><p>Once configural invariance has been established, we will employ the alignment optimization procedure to determine the degree of invariance across countries and identify the non-invariant parameters. We will consider the model to possess configural invariance, thus making it suitable for the application of the alignment optimization procedure, if the improved model achieves satisfactory fit indices (RMSEA &lt; .10, SRMR &lt; .10, CFI &gt; .80). We use less strict cutoff values here than is suggested in the literature (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Hu &amp; Bentler, 1998</ref>), as we do not expect any of the models to be a great fit to the data this diverse (50 or more countries) before the alignment optimization procedure is used (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Groskurth et al., 2024</ref> discussion on sensitivity of model fit indices to data and analysis characteristics). We consider these cutoff values to provide good enough evidence for a common configural model, which can then be used as a starting point for the alignment optimization procedure.</p><p>Once a common configural model is established, we will proceed to test invariance of the measure across samples using the alignment optimization procedure.</p><p>Testing approximate measurement invariance. The alignment optimization procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Asparouhov &amp; Muthén, 2023</ref>) is an alternative to traditional invariance testing using multiple group CFA since it offers more flexibility and is more suitable for testing invariance across a large number of groups. All intercepts and factor loadings will be fixed across groups. The results will indicate which parameters are not invariant (i.e., different) across samples, allowing us to find the optimal factor structure for comparing the latent means across the highest number of groups.</p><p>The individual endorsement latent variable structure will be used to calculate DHF endorsement indices at the individual level for all individual-level analyses (H2, H4, H5). The cultural norms measure will be used to calculate DHF norms indices at the sample level and will be used for all analyses involving countries (H3 and mapping of DHF scores across the world).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cultural logics and prosocial behavior (H2).</head><p>The amount of contribution in the dictator game is the measure of universal prosociality. We will run a multilevel regression analysis predicting prosociality from the six facets of DHF individual endorsement scores. The hypothesized model will only include random country intercepts for prosociality, but we will additionally explore whether the effects of DHF scores on prosociality vary by country by testing whether the addition of random slopes improves the model. A positive main effect of the other-concern facet of each cultural logic on prosociality in the random-intercept model will support the hypothesis. If the 3-factor model of DHF is supported in the previous stage, we will test the effects of endorsement of each factor on prosociality in an exploratory manner.</p><p>Cross-country differences in prosociality (H3). We will run a multilevel path model predicting universal prosociality and positive and negative reciprocity from individual-level and sample-level DHF cultural norm scores. The model will be clustered by country. Level 1 of the model will include dignity, honor, and face mean scores predicting the three dependent variables of prosociality, positive reciprocity, and negative reciprocity at the individual-level. Level 2 will include the same regression structure using sample-level aggregates for dignity, honor, and face. We expect sample-level face and honor norms to positively predict positive reciprocity and sample-level honor norms to positively predict negative reciprocity. We do not have specific predictions for universal prosociality and sample-level DHF norms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Criterion validity (H4-H5).</head><p>In a series of multilevel models with a random intercept for country, we will test if individual endorsement of dignity, honor, and face cultural logics show expected associations with other constructs. In all models, we will use the individual-level endorsement of the three cultural logics as individual-level predictors. We will also explore if these associations hold at the country level by using the country norms as predictors. For H4, two multilevel linear regression models will be examined using attitudes toward violence and other-face concern as dependent variables. The independent variables will be DHF individual-level participant means and mean DHF country norm ratings. For H5, a multilevel path model will be analyzed using individual-level models at Level 1 to predict retaliation, withdrawal, and humor scores. Level 2 will include these same dependent variables using sample-level aggregated DHF scores as predictors.</p><p>Exploratory analyses. If the DHF factor structure shows considerable variability across countries, we might explore potential sources of non-invariance or factor structure variability. We will further explore whether endorsement of these cultural logics correlates with participant characteristics, such as values, moral foundations, and religiosity. We will then test whether modern country-level dignity, honor, and face scores can be predicted from historical data on population density, resource scarcity, and threats, and examine how these indices are related to other dimensions of cultural comparison (values, relational mobility, tightness-looseness) and objective indicators of country performance (GDP per capita, inequality, democracy). Finally, as we will match participants within each country after the data is collected and calculate their earnings based on their decisions in the dictator and ultimatum games, we can further explore how country-level DHF scores relate to group-level earnings in the games. Some of these tests can be preregistered as secondary data analyses once the foundational work of establishing the generalizability of the cultural logic constructs and their measurement is completed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>This project will be the first global and well-powered study of the cultural logics of dignity, honor, and face. It will substantively advance the conceptualization and measurement of these constructs and will create a unique cross-cultural dataset for testing new hypotheses in the future. This project will also set a precedent for collaborative scale development that can help the scientific community to move beyond Western-centric measurement and etic approach to cross-cultural research. Finally, this project will shed light on cross-cultural differences in prosociality and contribute to our understanding of how criteria for evaluating character virtue help regulate social behavior across the world.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H-Other</head><p>If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense * H-Other When making decisions, people should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones * F-Self People should control their behavior in front of others 1 F-Self People should think twice before speaking to not embarrass themselves * F-Self People should know their place in society and act according to it * F-Self People should avoid situations where they could be embarrassed * F-Self A person cannot respect themselves if they are not fulfilling their responsibilities * F-Other People should be humble so as to maintain good relationships 1 F-Other People should be extremely careful not to embarrass other people 1 F-Other People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs 1 F-Other It is important to maintain harmony within one's group 1 F-Other People should never criticize others in public 1 Note. 1 -Adopted or adapted with minor modifications from Yao et al., 2017, Smith et al., 2024, and Vignoles et al., 2024. 2 -adapted from Grigoryan &amp; Khachatryan, 2023. * -new items. Instructions for measuring personal endorsement: "Please read the statements below and indicate to what extent you personally agree with each of them." Instructions for measuring perceived norms: "Now please read the same statements, but instead of your personal opinion, indicate to what extent you think other people in [Country] would agree with each of them."</p><p>All items were answered on a 6-point scale from 1 -"strongly disagree" to 6 -"strongly agree".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>DHF questionnaire. Tables below show the results of exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis testing the structure of the DHF questionnaire. We initially proposed a six-factor model of the DHF questionnaire, and the results below correspond to this initial hypothesis. In the main study, we hypothesized that the data would be described by a hierarchical model, which is more consistent with the literature and will allow us to generate scores both for the three cultural logics and for the six facets.</p><p>Exploratory factor analysis. First, we conducted an exploratory factor analysis (EFA) with oblimin rotation on both endorsement and perceived norm items. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S2</ref>.1 presents the pattern matrix with standardized item loadings for the endorsement items, and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S2</ref>.2 presents the same matrix for the norms items. Model fit indices are presented in table notes.</p><p>Table S2.1. Standardized loadings of DHF endorsement items in the EFA F1 F2 F3 F4 F5 F6 Dignity: Self People should stand up for what they believe in even when others disagree .52 .04 -.07 .24 .02 -.06 How much a person respects themselves is far more important than how much others respect them .39 .13 -.09 .07 .03 -.02 People should be true to themselves regardless of what others think .43 .05 -.04 .34 -.13 .02 People should make decisions based on their own opinions and not based on what others think .77 .03 .02 -.11 -.08 .11 People's opinions should be independent of what others around them think .68 .01 .02 -.03 .16 -.11 Dignity: Other People should never take someone's belongings without permission .16 .66 -.14 -.03 .02 -.10 People should never talk about others behind their back in a negative way -.06 .75 -.08 .07 .02 &lt;.01 People should always keep the secrets they have been trusted with .24 .39 .04 .22 .05 -.07 People should never lie to another person, no matter the circumstances -.06 .64 .13 -.03 -.15 .18 People should always keep promises that they made to another person, no matter who that person is .16 .63 .12 .01 -.01 .03 Honor: Self People should always be ready to defend their honor .07 .07 .31 .57 -.17 .14 If a person is insulted and they don't respond, they will look weak -.08 .06 .62 .02 .09 -.06 A person must show strength to be respected &lt;.01 .05 .40 .2 .18 .05 People should punish those who insult them .06 -.09 .70 .07 -.04 &lt;.01 People should not expect respect from others if they did not earn it .10 .03 .20 .04 .39 -.04 Honor: Other People should uphold and defend their family's reputation -.01 .06 .10 .79 -.05 .02 If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense .19 -.07 -.04 .54 -.02 .14 Men should protect the reputation of women they are related to -.02 .01 -.09 .79 .08 .03 People should be concerned about damaging their families' reputation -.05 .09 .12 .66 .16 -.05 When making decisions, people should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones -.03 .03 .07 .43 .31 .14 Face: Self People should control their behavior in front of others .05 -.02 -.15 .25 .31 .15 People should avoid situations where they could be embarrassed -.11 -.02 .11 .11 .34 .33 A person cannot respect themselves if they are not fulfilling their responsibilities .06 .32 .20 .21 .34 -.16 People should think twice before speaking to not embarrass themselves .02 -.04 .09 &lt;.01 .62 .19 People should know their place in society and act according to it -.11 .06 .43 .01 .31 .13 Face: Other People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs .01 .09 .08 -.03 .08 .62 People should be humble so as to maintain good relationships .04 .34 .03 .11 .18 .22 People should never criticize others in public &lt;.01 .43 .02 .03 .10 .35 It is important to maintain harmony within one's group .05 .05 -.14 .28 .09 .55 People should be extremely careful not to embarrass others -.02 .25 -.07 .20 .33 .22 Note: Factor loadings &gt;.30 are in bold. Model fit: TLI = .927, RMSEA = .042 (90%CI [.03, .05]) Table S2.2. Standardized loadings of DHF norms items in the EFA F1 F2 F3 F4 F5 F6 Dignity: Self People should stand up for what they believe in even when others disagree .44 -.04 -.03 .40 -.02 -.09 How much a person respects themselves is far more important than how much others respect them .41 .38 .01 -.14 -.03 -.05 People should be true to themselves regardless of what others think .56 .17 -.15 .16 .01 -.14 People should make decisions based on their own opinions and not based on what others think .87 -.08 .10 -.04 -.03 .04 People's opinions should be independent of what others around them think .82 .03 -.02 -.02 .05 .03 Dignity: Other People should never take someone's belongings without permission .09 .50 -.09 .15 .10 .15 People should never talk about others behind their back in a negative way .18 .41 -.17 .03 .01 .37 People should always keep the secrets they have been trusted with -.02 .76 -.03 .14 .03 -.04 People should never lie to another person, no matter the circumstances -.01 .49 .18 -.08 -.07 .44 People should always keep promises that they made to another person, no matter who that person is .06 .60 .06 .00 .14 .06 Honor: Self People should always be ready to defend their honor .09 .03 .28 .60 -.13 .08 If a person is insulted and they don't respond, they will look weak .06 .06 .77 .04 .02 -.05 A person must show strength to be respected .14 .03 .57 .23 -.03 -.06 People should punish those who insult them -.01 -.06 .75 .09 -.02 -.04 People should not expect respect from others if they did not earn it .04 .01 .11 .35 .30 -.13 Honor: Other People should uphold and defend their family's reputation .00 .03 .15 .73 -.06 .12 If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense .14 .06 .03 .62 .07 -.19 Men should protect the reputation of women they are related to -.02 .16 .04 .61 .12 .03 People should be concerned about damaging their families' reputation -.12 .16 .06 .49 .25 .03 When making decisions, people should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones -.01 .32 .13 .19 .46 -.09 Face: Self People should control their behavior in front of others .04 .09 .02 .02 .40 .22 People should avoid situations where they could be embarrassed .01 -.10 .05 -.07 .58 .19 A person cannot respect themselves if they are not fulfilling their responsibilities .02 .16 .15 .41 .23 -.04 People should think twice before speaking to not embarrass themselves .00 .15 .10 .00 .57 .01 People should know their place in society and act according to it -.09 -.04 .55 .00 .30 .11 Face: Other People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs .06 -.07 -.06 .04 .36 .51 People should be humble so as to maintain good relationships .10 -.03 -.24 .30 .27 .36 People should never criticize others in public -.02 .13 -.10 -.01 .08 .65 It is important to maintain harmony within one's group .01 .02 -.10 .25 .20 .43 People should be extremely careful not to embarrass others .05 .10 -.04 .02 .57 .07 Note: Factor loadings &gt;.30 are in bold. Model fit: TLI = .896, RMSEA = .055 (90%CI [.05, .06])</p><p>Confirmatory factor analysis: Model comparison. We initially hypothesized a six-factor model and expected it to perform better than a three-factor model, or a higher-order 3-factor model with two nested facets in each. In all models, each item significantly loaded on the respective latent construct with p &lt; .001, and βs mostly &gt; .50, and always &gt; .30. Table <ref type="table">S3</ref>.1 presents the results of model comparison for the endorsement items and model S3.2 for the norms items. In both cases, in addition to showing worse fit to the data based on fit indices, Model 3 also produced negative variances (for Dignity_other in both endorsement and norms, and for Honor_other in norms). Overall, the six-factor model performs best both for endorsement and perceived norms items.</p><p>Table S3.1. Model comparison for the endorsement items. Model 1 6 factors Model 2 3 factors Model 3 3 higher-order factors χ 2 (df) 965 (390) 1196 (402) 1015 (397) BIC 24607 25047 24894 AIC 24607 24813 24642 CFI .833 .769 .820 TLI .813 .750 .803 RMSEA .070 .081 .072 SRMR .075 .085 .079 Table S3.2. Model comparison for the norms items. Model 1 6 factors Model 2 3 factors Model 3 3 higher-order factors χ 2 (df) 1235 (390) 1821 (402) 1320 (396) BIC 25832 26350 25883 AIC 25554 26116 25627 CFI .790 .647 .770 TLI .765 .618 .747 RMSEA .085 .108 .088 SRMR .098 .123 .111</p><p>For the pilot study, we calculated the mean dignity, honor, and face scores based on the items that did not show significant cross-loadings in the EFA. The dignity-self and dignity-other means are based on all five items, honor-self is based on three items (excluding items 1 and 5), honor-other is based on 4 items (excluding item 5), face-self is based on three items (excluding items 3 and 5), and face-other is based on 4 items (excluding item 5). The 6-factor CFA models based on this specification showed better fit to the data (endorsement: CFI = .891, RMSEA = .061, SRMR = .067; norms: CFI = .878, RMSEA = .071, SRMR = .075).</p><p>The measures of personal endorsement and perceived norms showed only modest correlations (.02 &lt; r &lt; .46, r mean = .29), further supporting the need to differentiate the two. The measure of perceived norms captured group differences better than that of personal endorsement: for example, we found expected differences in honor between Texas and New York when asking about norms (Texas </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">scored</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prosocial behavior.</head><p>In the adapted version of the dictator game where we asked participants to distribute 10 monetary units between themselves and another person they did not know, participants gave away about 40% of their endowment, which is higher but comparable to the average of about 30% given in incentivized games <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Engel, 2011)</ref>. The results of the regression model predicting prosociality from the six facets of DHF are presented in Table <ref type="table">S4</ref>. Not all effects were significant, but the effect sizes for all three other-concern facets were positive (.19 &lt; b &lt; .32) and the effect sizes for all three self-concern facets were negative (-.13 &lt; b &lt; -.61).</p><p>Table S4. Predicting prosocial behavior from the DHF facets b SE 95% CI t-value p-value lower upper (Intercept) 5.10 0.98 3.17 7.04 5.19 &lt;.001 Dignity: Self -0.61 0.18 -0.97 -0.26 -3.39 &lt;.001 Dignity: Other 0.31 0.17 -0.03 0.64 1.80 .073 Honor: Self -0.26 0.12 -0.50 -0.02 -2.15 .033 Honor: Other 0.19 0.16 -0.12 0.51 1.21 .228 Face: Self -0.13 0.18 -0.48 0.21 -0.75 .453 Face: Other 0.32 0.18 -0.03 0.67 1.83 .069</p><p>In the first round of the ultimatum game, where participants acted as the Receiver, they showed stronger negative reciprocity than is commonly found in incentivized ultimatum games: about 60% of participants rejected offers below 40%, whereas only about 50% of participants rejected offers below 20% in incentivized games <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Houser &amp; McCabe, 2014)</ref>. In the last round, when participants are in the role of the Proposer, on average, they proposed about 43%, which is in line with the average of 40-50% found in incentivized games <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Houser &amp; McCabe, 2014)</ref>. The proportion of offers that are equal or greater than the proposal of the other person is considered a measure of positive reciprocity.</p><p>Note that in the pilot study, we did not tell the participants that the other person won't be able to reject their offer -this change to the procedure was made after the pilot study was finalized. As an additional validity test, we tested correlations between self-reported and behavioral measures of positive and negative reciprocity. Self-reported measures correlated positively with the corresponding behavioral measure (r = .14, p = .015 for positive and r = .21, p &lt;. 001 for negative reciprocity) and were not significantly correlated with the other measure (r = -.04, p = .522 and r = -.05, p = .404).</p><p>The benefits of this procedure are that (1) it can be implemented without financial incentives,</p><p>(2) participants do not need to interact in real time, (3) no personal data needs to be collected, (4) it can be implemented both online and offline, and ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) it provides rich within-individual behavioral data rather than a single-shot behavioral reaction. The only drawback is that the hypothetical Monetary Units are valued less than actual money, as the differences in mean contributions in the two games suggest. However, for a large cross-cultural study where maximization of access is the priority, the benefits clearly outweigh the costs.</p><p>Revising the DHF questionnaire. We revised the item list based on the results of the pilot study and reviewer feedback. Table <ref type="table">S5</ref> presents the revised list of items.</p><p>Table S5. Revised DHF item list n Facet Items 1 D-Self People should make decisions based on their own opinions and not based on what others think 2 D-Self People should be true to themselves regardless of what others think 3 D-Self People should stand up for what they believe in even when others disagree 4 D-Self How much a person respects themselves is far more important than how much others respect them 5 D-Self People's opinions should be independent of what others around them think 6 D-Self A person's sense of worth should not depend on what others think of them** 7 D-Other People should always keep promises that they made to another person, no matter who that person is 8 D-Other People should never talk about others behind their back in a negative way 9 D-Other People should not lie to another person, no matter who that person is* 10 D-Other People should be treated with respect, no matter who they are** 11 D-Other People should keep the secrets they have been trusted with, no matter whose secret it is* 12 D-Other People should respect others' right to have a different opinion or a different lifestyle** 13 H-Self People should be ready to defend their honor at any cost* 14 H-Self People should punish those who insult them 15 H-Self A person who has no honor is not worthy of respect** 16 H-Self If a person is insulted and they don't respond, they will look weak 17 H-Self A person must show strength to be respected 18 H-Self People should not expect respect from others if they did not earn it 19 H-Other People should uphold and defend their family's reputation 20 H-Other If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense 21 H-Other People should be concerned about damaging their families' reputation 22 H-Other Men should protect the reputation of women they are related to 23 H-Other When making decisions, people should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones 24 H-Other A person cannot be respected if they are not true to their word** 25 H-Other A person cannot be respected if they are not loyal to their family** 26 F-Self People should control their behavior in front of others 27 F-Self People should think twice before speaking to not embarrass themselves 28 F-Self People should know what is expected of them and act accordingly* 29 F-Self People should avoid situations where they could be embarrassed 30 F-Self A person cannot respect themselves if they are not fulfilling their responsibilities 31 F-Self People worthy of respect are those who do what is expected of them and do it well** 32 F-Other People should be humble so as to maintain good relationships 33 F-Other People should be extremely careful not to embarrass other people, especially if it is someone of a higher rank* 34 F-Other People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs 35 F-Other It is important to maintain harmony within one's group 36 F-Other People should never criticize others in public, especially if it is someone older or more experienced* Note. * Modified items **Items added after review</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Collaborator survey</head><p>We conducted a survey among the collaborators of the project to gather feedback on the conceptualization and measurement of these cultural logics. The goal was to co-develop the final version of the questionnaire with the collaborators from different countries, to ensure that the measure will be culturally sensitive and capture relevant beliefs and behaviors across cultures.</p><p>Overall, 141 collaborators provided feedback. The collaborators represented 50 different countries where data collection is planned, with the largest representation from the USA (n = 14), Türkiye (n = 12), and Poland (n = 8). About 30% of all collaborators who provided feedback plan to collect data in English, and about 70% plan to collect data in other languages. In terms of expertise, fewer collaborators were familiar with face cultures (26% were not familiar at all, 57% had some familiarity, 17% had some expertise) and dignity cultures (24%, 60%, and 16%, respectively) than with honor cultures (14%, 63%, and 23%, respectively). Below we summarize the main issues identified by collaborators and describe how we plan to address them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conceptualization of dignity, honor, and face cultural logics</head><p>Overall, 26 participants (18%) gave feedback on the conceptualization of the DHF constructs, five of whom mentioned that they had no comments, and nine liked the definitions. Therefore, 54% of the feedback provided was positive, and only 8.5% of all participants gave critical feedback. The three issues described below summarize this critical feedback.</p><p>The multifaceted nature of the constructs. The only critical comment on the conceptualization of honor was that we ignore the multifaceted nature of this construct. While we agree that each of these cultural logics can be differentiated further (morality and respect components, differentiation between self-respect and social status, positive vs. negative reciprocity, differentiation based on gendered expectations in case of honor and face, etc.), our goal here is to develop a framework that can accommodate both similarities and differences between the three cultural logics in a consistent manner. We try to incorporate both morality and respect-related aspects of the three cultural logics through a diverse set of items that reflect these aspects in ways that are relevant to each cultural logic. We only differentiate between self-and other-concern facets at the construct level because these facets have the same psychological underpinnings across all three cultural logics and are likely to be differentially predictive of relevant outcomes. This conceptualization certainly simplifies these cultural logics, but we hope this level of simplification would be helpful in bringing together literature on the three cultural logics while still offering enough nuance for the constructs to be meaningful and have predictive power.</p><p>The intertwined nature of the constructs. Several comments pointed to the fact that the three constructs are closely linked and are likely to be present in all cultures to some extent. We now acknowledge in the manuscript that "despite the recognition that certain regions or cultures are typically considered to align with one of the three logics, we assume that any given cultural or national group will endorse all three logics to some extent, and that any given culture will have high between-individual variability in personal endorsement of each of these logics." We will also aim to reflect this continuous and interconnected nature of the constructs when mapping countries by DHF scores: for example, we could use a combination of the three basic colors -red, green, and blue -to show the prevalence of all three logics in each culture, rather than assigning each country to a single category.</p><p>What is "universalistic morality"? Some collaborators pointed out that when we use the term "universalistic morality" in the definition of dignity, we would need to agree on which moral foundations are relevant for dignity cultures. This is an excellent point that made us re-evaluate the items we were using for the dignity other-concern facet. Indeed, the moral norms that we used in formulating dignity items, like not lying or talking about people behind their back, are in fact universally important across cultures and are not unique to dignity cultures. What is unique to dignity cultures, is the idea that all people should be treated with dignity and respect, no matter who they are. We therefore moved away from using specific moral issues in the item wording and instead used items (some suggested by collaborators, some new), that focus exclusively on this aspect of treating others with dignity, no matter who they are.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Item selection</head><p>Each collaborator received the operational definitions of each of the constructs and a list of 18 items randomly selected from the full list of 36. For each item, they were asked to first guess which of the six facets the item is supposed to measure. Then, they rated how well that item represents the construct on a 5-point scale from low to high quality. And finally, they rated how difficult it would be to translate this item to the language of data collection (if not English) on a 5-point scale from easy to difficult. At the end, the full list of potential items for each subscale was shown and each collaborator could suggest replacements for existing items or new items to add.</p><p>We considered dropping or replacing items if (1) fewer than 70% of collaborators correctly guessed which construct it measures; (2) if among those who guessed correctly, the average rating of the quality of the item was below 3 on a 5-point scale; or (3) if the average translation difficulty was above 4 on a 5-point scale. The excluded items were dropped if at least 5 items still remained per construct, or replaced if fewer than 5 items remained. The replacement items were either picked from the pool of items proposed by the collaborators or, if necessary, were newly developed by the lead team.</p><p>The tables below present the results for each construct. The first column shows the percentage of collaborators who correctly guessed which construct that item measures, the second column shows the same number but in the subgroup of collaborators who said they had some or considerable expertise in that construct, the third column shows the mean quality rating, and the last column shows the mean of translation difficulty rating. Since not all collaborators saw all the items, we additionally report the number of responses for each question. The number of responses in the "quality assessment" column is the same as in the first column since we only calculated the quality score in the subgroup of collaborators who guessed the construct correctly. The translation difficulty item was only shown to collaborators who plan to collect data in languages other than English.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dignity</head><p>-self % guessed the construct correctly % of experts who guessed correctly Quality assessment Translation difficulty D-Self_1: People should make decisions based on their own opinions and not based on what others think (N=62) 72.6%(45) 85.7% (6) M=4.02 SD=0.783 M=1.59 SD=0.751 (N=39) D-Self_2: People should be true to themselves regardless of what others think. (N=63) 88.9% (56) 91.7% (11) M=4.04 SD=0.613 M=1.98 SD=0.886 (N=43) D-Self_3: People should stand up for what they believe in even when others disagree. (N=61) 62.3% (38) 70% (7) M=3.76 SD=0.852 M=1.80 SD=0.813 (N=41) D-Self_4: How much a person respects themselves is far more important than how much others respect them (N=68) 80.9% (55) 71.4% (5) M=4.02 SD=0.693 M=1.60 SD=0.780 (N=45) D-Self_5: People's opinions should be independent of what others around them think. (N=62) 71% (44) 69.2% (9) M=3.73 SD=0.758 M=1.61 SD=0.586 (N=41) D-Self_6: A person's sense of worth should not depend on what others think of them. (N=65) 83.1% (54) 80% (4) M=4.36 SD=0.682 M=1.59 SD=0.726 (N=44)</p><p>Five out of six items passed all the quality checks, meaning more than 70% of collaborators correctly identified which construct the item is supposed to measure, the quality ratings were all above the scale mid-point (3), and the translation difficulty ratings were all below 2. Therefore, these five items will be used to measure dignity-self: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dignity-other</head><p>% guessed the construct correctly % of experts who guessed correctly Quality assessment Translation difficulty D-Other_1: People should always keep promises that they made to another person, no matter who that person is. (N=66) 57.6% (38) 100% (2) M=3.66 SD=0.745 M=1.57 SD=0.695 (N=44) D-Other_2: People should never talk about others behind their back in a negative way (N=64). 51.6% (33) 42.9% (3) M=3.55 SD=0.711 M=1.50 SD=0.741 (N=42) D_Other_3: People should not lie to another person, no matter who that person is. (N=65) 63.1% (41) 87.5% (8) M=3.65 M=1.43 SD=0.736 SD=0.655 (N=46) D-Other_4: People should be treated with respect, no matter who they are. (N=64) 81.3% (52) 71.4% (5) M=4.25 SD=0.738 M=1.44 SD=0.616 (N=48) D-Other_5: People should keep the secrets they have been trusted with, no matter whose secret it is. (N=63) 42.9% (27) 63.6% (7) M=3.11 SD=0.974 M=1.79 SD=0.833 (N=43) D-Other_6: People should respect others' right to have a different opinion or a different lifestyle. (N=66) 84.8% (56) 76.9% (10) M=4.00 SD=0.831 M=1.68 SD=0.695 (N=47)</p><p>Only two items passed all quality checks: "People should be treated with respect, no matter who they are" and "People should respect others' right to have a different opinion or a different lifestyle." As described above, all the items that referred to specific (im)moral acts can be relevant in any culture, and this issue is reflected in both quantitative results and the responses to open-ended questions. We kept the two items that passed the quality control checks and added three new items that reflected this idea of "treating others with dignity no matter who they are" from the list of items suggested by collaborators. We slightly modified the second item from the initial list by removing the reference to "lifestyle", as we used "lifestyle" in one of the other items. The final list of dignity-other items is as follows:</p><p>1. People should be treated with respect, no matter who they are. 2. People should respect others' right to have a different opinion. 3. People are equally worthy of respect regardless of their beliefs or lifestyle. 4. People should be treated with dignity no matter who they are or where they are from. 5. People should respect others' choices, even if they disagree with them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Honor-self % guessed the construct correctly % of experts who guessed correctly</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quality assessment</head><p>Translation difficulty</p><p>H-Self_1: People should be ready to defend their honor at any cost. (N=60) 81.7% (49) 76.9% (10) M=4.33 SD=0.718 M=1.52 SD=0.792 (N=44) H-Self_2: People should punish those who insult them. (N=64) 56.3% (36) 80% (12) M=3.78 SD=0.797 M=1.41 SD=0.658 (N=44) H-Self_3: A person who has no honor is not worthy of respect. (N=65) 75.4% (49) 80% (12) M=3.88 SD=0.857 M=1.75 SD=0.840 (N=40) H-Self_4: If a person is insulted and they don't respond, they will look weak. (N=62) 54.8% (34) 71.4% (10) M=4.03 SD=0.758 M=1.65 SD=0.805 (N=49) H-Self_5: A person must show strength to be respected. (N=66) 65.2% (43) 84.6% (11) M=3.79 SD=0.782 M=1.51 SD=0.736 (N=43) H-Self_6: People should not expect respect from others if they did not earn it. (N=66) 40.9% (27) 50% (7) M=3.54 SD=0.706 M=1.68 SD=0.771 (N=44)</p><p>Only two items passed all quality checks: "People should be ready to defend their honor at any cost" and "A person who has no honor is not worthy of respect". Importantly, all items except the last one made the &gt;70% cut among the experts, so we focused on revising the existing items based on open responses from the collaborators rather than coming up with new items. The "strength" item was revised to read "People must show they can stand up for themselves to be respected". Only one of the two "insult" items was retained: "If a person gets insulted and they don't respond, they will look weak". Finally, we added another item to supplement the list: "People should never tolerate being disrespected", which is an adaptation of an item from <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Barnes et al. (2014)</ref>. The final list of items is as follows:</p><p>1. People should be ready to defend their honor at any cost 2. A person who has no honor is not worthy of respect 3. People must show they can stand up for themselves to be respected 4. If a person gets insulted and they do not respond, they will look weak</p><p>5. People should never tolerate being disrespected Honor-other % guessed the construct correctly % of experts who guessed correctly Quality assessment Translation difficulty H-Other_1: People should uphold and defend their family's reputation. (N=62) 79% (48) 86.7% (13) M=4.16 SD=0.688 M=1.62 SD=0.739 (N=47) H-Other_2: If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense. (N=63) 81% (51) 76.9% (10) M=4.02 SD=0.632 M=1.80 SD=0.833 (N=46) H-Other_3: People should be concerned about damaging their families' reputation. (N=63) 77.8% (49) 73.3% (11) M=4.19 SD=0.607 M=1.87 SD=0.963 (N=38) H-Other_4: Men should protect the reputation of women they are related to. (N=63) 58.7% (37) 66.7% (8) M=3.72 SD=0.741 M=1.59 SD=0.658 (N=44) H-Other_5: When making decisions, people should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones. (N=68) 73.5% (50) 82.4% (14) M=3.96 SD=0.807 M=1.69 SD=0.841 (N=42) H-Other_6: A person cannot be respected if they are not true to their word. (N=66) 9.1% (6) 23.1% (3) M=3.83 SD=0.408 M=1.58 SD=0.739 (N=48) H-Other_7: A person cannot be respected if they are not loyal to their family. (N=60) 36.7% (22) 33.3% (4) M=3.50 SD=0.859 M=1.71 SD=0.802 (N=38)</p><p>Four items passed all quality checks: "People should uphold and defend their family's reputation", "If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense", "People should be concerned about damaging their families' reputation", and "When making decisions, people should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones". We will slightly modify the third item, as some open responses indicated that "concerned" might be misinterpreted or difficult to translate, the revised wording is "People should not do anything that would damage their families' reputation". We will also simplify the last item: "People should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones".</p><p>Although the item "Men should protect the reputation of women they are related to" did not make the cut, it was the next best-performing item in the list (nearly 60% of all collaborators and nearly 70% of all collaborators with expertise in the subject identified this item as measuring honor other-concern). Considering (1) the centrality of masculine and feminine gender expectations to the concept of honor, (2) that this item performed well in previous cross-cultural studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">(Smith et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Vignoles et al., 2024)</ref> and (3) that this item performed well in our pilot study, we decided to keep this item as the fifth item of the honor-other subscale. Therefore, the final item list is as follows:</p><p>1. People should uphold and defend their family's reputation 2. If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense 3. People should not do anything that would damage their families' reputation 4. People should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones 5. Men should protect the reputation of women they are related to read "People should avoid doing anything inappropriate so as not to embarrass themselves" and the "respect" item was slightly modified to shift it from self-respect to deserving respect from others, to bring it in line with other "respect" items in honor and dignity scales: "People worthy of respect are those who do their utmost to fulfill the expectations of their role". The two items that tapped into controlling one's behavior to meet others' expectations (F-Self_1 and F-Self_3) both were identified as face items by more than 70% of collaborators, suggesting that this is an important element of face cultural logic. We suggest a new item that we hope will capture this aspect better: "People should always know what is appropriate for a given situation and act accordingly". Finally, based on open responses, we added a new item: "If someone made me lose face, I would avoid this person in the future". Therefore, the final list of items is as follows:</p><p>1. People should think twice before speaking so as not to embarrass themselves 2. People should avoid doing anything inappropriate so as not to embarrass themselves 3. People worthy of respect are those who do their utmost to fulfill the expectations of their role 4.</p><p>People should always know what is appropriate for a given situation and act accordingly 5. If someone made me lose face, I would avoid this person in the future Face-other % guessed the construct correctly % of experts who guessed correctly % guessed incorrectly but within the same domain Quality assessment Translation difficulty F-Other_1: People should be humble so as to maintain good relationships. (N=68) 38.2% (26) 58.3% (7) 23.5% (16) M=3.35 SD=0.977 M=1.68 SD=0.639 (N=44) F-Other_2: People should be extremely careful not to embarrass other people, especially if it is someone of a higher rank. (N=63) 76.2% (48) 90.9% (10) 6.3% (4) M=4.19 SD=0.741 M=1.68 SD=0.784 (N=37) F-Other_3: People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs. (N=64) 42.2% (27) 37.5% (3) 17.2% (11) M=3.00 SD=0.961 M=1.57 SD=0.683 (N=47) F-Other_4: It is important to maintain harmony within one's group. (N=63) 44.4% (28) 55.6% (5) 6.3% (4) M=3.26 SD=1.023 M=1.67 SD=0.764 (N=40) F-Other_5: People should never criticize others in public, especially if it is someone older or more experienced. (N=63) 73% (46) 83.3% (5) 4.8% (3) M=3.93 SD=0.654 M=1.43 SD=0.668 (N=42)</p><p>Two items passed all initial quality checks: "People should be extremely careful not to embarrass other people, especially if it is someone of a higher rank" and "People should never criticize others in public, especially if it is someone older or more experienced". We also decided to retain the item "People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs", as the idea of group harmony and avoiding open conflict is central to the face cultural logic and this item performed well in previous cross-cultural studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">(Smith et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Vignoles et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b86">Yao et al., 2017)</ref>. Two more items were added/modified based on collaborator suggestions: "People should avoid making others look incompetent" and "People should treat others according to their social status to maintain good relationships". The final list of items is as follows:</p><p>1. People should be extremely careful not to embarrass others, especially if it is someone of a higher rank 2. People should never criticize others in public, especially if it is someone older or more experienced 3. People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs 4. People should avoid making others look incompetent 5. People should treat others according to their social status to maintain good relationships</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pilot study 2</head><p>We pilot-tested this revised item list in a new sample of participants. We recruited a sample of US and UK residents of diverse ethnic backgrounds, where we expected to see cultural differences in the perceived norms of the three cultural logics: White European/Caucasian participants who were expected to report stronger dignity norms than others (N=189), Middle Eastern participants who were expected to report stronger honor norms than others (N=108), and East Asian participants who were expected to report stronger face norms than others (N=153). We additionally included 9 items that were used in the earlier versions of the questionnaire, to be able to test alternatives if the items from the final item list do not perform well. Finally, we included the 6-item measure of self-reported positive and negative reciprocity <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Egloff et al., 2013)</ref> to test the predictive validity of the measure. We expected the other-concern facet of each cultural logic to predict more positive reciprocity, and additionally the self-concern facet of honor to predict negative reciprocity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>We ran a confirmatory factor analysis with 6 latent constructs corresponding to the self and other facets of each cultural logic. We included both items from the revised item list presented above and the backup items, to check if the backup items might perform better. The results are presented in Table <ref type="table">S6</ref>.</p><p>Table S6. Factor loadings of all items included in the second pilot study in a 6-factor CFA Norms Endorsement b SE z 𝛽 b SE z 𝛽 Dignity-self People should make decisions based on their own opinions and not based on what others think 1 0.760 1 0.564 People should be true to themselves regardless of what others think 1.052 0.059 17.851 0.809 1.233 0.117 10.5 0.721 People's opinions should be independent of what others around them think 0.915 0.058 15.695 0.724 0.985 0.115 8.558 0.523 How much a person respects themselves is far more important than how much others respect them 0.833 0.056 14.793 0.687 0.889 0.126 7.045 0.407 A person's sense of worth should not depend on what others think of them 0.884 0.058 15.28 0.707 0.951 0.112 8.491 0.517 (B) People should stand up for what they believe in even when others disagree 0.749 0.055 13.51 0.633 1.089 0.109 9.967 0.657 (B) People should speak their mind 0.959 0.06 15.86 0.730 0.81 0.11 7.359 0.429 (B) People should not care what others around them think. 1.027 0.061 16.777 0.767 1.303 0.145 8.989 0.560 Dignity-other People should be treated with dignity no matter who they are or where they are from 1 0.724 1 0.610 People are equally worthy of respect regardless of their beliefs or lifestyle 1.213 0.073 16.656 0.809 1.499 0.132 11.331 0.703 People should respect others' choices, even if they disagree with them 1.024 0.069 14.773 0.719 1.221 0.113 10.787 0.654 People should respect others' right to have a different opinion 1.166 0.068 17.139 0.833 1.036 0.098 10.539 0.633 People should be treated with respect, no matter who they are 1.202 0.07 17.133 0.832 1.464 0.123 11.947 0.769 Honor-self People should never tolerate being disrespected 1 0.575 1 0.400 People should be ready to defend their honor at any cost 1.317 0.117 11.256 0.718 1.961 0.256 7.659 0.728 A person who has no honor is not worthy of respect 1.255 0.122 10.262 0.624 1.422 0.217 6.538 0.483 People must show they can stand up for themselves to be respected 0.853 0.094 9.092 0.528 1.578 0.222 7.101 0.582 If a person gets insulted and they don't respond, they will look weak. 1.418 0.128 11.036 0.696 1.595 0.226 7.064 0.574 (B) People should punish those who insult them 1.413 0.128 11.037 0.696 1.219 0.181 6.73 0.513 (B) People always need to show off their power in front of their competitors. 1.355 0.134 10.138 0.613 1.439 0.208 6.912 0.545 Honor-other People should not do anything that would damage their family's reputation 1 0.883 1 0.771 People should always think about how their behavior will reflect on the reputation of their close ones 0.943 0.037 25.324 0.863 0.858 0.054 15.876 0.738 People should uphold and defend their family's reputation 0.853 0.035 24.091 0.842 0.886 0.054 16.313 0.756 Men should protect the reputation of women they are related to 0.714 0.046 15.613 0.644 0.792 0.06 13.163 0.624 If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense 0.321 0.045 7.137 0.335 0.251 0.04 6.198 0.306 (B) People should be concerned about their family having a bad reputation. 0.938 0.04 23.436 0.829 0.929 0.056 16.451 0.761 Face-self People should always know what is appropriate for a given situation and act accordingly 1 0.585 1 0.418 People worthy of respect are those who do their utmost to fulfill the expectations of their role 0.911 0.101 9.03 0.501 1.132 0.194 5.825 0.373 People should avoid doing anything inappropriate so as not to embarrass themselves 1.556 0.127 12.293 0.768 2.296 0.288 7.972 0.706 People should think twice before speaking so as not to embarrass themselves 1.466 0.121 12.085 0.747 1.686 0.227 7.426 0.584 If someone made me lose face, I would avoid this person in the future 0.851 0.11 7.745 0.416 1.079 0.178 6.063 0.397 (B) People should control their behavior in front of others 1.392 0.116 12.008 0.740 1.606 0.211 7.616 0.622 Face-other People should treat others according to their social status to maintain good relationships 1 0.597 1 0.486 People should be extremely careful not to embarrass others, especially if it is someone of a higher rank 1.244 0.100 12.487 0.761 1.357 0.146 9.327 0.699 People should avoid making others look incompetent 0.596 0.087 6.884 0.361 0.579 0.099 5.852 0.336 People should never criticize others in public, especially if it is someone older or more experienced 1.177 0.099 11.849 0.704 1.159 0.134 8.629 0.597 People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs 0.894 0.086 10.361 0.587 0.840 0.103 8.113 0.536 (B) It is important to maintain harmony within one's group 0.710 0.068 10.42 0.591 0.428 0.069 6.173 0.360 (B) People should be very humble to maintain good relationships 0.936 0.089 10.51 0.598 0.690 0.098 7.058 0.432 Note: Norms model fit: CFI=.865, RMSEA=.065, SRMR=.085, Endorsement model fit: CFI=.781, RMSEA=.063, SRMR=.082. All loadings are significant at p &lt; .001. 17 H-Other People should uphold and defend their family's reputation 18 H-Other People should not do anything that would damage their family's reputation 19 H-Other Men should protect the reputation of women they are related to 20 H-Other If a person's friend's reputation is questioned, they should come to their defense 21 F-Self People should think twice before speaking so as not to embarrass themselves 22 F-Self People should control their behavior in front of others 23 F-Self People should always know what is appropriate for a given situation and act accordingly 24 F-Self People worthy of respect are those who do their utmost to fulfill the expectations of their role 25 F-Self People should avoid doing anything inappropriate so as not to embarrass themselves 26 F-Other People should be very humble to maintain good relationships 27 F-Other People should be extremely careful not to embarrass others, especially if it is someone of a higher rank 28 F-Other People should treat others according to their social status to maintain good relationships 29 F-Other People should minimize conflict in social relationships at all costs 30 F-Other People should never criticize others in public, especially if it is someone older or more experienced</p><p>We calculated DHF norms mean scores based on this final item list to see if we can observe the expected group differences. Table <ref type="table">S8</ref> shows these mean scores. All means were significantly different between the three groups. As expected, White Europeans scored highest on both facets of dignity, but particularly high on dignity-self; Middle Easterners scored highest on both facets of honor, but particularly high on honor-other; East Asians scored highest on face-other, but there were no significant differences between East Asian and Middle Eastern participants on face-self. Overall, these results suggest that the final version of the questionnaire captures quite well the expected group differences in perceived norms associated with dignity, honor, and face cultural logics.</p><p>Table S8. Group differences in dignity, honor, and face norms Mean (SD) F-value (p-value) White Europeans Middle Easterners East Asians Dignity-Self 4.59 (0.77) 3.64 (1.16) 3.61 (0.92) 60.37 (&lt; .001) Dignity-Other 4.45 (1.01) 3.88 (1.21) 4.00 (0.96) 12.74 (&lt; .001) Honor-Self 4.29 (0.88) 4.87 (0.79) 4.31 (0.72) 20.93 (&lt; .001) Honor-Other 4.48 (0.88) 5.36 (0.64) 4.87 (0.67) 46.42 (&lt; .001) Face-Self 4.44 (0.73) 5.09 (0.62) 5.00 (0.70) 40.12 (&lt; .001) Face-Other 3.99 (0.84) 4.73 (0.73) 4.87 (0.70) 63.86 (&lt; .001)</p><p>Finally, we tested whether the two facets of each cultural logic are differentially predictive of self-reported positive and negative reciprocity. Table <ref type="table">S9</ref> presents the results.</p><p>Table S9. Regression models predicting self-reported positive and negative reciprocity from the selfand other-facet of dignity, honor, and face cultural logics. Positive reciprocity Negative reciprocity b SE p-value b SE p-value Dignity-Self 0.26 .08 &lt; .001 -0.10 .12 .388 Dignity-Other 0.31 .07 &lt; .001 -0.30 .11 .005 Honor-Self -0.04 .07 .545 0.68 .10 &lt; .001 Honor-Other 0.19 .07 .007 -0.14 .11 .217 Face-Self -0.07 .08 .396 0.34 .13 .008 Face-Other -0.03 .07 .653 -0.15 .11 .169</p><p>Consistent with expectations, the other-concern facet of dignity and honor predicted more positive reciprocity; however, this was not the case for the other-concern facet of face. Additionally, dignity-self also predicted more positive reciprocity. We found the expected positive association between honor-self and negative reciprocity. However, we also observed a negative relationship between dignity-other and negative reciprocity and a positive relationship between face-self and negative reciprocity. The latter finding, combined with nearly identical mean scores for face-self in the Middle Eastern and East Asian subsamples suggests that the self-protective aspect of face might be very similar to honor and might be equally prevalent in what are typically considered honor and face cultures.</p><p>Overall, the questionnaire fit the theoretical factor structure well enough, the scores based on the current version of the questionnaire were able to capture meaningful group differences, and the relationships with self-reported positive and negative reciprocity were mostly consistent with predictions, showing some additional nuances for the self-and other-facet differentiation that can be further explored in the main study. Response scale: strongly disagree (1), disagree (2), somewhat disagree (3), somewhat agree (4), agree <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">(5)</ref>, strongly agree (6) [See table <ref type="table">S7</ref> for the full DHF item list. Item order is randomized]</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main study questionnaire</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DHF_norms</head><p>Now please read the same statements, but instead of your personal opinion, indicate to what extent you think other people in your country would agree or disagree with each of them.</p><p>The item list and the response scale are the same as above.</p><p>Additionally, this page will include one attention check question: "Hello, are you still paying attention? If you are reading this question, please choose the option "Disagree"" Block 2. Dictator game</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General introduction</head><p>Now we would like to ask you to make decisions in a series of tasks. You will be playing for Monetary Units (MU), a fictional currency that gauges how well you are doing at the decision-making task. These Monetary Units are meaningful in the context of the experiment, but have no value in the real world.</p><p>In each task, we will randomly match you with another participant. You don't have to wait for the other participant to make your decisions. Your responses will be matched at the end of the session. Your decisions are anonymous.</p><p>Please read the instructions for each task carefully. We will ask you a couple of questions at the end to check your understanding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dictator game instructions</head><p>Page 1:</p><p>In this task you will be matched with a randomly selected participant. One of you will divide 10 Monetary Units between the two of you. You will be randomly assigned to one of the two roles: the Giver or the Receiver.</p><p>The Giver will decide how the 10 Monetary Units will be divided between you two. The Giver can distribute these Units in any way they want.</p><p>The Receiver has no say in the decision of the Giver. The Receiver will get as many Monetary Units as the Giver decided to give them. If the participant answered both questions correctly, they will receive the message: "Well done, you have correctly answered both questions! Now you can proceed to the task."</p><p>If the participant answered one or both of the comprehension questions incorrectly, they will see this message, followed by a second attempt at answering the same question(s) "Your answer to this question was incorrect. Please read the instructions carefully and try answering the question again.</p><p>The Giver will decide how the 10 Monetary Units will be divided between you two. The Giver can distribute these Units in any way they want. The Receiver has no say in the decision of the Giver. The Receiver will get as many Monetary Units as the Giver decided to give them."</p><p>Then, if the participant answers incorrectly again, they will be given the following feedback and will be allowed to continue: "You have given an incorrect answer to at least one of the comprehension questions. Please read the instructions one more time.</p><p>In this task you will be matched with a randomly selected participant. One of you will divide 10 Monetary Units between the two of you. You will be randomly assigned to one of the two roles: the Giver or the Receiver.</p><p>The Giver will decide how the 10 Monetary Units will be divided between you two. The Giver can distribute these Units in any way they want. The Receiver has no say in the decision of the Giver. The Receiver will get as many Monetary Units as the Giver decided to give them. Therefore, if the Giver decides to send 0 MU to the Receiver, then the Giver will earn 10 MU (10-0=10) and the Receiver will earn 0 MU.</p><p>If the Giver decides to send 6 MU to the Receiver, then the Giver will earn 4 MU (10-6=4) and the Receiver will earn 6 MU. Now you can proceed to the task."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dictator game decision</head><p>You are in the role of the Giver. Now it's time to make your decision! You must decide how many Monetary Units (MU) to send to the Receiver and how many Monetary Units to keep for yourself. We remind you that the Monetary Units can be distributed in any way you want and the Receiver has no control over your decision.</p><p>Please choose how many Monetary Units, if any, you want to send to the Receiver?</p><p>Response scale from 0 to 10.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Block 3. Ultimatum game</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ultimatum game instructions</head><p>"In this task, you will be matched with a new participant. One of you will divide 10 Monetary Units between the two of you. You will first be in the role of the Receiver and then in the role of the Proposer. You will be matched with the same person for the two rounds of this decision-making task.</p><p>The Proposer will decide how the 10 Monetary Units will be divided between you two.</p><p>The Receiver will then choose to either accept or reject the proposal.</p><p>If the Receiver chooses to accept the proposal, you will both receive Monetary Units in accordance with the Proposer's decision. To what degree do the following statements apply to you personally?</p><p>Response scale: 1 -"Does not apply to me at all" to 7 -"Applies to me perfectly"</p><p>between two people that involves incompatible goals, needs, or viewpoints. Please think of a situation that meets this definition in which you were involved during the past two years. Of course your responses are anonymous, but it would help our analyses if you would provide some information as to who was the other party in the conflict that you have chosen to describe: Please select the best description of the other person: ___your romantic partner, ___a close friend, ___a family member, ___someone from work or college ___other The other party was: ___male ___female ___non-binary Here are a series of statements referring to the conflict with which you may agree or disagree. Using the scale below, indicate your agreement with each item by selecting the appropriate number.</p><p>Response scale: 1 -"Strongly disagree" to 5 -"Strongly agree".</p><p>[Item order is randomized, except for the first question]</p><p>1. The conflict was satisfactorily resolved 2. Maintaining peace in our interaction was important to me 3. Maintaining humbleness to preserve the relationship was important to me 4. I was concerned with helping the other person to maintain their poise 5. I was concerned with helping the other person to maintain their credibility 6. I tried to be sensitive to the other person's self-worth 7. Helping to maintain the other person's pride was important to me 8. I was concerned with not bringing shame to myself 9. I was concerned with protecting my self-image 10. I was concerned with not appearing weak in front of the other person 11. I was concerned with protecting my personal pride Block 6. Attitudes towards violence</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>[Item order is randomized]</head><p>To what extent do you agree with the following statements?</p><p>Response scale: 1 -"Strongly disagree" to 5 -"Strongly agree".</p><p>1. Capital punishment is often necessary. 2. Violent crimes should be punished violently.</p><p>3. The death penalty should be part of every penal code.</p><p>4. War is often necessary. 5. War can be just. 6. Every nation should have a war industry. 7. A parent hitting a child when they do something bad on purpose teaches the child a good lesson. 8. A child's habitual disobedience should be punished physically. 9. Giving mischievous children a quick slap is the best way to quickly end trouble. 10. Partners should work things out together even if it takes violence. 11. The male should not allow the female the same amount of freedom as he has. 12. It is all right to coerce one's partner into having sex when they are not willing by forcing them.</p><p>Additionally, this page will include one attention check question: "Hello, are you still paying attention? If you are reading this question, please choose the option "Strongly agree"" Block 7. Reactions to provocation</p><p>Below you can find a description of three insulting situations. Each situation has three different endings. Do you think you would behave this way in a real situation? Please assess each of the described behaviors in terms of how likely you would be to behave this way. Please use the scale from 1 (I would never behave this way) to 7 (I would do it for sure).</p><p>1. During an informal meeting with co-workers, your colleague unfavorably spoke of your spouse by questioning their intellect.</p><p>As a reaction to this insult, you would:</p><p>-do nothing and expect others to intervene -return the insult or defend the person insulted -humorously comment on that person's behavior 2. During a party in the presence of many of your friends your acquaintance insulted your mother by calling her a prostitute.</p><p>As a reaction to this insult, you would:</p><p>-do nothing and expect others to intervene -return the insult or defend the person insulted -humorously comment on that person's behavior 3. During a family trip to another country someone at the railway station heard you use your language and called you 'stupid foreigners'.</p><p>As a reaction to this insult, you would:</p><p>-do nothing and expect others to intervene -return the insult or defend the person insulted -humorously comment on that person's behavior Block 8. Values</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Choice of pronouns</head><p>[This question will be altered or skipped for languages where all three options cannot be used.]</p><p>The following questionnaire uses gendered language in statements that might apply to you. Please select which version of the questionnaire you would like to see:</p><p>₋ male (pronouns he/him) ₋ female (pronouns she/her) ₋ gender neutral (pronouns they/them)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Values</head><p>Here we briefly describe some people. Please read each description and choose an option on each line that shows how much each person is or is not like you.</p><p>Response scale: 1 to 6, with labels "Not like me at all", "Not like me", "A little like me", "Somewhat like me", "Like me", "Very much like me".</p><p>[Items below represent the gender neutral version of the scale.]</p><p>1. Thinking up new ideas and being creative is important to them. They like to do things in their own original way. 2. It is important to them to be rich. They want to have a lot of money and expensive things. 3. They think it is important that every person in the world should be treated equally. They believe everyone should have equal opportunities in life. 4. It's important to them to show their abilities. They want people to admire what they do. 5. It is important to them to live in secure surroundings. They avoid anything that might endanger their safety. 6. They like surprises and are always looking for new things to do. They think it is important to do lots of different things in life. 7. They believe that people should do what they're told. They think people should follow rules at all times, even when no-one is watching. 8. It is important to them to listen to people who are different from them. Even when they disagree with them, they still want to understand them. 9. It is important to them to be humble and modest. They try not to draw attention to themselves. 10. Having a good time is important to them. They like to "spoil" themselves. 11. It is important to them to make their own decisions about what they do. They like to be free and not depend on others. 12. It's very important to them to help the people around them. They want to care for their well-being. 13. Being very successful is important to them. They hope people will recognize their achievements. 14. It is important to them that the government ensures their safety against all threats. They want the state to be strong so it can defend its citizens. 15. They look for adventures and like to take risks. They want to have an exciting life.</p><p>16. It is important to them always to behave properly. They want to avoid doing anything people would say is wrong. 17. It is important to them to get respect from others. They want people to do what they say. 18. It is important to them to be loyal to their friends. They want to devote themselves to people close to them. 19. They strongly believe that people should care for nature. Looking after the environment is important to them. 20. Tradition is important to them. They try to follow the customs handed down by their religion or their family. 21. They seek every chance they can to have fun. It is important to them to do things that give them pleasure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Block 9. Moral foundations</head><p>For each of the statements below, please indicate how well each statement describes you or your opinions.</p><p>25. Everyone should try to comfort people who are going through something hard. 26. When people work together toward a common goal, they should share the rewards equally, even if some worked harder on it. 27. In a fair society, those who work hard should live with higher standards of living. 28. Everyone should feel proud when a person in their community wins in an international competition. 29. I believe that one of the most important values to teach children is to have respect for authority. 30. People should try to use natural medicines rather than chemically identical human-made ones. 31. It pains me when I see someone ignoring the needs of another human being. 32. I get upset when some people have a lot more money than others in my country. 33. I feel good when I see cheaters get caught and punished. 34. I believe the strength of a sports team comes from the loyalty of its members to each other. 35. I think having a strong leader is good for society. 36. I admire people who keep their virginity until marriage.</p><p>Additionally, this page will include one attention check question: "Hello, are you still paying attention? If you are reading this question, please choose the option "Moderately describes me"" Block 10. Religiosity</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Public religious practice</head><p>How often do you attend religious services or meetings? 1 -Never; 2 -Once a year or less; 3 -A few times a year; 4 -A few times a month; 5 -Once a week; 6 -More than once/week</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Private religious practice</head><p>How often do you spend time in private religious activities, such as prayer, meditation or religious reading? 1 -Rarely or never; 2 -A few times a month; 3 -Once a week; 4 -Two or more times/week; 5 -Daily; 6 -More than once a day</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intrinsic religiosity</head><p>The following section contains 3 statements about religious belief or experience. Please mark the extent to which each statement is true or not true for you. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Country of residence</head><p>Where do you currently live? [A drop-down list of countries, plus "I prefer not to respond"]</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Migration background</head><p>Which of the following applies to you? By "this country" we mean the country where you currently live.</p><p>₋ I was born and raised in this country.</p><p>₋ I immigrated to this country from another country ₋ I was born and/or raised in this country, but at least one of my parents immigrated here from another country ₋ I prefer not to respond The response options will be determined for each regional subsample using data from the United Nations Statistics Division Demographic Statistics Database (most recent year available), the World Values Survey (Wave 7), or the Central Intelligence Agency World Factbook (most recent year available). If data is incomplete (i.e., less than 5 categories available) or unavailable from these sources, data from other reputable statistical agencies will be used to determine response options. The categories will be reviewed by local collaborators and adjusted if needed to best fit the cultural context of the geopolitical region.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis plan summary</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis</head><p>Analysis plan Interpretation given different outcomes Power analysis</p><p>H1a: A hierarchical model with three higher-order factors of dignity, honor, and face, each represented by two facets of self-concern and other-concern, will appropriately describe the data.</p><p>Individual endorsement and cultural norms will be tested separately. For each model, country will be used as a cluster variable.</p><p>Factor structure (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>): Multilevel confirmatory factor analysis (MCFA), specifying a hierarchical model with three correlated higher-order latent factors representing dignity, honor, and face, each with two sub-factors representing the self-concern and other-concern facets.</p><p>Test 1: Level 1 will include the proposed factor structure, and Level 2 will include only the saturated model where all observed variables are intercorrelated.</p><p>Test 2: Level 1 will include only the saturated model of observed variable correlations, and Level 2 will include the proposed factor If the model converges, it will be compared to the models below (see notes below). If the model does not converge after making adjustments as described under "Overall model plans", we will test the simpler alternative model with 6 correlated latent factors (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>).</p><p>After model selection, we will use the guidelines in the model improvement and alignment section to improve model fit.</p><p>Calculated for a single country/level: n = 43 to detect an RMSEA of .08 and n = 78 to detect an AGFI (adjusted goodness of fit index) of .90 with a power of 0.90, alpha =.05, df = 306 (calculated based on a three-factor hierarchical model).</p><p>Power calculated using semPower package in R <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Moshagen &amp; Bader, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>structure.</p><p>H1b: The hierarchical model will fit the data better than the three-factor model.</p><p>(We will alternatively test a six-factor model in case the hierarchical model does not converge.)</p><p>Individual endorsement and cultural norms will be tested separately. For each model, country will be used as a cluster variable.</p><p>Factor structure (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>): MCFA with three-factor correlated model of the DHF latent variables.</p><p>Test 1: Level 1 will include the proposed factor structure, and Level 2 will include only the saturated model where all observed variables are intercorrelated.</p><p>Test 2: Level 1 will include only the saturated model of observed variable correlations, and Level 2 will include the proposed factor structure.</p><p>The model will be considered significantly better than an alternative if <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Chen, 2007</ref>):</p><p>-AIC is lower -BIC is lower -ΔCFI &gt; .010 (the model with higher CFI is better) -ΔRMSEA &gt; .015 (the model with lower RMSEA is better)</p><p>All these criteria will be considered together, and if the majority of them are fulfilled, the model will be considered significantly better than the alternative. If models are not significantly different from each other, the theoretically hypothesized hierarchical model will be preferred.</p><p>semPower suggests n = 25 to n = 31 to detect a change in RMSEA of .015 to achieve power of 0.90, alpha = .05, Δdf = 6 for the three-factor model comparison to the hierarchical model, Δdf = 12 for the three-factor comparison to a six-factor model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Model improvement and evaluation (see hypotheses above)</head><p>The final model will be examined for:</p><p>-Poorly loading items.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Item evaluation:</head><p>-if a given item does not significantly load on the respective factor AND the model fit NA -Modification indices.</p><p>-Model fit.</p><p>improves after removing the item, or the item loads in the opposite to expected direction, the items will be removed. Otherwise, the item will be retained. -If modification indices suggest a strong residual correlation between items AND this correlation is theoretically justified, a residual correlation will be added. Model Evaluation -We will consider the model to have a good fit to the data if RMSEA ≤ .08 and SRMR_within ≤ .08. If ICC &lt; .10, we will additionally use CFI &gt; .90, and SRMR_between &lt; .08 as criteria (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ene, 2020</ref>). -If .08 &lt; RMSEA &lt; .10, .08 &lt; SRMR &lt; .10, and .80 &lt; CFI &lt; .90, we will consider the model acceptable, unless there are specific issues with items as described above. -If RMSEA &gt; .10, SRMR &gt; .10, CFI &lt; .80, we will consider the model unacceptable.</p><p>All model fit indices will be considered together, and if the majority of indices suggest acceptable fit, a single indicator will not be considered sufficient to reject the model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measurement alignment</head><p>Alignment optimization procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Asparouhov &amp; Muthén, 2023)</ref> will be used to estimate the degree of metrics and scalar invariance and to compare the group means.</p><p>We will first test the full configural model identified at the previous step. Considering the large number of groups and parameters, it is possible that the model will be computationally too intensive. If this is the case, we will consider running the alignment procedure for each factor separately.</p><p>The sample size estimate is based on a simulation study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Wen and Hu (2022)</ref> that suggests that with a high number of groups (&gt;15), a group size of 250 would be sufficient for a model that Level 2: prosocial, positive reciprocity, and negative reciprocity will be predicted by DHF scores for sample aggregated norms.</p><p>H4a: Individual endorsement of honor culture will positively predict attitudes toward violence.</p><p>A multilevel, random-intercept model (country) predicting attitudes toward violence from individual-level endorsement and country-level norm scores for honor, face, and dignity.</p><p>A significant (p &lt; .05) positive effect of individual-level honor will be interpreted as support for the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis.</p><p>Power was simulated using pilot data to estimate fixed effects for the individual endorsement of DHF, standard errors, and random effects.</p><p>The data was simulated with = .20 for A: honor, B: face, C: Dignity (negative). Given 50 expected countries, 20-30 participants per country are needed to achieve 80% power.</p><p>H4b: Individual endorsement of face culture will positively predict other-face concern in interpersonal conflict.</p><p>A multilevel, random-intercept model (country) predicting other-face concern in interpersonal conflict from individual-level endorsement and country-level norm scores for honor, face, and dignity.</p><p>A significant (p &lt; .05) positive effect of individual-level face will be interpreted as support for the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis.</p><p>H4c: Individual endorsement of dignity culture will negatively predict other-face concern in interpersonal conflict.</p><p>A significant (p &lt; .05) negative effect of individual-level dignity will be interpreted as support for the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis.</p><p>H5a: Individual endorsement of honor culture will positively predict retaliation in response to provocation.</p><p>A multilevel, random-intercept path model predicting retaliation, withdrawal, and humor as reactions to provocation from individual-level endorsement and sample-level aggregate scores for honor, face, and dignity.</p><p>A significant (p &lt; .05) positive effect of individual-level honor on retaliation will be interpreted as support for the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis.</p><p>Parameters are based on z-score estimation, which do not involve degrees of freedom for significance purposes. If we assume our standard errors are approximate from the sample data (~.10 across parameters H5b: Individual endorsement of face culture will positively A significant (p &lt; .05) positive effect of individual-level face on withdrawal will be</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Competing models for the DHF questionnaire structure</figDesc><graphic coords="9,78.75,149.65,390.75,195.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>CFA model with three correlated DHF latent variables, without further differentiation into the facets (H1b. Fig.1B). If the hierarchical model fails to converge, we will compare a three-factor model to a six-factor model of each of the self and other facets separately. Each model will be clustered by country. Each factor structure will be tested separately at the individual level (Level 1) and country level (Level 2). When testing the individual-level factor structure, Level 1 in the model will include the proposed factor structure. Level 2 will include only the saturated model where all observed variable residuals are intercorrelated. When testing the country-level factor structure, Level 1 in the model will include only the saturated model of observed variable residual correlations, and Level 2 will include the proposed factor structure. We will select the best-fitting model for each level (see Analysis Plan Summary for model selection criteria) and combine them into a unified multilevel model. The individual endorsement and cultural norms will be tested separately resulting in 8 models: two ratings (individual endorsement, cultural norms) by two level tests (Level 1 factor structure, Level 2 factor structure) by two factor structures (hierarchical vs. three-factor or three-factor vs. six-factor) models.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>higher on both honor facets, self: d = 0.33, F(1,291) = 7.92, p = .005 and other: d = 0.47, F(1,291) = 15.83, p &lt;. 001), but not when asking about personal endorsement (self: d = -0.18, F(1,291) = 2.47, p = .117, other: d = 0.01, F(1,291) = .002, p = .965).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>1.</head><figDesc>People should make decisions based on their own opinions and not based on what others think. 2. People should be true to themselves regardless of what others think. 3. How much a person respects themselves is far more important than how much others respect them. 4. People's opinions should be independent of what others around them think. 5. A person's sense of worth should not depend on what others think of them.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc>Participant information sheet and consent form [see ethics documentation] Block 1. Dignity, honor, face DHF_endorsement Please read the statements below and indicate to what extent you personally agree or disagree with each of them.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc>the Giver sends 0 MU to the Receiver The Giver earns: 10 MU The Receiver earns: 0 MU 2. If the Giver sends 5 MU to the Receiver The Giver earns: 5 MU The Receiver earns: 5 MU Page 3: Comprehension questions: 1. Suppose the Giver decides to send 0 MU to the Receiver. How many MU does each person then earn? • Giver: 0 MU; Receiver: 0 MU • Giver: 10 MU; Receiver: 0 MU • Giver: 5 MU; Receiver: 0 MU 2. Suppose the Giver decides to send 6 MU to the Receiver. How many MU does each person then earn? • Giver: 0 MU; Receiver: 6 MU • Giver: 10 MU; Receiver: 6 MU • Giver: 4 MU; Receiver: 6 MU Page 4:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc>If the Receiver chooses to reject the proposal, neither of you will receive any Monetary Units." the Proposer sends 0 MU to the Receiver and the Receiver rejects the offer The Proposer earns: 0 MU The Receiver earns: 0 MU 2. If the Proposer sends 5 MU to the Receiver and the Receiver accepts the offer The Proposer earns: the Proposer decides to send 6 MU to the Receiver and the Receiver rejects the proposal. How many MU does each person then earn? • Proposer 0 MU; Receiver 0 MU • Proposer 10 MU; Receiver 0 MU • Proposer 4 MU; Receiver 0 MU Ultimatum game decision: Receiver Now you are in the role of the Receiver. It's time to make your decision! Please review the options listed below. For each possible number of Monetary Units (0-10), consider whether to accept or reject the Proposer's proposal. Please make your decisions on the following proposals: in the role of the Proposer. It's time to make your decision! Remember that you are playing with the same person as before. Only this time, they will not be able to reject your proposal. They will receive as many Monetary Units as you propose now. Please decide how many Monetary Units you would want to propose to the other person for each possible number of Monetary Units they could have sent to you in the first round. If they proposed 0 MU before, person had the power to accept or reject your proposal in this last round, do you think the other person would accept or reject your proposal if you proposed: List of proposals from 0 to 10 MU with response options "The other person would accept" and "The other person would reject". Block 4. Positive and negative reciprocity [Item order is randomized]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>1.</head><figDesc>In my life, I experience the presence of the Divine (in other words, God). 1 -Definitely not true; 2 -Tends not to be true; 3 -Unsure; 4 -Tends to be true; 5 -Definitely true of me 2. My religious beliefs are what really lie behind my whole approach to life. 1 -Definitely not true; 2 -Tends not to be true; 3 -Unsure; 4 -Tends to be true; 5 -Definitely true of me 3. I try hard to carry my religion over into all other dealings in life. 1 -Definitely not true; 2 -Tends not to be true; 3 -Unsure; 4 -Tends to be true; 5 -Definitely true of me Block 11. Subjective well-being Below are five statements that you may agree or disagree with. Using the 1 -7 scale below, indicate your agreement with each item by placing the appropriate number on the line preceding that item. Please be open and honest in your responding. Response scale from 1 -"Strongly disagree" to 7 -"Strongly agree". 1. In most ways my life is close to my ideal. 2. The conditions of my life are excellent. 3. I am satisfied with my life. 4. So far I have gotten the important things I want in life. 5. If I could live my life over, I would change almost nothing. Block 12. Socio-demographic characteristics This is the last part of the questionnaire. Please tell us a bit about yourself. Age How old are you? [A drop-down list of ages from &lt;18, 18 to 99, plus "I prefer not to respond"] Gender What is your gender identity? ₋ Woman ₋ Man ₋ Non-binary ₋ Other (please describe)_____ ₋ I prefer not to respond</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>[</head><figDesc>if family immigrated, show the question below] You said that at least one of your parents immigrated from another country. Which country did they come from? If your parents immigrated from different countries, please indicate both countries. Parent 1: [Dropdown list of countries] Parent 2: [Dropdown list of countries] Location growing up What best describes where you grew up? cultural group do you identify with most? [the list will include the five largest ethnic groups in each geopolitical region 2 , plus "Other (please describe)" with an open text box, "Multiple groups (please describe)" with an open text box, and "I prefer not to respond"] Religion Which religion, if any, do you identify with? ₋ None (atheist/agnostic) ₋ Christianity ₋ Islam ₋ Judaism 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Terminology</figDesc><table><row><cell>Term</cell><cell>Definition</cell></row><row><cell>Individual endorsement of DHF</cell><cell>Ratings on DHF items when the instruction reads "indicate to</cell></row><row><cell>cultural logics</cell><cell>what extent you personally agree or disagree with each of them".</cell></row></table><note><p>DHF perceived cultural norms</p><p>Ratings on DHF items when the instruction reads "indicate to what extent you think other people in your country would agree or disagree with each of them".</p><p>Individual level scores</p><p>Participants' individual ratings of the items.</p><p>Sample/country level scores Aggregated scores by country, average of all valid responses by participants in that country.</p><p>Level 1 [within]</p><p>Refers to a level of analysis in multilevel models where individual level scores and variances are used for modeling.</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Data from younger participants (16-17 y.o.) can be collected in some instances when local collaborators have obtained ethical approval for it. However, the main analysis will only include participants who are 18 or older.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Materials</head><p>for "(In)alienable worth? The prevalence of cultural logics of dignity, honor, and face and their links to prosociality across the world" </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contents</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pilot study 1 Method</head><p>The pilot questionnaire included the DHF scale as shown in Table <ref type="table">S1</ref> (both individual endorsement and perceived norms), universal prosociality measured with a dictator game, positive and negative reciprocity measured with an ultimatum game, and self-reported positive and negative reciprocity. Pilot study materials, code, and data are available on OSF: <ref type="url" target="https://tinyurl.com/4dzcdc3w">https://tinyurl.com/4dzcdc3w</ref>.</p><p>We recruited 300 US American participants from the crowdsourcing platform Prolific academic. The sample was balanced on gender (49% men, 48% women, 2% non-binary, and one person did not answer), and the mean age of participants was 38.7 years (SD = 14). We recruited an equal number of participants from New York (N = 146) and Texas (N = 147), which are expected to differ in DHF scores. The questionnaire took about 15 minutes to complete and participants received £2.25 for their time. Face items performed worse than dignity and honor items. This outcome might be because fewer collaborators had expertise in this area, or because the cultural logic of face is relational at its core, which makes it difficult to differentiate between self and other concerns. Finally, more face items were developed specifically for this study and have not been tested before (5 out of 6 face-self items and 1 out of 5 face-other items) compared with dignity and honor. Considering all this, especially the relational nature of the concept of face, we apply less strict criteria to the choice of face items. Specifically, we consider the percentage of collaborators who correctly identified that the item measures face, but not the specific domain (self or other).</p><p>We decided to keep items that were correctly identified by at least 50% of the collaborators if over 60% of collaborators correctly guessed that the item measures face cultural logic. Three items satisfied these criteria: "People should think twice before speaking not to embarrass themselves", "People should avoid situations where they could be embarrassed", and "A person cannot respect themselves if they are not fulfilling their responsibilities". The "avoid" item was slightly modified to For dignity-self, all items performed well and the loadings were &gt;.40 for both endorsement and norms measures. We will therefore keep the five items that passed all previous rounds of item selection. For dignity-other, all five items performed well and no backup items were included. For honor-self, all items performed well (𝛽s &gt; .40), we will therefore keep the five items that passed all previous rounds of item selection. For honor-other, the backup item about family reputation performed better than the item about friend's reputation (𝛽 =.8 vs. 𝛽 =.3). This is not surprising, given the scale contains two other items about family reputation that would all be strongly correlated. This backup item would be a replacement for one of the other family items, but since both of the family items performed well and the friend item performed very well in the collaborator survey and increases the overall validity of the construct by covering other aspects of honor-other besides family, we decided to keep the original five items. For face-self, the backup item ("People should control their behavior in front of others") performed better than the new item that was introduced based on the collaborator survey ("If someone made me lose face, I would avoid this person in the future"). We decided to keep the "control behavior" item and discard the new item, as it has been successfully used in earlier studies and performed well in our first pilot study. Finally, for face-other, one item ("People should avoid making others look incompetent") underperformed, with loadings &lt;.40 on both norms and endorsement measures. Since this was a new item added based on the results of the collaborator survey, we will replace it with an item that has been successfully used in earlier studies and performed better in the pilot: "People should be very humble to maintain good relationships". The final item list is presented in table <ref type="table">S7</ref>. The item order will be randomized in the survey. If the participant answered both questions correctly, they will receive the message:</p><p>"Well done, you have correctly answered both questions! Now you can proceed to the task."</p><p>If the participant answered one or both of the questions incorrectly, they will see this message, followed by a second attempt at answering the same question(s):</p><p>"Your answer to this question was incorrect. Please read the instructions carefully and try answering the question again.</p><p>The Proposer will decide how the 10 Monetary Units will be divided between you two. The Receiver will then choose to either accept or reject the proposal. If the Receiver chooses to accept the proposal, you will both receive Monetary Units in accordance with the Proposer's decision. If the Receiver chooses to reject the proposal, neither of you will receive any Monetary Units."</p><p>Then, if the participant answers incorrectly a second time, they will be given the following feedback and will be allowed to continue:</p><p>"You have given an incorrect answer to at least one of the comprehension questions. Please read the instructions one more time.</p><p>In this task, you will be matched with a new participant. One of you will divide 10 Monetary Units between the two of you. You will first be in the role of the Receiver and then in the role of the Proposer. You will be matched with the same person for the two rounds of this decision-making task.</p><p>The Proposer will decide how the 10 Monetary Units will be divided between you two. The Receiver will then choose to either accept or reject the proposal. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Student status</head><p>Are you currently enrolled as a full-time student at a College or University?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subjective income</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Which of the descriptions below comes closest to how you feel about your household's income nowadays?</head><p>₋ Living comfortably on present income ₋ Coping on present income ₋ Finding it difficult on present income ₋ Finding it very difficult on present income [If certain socio-demographic questions are considered problematic in some countries, collaborators can argue for their exclusion from the questionnaire in that country. Participants can skip any of the socio-demographic questions, except the ones that will be used for screening: age, country of residence, and migration background.]</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Debriefing form [see ethics documentation]</head><p>Model fit in the alignment procedure is the same as for that of a configural model in MGCFA. Since our initial model selection uses multilevel CFA, the model fit indices might be different from the ones described above. We will use the same criteria as above to evaluate the configural model. We will use free alignment unless we get a warning message that the free alignment is compromised (this can happen when the number of groups and items is small), in which case we will switch to fixed alignment. We will assess the alignment results based on the following criteria: -If a parameter (loading or intercept) is invariant across 70% of all samples, we will consider this parameter to be acceptable for cross-cultural comparisons. -If 50% of all items in a scale (see the results of a simulation study in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Asparouhov &amp; Muthén, 2023)</ref> show an acceptable level of invariance based on the criteria described above, we will consider the latent scores for this factor to be comparable across countries. -If either of the above criteria are not satisfied, we will consider dropping items if specific items show a high degree of non-variance, or testing alternative factor structures if certain clusters of countries/samples show non-invariance on multiple parameters. In all multilevel models (H2-H5), individual-level predictors will be group-mean centered and sample-level predictors will be grand-mean centered.</p><p>support the hypotheses. Significant effects for some but no effect for other other-facets will be interpreted as partial support for the hypothesis. Non-significant effects for any or negative effects for some will be interpreted as evidence against the hypothesis.</p><p>If the 3-factor model is used (dignity, honor, face), the test will be exploratory.</p><p>effects for the self-facets, standard errors, and random effects. The data was simulated with = .20 for each other-facet. Given 50 expected countries, 40 participants per country are needed to achieve 80% power.</p><p>H3a: Higher country-level honor logic scores will predict higher positive reciprocity.</p><p>A multilevel, random-intercept path model predicting universal prosociality and positive and negative reciprocity from individual-level and sample-level DHF norm scores. The models below and in further hypotheses use 3 factors at the individual and 3 factors at the sample level; this analysis is conditional upon the higher-order DHF factors showing appropriate fit for both endorsement and norms measures.</p><p>Country will be used as the cluster variable for random intercepts.</p><p>Level 1: prosocial, positive reciprocity, and negative reciprocity will be predicted by DHF scores for individual endorsement.</p><p>A significant positive effect (p &lt; .05) of sample-level honor logic on positive reciprocity will support the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis. H3b: Higher country-level face logic scores will predict higher positive reciprocity.</p><p>A significant positive effect (p &lt; .05) of sample-level face logic on positive reciprocity will support the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis.</p><p>H3c: Higher country-level honor logic scores will predict higher negative reciprocity.</p><p>A significant positive effect (p &lt; .05) of sample-level honor logic on negative reciprocity will support the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis.</p><p>Country will be used as the cluster variable for random intercepts.</p><p>Level 1: Retaliation, withdrawal, and humor will be predicted by DHF scores for individual endorsement.</p><p>Level 2: Retaliation, withdrawal, and humor will be predicted by DHF scores for sample aggregated norms.</p><p>as high estimate with smaller sample size models), we would be able to detect regression loadings of approximately .20 (i.e., 1.96 * SE).</p><p>predict withdrawal in response to provocation.</p><p>interpreted as support for the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis.</p><p>H5c: Individual endorsement of dignity culture will positively predict humor in response to provocation.</p><p>A significant (p &lt; .05) positive effect of individual-level dignity on humor will be interpreted as support for the hypothesis. Non-significant effect or an effect in the opposite direction will provide evidence against the hypothesis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis Pipeline</head><p>Please see the GitHub repository at: <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/psysciacc/JTF002-DHF">https://github.com/psysciacc/JTF002-DHF</ref> for the full code of the analysis pipeline.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and testing of the velicer attitudes toward violence scale: Evidence for a four-factor model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Benjamin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bonacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ab.20112</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/ab.20112" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aggressive Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple group alignment for exploratory and structural equation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asparouhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10705511.2022.2127100</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10705511.2022.2127100" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morality beyond the WEIRD: How the nomological network of morality varies across cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Atari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koleva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dehghani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/pspp0000470</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/pspp0000470" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1188" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ingroup favoritism in cooperation: a meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Balliet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K W</forename><surname>De Dreu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1556" to="1581" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Honor ideology for Womanhood Scale (HIW)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lenes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bosson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Carvallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/t61311-000</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/t61311-000" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">APA PsycTests</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Database record</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Don&apos;t tread on me: Masculine honor ideology in the U.S. and militant responses to terrorism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Osterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167212443383</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167212443383" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1018" to="1029" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structural organization of human values-evidence from three rounds of the European Social Survey (ESS)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bilsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Janik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022022110362757</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0022022110362757" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="759" to="776" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An evolutionary perspective on social identity: Revisiting groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Caporael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9780203782965</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9780203782965" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Evolution and Social Psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schaller</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kenrick</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Psychosocial Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="161" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">School violence and the culture of honor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Osterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-9280.2009.02456.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2009.02456.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1400" to="1405" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sensitivity of goodness of fit indexes to lack of measurement invariance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10705510701301834</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10705510701301834" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="464" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interdependence and cooperation in daily life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Columbus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Molho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Righetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Balliet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/pspi0000253</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/pspi0000253" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="626" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cultural prototypes and dimensions of honor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Uskul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gerçek-Swing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sunbay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Alözkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Günsoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ataca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Karakitapoğlu-Aygün</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167213510323</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167213510323" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morality as cooperation: A problem-centred approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Curry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-319-19671-8_2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-19671-8_2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The evolution of morality</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shackelford</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="51" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is it good to cooperate?: Testing the theory of morality-as-cooperation in 60 societies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Curry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mullins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Whitehouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/701478</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1086/701478" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Anthropology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Satisfaction With Life Scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Diener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Emmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Larsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Griffin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9781003035312-41</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781003035312-41" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality Assessment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collaborative and iterative translation: An alternative approach to back translation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/25049073" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Explaining altruistic sharing in the dictator game: The role of affective empathy, cognitive empathy, and justice sensitivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Edele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dziobek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.lindif.2012.12.020</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lindif.2012.12.020" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Learning and Individual Differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Need for conclusive evidence that positive and negative reciprocity are unrelated</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Egloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schmukle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1221451110</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1221451110" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="786" to="E786" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Investigating accuracy of model fit indices in multilevel Confirmatory Factor Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://scholarcommons.sc.edu/etd/6024" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Doctoral dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dictator games: A meta study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Engel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10683-011-9283-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10683-011-9283-7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Experimental Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="610" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceptions of the appropriate response to norm violation in 57 societies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Eriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Strimling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gelfand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Abernathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Akotia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aldashev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrighetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Anum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Arikan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Aycan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bagherian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Barrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Basnight-Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Batkeyev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Belaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Berezina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Björnstjerna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Van Lange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41467-021-21602-9</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.fao.org/faostat" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2024</date>
			<publisher>United Nations</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Culture and prosocial behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Feygina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordhb/9780195399813.013.009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780195399813.013.009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Oxford Handbook of Prosocial Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Farmers, herders, and fishers: The ecology of revenge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Figueredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mcneil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Guillén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2004.05.005</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2004.05.005" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution and Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocity, culture and human cooperation: previous insights and a new cross-cultural experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gächter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2008.0275</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2008.0275" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">364</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1518</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="806" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differences between tight and loose cultures: A 33-nation study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gelfand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Raver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nishii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leslie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Almaliach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Arnadottir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Aycan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Boehnke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Boski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cabecinhas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chhokar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>D'amato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ferrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fischlmayr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Yamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.1197754</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/doi:10.1126/science.1197754" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">332</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6033</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1100" to="1104" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why we need to abandon fixed cutoffs for goodness-of-fit indices: An extensive simulation and possible solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Groskurth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bluemke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lechner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3758/s13428-023-02193-3</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3758/s13428-023-02193-3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavior Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3891" to="3914" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two dimensions of Dignity and Honor: the adaptation of the measurement in the Armenian language</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Grigoryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Khachatryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4087/VZBZ5973</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4087/VZBZ5973" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings from the 26th Congress of the International Association for CrossCultural Psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Buchtel</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Friedlmeier</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>from the 26th Congress of the International Association for CrossCultural Psychology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="223" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Year of the Golden Jubilee: Culture Change in the Past, Present and Future</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Honor Scale: Evidence on construct validity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Gouveia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Araújo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>De Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gaudêncio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jasp.12089</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/jasp.12089" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1273" to="1280" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An experimental analysis of ultimatum bargaining</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Güth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schmittberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schwarze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0167-2681(82)90011-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/0167-2681(82)90011-7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the concept of Face</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>.-F</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2777600" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="867" to="884" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hofstede&apos;s culture dimensions: An independent validation using Rokeach&apos;s Value Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hofstede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022002184015004003</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0022002184015004003" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental economics and Experimental Game Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Houser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mccabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/B978-0-12-416008-8.00002-4</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-416008-8.00002-4" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Neuroeconomics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Glimcher</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fehr</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="34" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2 nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Chinese concepts of &quot;Face</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/662926" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Anthropologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="1944">1944</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fit indices in covariance structure modeling: Sensitivity to underparameterized model misspecification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>-T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bentler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/1082-989X.3.4.424</idno>
		<ptr target="https://sites.duke.edu/icbdata/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Behavior (ICB) dataset</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998. 2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="453" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revenge: A Multilevel Review and Synthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gelfand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-psych-010418-103305</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-psych-010418-103305" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement invariance of the Satisfaction With Life Scale across 26 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lapierre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>O'driscoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Sanchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Spector</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A Y</forename><surname>Poelmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Abarca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alexandrova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-S</forename><surname>Antoniou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Beham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Brough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Carikci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ferreiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fraile</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Geurts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022022117697844</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0022022117697844" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="560" to="576" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fairness as a constraint on profit seeking: Entitlements in the market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Knetsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/1806070" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="728" to="741" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.earlymoderntexts.com/assets/pdfs/kant1785.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Grundlegung zur Metaphysik der Sitten (Groundwork for the Metaphysic of Morals</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>J. Bennett</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1785">1785</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Trans.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information, perspective, and judgments about the self in face and dignity cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167210362398</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167210362398" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Duke University Religion Index (DUREL): A five-item measure for use in epidemiological studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Koenig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Büssing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/rel1010078</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/rel1010078" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Religions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Punches or punchlines? Honor, face, and dignity cultures encourage different reactions to provocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Krys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zelenski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Capaldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wojciszke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1515/humor-2016-0087</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1515/humor-2016-0087" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Humor</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Within-and between-culture variation: Individual differences and the cultural logics of honor, face, and dignity cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0022151</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0022151" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="526" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-cultural differences in helping strangers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Norenzayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Philbrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022022101032005002</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0022022101032005002" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="543" to="560" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Japanese folk concept of mentsu: An indigenous approach from psychological perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4087/CEZM3471</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4087/CEZM3471" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Perspectives and progress in contemporary cross-cultural psychology: Proceedings from the 17th International Congress of the International Association for Cross-Cultural Psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Adair</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Need for approval from others and face concerns as predictors of interpersonal conflict outcome in 29 cultural groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M C</forename><surname>Lun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Grigoryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Papastylianou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lopukhova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sunar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Easterbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Koc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Selim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chobthamkit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chaleeraktrakoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perez Floriano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Diaz-Loving</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kwantes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ogusu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Van Osch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Hakobjanyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ijop.12895</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/ijop.12895" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="271" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">National Culture and Prosocial Behaviors: Results From 66 Countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Luria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cnaan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Boehm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0899764014554456</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0899764014554456" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1041" to="1065" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sufficient sample sizes for multilevel modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J M</forename><surname>Maas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1027/1614-2241.1.3.86</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1027/1614-2241.1.3.86" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methodology: European Journal of Research Methods for the Behavioral and Social Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceptions of emotional functionality: similarities and differences among dignity, face, and honor cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Maitner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Decoster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Eriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sherbaji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Giner-Sorolla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mackie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aveyard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Claypool</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gritskov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Habjan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hartanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kiyonari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Kuzminska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Manesi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Molho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Munasinghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Peperkoorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/00220221211065108</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/00220221211065108" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do dimensions of culture exist objectively? A validation of the revised Minkov-Hofstede model of culture with World Values Survey items and scores for 102 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Minkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.intman.2022.100971</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.intman.2022.100971" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100971</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">semPower: General power analysis for structural equation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moshagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3758/s13428-023-02254-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3758/s13428-023-02254-7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavior Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Masculine and feminine honor codes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M R</forename><surname>Mosquera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1174/021347411794078499</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1174/021347411794078499" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Revista de Psicología Social</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Historical prevalence of infectious diseases within 230 geopolitical regions: A tool for investigating origins of culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schaller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022022109349510</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0022022109349510" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Culture of honor: The psychology of violence in the South</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nisbett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Westview Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Evolutionary Basis of Honor Cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gelfand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Borkowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0956797615602860</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797615602860" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Face concerns in interpersonal conflict: A cross-cultural empirical test of the face negotiation theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Oetzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ting-Toomey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0093650203257841</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0093650203257841" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communication Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="599" to="624" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Face and facework in conflict: A cross-cultural comparison of China, Germany, Japan, and the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Oetzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ting-Toomey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Masumoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yokochi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Takai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wilcox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communication Monographs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">There is no such thing as a right to dignity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>O'mahony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/icon/mos010</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/icon/mos010" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Constitutional Law</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="574" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the importance of internal and external self-esteem and their relationship to honor concerns in six countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Van Osch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kunuroglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Tillman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Benítez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sekaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mamathuba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1069397120909383</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1069397120909383" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cross-Cultural Research: The Journal of Comparative Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A different kind of honor culture: Family honor and aggression in Turks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Van Osch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Breugelmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zeelenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bölük</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1368430212467475</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1368430212467475" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Group Processes &amp; Intergroup Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="334" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Culture of Honor and Violence Against the Self</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Osterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167211418529</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167211418529" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1611" to="1623" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-cultural comparison of self-construal and well-being between Japan and South Korea: The role of self-focused and other-focused relational selves</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Norasakkunkit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1516</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Peristiany</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ZdsdNQAACAAJ" />
		<title level="m">Honour and Shame: The Values of Mediterranean Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Weidenfeld and Nicolson</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Honour and social status</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pitt-Rivers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Honour and Shame: The Values of Mediterranean Society</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Peristiany</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Weidenfeld and Nicolson</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="78" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Different Dialects&quot;: Examining masculine and feminine honor across gender and ethnicity in an American context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pomerantz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mccollum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12144-022-03328-z</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12144-022-03328-z" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22623" to="22636" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moral psychology is relationship regulation: moral motives for unity, hierarchy, equality, and proportionality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fiske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0021867</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0021867" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of honor concerns in emotional reactions to offences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodriguez Mosquera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S R</forename><surname>Manstead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02699930143000167</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02699930143000167" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognition and Emotion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parochial trust and cooperation across 17 societies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Romano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Balliet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamagishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1712921114</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1712921114" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12702" to="12707" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">National parochialism is ubiquitous across 42 nations around the world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Romano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamagishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Balliet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41467-021-24787-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-24787-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4456</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Individual differences in masculine honor beliefs predict attitudes toward aggressive security measures, war, and peace. Peace and Conflict</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Saucier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mcmanus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sonnentag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'dea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Strain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/pac0000303</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/pac0000303" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Peace Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Repository of Schwartz Value Scales with Instructions and an Introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.9707/2307-0919.1173</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.9707/2307-0919.1173" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Online Readings in Psychology and Culture</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is an emphasis on dignity, honor and face more an attribute of individuals or of cultural groups?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Easterbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Koc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-C</forename><surname>Papastylianou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Grigoryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Efremova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Abbas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Al-Bayati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Selim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Delfino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Gamsakhurdia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gavreliuc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gavreliuc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chobthamkit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1069397120979571</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1069397120979571" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cross-Cultural Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Self-Construals in Cultures Differing in Dignity, Honor and Face Logics: A Study of 29 Nations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Grigoryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Delfino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chobthamkit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Efremova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Daganzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ogusu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Maldonado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gamsakhurdia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perez Floriano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Diaz Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Lopukhova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abbas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Papastylianou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tripodi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gunsoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hakobjanyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grigoryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kocak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mendes Texeira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Selim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Milfont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gavreliuc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gavreliuc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bilewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kwantes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Easterbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Koc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Manuscript in preparation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the scale for measuring independent-interdependent view of self</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of Research Institute</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Nara University</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relational mobility predicts social behaviors in 39 countries and is tied to historical farming and threat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Talhelm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ayanian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ferreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fülöp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Houghton-Illera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Joasoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kavanagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Khutkyy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Manzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Visserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1713191115</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1713191115" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7521" to="7526" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intercultural conflicts: A face-negotiation theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ting-Toomey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Theories in intercultural communication</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gudykunst</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Facework competence in intercultural conflict: An updated face-negotiation theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ting-Toomey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kurogi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0147-1767(98)00004-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0147-1767(98)00004-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Intercultural Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Managing intercultural conflict effectively</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ting-Toomey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Oetzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>Sage Publications, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Origins of human cooperation and morality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tomasello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vaish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-psych-113011-143812</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-psych-113011-143812" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="255" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Religiousness worldwide: Translation of the Duke University Religion Index into 20 languages and validation across 27 nations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Toscanelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Shino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Thalmayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s42409-022-00041-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/s42409-022-00041-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Measurement Instruments for the Social Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Socio-ecological roots of cultures of honor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Uskul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.copsyc.2019.11.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copsyc.2019.11.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of honour in interpersonal, intrapersonal and intergroup processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Uskul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Günsoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/spc3.12719</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/spc3.12719" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social and Personality Psychology Compass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stand by your man: Indirect prescriptions for honorable violence and feminine loyalty in Canada, Chile, and the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vandello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grandon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Franiuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022022108326194</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0022022108326194" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A measurement model for measuring attitudes toward violence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Huckel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167289153006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167289153006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Are Mediterranean societies &apos;cultures of honor&apos;? Prevalence and implications of a cultural logic of honor across three world regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Vignoles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kirchner-Häusler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Uskul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Uchida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rodriguez-Bailón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R L</forename><surname>Bossom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gezici Yalçın</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Harb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Husnu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ishii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Karamaouna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kafetsios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kateri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Matamoros-Lima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Miniesy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Özkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pagliaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Psaltis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rabie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Teresi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Uchida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Wohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Manuscript submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating the applicability of alignment: A Monte Carlo simulation study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.845721</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.845721" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">845721</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rejection of unfair offers in the ultimatum game is no evidence of strong reciprocity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamagishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Horita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mifune</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hashimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shinada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Miura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Inukai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takagishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Simunovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1212126109</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1212126109" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20364" to="20368" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A measurement model for dignity, face, and honor cultural norms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ramirez-Marin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aslani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Semnani-Azad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/mor.2017.49</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/mor.2017" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management and Organization Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="738" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">intense disagreement Response options: Does not describe me at all (1); slightly describes me (2); moderately describes me (3); describes me fairly well (4); and describes me extremely well</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Interpersonal conflict Now we would like to ask you to recall a recent conflict in which you have been involved and answer some questions about how it was handled By a conflict we mean a relatively</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Caring for people who have suffered is an important virtue</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">have fewer problems if people had the same income</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>I believe that compassion for those who are suffering is one of the most crucial virtues. 8. Our society would</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">I am empathetic toward those people who have suffered in their lives</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">We all need to learn from our elders</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
