<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Real-time assessment of motives for sharing and creating content among highly active Twitter users</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Joachim Herz Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_n2s3nsq">
					<orgName type="full">Volkswagen Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-07-02">July 2, 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Philipp</forename><surname>Lorenz-Spreen</surname></persName>
							<email>lorenz-spreen@mpib-berlin.mpg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Adaptive Rationality</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Max Planck Institute for Human Development</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ruben</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Arslan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Adaptive Rationality</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Max Planck Institute for Human Development</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anastasia</forename><surname>Kozyreva</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Adaptive Rationality</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Max Planck Institute for Human Development</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Briony</forename><surname>Swire-Thompson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Northeastern University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Geers</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Adaptive Rationality</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Max Planck Institute for Human Development</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Humboldt University of Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Adaptive Rationality</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Max Planck Institute for Human Development</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ralph</forename><surname>Hertwig</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Adaptive Rationality</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Max Planck Institute for Human Development</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Real-time assessment of motives for sharing and creating content among highly active Twitter users</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-07-02">July 2, 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D88322FCD8AB1297EF10F7A26036661E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-23T06:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>What motivates people to share and create content online? In real time, we linked each of N = 2, 762 individual posts (retweets and newly created content) with the self-reported motives from a sample of N = 137 highly active US Twitter users over the course of one week. We also captured their total activity of N = 48, 419 posts over 10 weeks (March-May 2022). Our results reveal that sharing (retweeting) political content stemmed mostly from motives related to expression and identity. When creating content, participants were more likely to be motivated by the goals of informing and persuading others, for which they used negative language and expressed outrage. In contrast, entertaining content and positive language was used for socializing and attention. Original and political content featuring outrage and anger was more likely to be subsequently retweeted by others. These findings may denote adaptive strategies in the incentive structure of social media that rewards such content.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Online--and on social media in particular-content is to a large extent shared and created through self-organized behaviour. As a result, individual decisions to share and create various types of content can drive the overall spread of information, thereby collectively influencing societal opinion formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. As a consequence, a question that is becoming increasingly important is: What motives are behind sharing and creating content, and do they link to expressions of outrage or negative emotionality?</p><p>While the sharing and creation of information has long been considered an integral part of cultural evolution beyond social media <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> their processes and roles have undergone considerable changes in the digital age <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. So far, there is little insight into why people choose to share or create certain content online. We therefore investigated in depth the motives of people who are very active on social media and how they relate to the modes of interaction on the platform and the content itself. We focused on Twitter (prior to its rebrand as X) and used the survey platform formr <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> to implement a novel paradigm for ecological momentary assessment (EMA) that connects actual behavior with small survey questionnaires in real time, using the Twitter API (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1A</ref> for an illustration). Our sample of active U.S. Twitter users allowed us to quantify various aspects of the content creation and sharing process, such as the actual content being created and the extent to which it was subsequently shared by others.</p><p>Ideally, for public discourse and accurate opinion-formation, people would share and create information on social media primarily because they consider the information to be important and true and follow the seemingly rational motive of disseminating correct information. But sharing and creating information may be disconnected from accuracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and may instead serve a variety of other goals and functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>. Qualitative interviews have found a plethora of motives behind posting on social media, including social interaction, entertainment, and expressing one's opinion <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>. Various surveys have found similar motives, including enjoyment, self-efficacy, social engagement, reputationbuilding <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, socializing and status seeking <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, and political engagement <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Moreover, sharing conspiracy theories specifically has been linked to motives such as fostering in-group beliefs and a need for chaos <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref>.</p><p>Another line of research investigating the dynamics of content dissemination has made use of platform data. For instance, studies have found that posts that are moral-emotional <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref> or derogatory <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> tend to receive more engagement and shares (but see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>). In addition, controlled experiments have shown that emotional content <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> and interesting-if-true content <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> can lead to subsequent sharing. Similarly, antagonistic social content seems to provoke replies <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. Yet none of these studies examined the specific motives driving users' behaviors.</p><p>Two recent studies did make the connection between motives and content. Namely, Osmundsen at al. linked survey data about motives with observational data from social media <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> and found that political polarization and pushing one's political agenda were the primary motives for sharing true as well as false news. However, motives were aggregated for individuals without examining whether different content was associated with different motives within individuals. Finally, another study, <ref type="bibr">Marie and</ref> Petersen, that built on the same method and combined observational data with a controlled experiment suggested that posting on social media may be also driven by the desire to garner positive reactions from a politically like-minded audience. However, it is important to note that the experiments were based on hypothetical content and sharing intentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. These studies show impressively how important the interplay of motives, content and context is, but do not yet reach the level of the individual posting decision in an ecologically valid setting.</p><p>In summary, the available evidence suggests a plethora of motives for information-sharing behavior on social media, comprising informational, social, and attention-directing goals. The connections between motives and actual online behavior, however, have rarely been studied. Past research has rarely taken into account that the motives for sharing and creating content on social media can depend on both context and content, and an individual may act on the basis of multiple motives. The existing evidence exhibits the strengths and weaknesses of each methodology. On one hand, retrospective surveys rely on participants' memory of past behaviors, and more controlled experimental studies rely on hypothetical rather than actual posting behaviors <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref>. On the other hand, observational data allow for measuring actual behavior, but the motivational drivers behind the behaviors are unknown. Combining ecologically valid digital trace data with self-reported survey responses on the level of individual posts therefore provides the best of both worlds <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36]</ref>. In addition, using EMA establishes a temporally closer link between behavior and self-report.</p><p>Our goal is to reveal and describe the multitude and complexity of the motives at play, as well as their context dependency. Understanding the motivational drivers behind posting behavior and the resulting dynamics is necessary for designing effective interventions and regulations for social media <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Although several behavioral interventions are based on the implicit assumption-supported by self-reports on the importance of accuracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>-that people share information on social media in order to accurately inform others <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38]</ref>, other motives may play an important role (e.g., when sharing misinformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>).</p><p>In this study, we aim to understand motives behind active posting behavior on Twitter <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> by linking actual posts on Twitter with small survey questionnaires sent via private message in real-time response to each post (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1A</ref> for an overview of the procedure; for a more detailed timeline and description see the Methods section and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>). We generally distinguish sharing content as retweets that merely forward an existing message and creating content as original tweets, quotes, and replies. By investigating actual posted content, we were able to not only connect participants' personal attributes with their motives, but also with the content and context of their individual posts. To analyze posts, we collected features from meta-data (e.g., number of followers, tweet type) and inferred others from the content itself using the ChatGPT API (e.g., topic, sentiment <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>; see Methods for details). This process resulted in three categories of variables: motives, person features, and content features (for details, see Methods and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1B</ref>). The Twitter API allowed us to automate our survey to react to activity and type of tweet in real time, gauging motives for sharing with almost no delay. We used this approach to investigate the following research questions: What are people's self-reported motives for creating content and sharing content on Twitter and how do they vary between and within individuals? A: General data-collection procedure for sharing and creating content. Shared content (content not created by the participant) is recorded via the API and a real-time survey about the motives for sharing it is sent via direct message. In the survey the respective content is repeated and the motive ratings are collected. The resulting three-dimensional data structure, where person features are collected once for each participant in the onboarding survey, motives are collected via multiple real-time survey for each post within the observation period (1 week), and content features are recorded from all content posted during the extended period (9 weeks). B: Network of positive Spearman's rank correlations between person features, content features, and motives. Weighted links represent the correlation coefficient within the 2, 762 posts recorded in the active period of data collection.</p><p>How do people's motives change depending on the type of post (retweet, original, quote, reply)? How are different content features associated with the motives behind sharing (retweets)? How are different motives associated with the features of content that is created (original tweets, quotes, replies)? And finally, how do these motives and associated content features relate to a post's success?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>We conducted an exploratory field study on Twitter over 10 weeks (March-May 2022) to assess people's motives for posting behavior in real time (see Methods for details). We used a stepped-wedge design to average out the influence of external events on posting behavior (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>, top row). Participants were recruited in 10 waves, each consisting of 1 week of active data collection. Of the n = 2, 762 posts collected, n = 907 were shared (retweets) and n = 1, 855 were created (original tweets, quotes, and replies). Participants allowed us to collect their posts for 4 weeks before and 4 weeks after the active observation, resulting in a total of n = 48, 419 posts (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref> for an overview). Overall, this resulted in an average of 39 posts per participant per week. This rate puts our sample in the ballpark of the 10% most active Twitter users-who, as a group, are responsible for 96% of the content on the platform <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>. The behavior of highly active users is of particular interest, given that "supersharers" of misinformation fall in this category <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>.</p><p>As an initial analysis and to provide an overview, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1C</ref> shows Spearman's rank correlations between all variables as a network visualization. The structure of the network suggests that motives cluster around features of content. For instance, motives related to informing and persuading were linked to political and negative content as well as retweets, while motives linked to expression and identity were more connected to original tweets and replies. Higher education and older age were more connected to political content and its associated motives, whereas younger age was more connected to nonpolitical content and motives related to socializing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General Distributions of Motives</head><p>To examine the self-reported motives for content sharing and creation, we asked participants to indicate the extent to which each of 16 preselected motives (see the methods section for a full list) captured the motives behind their posting behavior. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">2A</ref> shows their average motive ratings, separately for two time points: at the beginning of the study (onboarding survey) and in real time, after they had posted on Twitter (EMA). Participants rated the motives of expressing their opinion, connecting with others, drawing attention to a topic, and informing others as most important at both time points. The rank order of motives was fairly consistent between the retrospective and the real-time surveys, with some notable discrepancies. In real-time, motives consistently drew lower average levels of endorsement. Presumably, when reflecting on a specific tweet, participants identified a few motives and excluded the rest, whereas reflecting on their general tweeting behavior made them more likely to endorse multiple motives. In the onboarding survey, participants also seemed to underestimate the importance of motives related to expression and identity, while overestimating the importance of motives related to socializing and attention, relative to the EMAs. Correlations on the level of individual participants between the general and real-time motives were all positive, ranging from .18 (showing achievement) to .67 (deceiving others; see Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Lower correlations may have been due to memory error or to the observed week being unrepresentative.</p><p>A multilevel structural equation model of the 16 motive real-time ratings suggested that they could be subsumed into four categories (see Supplementary Material for details): motives related to informing and persuading others, to expression and identity, to socializing and attracting attention, and to provocation (see additional labels in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). The correlation matrix in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> further supports the notion that there are clusters of motives at play. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">2B</ref> shows the distributions of the average ratings per participant over the real-time surveys, split by political views. Although the sample of Republican participants consistently gave lower agreement ratings than the samples of Democrats or Independents, the general patterns of agreement were largely similar between all groups. Agreement differences were largest for motives related to socializing and attracting attention, which were more important for Democrats, and for motives related to expression and identity, which were more important for both Independents and Democrats. The ratings of all three groups were similar for the motive of 'proving a point.' Other sociodemographic A: Average agreement ratings for all 16 motives in the onboarding survey (blue) and for the per-participant averaged ratings over all their EMA real-time surveys (red). B: Distributions of average agreement ratings averaged for each participant over the real-time surveys, split across shared and created content. C: Distributions of average agreement ratings, split across Republicans, Democrats, and Independents. D: Explained variance R 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> for the Bayesian regression model 1 for the model components: sociodemographic variables (age, political orientation, employment status, gender, and education), random intercept for each individual participant, type of tweet (original, retweet, quote, and reply), and the within-subject residual that remains unexplained.</p><p>variables did not yield large differences in the agreement distributions (see Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>). The most notable difference can be seen as a function of age: Younger participants agreed more strongly that they posted content for motives related to expression and identity, whereas older participants agreed more strongly that they posted for motives related to informing and persuading. Also, female participant agreed more strongly that they posted to 'show their emotions' than male participants, who identified more with the motive of 'showing their attitude'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Motives for Sharing Versus Creating Content</head><p>We next examined whether motives for sharing or creating content differed. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">2C</ref> shows the average motive ratings per participant, split between shared and created content. While the distributions of motives are similar, small differences can be discerned. Motives of information and persuasion were the dominant motives for sharing content, whereas motives related to expression and identity topped the list of motives to create content. In addition, compared to sharing content, creating content was more strongly associated with the motive of connecting with other. This suggests that, notwithstanding the similar motivational landscape, people create content more out of a desire for personal expression, and share content more to inform others and draw attention to issues. These results also shed light on an important property of individuals' motivational repertoire: Participants invoked multiple motives, not just a single one. To analyze further how motives vary not only between, but within individuals, we conducted a simple linear regression model for each motive rating (model 1, see Methods for details). The model permits for variations via random intercepts for individual participants as well as for the type of tweet (retweet, original, quote, reply) and includes fixed effects for the following demographic variables: education, employment, age, gender, and political stance. We used the R 2 for Bayesian regression models <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> to calculate the relative contributions of the components of this model to the variance explained, for all 16 motive ratings in the real-time surveys. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">2D</ref> shows that demographic variables only explained a small fraction of the variance in the data; individual differences unrelated to demographic variables accounted for a bigger part of the variance the model captures. However, for almost all motives the biggest part of variance was the within-participant residual that remained unexplained by the model. This suggests that other factors may shape people's motives for posting content on Twitter, although it should be noted that the residual also includes noise. This picture is corroborated by descriptive data in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>, which shows the within-subject variability in the top-rated motives. On average, participants reported over five different motives within a week as being the most important for posting a particular content. Almost all participants had a clearly positive Shannon entropy of the distribution of motives they reported in that time, suggesting heterogeneity in an individual's motives over time.</p><p>Our approach also allowed us to consider a variety of content features of posts within participants. We collected several features of the content itself, namely, topic, sentiment, emotions being expressed, and the inclusion of an external URL. To consider social context, we collected the follower relationship between the original author of content that was retweeted by our participants. For original tweets, quotes, and replies, we collected the subsequent number of retweets our participants' posts received (see Methods for a full list of content features). Furthermore, when considering the connection between motives and content, the type of posting behavior is crucial <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. For original tweets, quotes, and replies, motives can be conceptualized as triggers of the tweet's content. For retweets, however, the content in all likelihood triggers motives for sharing. To account for differences in the triggering process, we split the following analysis between pre-existing content that our participants shared (retweets) and content that they themselves created (original tweets, quotes, and replies).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Predictors of Sharing Motives</head><p>When someone retweets, they are sharing another person's content with their own followers. To investigate whether this choice is driven by a distinct set of motives, we focused on retweets only, annotated with motive ratings. This resulted in 907 data points that we used in the following linear regression model (in modified Wilkinson notation):   , where the dependent variables are the four categories of motive ratings: informing and persuading, expression and identity, socializing and attention, and provocation. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> shows the resulting marginal contrasts of the content-level variables on motive ratings (expressed in their original units). The results reveal several associations. For example, the presence of external links was generally an important factor for retweeting across most motives, but in particular for motives related to expression and identity as well as to informing and persuading. Furthermore, political content was mostly shared for motives related to expression and identity, but not for motives related to socializing and attention or provocation. Outrage content was retweeted to inform and persuade. Content showing the emotions of joy, anger, and disgust, as well as positive sentiment, seemed to have no pronounced relationship with motives. Whether the tweet's original author was someone the participant followed also had no strong relationship with any motive. In summary, a multitude of motives were at play when content was retweeted, and these motives varied depending on the content. Political content, negative content, and content expressing outrage was shared for motives that had a public-facing end, such as informing and persuading and expression and identity. Social motives were more closely linked to sharing entertainment content than political content.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Motives predicting Created Content</head><p>We used a different set of models to examine the association between motives and the content people create. In these models, content features are the dependent variable and motives are the predictors. This results in a set of logistic regression models, where content_feature is the dependent variable, entailing several binary variables (e.g., whether the content expresses outrage, whether it is political, whether the sentiment is positive or negative), while the four categories of motives represent the predictor variables: Filtering the data for creation (original tweets, quotes, and replies) resulted in 1, 855 data points. They are the basis of our regression model. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4A</ref> shows the resulting marginal contrasts in units of probability (0 to 1), highlighting that different motives clearly predicted different created content. For example, when people are motivated by informing, persuading, or provoking, it was much more likely that they had written political content. Relatedly, when participants wanted to provoke others, it was much more likely that their created content contained negative emotions like disgust and anger. Content that expressed outrage was mostly created to inform and persuade others, as well as for motives related to expression and identity. For motives related to socializing and gaining attention, participants created mostly nonpolitical content and entertainment content, incorporating positive sentiment and language expressing joy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Predictors of Retweet Success</head><p>Why do social media users resort to negative emotions and outrage when aiming to spread their message, express themselves, and signal their identity? One possibility is that users who are active and experienced on the platform have learned to take advantage of emotions when their goal is to increase the reach of their messages on Twitter <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>. Here we investigate this issue in more detail.</p><p>To model a tweet's success (i.e., the likelihood of it being retweeted and the number of retweets it receives), we used a hurdle lognormal model with the dependent variable being the number of retweets. Only a few motives related to informing and persuading others predicted retweet success (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4B</ref>). This resonates with the public-facing nature of those motives.</p><p>We used another hurdle lognormal model to examine which content features in the full dataset of original content from our sample of created posts (32, 870 data points) predicted subsequent retweets: Resulting marginal contrasts are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4C</ref>. Structural factors such as being a hub (i.e., having more than 3,000 followers) and being original content (vs. quotes or replies) led to more retweets, as did content that was political and expressed outrage or anger.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The current study aimed to understand motives behind active posting behavior on Twitter. A number of studies have shed light on what motivates people to share and create content online. However, due to methodological limitations they could not directly connect motives with content. We took a novel approach that combined the real-time elicitation of motives via EMA with the actual behavior in question-namely, sharing or creating content-on the level of individual posts. We observed five key results. First, we found that people have a large variety of motives when posting content, beyond simply informing others. This rich repertoire can be collapsed into four categories: expression and identity, informing and persuading, socializing and attention, and provocation. In our 1-week observational window, participants selected more than five different motives as the "most important," thereby demonstrating the broad array of motives underlying posting behavior.</p><p>Second, even though the distributions of motives behind sharing and creating content were not strikingly different, the motives that participants invoked most were: Motives related to identity and expression were ranked top for creation, whereas motives related to informing and persuading were ranked top for sharing.</p><p>Third, people shared political content primarily for the purposes of expression and identity, and less so to socialize or attract attention. By contrast, people created political content to inform, persuade, or provoke. When provocation was the driving force, negative emotions such as anger and disgust permeated the content, whereas when people's motivations were related to informing and persuading, outrage was commonly displayed. Anger, disgust, and outrage were also predictors of the success of a tweet, alongside the number of followers a person has and whether the content is political.</p><p>Fourth, for motives related to socializing and gaining attention, people mostly posted entertaining rather than political content. These motives also tend to be linked to joyful content and positive sentiment, possibly because such positive interactions foster bonding and in-group interactions.</p><p>Fifth, our results align with previous findings that older adults are generally more interested in news and visit more news sites <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> than younger people. In our sample, older participants reported being more strongly motivated by informing and persuading than younger participants, who were more strongly motivated by expression and identity.</p><p>Limitations of our study revolve around the limited number of participants we were able to recruit due to the long and laborious participation for each individual. However, as a trade-off, the design gave us access to many data points on the content level. Our study is therefore not as well powered to detect associations with demographic variables as it is for content features. In future studies, the observation period could be shortened in order to reduce the burden on each participant and thereby be able to involve more participants. This trade-off during recruitment also resulted in some deviations from the preregistration that mostly regarded the data portioning approaches, which were not feasible with our small sample (see <ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/n7wfm">https://osf.io/n7wfm</ref>; see Methods for a detailed description). Another limitation of the study is rooted in the current lack of a coherent conceptual framework of the types of behaviors we observed and their dependency on platforms' technical affordances <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. We had to refine our research questions along different types of posts in order to accommodate a phenomenon we had initially overlooked: There are mechanistically different relationships between motives and content depending on whether the content is shared or created. Based on our insights, future studies could focus more specifically on those mechanistic differences.</p><p>The use of negative and outraging language (also observed in other studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>) for motives related to informing and persuading can be understood as behavior adapted to a platform's affordances and incentives. The engagement-based algorithms that curate content on platforms like Twitter have been shown to favor emotionally charged content <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>, thereby increasing its reach. We believe that the negative language and outrage we observed may be a technique people use to reach their goal of spreading their message further. Using negative and outraging language may well be a strategy that our participants have learned through reward learning, with social feedback as the reward <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50]</ref>. It seems to work: Content that is created with the goal of informing and persuading others does receive more retweets than content created for other motives. Given that our sample belonged to the small group of highly active (and likely experienced) Twitter users, those results may be indicative of how the platform incentivizes the creation of such content by favoring it with social feedback and algorithmic selection.</p><p>Motives related to socializing also influence people's posting behavior. The clear differences between content posted for motives related to socializing and content posted for motives related to informing align with previous findings on the general differences between broadcasting versus narrowcasting <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. Retweets geared at informing others and bringing attention to a topic represent broadcasting; these include more critical and political content. Replies, on the other hand, represent narrowcasting; in our study, these contained less political content and more positive language, and were posted for motives related to socializing.</p><p>In sum, our results confirm that motives vary on the level of individual tweets, and show how motives may drive people to share negative and outraging content. Our findings also highlight the importance of designing online environments that do not favor this potentially divisive content <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>, of implementing interventions against sharing misinformation that shift people's motives further towards accuracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>, and of employing algorithms that maximize metrics other than pure engagement <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55]</ref>. The interplay of motives, content, and platform affordances should be taken into account in all </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Variables Collected</head><p>Participants were asked to rate their agreement with the statement "I shared the above tweet ..." followed by 16 predefined motives on a 6-point Likert scale ("strongly agree" to "strongly disagree") derived from the literature <ref type="bibr">[11, 13-23, 25, 29, 30, 32, 56, 57]</ref>. The following 16 items were presented in randomized order:</p><p>• to inform.</p><p>• to entertain.</p><p>• to express my opinion (to share my views)</p><p>• to provoke others.</p><p>• to save the content to my timeline.</p><p>• to show my emotions.</p><p>• to connect with others (start a conversation).</p><p>• to show an achievement.</p><p>• to show my attitude.</p><p>• to deceive others.</p><p>• to gain attention, likes, or followers.</p><p>• to prove a point.</p><p>• to cause chaos.</p><p>• to bring attention to the topic.</p><p>• to influence or persuade others.</p><p>• to surprise.</p><p>We collected the following participant features through the onboarding survey and the Twitter API:</p><p>• age</p><p>• gender (male, female, other)</p><p>• political affiliation (Democrat, Republican, Independent)</p><p>• education (no college degree, some college degree or higher)</p><p>• employment status (full-or part-time employment; not employed, including students and others)</p><p>• number of followers (hub = more than 3,000 followers; no hub = fewer than 3,000 followers)</p><p>• activity on Twitter (active = more than 10 posts per day; not active = fewer than 10 posts per day).</p><p>We also collected features of individual posts:</p><p>• tweet type (original, retweet, quote tweet, reply)</p><p>• URL types (entertainment, mainstream news, alternative news)</p><p>• number of retweets (number).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Content Coding With ChatGPT</head><p>For summaries of the content itself we used a simple ChatGPT pipeline, which can be found in the preprocessing script (<ref type="url" target="https://github.com/philipplorenz/real_time_motives">https://github.com/philipplorenz/real_time_motives</ref>), including all exact prompts. We used this method to infer the following features of individual posts from the text:</p><p>• topic (political, social, entertainment, others)</p><p>• sentiment (positive, negative)</p><p>• outrage (present, not present)</p><p>• emotion (anger, joy, disgust, other)</p><p>The results were cross-checked with a human coder (100 random posts) who received the exact same instructions. The interrater reliability was 0.72 for sentiment, 0.76 for outrage, 0.77 for political vs. not and 0.46 for the type of emotion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reactivity to EMAs</head><p>Another unique feature of our dataset is the data we were able collect historically through the API, which had been created by participants even before they joined the study. With participant consent, we collected data from 4 weeks of their timeline both before and after the study. This allowed us to quantify whether and how participants changed their behavior during and after our study. Fig. <ref type="figure">6A</ref> shows the descriptive results and indicates that slightly fewer original tweets, quotes, and replies were created during the study period than prior to it. This change in behavior could be due to the feeling of being observed (especially given the direct messages they received after each tweet). Participants may also have tweeted less so as to avoid the burden of responding to more real-time surveys. The results of modelling different content features as dependent on the study period (before, during, and after the active observation period) indicate that the type of content did not change credibly during our study (Fig. <ref type="figure">6B</ref>). Slightly more negative sentiment, outrage, and disgust were observed after the study, but this could also be due to exogenous events that were not averaged out by the stepped-wedge design. A B C D E F education Supplementary Figure 2: Descriptive data of the final sample, with A the age distribution, B the gender, C the political affiliation, D level of education, E status of employment and F self-reported twitter use. motive_expressopinion motive_showemotions motive_showattitude motive_bringattention motive_informothers motive_provepoint motive_influence motive_deceiveothers motive_provoke motive_causechaos motive_entertain motive_savecontent motive_connectwothers motive_showachievement motive_gainattention motive_surpriseothers motive_expressopinion motive_showemotions motive_showattitude motive_bringattention motive_informothers motive_provepoint motive_influence motive_deceiveothers motive_provoke motive_causechaos motive_entertain motive_savecontent motive_connectwothers motive_showachievement motive_gainattention motive_surpriseothers surprise others gain attention show achievement connect with others save the content entertain cause chaos provoke deceive others influence others prove a point inform others bring attention show my attitude show my emotions express my opinion Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>: The distributions of average agreement ratings (ranging from 1 "disagree completely" to 6 "agree completely") averaged for each participant over the real-time surveys, split across sociodemographic variables, namely, education and employment, age and gender, respectively. of different top motives per user base 2 shannon entropy per user _D1O1sQBYtwiA3JtOADRZlYD5i-I0qIQME4_RXoAY2gUl7OOdbnFk4MtLxkQpabU -5wvYkXTIHpFKjb8NqRxuLM_WsyDc1YaS3HGnp6d5-VLI3Xic_kLVdS2VU8Rh9IM -dvwS_3bH3v7PDHbpZmODAYYkwkIbkd-pgT5n6nKmCDin9MotNQuBWVatxBpXCUL -EucvgRg40O4u2YEDClySAaRmf7LYhtZioPoZ1tX2pzzFD3zi_e7QsAfO3stQSn6 -sOB_rKOgiqm-OdXAJEhl2qF7f8yGbMg17ikNA6Fy1tRx-J2YgF0MLZhp-8tL8qK 1JgJn6Zl1T3UqpC3ndwKD0rAADhVB7n_01Ncn0kxiB-VZlo3I3iPGyk7zGdbFqGg 1M_tcqo7twXv4C8tdqahdlSrzaNKxs4tO-BRL6Z3c5l6YqUoytn98K5fGvxDKIj1 2Os2ZabiemWmwzHvybu4BQm26lyJ7GWd-TBd6F5Ocx2K6OnHpv752f6rN3WSYMSj 3cL4Gq28wQ_RdSQrFsxaWI9i2yGYp6A08RfzdO_JUhD853A3l28GlAXQsjOoPN3w 4hOM1KvOXNZkJxF408fwieWFN0SnZFCSGwDCBBSdg_L5NId_dnfMmt8MMxvHhakG 5caHXCLqoDn3e9ttJlueqkgh1HR6_O-sLJqKObOiSpl41doQtEz_VCvK0c7vSPff 5GpNQtOS_1z5aB5ydOThWjiE1gqgq5M2n0VKi95Y9k6fen29oIMHrvaXc3wqXlpS 7RWX2euCudId68-vAhtiRNWcsTajONjDZWaTkymBsNWY08XeHbcg2riIHbMsu5wZ 8P-_53b1Kesrp0-1Iu3BTRIgiV749wblTN7rTNQQ0qTg8EFnIJmsyMcCGpGXhd-A 8utpwU2TOlY86OhTBTqHLxlRCZXWsMggZUGfbiaxo4r6E1Wn5qqKM0pKnBMhRlbP 98uPPRzJtIEtdxnpgkkd6wsl_aLQK01bso3dEsD2lQl-m-rfCLZJzpurWRJNIYap 9IFLzRKEbkAZl3ln-1atRk0wh8NqGRHPhgdDfQpkaZB9WC58dYvM3qrHoq21nYXr 9N7oj1oUxasy1gacV0-QNSDKUze9bNXs7m5kWk4vEjr6Xou_nfKyTYRX6UQ9Tesm 9QOEMd3qLLTqXt3nxPOAjRRXNbka1RW7U_cpD64l_F7pWkcav5dywAXIw-jv6XdT A2xA2i0nswfBI-r8jJ_VIpUFTvKYnoDGQWJWspV5ONv_7XWGnFdam2J3qrqIH2eQ aEQav1Snsg7lQzDwea8zmi0ak6D0dMuoWLf3nxSYNwdhI4JcJFKGsMyCDj9MBUlJ An7_EIcMa3A6K4cJ21ttNX1h65NALq3ghANGcnp-yIamoXrYY3IIHuzeP6UWdR6S aTNaDqrY65RsnoWquwWZl4bEdn3x24Q3RKgct358kZbEkNLTN0VIWfGHHvfDKK7g AWiSsn4Wz2LWMjVnxLjl2AUj7yrFFse3xHmzRb1XUUJgJQ6PbdGqdU28bTd9Vr9h b9EqMuzPssxaDSyl4hViJ9ObQUR0T4q1zOdRi47YgnDgyK8wk_yCwffcINHZGnIX BTB3h91tZC-bO-Tc8u7K56pas_a6zVcV9mBlJKQEfEfPbeqV_PYhBF4lE2AA4pgD c3VmAfsyD2YrpdF6BRF4yba4vC4cI27B_eNJm69Yryr953HGNZyVcipjDerLiFrT CmG6ZSlPPxasTSq-GO4LkI-Yk8NGVsdcHYhczXefu3aTZkdBrPQlpGjlnlfzhn_A D_-JJd42IVhBv8Q9Krb4s4qmi7OQ7xxmge7Z0sc1Akep2_8KeUZPAzxCIyexJ4Gi D-XJ8ti3EjDfbmCST0Ke3ULiGoPjfxRy8r7_bqZ3vAYxnd0lCGmBdJWibHQT2Svm dAPxY0MiJAyoYdS_LkfgnGfLlzYnFvNuaCsHVHtE5BoMyAEGJEx-0yfGfSDFg7UR divcs-bz1le8W6gyJMzd8PN797Ny0yTpv7z__tHLy1yq9R5SWw2_zeL8vxmG7hiF DKMtY0_qHdvjDiTIixUzhrjsU3itdn6esKm4EopxtKl-gxYgwLZ5E4fqRqh8Nxmq dlgu4_Mg8yLXU91BbZo7ozgfAFHrwK9Kc-eOdKthuslQMAyuzegTLDye_oKzdPOS dyUZENfze8j4JKYpXhUx699yqUk90kRGNB6z5SOsteAQuKYwSmi4BSoxVcqITzYL e7JEhWcYiZjIL1mzpRBlAOZWxSJUYsIxB6p3J6BwifeuCRUhKw5hLfeqqyc3nwrj eAMZABBViYYC-_3XVUKneIxkUrfB3201Bx5YqR5SMA4idqYaICp1s1LbKeXcRuA_ EBWcvPNYypYAvtngsTF7bylo7IQ53fRUQ1pi0Y_gDvBDfKpsdcl2Qs-c8-AJ3ysy edXha_qPn6Z5pR0HEhqpWDu59ogI062ldCW6tz8L5U055l3hhIwMgqpWnwFnKaQo ejjZDXdftwo5yamkdS6owEeZFIawTGGt9pN-zgh64BowWPrkQmafBgNnSGG5S8Hc ek55tU-wSMJYeDywNDqZldmGspoWi3zIAah2Na063D_h-cCy7HQ10AtM7whvq9Ta ENBxbLux58TWH4BVVJ0SvQkVblq2YEKjufxfrJYQfrbl0LHLxdP5nwnASYWJ87jT EnkjnwGuLnrkdjbjABk5j_AZW_5X5-GD6trq9o5OTvakPkrBxGRjjp4uYq3EAKY-EPd0_XAgczWPhRFmPyWaZqafDzxG4j_47-3lCuaidzeLmte8xMNLTDY9-SXvitaf Ez_D9vCYPELvk4EH94OWYNwap-5S2tUpGZvQ9u-k5LoPI8_B7Ak2rLlsE8t9lzeM FB7d_kFUUCY3x2vVNYq5pIwu0Us6H-RTMNbOOpRGlzOU_YJveL0hwoIrMuHL2_k6 FcejM0qrXc4fI-Jyxsops9t7UOLtt64VJnOqWcs-fHAeGlU7IDZl0gS6qQKLlmgr fO56jhwNE3I3r9DTKIrXvweJHNJdhFjiX4ndu6z3Vfj80oSkDnpUQudbMRaSfXF1 gCuH8dbzwE41gNvWnmKrYjdwwxuvSf7M2Vtrfe1J7KsWNmzNi6RHcaGLqHSVaRJI GPPl6xXlfL1iVkCjZCmvDszRDbftqCJart8r9FSRHc7MbyRCulj4mHv_C7V7adB8 gY8h4d7FDs7o24ogmTd6zmcbmmrP2hxQw-j15V8F-K7wE-fszJ76I2i-wK21RKrk H9WQ3DVEjHMozk1yN9qBZP72rKJu2allEStS_F0Igda2B17INsKDVLroMLOQTL_s IM3iNpeEndjuPDqM5QmMCuGnL2LJUe32t76_ug2u318QcMlkNWHKIh8hWASDlxlk j5QzchsVn1LIIWeddzN00GL1WDA0hEd23wB2f_Hs6ISfIlV8FGA90MEgFif3EnG7 J66asTegWRkDFjvcA9_kAirQMIT2cIBCUgRuWtkQquMJdDUzVNT7k6Fc8n5nRZL7 Jff7MclgeMwSyzX81NGpBrYq4Pj8U-VequpU8KiHO57B0mp5VE_VKGtjJj74M4iP JXuwiFl6HMSkEKmC4_kASEPNSg0IiwxmaopGVAxtNVOf6CeoSMdcLophOyMp8Ju8 k6M_qBKnoRJZvdXD8pcYSUdwAOooWoj_vKUtuT2DADUYfcgdyvV7F_F-1S_9TDGq KoBGjSj04mcJFp6T9UNi5_RGwFTMVROhuPpLcYKuoYYlTGPrtPaJRCB0Os9vEnD4 KsBm40CLSvA-p9nZs1CZfGBLQ8u_bVzEBaLM4nZL17EW5EZkVxv3zIdGqIUszHQ7 l-p4Swdgn36e566NDkk-h4eTnWsRpOyHGHz81jSCFDG4y6tBlbw3Vr4Jd0eJmR2C lbFZADldkdmPuqJpb11F5Au2cs8HiLJxcDg1ySf9xoQrkbpVD21Ln1e6E0NDlof0 LBiQ_2EbKIyjZ6OqBTAnQD3OFptDuseglHGdqfSfL8pWz9Zf-5pGtSeWPHbphXc9 lBswpaTJPIrB32D7lFGRRmoeij3JAbSwjSkidD8DvOob6Rdb9AWNENIAQiJxRlMv LeDNw3Tqau5-efu-_5wRaSiW9w580YQMayYocmbAzTr9rFPNO93BWuScHEBxoDNm lfnoV_N2OF7NXo5OpoGS3QcRzRnlWQ6sz95H2VGFcBiG1W1bgbe3hF2EvWCjAGMW LJ4SUJsn9H3Ay1BBHWfvPfg8KGtxn8OH36wF306HLR1VI43vGHtu_UJcFxS_Qu9D LJBXaB6mGnQwWmbBH2ay7Evy-KWbd0eXNPE7B_dLKT6VcQ-pt1zfBmCzTT_zMemB lnqURNu9TFnIBuUhgPbIprxsjACgcfDr1O-OLNBWy5S2HwovqymKuHxx63hZIGyj Luek9mRuJC_9OUW4AgyAyi5hTAXnp3G9FqpONhARpcEC3xX0PEZvuwHzhhOHAnoc lv4d1-mfABWpDsO3gk46E8l2elJQsBpVSS02oD44KXymjzHadMrXaSdGk_tfOUVL LvwAi27hZCkiq8Ht7PQVXDtYw-HfQB3joL1eOt4CT9H_jGFkU1S6zXot4KQz3CUJ m3CYgG-wM5LN28G6bbBAnw9EJcu0LZE8scbv4ezni5fnPtC8KO-aU3hhjEmPRSA2 mdMN4GBqDmZkoUlAiDfRma2Fcp-k3i-eRvBeYML7v5xg2SIqqmdQhAljDE6vhotm mhEOJBTPkDDxu6scSDP2R_VmzVkou4nu7L9sSS8o1qME68yoGMkIj0XCCTvyInYm Mp8hcLlCTddE6IjluzVTiRJWLp15fgnjIbiabJELD9r6dwRS1E4anVhsKn49bVnJ MSIY1y6FP10ieV3fNewOuLnITSbWmQ7X6OLHeiux2Ja05rRSTQpoXkUtTzUuhoQU MsSQUtIC_SoygMgo6JbMu6WYAmz_dLozIxWvXKC46FL_bj3NOf_veHyHNiVaIUkV mWpoQ62wsgwywzwopFlJr7gd6UtAC9Yn6z-kkBY173W0Q5HcyOy-PWgL4qZhyegA MZ5vuqSags_geY_0jPCnv2ccxfYTZ1crVToC4W9MPjAleV3wHZqMqKBD96NfGoBC n1XHJ8z13pUpdps2VhiUU61y6uT20zgNH8RQQf9T3iwVbeZD94miIE3vAlVOpqDO nI_mMOjmJPY3_xN7q9DnOOQBX-z-r3hm4xiCyuBvLgDImSkCVgk-terbi5hEmACs nWHoiDseEB96V4IJldLmQGHR2G9Yb_FcE7rXfyX_l6XOJEDmt4pdo06az0gicJTS o4zlir4jZR5d9IiEwFKkn4FJyu2ecOj15jubFRqTYsxdBfiKCkQE4nQPls5G551w occ4aFrUw7aVnJUE7nkJGqRwkokt2tCQyLKSn2Xo1GERde5x0-12UnQuOF4wPyHU oKvuhayjOpTSJvKCAE8TzWB2sy5tkk7EINRlwDmErPmrooeQb_zHTHPX3dDfdTx_ oMonvZuU5WsjzAuQ5tvp72a4Qn8v_48Mdue69UnB2FhPAIiK8depSHr_a8OlcMd2 Orl9r5Wal1jPDJzF8rpUKcWieu1Rrnf3myBYa-a4UoBJi172erPWSzJQbvsTDK0N p7IT6Js9SFivvfpfjLEBJ-Hx_PGzmAr1lzONeQt92DNPByb8PeNKPv6u7PRVV3Wa Ph2j3K36IwFNt2XFnIzQqNePBMdMXOuc1VSqUC1uPQUcBrxtoUn7xi551lOY_7ji PqgvCnpXD7NTBibVbgrigFtaVVDs-JD2POeTjK0OG8mUaEJSconpxSK2Wj8l8Kjd Q1eJ-HwAl-A8fyJvYpx6YI8ozmhA4JTXjj54aL8_ziuep37WVSr7ZvzIp0LVMnZZ qdEBW6djH4l7ZWpfw-xF76TUaM1QE2NWkcuNjVr9q0I_7UIZGbumUGrjDze0Lsku qlb0-IUGrvTn8YuLWedt4rAtzHA762LsSPLDJhU6woOhHVJPwsYlJZMLZqE5FB5_ QQhsPN_VqlY-RPS7cdYvjMhoZ5ByXv973KhDffnioev94uRwAQxHHAkKcMo_KXHy QyX5FbyMiWx_d0M6GYEAiL17mGwcf_Q4-7pjzGT37dap_iP4rhP2xTiJus6Pl8e1 rASfqZnUsDmDHpkcQAScclOwIiDmrdSbt98KaJdXkydeJfZRjjIblQhN3fVa-7Ma Rpzk41FLQi80mAbjm40lzOexiRhFlTZEuAwan14dk5zHBAzBsr3Lv1JIC6IUDY3D rWmQSZUreNV-T943VmLKQGmEAaBYb12sTIIneWGpXdpiVkcWRIO7QcRZkYebf38J SJsq1LGKRiCCsMfdw3Ebz6EcV6J_safeckJBSaEQpcEtOCn7AUaXlHk7glv3Dsar soLZacM876L_J8bWhO1iJEsUGqdy0ShlPaon7byJ8PkPY20rXXammjaB09NmpAOe T4uCTtmYOzNcnH2nj1hgPVuN6WVXI36P9s_Bajyp96BZM_fUhOwYwD_eYXoZkwYw TaRhf5xaOwptrS-_9pFbeLAS_iV4D2UEsiBsEV7nm6dI3_Q8wDdHfSl5f3KVJwaY tJJMTk67zIxZsmXXrwpl4GrI9UPLa-1ZsTIOqobQuqmZ3A7XXFUwgjCv6OK3xELr tOb-NVzV8YzVzHrsvfVKRuXhtnG-9bad0Rp2q6_5KEEyfDbBHH38A22i9K8g7X4Z Tqy9lKPffBlM4gSZEokq92OUpodgoofQUJVTjNDEshUhUOsecyYlbqs2MKJrh-uG TTlqA5p4W5fDydGihD9uLe8agLIu3i8KDipmoSHiqP6859_Wuepn9bF6IPJLUYmM U_kypfjnxZzVTZRPwzmCRrWM8Vb_rLQpJ-qbMF9jzDwUorAQsU_g0j1z2wr5BE9h U6bZuoVdHTkCBfEVlyovG1mn32eRuHcxoPPwi91OIuujuJ_B4YQ9ItAKsnpJcp29 uWcdtLzdy3dEZpCB_Q6r_wnppVQ3f_63jq2iIhoRPssTiibYB304AQNglq9PbCTn V1FVAaDV00lS_oGG9PtazBFglGkBjWkRGK7i9Up_rtu-oRoK4wDUJRv1i0j_lEbc vaBSjPKw837cimxtYNZBe1sW9mItpdBI4r4CTlmMN6t_cYiGojj1kVnN3g4AxDyp vfWTnHY2ds7KV6nLsFisM5MoQLYW3PEwUPyyLO2hA2xYZeispjV6YyFyzbcQIBDl VqUHaf6UBK9wEGvz8I67lp9aCjm3rK-GywucTvSCzQ-2QpOoEUu-owSzbyzmGKIB VSg4TBzD3ZBGqyBPgtGCoZvRP8CKOixwx4jFqeSFkRRoIDdXw1vBo6hLDDrGq0OO Vtd7rJPSwOvflLQO8Fdt99zGpY-MHGzFWSGIM_ohi9PQoWRMdX9a__YjGpQ5fGU4 W_BuypKeGSHttYjmasH-8mZPLSVUh9GJbn_nA9rP1aKiOE9lMkcUfSO8VzAKiTXM WAkq8Ia1or2vDU1-rujM7wbvWdSa7wg0f_LNew0UBt8s02RMAqQnLKC5SGxqvAlf wGJSkAnPdWUL4PQOaezm8IDPM_AMxFEMNL3ZEBJwlAHhBkgq7F_TmhW9mKPTPzPg wHjy159ZEez9Z-eWzv2_xBanudGfjxu4WmOKyPm914JR91Shw42yk9vpmqagRYP0 X0US6LxPIjtpZF45suk4G9GgQya-EcLd7n0Mec2GgB-7pQu5gphdDA5Oi9-lbU5Q XHjBgm7dPFJKyrP6VD3Nmps8xzZIrRuW67ey68cAnVMd_ybOH-whU8fugEfu0rR9 xnSsP1vKvHaUHdHTu0Xf5STbiMd61wf-pi9UePTjcFVblKn_43DivgqKraAK5z4x xNwvjp6aL4VZMrHVxP566j6L6irq_pDs3S_O0wC0xRA6_utFiKGKmdSJiWJ-zslz xpQRN03o3Gdh7e0c85y9FjXnDUIPUznPWOj4uf_JQ2GfZ9Zh8LqXcZGqrX0pjX1A xUXVSM9F-rhc8smOuQi23rU-liWhsuz8E-KRt8Cx9lCkgAkDy-teY9wl6hBwg7fF Y-0mlaT6rojBCX46Ui2cghnlvJk1SVizgo8qz0_cxnwQcz5qA0zgvpE01TR2wT1q yIQziPXuoELh-c4yWn46Us0fbkWC0BZe8y26gNr8SuMyXfVXFtoIJN8c85XHBFIF YqmwXKTj9QOAIwlXm0Eb0yB6xKGF5LF4cmxLz4BgVhFzLma2yMzyqU-UWm4zZ09Y z5SdHun5skbf-EKCAxTnmuE2UmDMsHUc2FyqeFcHIJ7-8IoZMAtNl9WIJmjLZebi ZO0O7zObhz-dCrJGceH2RUdHQNDfbe6qINE9b87L5GTKGpnyAcXhkwF0eciykFhc ZPJrdoV1IsVBvFOHH-g7jYaNFbkPsp_gFGrFbwMkfoGkRlPdh0T1zbMMi3ShJ_Cf ZzhHNt32nPRWUPkuRzna-s_xoJZb1UeRL85sEJUyTrMRMP4a35Hl6NEH5QqSkCjN Mar Apr May  Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>: Full model results for content types predicting sharing motives as in model 2 and model 3 and as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Overview of experimental setup, data structure, and correlational network of variables.A: General data-collection procedure for sharing and creating content. Shared content (content not created by the participant) is recorded via the API and a real-time survey about the motives for sharing it is sent via direct message. In the survey the respective content is repeated and the motive ratings are collected. The resulting three-dimensional data structure, where person features are collected once for each participant in the onboarding survey, motives are collected via multiple real-time survey for each post within the observation period (1 week), and content features are recorded from all content posted during the extended period (9 weeks). B: Network of positive Spearman's rank correlations between person features, content features, and motives. Weighted links represent the correlation coefficient within the 2, 762 posts recorded in the active period of data collection.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure2: Person features and posting type and their relation to motives. A: Average agreement ratings for all 16 motives in the onboarding survey (blue) and for the per-participant averaged ratings over all their EMA real-time surveys (red). B: Distributions of average agreement ratings averaged for each participant over the real-time surveys, split across shared and created content. C: Distributions of average agreement ratings, split across Republicans, Democrats, and Independents. D: Explained variance R 2<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> for the Bayesian regression model 1 for the model components: sociodemographic variables (age, political orientation, employment status, gender, and education), random intercept for each individual participant, type of tweet (original, retweet, quote, and reply), and the within-subject residual that remains unexplained.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>model 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Predictors of sharing motivesmotive_rating ˜outrage + category + sentiment + following + url_type + emotion + (1 | user) -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -0.2 0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 socializing_attention category-entertainment -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUEcategory-entertainment -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA category-entertainment -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -1.0 -0.5 0.0 0.5 informing_persuasion category-entertainment -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -0.25 0.00 0.25 provocation category-entertainment -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -0.2 0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 socializing_attention sharing content average marginal contrast [agreement] category-entertainment -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -1.0 -0.5 0.0 0.5 informing_persuasion category-entertainment -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -0.25 0.00 0.25 provocation category-entertainment -NA category-politics -NA category-social -NA emotion_top-anger -NA emotion_top-disgust -NA emotion_top-joy -NA following_retweeter-TRUE -FALSE has_url-TRUE -FALSE outrage-1 -0 sentiment_bin-negative -NA sentiment_bin-positive -NA -0.2 0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 socializing_attention average marginal contrast [agreement] contains URL (vs. not) positive negative sentiment (vs. NA) outrage (vs. none) following (vs. not) emotion (vs. other) category (vs. NA)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure3: Marginal effect comparison of model estimates for content-feature variables on motive ratings for retweets only, using a linear regression model (see Methods for details). The four dependent variables are the averaged motive ratings of the factors determined by the factor analysis: expression and identity, informing and persuading, socializing and attention, and provocation. Independent variables and their levels are listed in the Methods section. Average marginal contrasts on the x-axes are shown in the units of ratings from the original Likert scale. Values describe the change in response to changing one of the predictor variables listed on the y-axes, relative to the baseline level listed in parentheses. Darker colors represent marginal contrasts further from zero and divided by the width of the confidence interval (95%).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Marginal effect comparison of model estimates for content-feature variables of created (original tweets, replies, and quotes) posts. A: Results of the logistic regression model 2 for political and entertainment content, outrage, sentiment (coded negative to positive), the top three emotions, and presence of an external URL. B: Resulting marginal effects of the hurdle lognormal model 3 for subsequent retweets per category of motive. C: Resulting marginal contrasts from the hurdle lognormal model for the full sample of posts containing original content.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>model 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Motives predicting created contentcontent_feature ˜expression_identity + informing_persuasion + socializing_attention + provocation + (1 | user)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>model 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Predictors of retweet successnumber_retweets ˜outrage + political + sentiment + tweet_type + emotion + log_followers + (1 | user)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure5: Overview of the study timeline and setup. The general timeline included 10 waves of recruitment in a stepped-wedge design. The participant timeline spanned 4 weeks of passive data collection (after consent, collected in hindsight via the API), 1 week of active data collection (including recruitment via advertisement, the onboarding survey, and the real-time surveys automatically triggered through the API by on-platform activity), and another 4 weeks of passive data collection. The resulting nested data structure from all phases of the study is shown in the bottom row.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 : 2 :Supplementary Figure 3 :</head><label>623</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Reactivity analysis to the ecological momentary assessment (EMA) approach. A: Descriptive average activities per user, per day, of the different types of posting behavior: retweet, original, quote, and reply. B: Resulting marginal contrasts in units of probability (0-1) of the logistic regression model content_feature ˜period + (1 | user), with 'period' representing a categorical variable that distinguished between pre-, during, and post-EMA treatment.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Supplementary Figure 5 :Supplementary Figure 6 :</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Variance of motives within participants. A shows the number of different motives that were reported as the most important for each participant during the one week observation time. B shows the corresponding Shannon entropy and C the different categories of motives over time for each participant row-wise.fully disagree -6 fully agree] density motive_deceiveothers Distributions of ratings over motives.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Supplementary Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>(vs. none) sentiment (vs. NA) outrage (vs. none) following (vs. not) emotion (vs. other) category (vs. NA) type of URL (vs. none) sentiment (vs. NA) outrage (vs. none) following (vs. not) emotion (vs. other) category (vs. NA) type of URL (vs. none) sentiment (vs. NA) outrage (vs. none) following (vs. not) emotion (vs. other) category (vs. NA)Full model results for content types predicting sharing motives as in model 1 and as shown in Fig.3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Correlation values of within-subject comparison between general motives stated in the onboarding survey and the average motives they report during the real-time surveys.</figDesc><table><row><cell>motive</cell><cell>within-subject correlation</cell></row><row><cell>informothers</cell><cell>0.32</cell></row><row><cell>entertain</cell><cell>0.40</cell></row><row><cell>expressopinion</cell><cell>0.25</cell></row><row><cell>provoke</cell><cell>0.48</cell></row><row><cell>savecontent</cell><cell>0.50</cell></row><row><cell>showemotions</cell><cell>0.27</cell></row><row><cell>connectwothers</cell><cell>0.34</cell></row><row><cell>showachievement</cell><cell>0.18</cell></row><row><cell>showattitude</cell><cell>0.44</cell></row><row><cell>deceiveothers</cell><cell>0.67</cell></row><row><cell>gainattention</cell><cell>0.40</cell></row><row><cell>provepoint</cell><cell>0.42</cell></row><row><cell>causechaos</cell><cell>0.45</cell></row><row><cell>bringattention</cell><cell>0.31</cell></row><row><cell>influence</cell><cell>0.47</cell></row><row><cell>surpriseothers</cell><cell>0.36</cell></row><row><cell>Supplementary</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgements: We thank <rs type="person">Friederike Stock</rs> for her help with recruitment via Twitter Ads, data collection, and design tasks; <rs type="person">Deborah Ain</rs> for editing the manuscript; and <rs type="person">Almog Simchon</rs> for inspiring discussions. <rs type="person">Philipp Lorenz-Spreen</rs>, <rs type="person">Stefan M. Herzog</rs> and <rs type="person">Ralph Hertwig</rs> aknowledge financial support from the <rs type="funder">Volkswagen Foundation</rs> (grant '<rs type="projectName">Reclaiming individual autonomy and democratic discourse online: How to rebalance human and algorithmic decision-making'</rs>). <rs type="person">Michael Geers</rs> is a fellow of the <rs type="institution">International Max Planck Research School on the Life Course in Berlin</rs> and is supported by the <rs type="funder">Joachim Herz Foundation</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_n2s3nsq">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Reclaiming individual autonomy and democratic discourse online: How to rebalance human and algorithmic decision-making&apos;</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Data availability: The data is stripped of details that would make it possible to re-identify participants in terms of user names, original text, or exact timing. All individual data points, including all variables used in this manuscript, can be found at <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/philipplorenz/real_time_motives">https://github.com/philipplorenz/  real_time_motives</ref>.</p><p>Code availability: All code used for preprocessing and anonymizing the data, as well as for analysis and plotting, can be found at <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/philipplorenz/real_time_motives">https://github.com/philipplorenz/real_time_motives</ref>.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>efforts to understand and improve public discourse online.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>We recruited 195 consenting participants through Twitter advertisements in four different campaigns, each aimed at balancing age and gender. A total of N = 137 participants followed through the whole 1-week observation period and were actively tweeting during that time (see Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> for a description of the sample).</p><p>The anonymized data (excluding the original text of posts, user names, exact timestamps, and other details; but including relevant derived content features, e.g., sentiment, topic, number of retweets) can be found at <ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/gqfjs/">https://osf.io/gqfjs/</ref> alongside the preprocessing and all analysis scripts. We used the survey platform formr <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> to implement an event-driven experience sampling approach during the active observation time, when our participants' Twitter accounts were continuously and automatically monitored. Within 2 minutes of tweeting during their 1-week period of observation, participants received a direct message containing a link to a short survey. The survey displayed the tweet that had just been posted and asked participants about their agreement with 16 statements, each corresponding to one motive for posting that content. The average response rate for the real-time surveys was 67%. See Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> for the detailed participant timeline, Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> for screenshots of the procedure, and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> for details on the sample. The resulting data structure consisted of observational data of participants' activity on Twitter, including posts from before and after the active observation period, as well as survey-based data on their demographic and political variables and their self-reported general motives for sharing content on Twitter.</p><p>Our original preregistered research questions-which we needed to subsequently refine-were:</p><p>• RQ1: What are the main self-reported motives for sharing information on Twitter and how do they vary within and between individuals?</p><p>• RQ2: How do these self-reported motives differ for the type of content (e.g., web domain, topic, sentiment) being shared, its context (e.g., popularity, original author), and the type of sharing (tweet, retweet, quote tweet, reply)?</p><p>• RQ3: How does sharing behavior change if participants are repeatedly prompted to reflect on their motives for sharing content on Twitter?</p><p>To:</p><p>• What are people's self-reported motives for creating content and sharing content on Twitter and how do they vary between and within individuals?</p><p>• How do people's motives change depending on the type of post (retweet, original, quote, reply)?</p><p>• How are different content features associated with the motives behind sharing (retweets)?</p><p>• How are different motives associated with the features of content that is created (original tweets, quotes, replies)?</p><p>• How do these motives and associated content features relate to a post's success?</p><p>The preregistered data partitioning was not feasible due to smaller than expected sample sizes and the exploratory research questions. This combination did not allow for developing an analysis pipeline of a (very small) subset of the data, as further steps depended on the results in our inherently exploratory approach. Without explicit hypothesis, we needed the full data set for identifying the most important relationships in the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preprocessing Pipeline</head><p>All preprocessing steps can be found in the 'Make public data' script at <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/philipplorenz/real_time_motives">https://github.com/  philipplorenz/real_time_motives</ref>. Supplementary Material for "Real-time assessment of motives for sharing and creating content among highly active Twitter users" </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stewardship of global collective behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bak-Coleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2025764118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lewandowsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Technology and democracy: Understanding the influence of online technologies on political behaviour and decision-making</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic review of worldwide causal and correlational evidence on digital media and democracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lorenz-Spreen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Oswald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lewandowsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hertwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mesoudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cultural evolution: How Darwinian theory can explain human culture and synthesize the social sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cultural evolutionary theory: How culture evolves and why it matters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Creanza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kolodny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7782" to="7789" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cultural traits operating in senders are driving forces of cultural evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Enquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghirlanda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Michaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">291</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20232110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Acerbi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cultural evolution in the digital age</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Brinkmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1855" to="1868" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study framework allowing for automated feedback generation and complex longitudinal experience-sampling studies using R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Arslan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Walther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Formr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavior Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="376" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shifting attention to accuracy can reduce misinformation online</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pennycook</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">592</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="590" to="595" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">tweet, retweet: Conversational aspects of retweeting on Twitter in</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Golder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lotan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tweet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2010 43rd Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Honolulu, HI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The partisan brain: An identity-based model of political belief</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Bavel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends in Cognitive Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why people use social media: A uses and gratifications approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Whiting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qualitative Market Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="362" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motivations for sharing news on social media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Y C</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burkell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Social Media &amp; Society</title>
		<meeting>the 8th International Conference on Social Media &amp; Society<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Article 57</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motivations for sharing information and social support in social media: A comparative analysis of Facebook, Twitter, Delicious, YouTube, and Flickr</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Syn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2045" to="2060" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do people share news in social media?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Goh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.-L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Active Media Technology: 7th International Conference</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Callaghan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ghorbani</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lanzhou, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6890</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="140" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Uses and gratifications of Twitter: An examination of user motives and satisfaction of Twitter use in Communication Technology Division of the annual convention of the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-U</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do people share political information on social media?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jones-Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kenski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Digital Journalism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1123" to="1140" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">News sharing in social media: The effect of gratifications and prior experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Users&apos; motivation in sharing information on social media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ghaisani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Handayani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Munajat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Procedia Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="530" to="535" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online social networks: Why we disclose</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Krasnova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spiekermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koroleva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hildebrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of information technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From online disagreement to offline action: How diverse motivations for using social media can increase political information sharing and catalyze offline political participation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Weeks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kwak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Media + Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some people just want to watch the world burn: The prevalence, psychology and politics of the &apos;Need for Chaos</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Arceneaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">376</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20200147</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">By any memes necessary: Beliefand chaos-driven motives for sharing conspiracy theories on social media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Farhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Fitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Saunders</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research &amp; Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Political communication and influence through microblogging-An empirical analysis of sentiment in Twitter messages and retweet behavior in</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stieglitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dang-Xuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2012 45th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Maui, HI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3500" to="3509" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emotion shapes the diffusion of moralized content in social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Bavel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7313" to="7318" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Out-group animosity drives engagement on social media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rathje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Bavel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Der Linden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Article e2024292118</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconsidering evidence of moral contagion in online social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cruz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Hahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1629" to="1635" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What makes online content viral</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Milkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">If this account is true, it is most enormously wonderful&quot;: Interestingness-if-true and the sharing of true and false news</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Altay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>De Araujo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mercier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Digital Journalism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online interaction turns the congeniality bias into an uncongeniality bias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Buder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1055" to="1068" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Partisan polarization is the primary psychological motivation behind political fake news sharing on Twitter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Osmundsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Vahlstrup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bechmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Political Science Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1015" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Motivations to affiliate with audiences drive the sharing of partisan (mis)information on social media</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Invoking self-related and social thoughts impacts online information sharing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Scholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Baek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Article nsad</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking lab and field research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Geers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Reviews Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">458</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Field experiments on social media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mosleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pennycook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Directions in Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validating the demographic, political, psychological, and experimental results obtained from a new source of online survey respondents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Coppock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcclellan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research &amp; Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toolbox of individual-level interventions against online misinformation and manipulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kozyreva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who shares misinformation on social media? A meta-analysis of individual traits related to misinformation sharing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">108271</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is Twitter, a social network or a news media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kwak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on World Wide Web</title>
		<meeting>the 19th International Conference on World Wide Web<address><addrLine>Raleigh, NC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="600" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GPT is an effective tool for multilingual psychological text analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rathje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">R-squared for Bayesian regression models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Goodrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gabry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vehtari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Statistician</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2020/10/PDL_10.15.20.twitter.dems_.reps_.fullreport.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Differences in how Democrats and Republicans behave on Twitter</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Pew Research Center</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supersharers of fake news on Twitter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Baribi-Bartov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Swire-Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Grinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">384</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="979" to="982" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quoting is not citing: Disentangling affiliation and interaction on Twitter in Complex Networks &amp; Their Applications X</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>St-Onge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Herms</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Tenth International Conference on Complex Networks and Their Applications COMPLEX NETWORKS</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Benito</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>the Tenth International Conference on Complex Networks and Their Applications COMPLEX NETWORKS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="705" to="717" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A computational reward learning account of social media engagement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lindström</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1311</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lyons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Montgomery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reifler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Partisanship and older Americans&apos; engagement with dubious political news</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A computational analysis of Telegram&apos;s narrative affordances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Willaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">293508</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Engagement, user satisfaction, and the amplification of divisive content on social media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Milli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sharing of misinformation is habitual, not just lazy or biased</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ceylan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2216614120</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Broadcasting and narrowcasting: How audience size affects what people share</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Barasch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Marketing Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for promoting online prosocial behavior via digital interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Grüning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kamin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Panizza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Katsaros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lorenz-Spreen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accuracy and social motivations shape judgements of (mis)information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rathje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roozenbeek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Bavel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Der Linden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="892" to="903" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bridging systems: Open problems for countering destructive divisiveness across ranking, recommenders, and governance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ovadya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Thorburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Simple changes to content curation algorithms affect the beliefs people form in a collaborative filtering experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lorenz-Spreen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">See something, say something: Correction of global health misinformation on social media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Vraga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1131" to="1140" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dark side of Facebook®: The Dark Tetrad, negative social potency, and trolling behaviours</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Craker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>March</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Individual Differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
