<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Feeling Seen, Feeling Joyful: An Intensive Longitudinal Study on Parenting Joy, Perceived Partner Responsiveness, and Parenthood Regret</title>
				<funder ref="#_uR3gTXQ">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-10-15">October 15, 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Ziwen</forename><surname>Teuber</surname></persName>
							<email>ziwen.teuber@uni.lu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Behavioral and Cognitive Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Luxembourg</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="LU">Luxembourg</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elouise</forename><surname>Botes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Behavioral and Cognitive Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Luxembourg</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="LU">Luxembourg</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Konrad</forename><surname>Piotrowski</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">SWPS University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="PL">Poland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kaisa</forename><surname>Aunola</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Jyväskylä</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Samuel</forename><surname>Greiff</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Social Sciences and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Technical University Munich</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Mcneish</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Arizona State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Behavioral and Cognitive Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Luxembourg</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2, place de I&apos;Université</addrLine>
									<postCode>L-4365</postCode>
									<settlement>Esch-sur-Alzette</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Occupational, Economic, and Social Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Vienna</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Feeling Seen, Feeling Joyful: An Intensive Longitudinal Study on Parenting Joy, Perceived Partner Responsiveness, and Parenthood Regret</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-10-15">October 15, 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">09DF61CC855D135FD21E735218F1BF7B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.17605/OSF.IO/4XGA6</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:57+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Author Contribution Z.T.: Conceptualization</term>
					<term>Methodology</term>
					<term>Formal Analysis</term>
					<term>Data Curation</term>
					<term>Writing -Original Draft</term>
					<term>Writing -Review and Editing</term>
					<term>Visualization</term>
					<term>Project administration E.B.: Conceptualization</term>
					<term>Data curation</term>
					<term>Writing -Review and Editing</term>
					<term>Project administration K.P.: Writing -Original Draft</term>
					<term>Writing -Review and Editing K.A.: Writing -Review and Editing S.G.: Writing -Review and Editing D.M.: Methodology</term>
					<term>Formal Analysis</term>
					<term>Writing -Original Draft</term>
					<term>Writing -Review and Editing</term>
					<term>Visualization experience sampling method, dynamic structural equation modeling (DSEM), family dynamics, parenting stress and resilience, romantic relationships</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Particularly for parents, the Christmas season is an emotionally intense period that offers a valuable window into affective and family dynamics. Drawing on a positive psychology perspective, we aimed to investigate how parenting joy and perceived partner responsiveness covary during this time and how they are related to the longer-term development of parenthood regret. We collected 35 days of experience sampling data, complemented by baseline and follow-up measures, from 269 parents in the United Kingdom (13,249 total observations). Using dynamic structural equation modeling (DSEM), we examined the within-person dynamics between momentary parenting joy and momentary perceived partner responsiveness. At the between-person level, we explored how participants' average levels of these momentary experiences predicted changes in parenthood regret from baseline to follow-up. DSEM revealed a unidirectional, positive prediction from perceived partner responsiveness to parenting joy at the within-person level. At the betweenperson level, person means of joy moderated parenthood regret from baseline to follow-up, after relevant sociodemographic variables were controlled for. These findings contribute to the emerging literature on parenthood regret by emphasizing the role of daily emotional experiences and partner dynamics in shaping parental identity. Practically speaking, even small everyday adjustments in family interactions may meaningfully dampen parenthood regret.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Feeling Seen, Feeling Joyful: An Intensive Longitudinal Study on Parenting Joy, Perceived Partner Responsiveness, and Parenthood Regret</head><p>Celebrated by approximately two billion people worldwide each year <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Syrek et al., 2018)</ref>, Christmas is often idealized as a season of joy, connection, and family togetherness <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Miller, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Syrek et al., 2018)</ref>. Meanwhile, it has also been well-documented as a source of heightened stress and emotional strain (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Schneider et al., 2023)</ref>. This duality is particularly salient for parents, who are expected to manage logistics, uphold traditions, and create joyful experiences for their children. As such, the Christmas season provides a valuable context for studying affective and family dynamics. One aspect that may fluctuate during this season is parenting joy-the fulfillment and emotional reward parents derive from interacting with their children <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Leerkes &amp; Augustine, 2019</ref>). An interpersonal resource that may support parents' emotional well-being during this period is perceived partner responsiveness <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Ter Kuile et al., 2017)</ref>, that is, feeling understood, valued, and cared for by one's partner <ref type="bibr">(Reis et al., 2004)</ref>. We hypothesized that perceived partner responsiveness enhances parents' capacity to experience parenting joy during the Christmas season and that both partner responsiveness and parenting joy can buffer against the development of parenthood regret. Parenthood regret reflects a deep, often stigmatized cognitive-emotional experience in which individuals question or mourn their decision to become a parent <ref type="bibr">(Piotrowski et al., 2023)</ref>. Though relatively understudied, it has critical implications for parental well-being, family functioning, and child development (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Piotrowski, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr">Piotrowski et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Examining how momentary experiences of parenting joy and partner responsiveness covary during the Christmas season and how they are related to parenthood regret can provide important insights into the factors that shape parental well-being and identity over time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parenthood Regret as a Research Agenda</head><p>Regret is a complex, negatively valenced self-conscious emotion, underpinned by counterfactual thinking; it arises when individuals reflect on a past decision or (in)action and believe that a different choice would have led to a better outcome <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Zeelenberg, 1999)</ref>. Parenthood regret refers to a parent's negative appraisal of their parental role and typically occurs when they question or mourn their decision to become a parent <ref type="bibr">(Piotrowski et al., 2023</ref><ref type="bibr">(Piotrowski et al., , 2024))</ref>. Most people experience regret about a decision at some point in their lives, and experiencing regret about having children is not as rare as societal narratives might suggest. In the United Kingdom, for example, 8% of parents experience parenthood regret "to some extent" <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(YouGov, 2021)</ref>. This percentage is even higher in Poland (14%; <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Piotrowski, 2021)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Germany (20%;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">YouGov, 2017)</ref>. Overall, younger, single parents, those facing financial or mental health challenges, and parents of children with special needs are more likely to regret having children <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Piotrowski, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">YouGov, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Despite its prevalence, parenthood regret remains a societally and culturally taboo topic, often surrounded by stigma and silence, which are factors that discourage open dialogue, hinder policy recognition, and limit research into the causes and potential interventions for parenthood regret <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bodin &amp; Fängström, 2025)</ref>.</p><p>Parenthood regret can have profound, detrimental effects not only on the parents themselves but also on the overall functioning of the family and the development of children <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Roskam et al., 2025)</ref>. Parents who regret having children often experience ambivalence or a sense of incongruence between their authentic feelings and the socially prescribed emotions expected of them in the parental role; this internal conflict frequently gives rise to feelings of shame, guilt, anxiety, and embarrassment <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Moore &amp; Abetz, 2019)</ref>. Empirical studies have additionally linked parenthood regret to reduced life satisfaction and poorer health conditions, as well as elevated P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d levels of parental burnout and depressive symptoms, all of which may further disrupt family functioning and child development <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Piotrowski, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr">Piotrowski et al., 2023</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Piotrowski et al., , 2025))</ref>. In light of these potentially far-reaching effects, researchers <ref type="bibr">(Piotrowski et al., 2023</ref><ref type="bibr">(Piotrowski et al., , 2024) )</ref> have called for greater scientific attention to be paid to parenthood regret. We aimed to advance this emerging field by identifying factors that may help mitigate parenthood regret over time. To situate our investigation in a context rich with emotional salience, we focused on the Christmas season, a period often marked by both joy and sorrow, thereby offering opportunities for reflection on partnership and parenting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parenting Joy and Perceived Partner Responsiveness During the Christmas Season</head><p>Christmas holds deep emotional and symbolic significance for many families, particularly in Christian-majority countries such as the United Kingdom <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Miller, 2017)</ref>. The season is imbued with traditions and rituals, such as sharing festive meals, singing carols, and decorating Christmas trees, activities that foster family togetherness and cultural continuity (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Páez et al., 2011)</ref>. From a positive psychology perspective, parenthood can be a profound source of joy, as it provides meaning and purpose, fulfills psychological needs, evokes positive emotions, and enriches social identity <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Novick, 2023)</ref>. Christmas traditions, in particular, create opportunities for joyful parentchild interactions. Activities such as reading festive stories, baking cookies, or witnessing a child's delight when unwrapping a gift can evoke a deep sense of fulfillment and connection. These emotionally rich interactions help affirm parents' identities and highlight the meaningful aspects of family life <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Musick et al., 2016)</ref>. However, this idealized version often contrasts with the lived realities of many parents. Christmas can be emotionally demanding and psychologically taxing, as it is frequently accompanied by elevated stress, family tension, financial strain, health issues, excessive drinking, and even feelings of loneliness <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Schneider et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Syrek et al., 2018)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</head><p>Moreover, the weeks leading up to Christmas are often saturated with time pressure, social obligations, and unrealistic expectations <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Miyazaki, 1993)</ref>. Thus, for many parents, the desire to create a "magical" holiday for their children can become an emotionally draining pursuit, leaving little space for genuine joy or connection.</p><p>In such emotionally charged contexts, it becomes crucial to have a responsive partner.</p><p>Perceived partner responsiveness is defined as the perception that one is understood, validated, and cared for by an interaction partner <ref type="bibr">(Reis et al., 2004)</ref>. Accordingly, feeling understood refers to the extent to which individuals perceive that their partner accurately grasps their inner world, including their beliefs, goals, history, emotions, and self-perceptions. Feeling validated reflects perceptions that one's partner genuinely values, appreciates, and affirms their core self, conveying that they are loved for who they are. Feeling cared for pertains to one's perception of the degree to which a partner expresses sincere concern for one's well-being through words, actions, and emotional responsiveness <ref type="bibr">(Reis et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Reis &amp; Clark, 2013)</ref>. Extensive research has demonstrated that perceived partner responsiveness is a powerful predictor of satisfaction and intimacy in relationships, well-being, positive emotions, and physical health (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arican-Dinc &amp; Gable, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Itzchakov et al., 2022)</ref>. Indeed, it has been proposed as an organizing concept in relationship and well-being research, as it integrates key elements of many fundamental relational constructs, provides essential validation of the self, and fosters feelings of warmth, acceptance, belonging, and trust <ref type="bibr">(Reis, 2012)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parenting Joy and Parenthood Regret as Proximal and Distal Consequences of Perceived</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Partner Responsiveness</head><p>Research has suggested that the "downstream consequences" <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Reis et al., 2022)</ref> of perceived partner responsiveness unfold across both proximal and distal levels of psychological P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d functioning <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Merolla et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr">Reis, 2001)</ref>. Accordingly, proximal consequences refer to immediate emotional or psychological responses (e.g., changes in positive or negative emotions) that emerge in the context of supportive partner interactions, whereas distal consequences emerge from accumulations of interactive moments (e.g., longer-term shifts in individual well-being, mental health, and relational satisfaction). Building on this assumption, we positioned momentary parenting joy as a proximal consequence in this study, representing a momentary experience shaped by feeling understood, validated, and cared for by one's partner in everyday interactions.</p><p>In comparison, we incorporated parenthood regret as a distal consequence that represents a painful evaluation of one's parenting identity and decisions. Such an evaluation may develop over time as a function of cumulative emotional experiences and relational dynamics.</p><p>In the parenting domain, perceived partner responsiveness has been linked to reduced parenting-related stress <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Ter Kuile et al., 2017)</ref> and positive developmental outcomes in children <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bierstetel et al., 2023)</ref>. Particularly during emotionally demanding periods, such as the Christmas season, the presence of a responsive partner may function as an emotional anchor, providing validation, reassurance, and a shared sense of connection. Importantly, partner responsiveness does more than mitigate negative affect; it may also amplify the capacity to savor joyful parenting moments, which reinforce parents' emotional engagement with their children and facilitate a deeper sense of meaning in family life. These momentary experiences of joy and responsiveness may accumulate to shape how parents make sense of their parenting role over time. When parents regularly experience moments of joy in their interactions with their children, coupled with consistent support from a responsive partner, they are more likely to construct a positive and coherent narrative of their parenting journey. This narrative can serve as a mechanism that buffers against parenthood regret, an emotion often rooted in ambivalent emotions, unmet expectations, P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d perceived failures, disbelief, or identity-related dissatisfaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Donath, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Piotrowski et al., 2025)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disentangling Between-and Within-Person Effects and Real-Time Assessments</head><p>In psychological research, disentangling between-and within-person effects has gained increasing importance, as each level offers distinct theoretical insights and practical implications.</p><p>Whereas between-person evidence helps researchers and practitioners understand how individuals differ from one another, within-person results offer information about how individuals differ from themselves across time <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Hamaker, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Hopwood et al., 2025)</ref>. The former is particularly useful, for example, for identifying risk and resilience factors and for guiding the selection of appropriate intervention strategies. The latter allows researchers and practitioners to understand within-person changes and to tailor treatment approaches to the individual's evolving needs and circumstances.</p><p>Although family life is dynamic in that personal interactions, conflicts, emotions, and perceptions can vary from one situation to the next, existing research on family life rarely reflects these dynamic changes. Empirical work in this area often utilizes assessments of trait-like tendencies and retrospective self-reports, which fail to capture the state-level fluctuations that occur in daily family life. Retrospective self-reports are especially prone to memory biases, as individuals tend to report what they believe they regularly experience as opposed to reporting on their accurate in-the-moment experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Gloster et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Goetz et al., 2013)</ref>. By contrast, the experience sampling method (ESM; for an overview of the method, see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Zirkel et al., 2015)</ref> offers the opportunity to examine participants' real-time experiences, which are only minimally affected by recall biases. As such, we assessed parenting joy and perceived partner responsiveness in real time at short, repeated intervals, multiple times a day across a 35-day period.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</head><p>Moreover, we measured the longer-term changes in parenthood regret with surveys administered before and after the experience sampling phase.</p><p>In analyzing the experience sampling data, we utilized dynamic structural equation modeling (DSEM; <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hamaker et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">McNeish &amp; Hamaker, 2020)</ref>, a cutting-edge approach for separating processes that occur within individuals from those that vary between individuals.</p><p>By integrating elements of structural equation modeling (SEM), time-series methods, and multilevel modeling, DSEM enables researchers to capture complex dynamics. The SEM component allows observed measures to be partitioned into transient, situational fluctuations (within-person variance) and stable, trait-like tendencies (between-person variance). Similar to time-series models, DSEM incorporates lagged outcomes and time-dependent predictors, whereas the multilevel aspect makes it possible to estimate how these dynamic effects differ across individuals. This combination makes DSEM particularly well-suited for studying state-like, shortterm variations in parenting experiences and how they accumulate into longer-term outcomes such as parenthood regret. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Hamaker et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">McNeish &amp; Hamaker, 2020)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Questions and Hypotheses</head><p>Adopting a positive psychology perspective, this study aims to examine the predictive association between momentary parenting joy and the momentary perception of partner responsiveness during the Christmas season and whether accumulations of these experiences buffer against the longer-term development of parenthood regret. To address these questions, we implemented a 35-day intensive longitudinal design using ESM to capture real-time variations in parenting joy and perceived partner responsiveness. Longer-term changes in parenthood regret were assessed with baseline and follow-up surveys administered before and after the experience sampling period. On the basis of this approach and the rationale outlined above, we formulated P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d two hypotheses. At the within-person level, momentary fluctuations in perceived partner responsiveness positively predict momentary fluctuations in parenting joy (Hypothesis 1). At the between-person level, person mean levels of parenting joy and perceived partner responsiveness across the experience sampling period moderate the changes in parenthood regret from baseline to follow-up, such that higher levels of these constructs attenuate increases in regret over time (Hypothesis 2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method Preregistration and Open Science Statement</head><p>This study was part of a larger, preregistered project investigating parental experiences during the Christmas season. The preregistration protocol is publicly available at https://osf.io/4xga6/?view_only=136f8723227148ed84e9f2c8f02eafe6. Whereas the overall study design was preregistered, specific hypotheses related to the current study were not included in the preregistration, and this study was therefore exploratory in nature. The data set and codes related to this study are available at https://osf.io/ad647/?view_only=e59b0fc4f8a24bf1a317e51c20039251. Ethical approval for the project was obtained from [blinded for peer review]. All participants provided written informed consent, and participation was entirely voluntary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants and Procedure</head><p>In November 2023, a total of 380 U.K. parents with at least one child under the age of 10 were invited to participate via the Prolific platform. The study ran from November 2023 to January Additional exclusion criteria included not residing with any children or being a single parent without a co-parenting partner, as the study focused on partner-related dynamics. For incentives, participants needed to respond to at least two prompts per day for 15 days during the experience sampling phase. A total of 27 participants (10%) did not fulfill this requirement.</p><p>After data cleaning, the final sample consisted of 269 participants (168 identified as mothers and 101 as fathers) with a mean age of 38.26 years (SD = 6.95). All participants were treated as representing distinct family units. The median annual household net income fell within the range of £50,000-£59,999, which is higher than the U.K. national median of £34,500 reported for 2023 (Office for National Statistics, 2024). On average, participants reported 1.86 children per household (SD = 0.81). The mean age of their youngest child in the household was 5.25 years (SD = 3.53). Additionally, 50 parents (18.59%) indicated that at least one of their children had special educational needs, such as ADHD and learning disabilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Momentary Perceived Partner Responsiveness</head><p>To measure momentary perceived partner responsiveness, we adapted the Perceived Partner Responsiveness Scale <ref type="bibr">(Gable et al., 2012)</ref>, originally developed for retrospective use in daily diary studies. In this study, three items were modified to capture participants' real-time experiences: "Currently my partner understands me," "… makes me feel like they value my abilities and opinions," and "… makes me feel cared for" (1 = strongly disagree, 7 = strongly agree). The average individual mean was Mi = 5.28 (SD = 1.66). The intraclass correlation P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d coefficient (ICC) indicated that 76.6% of the total variance was attributed to between-person variance. The within-person reliability was α = .89, and the between-person reliability was α = .99, estimated as specified by Nezlek (2017). Additional methodological details can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">McNeish's (2025)</ref> preprint.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Momentary Parenting Joy</head><p>Momentary parenting joy was assessed with a single self-constructed item: "How much are you currently enjoying parenting?" rated on a 7-point Likert-type scale (1 = not at all, 7 = extremely). The average individual mean was Mi = 5.47 (SD = 1.32). The ICC showed that 62.3% of the total variance could be attributed to between-person variance. Using the measurement error autoregressive method for single-item assessments <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Schuurman &amp; Hamaker, 2019)</ref>, the withinperson reliability was estimated to be .52, whereas the between-person reliability was .99.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parenthood Regret</head><p>Parenthood regret was assessed at baseline and follow-up with the 12-item Parenthood Regret Scale by <ref type="bibr">Piotrowski et al. (2023)</ref>. Sample items included statements such as "I should have prevented myself from having a child while it was still possible." Participants rated each item on a 7-point Likert-type scale (1 = strongly disagree, 7 = strongly agree). The scale demonstrated excellent internal consistency at both baseline (𝜔 = .97) and follow-up (𝜔 = .98). Confirmatory factor analyses supported its unidimensional structure at both time points and indicated partial scalar longitudinal invariance over time (see Supplementary Material A).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sociodemographic Variables</head><p>Sociodemographic variables were measured at baseline and included participants' gender, age, socioeconomic status, and the presence of special educational needs in their children. Gender was dummy-coded (1 = female, 0 = male). Socioeconomic status was estimated on the basis of P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</p><p>participants' total annual net household income (1 = less than £10,000, 13 = more than £150,000).</p><p>Finally, the presence of special needs was determined by asking parents whether any of their children had special educational needs (1 = yes, 0 = no).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Analysis</head><p>To test our hypotheses, we applied DSEM <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Hamaker et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">McNeish &amp; Hamaker, 2020)</ref> using Mplus 8.11 <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Muthén &amp; Muthén, 1998</ref><ref type="bibr">-2025)</ref>. The first hypothesis concerned withinperson associations between two variables, which is straightforward to assess with a vector autoregressive model within the DSEM framework. The second hypothesis concerned moderating effects involving person means. This analysis is conceptually straightforward but presents some computational challenges and is not directly supported in the most recent version of the Mplus software (Version 8.11). Specifically, moderating effects in DSEM can be tested by allowing two predictors to interact with each other, similar to standard regression modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Cohen et al., 2003)</ref>.</p><p>However, a complication with moderating effects in DSEM is that the model uses latent centering to avoid Nickell's bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Nickell, 1981</ref>) and Luedtke's bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Lüdtke et al., 2008)</ref>, which can arise in multilevel time-series data <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Asparouhov &amp; Muthén, 2019)</ref>. Thus, the person means are latent variables, so testing for moderating effects involving a person mean in DSEM results in a latent interaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Holtmann &amp; Koslowski, 2025)</ref>, which is far more difficult to estimate because latent variables are not observed directly <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Maslowsky et al., 2015)</ref>. To work around this issue, we relied on plausible values <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Mislevy, 1991)</ref>, an approach that has been recommended as a Bayesian solution for latent interactions in the related area of multilevel SEM <ref type="bibr">(Asparouhov &amp; Muthén, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Zyphur et al., 2019</ref>). An analysis with plausible values is essentially multiple imputation where the unobserved latent variable is treated as if it were an observed variable with 100% missing data <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Enders, 2025)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</head><p>The analysis comprised two steps. The first step consisted of only a latent decomposition, which split the observed variables into within-person and between-person latent variables, which is standard procedure for all DSEM models <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Hamaker et al., 2021)</ref>. After the latent decomposition, each latent variable had a conditional posterior distribution from which 100 plausible values were drawn for each observation <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Jewsbury et al., 2025)</ref>. This process resulted in 100 different data sets, each with different possible values of the within-person and between-person latent variables for each observation (i.e., each person's latent variable values were imputed 100 times). The second step fit the model to all 100 data sets and used multiple imputation pooling rules to preserve uncertainty in the parameter estimates (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Enders, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Rubin, 1987)</ref>. The benefit was thatwithin each analysis-the plausible values were treated as observed variables, so it was straightforward to create a product term to test for moderating effects rather than requiring a latent interaction. Pooling across 100 sets of plausible values incorporates uncertainty in the plausible values and is computationally expedient relative to the high-dimensional integration required with alternative approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Zyphur et al., 2019)</ref>. Each of these components is a latent variable, which is denoted by a circle. Because moderating effects were a key interest, plausible values were drawn for each latent variable, which were represented by placing a tilde over the variable name. The plausible values were treated as observed in the model, and their uncertainty was preserved by pooling them across 100 different draws from the conditional posterior of the latent variable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</head><p>The within-person model is shown in the lower left panel of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>. The model has two outcomes, the plausible value for parenting joy and the plausible value for perceived partner responsiveness. Each variable is autoregressed on itself at the previous timepoint (captured by ϕ1i and ϕ2i ) and is predicted by the cross-lag of the other variable (captured by ϕ3i and ϕ4i ). All autoregressions and cross-lags are modeled as person-specific via random effects, which means that the magnitude of the coefficient is modeled as a distribution rather than as a single fixed value to allow for between-person heterogeneity in these effects. This is denoted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>  regret at follow-up was the primary outcome, which was predicted by the plausible value for the person mean of parenting joy, the plausible value for the person mean of perceived partner responsiveness, and baseline parenthood regret. Two-way interactions were also formed between baseline parenthood regret and the person means. These interactions were the sole motivation for using plausible values; without plausible values, it would not be possible to create an interaction between a latent variable and an observed variable in DSEM in Mplus (as of Version 8.11).</p><p>Demographic variables were also included as predictors of the person means and parenthood regret at follow-up.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</head><p>The model was estimated using Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) via a Gibbs sampler in Mplus Version 8.11. Diffuse priors were used for all parameters given that the number of individuals was rather large for a DSEM analysis, so priors should have had minimal influence on the posterior distributions, and primacy was given to information in the data <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(McNeish, 2019)</ref>. The model was applied to 100 data sets, each with a unique set of plausible values for each observation.</p><p>Each data set used two MCMC chains with 2,000 iterations and a thinning of 5, resulting in 10,000 iterations per data set or 1,000,000 total iterations when pooled across all sets of plausible values.</p><p>The potential scale reduction factor was used to assess convergence; the PSR was below 1.01 for all parameters, which was well below the typically recommended 1.10 threshold (where values closer to 1 are better; <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Brooks &amp; Gelman, 1998)</ref>. Posterior distributions were summarized with the median to provide a point estimate for each parameter. Parameters with a 95% credible interval (CI) that did not include 0 were considered to provide evidence that the population effect was nonnull.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Participants provided an average of 49.25 repeated measures (SD = 23.01) during the experience sampling period, yielding a total of 13,249 observations across 269 participants. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> presents descriptive statistics and correlations between the variables of interest after latent decomposition in Mplus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Within-Person Associations Between Parenting Joy and Perceived Partner Responsiveness</head><p>We examined autoregressive and cross-lagged effects of parenting joy and perceived partner responsiveness at the within-person level in DSEM. We found non-null autoregressive effects for both constructs. Across the sample, the average autoregressive coefficient for parenting joy was B = .289 <ref type="bibr">[.255, .322]</ref>, and for momentary perceived partner responsiveness, B = .370 P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d <ref type="bibr">[.333, .409</ref>]. These results indicated that individuals were likely to report elevated levels of parenting joy or perceived partner responsiveness at a given moment if they had experienced elevated levels of the same construct at an earlier moment, relative to their own average.</p><p>With regard to our first hypothesis, a positive cross-lagged effect was observed from perceived partner responsiveness to parenting joy (B = .030 [.012, .051]) but not in the other direction from parenting joy to perceived partner responsiveness (B = .013 [-.003, .051]). That is, when a participant reported a higher level of perceived partner responsiveness in one moment, they experienced greater parenting joy in the subsequent moment. However, momentary fluctuations in parenting joy did not predict fluctuations in later perceptions of partner responsiveness (although 0 was barely inside the credible interval). The within-person R 2 was 19% for parenting joy and 11% for perceived partner responsiveness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Between-Person Associations Between Parenting Joy, Partner Responsiveness, and</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parenthood Regret</head><p>At the between-person level of DSEM, we investigated how the person means of parenting joy and perceived partner responsiveness, captured during the experience sampling period, were related to parenthood regret assessed at both baseline and follow-up, while accounting for relevant sociodemographic covariates. One consideration in the between-person model was that the raw values of parenthood regret at follow-up had a notable positive skew such that most responses were toward the lower end of the scale. However, an underlying assumption of DSEM is that the residuals are normal, not the outcome variable itself. We initially fit a model treating parenthood regret at follow-up as continuous to inspect whether the residuals were reasonably normal. QQ plots and histograms suggested that the residuals may deviate mildly from normality (plots are provided in Supplementary Material B), exhibiting some excess kurtosis but almost no skewness P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</p><p>(sign test = -4.5, p = .63). Nonetheless, inferential tests such as the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test (D = .077, p = .08) and the Cramer-von Mises test (ω 2 = 0.21, p = .25) provided some evidence that the residuals were approximately normal, although the Anderson-Darling test did not support the normality of the residuals (A 2 = 16.70, p &lt; .01). Additional diagnostic tests suggested that the residual distribution had heavier tails. An Anderson-Darling test for whether the residuals followed a t distribution with 4 degrees of freedom was not significant (A 2 = 2.10, p = .08), and neither were the Cramer-von Mises test (ω 2 = 0.11, p = .54) or the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test (D = .050, p = .51).</p><p>In general, there seemed to be reasonable evidence to support treating parenthood regret at followup as continuous rather than adopting alternative approaches that might complicate the interpretation, such as probit models, hurdle models, or log transformations. The results indicated that participants with higher parenthood regret at baseline tended to have higher parenthood regret at follow-up <ref type="bibr">(B = 1.176 [0.924, 1.433]</ref>) and that participants with higher person means in parenting joy tended to have lower parenthood regret at follow-up (B = -.135 <ref type="bibr">[-.206, -.065]</ref>). However, there was a non-null moderating effect whereby higher person means in parenting joy dampened the effect of baseline parenthood regret (B = -.125 <ref type="bibr">[-.201, -.051]</ref>). Therefore, the 1.176 effect reported above was conditional on the person mean of parenting joy being equal to 0.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> probes the moderating effect to show how the effect of parenthood regret at baseline changed as a function of the person means of parenting joy. The vertical axis shows the effect of parenthood regret at baseline, and the horizontal axis shows the person mean of parenting joy. The black line represents the effect of baseline parenthood regret on follow-up parenthood regret, and the grey lines represent the 95% CI. For low values of parenting joy, the effect of baseline parenthood regret on follow-up parenthood regret was much stronger (slightly above 1).</p><p>However, for the parenting joy person means that were near the top of the scale range (i.e., 6.65 P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</p><p>and above; about 17% of the sample), the effect of baseline parenthood regret dissipated and became indistinguishable from 0. The person means of perceived partner responsiveness did not seem to be related to parenthood regret at follow-up (B = -.032 [-.077, 0.012]) nor did they appear to moderate the effect of parenthood regret at baseline (B = .018 [-.025, .062]). All covariates for parenthood regret at follow-up were plausibly null such that 0 was firmly within the 95% CI.</p><p>Overall, the model explained 76% of the between-person variance in parenthood regret at followup. A few covariates were plausibly non-null in predicting the person means. Having a child with special needs was associated with lower person means in parenting joy (B = -.333 [-.662, -.000]), and mothers reported lower person means in perceived partner responsiveness than fathers did (B = -.569 <ref type="bibr">[-.938, -.205]</ref>). Older participants also showed borderline evidence of having slightly lower person means in perceived partner responsiveness, as 0 was barely within the credible interval (B = -.022 [-.048, .004]).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>In this study, we used the DSEM framework to examine how fluctuations in perceived partner responsiveness were associated with fluctuations in parenting joy across the Christmas season and how these experiences were related to the longer-term development of parenthood regret. The results provide novel insights into the emotional ecology of parenting, revealing both short-term within-person dynamics and longer-term between-person associations that are relevant for understanding parenthood regret.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Perceived Partner Responsiveness as a Momentary Resource for Parenting Joy</head><p>In line with our first hypothesis, increases in perceptions of partner responsiveness at one moment predicted increases in parenting joy at the subsequent moment but not the other way around at the within-person level. This observed unidirectional effect suggests that, whereas P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d responsive interactions within the couple are emotionally enriching for parenting, joyful parenting moments do not necessarily spill over to enhance perceived partner responsiveness. This pattern can be interpreted in at least two ways. First, experiencing elevated parenting joy may temporarily reduce the additional need for partner responsiveness. Partner responsiveness often serves key emotional and relational functions, such as promoting closeness and intimacy, fulfilling attachment needs, and supporting a partner's goals and well-being <ref type="bibr">(Reis, 2012)</ref>. When parents feel more competent, connected, and fulfilled in their parenting role than they usually do, their emotional and relational needs may be sufficiently met through the parenting experience itself. As a result, the activation of additional support-seeking motives and thus the perception of partner responsiveness may be reduced in these moments.</p><p>Second, this unidirectional pattern may reflect differences in the psychological and interpersonal functions of the two constructs. Perceived partner responsiveness in our study was relational, as it involved a parent's perception that their partner understands, validates, and cares for their inner states <ref type="bibr">(Reis et al., 2004)</ref>, and it plays an important role in emotion regulation and well-being across relational and individual domains (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Feeney &amp; Collins, 2015)</ref>. In this sense, responsiveness may act as a cross-domain emotional resource, fostering a secure emotional climate in the family that facilitates parental attunement and amplifies the emotional rewards of caregiving.</p><p>In other words, when parents feel supported by their partner, they may be more emotionally available and present with their children, thereby enhancing the potential for joyful parenting experiences even in emotionally charged periods. In comparison, parenting joy may be more specific to the experience of parenting, as it is often grounded in momentary experiences of connection, progress, or meaning in the parent-child relationship (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Leerkes &amp; Augustine, 2019)</ref>. Such experiences may enhance personal well-being and parental self-efficacy <ref type="bibr">(Salo et al.,</ref> P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d 2022) but do not necessarily involve the partner. Unless such joyful experiences are explicitly shared or co-constructed within the couple (e.g., through mutual reflection or co-parenting activities), they may not feed back into perceptions of partner responsiveness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Role of Parenting Joy and Partner Responsiveness in Parenthood Regret</head><p>Our second hypothesis addressed the moderating effects of person means of parenting joy and perceived partner responsiveness on parenthood regret. This hypothesis was partially supported: Individuals with higher means in parenting joy, but not perceived partner responsiveness, reported lower parenthood regret at follow-up at the between-person level.</p><p>Moreover, person means of parenting joy moderated the development of parenthood regret from baseline to follow-up, suggesting that experiencing greater parenting joy may buffer against the development of parenthood regret across a longer period of time. Parenthood regret, though less frequently studied than other forms of parenting-related negative experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Roskam et al., 2025)</ref>, represents a particularly poignant form of distress, often involving a global and retrospective negative appraisal of one's decision to become a parent or of the parenting role itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Piotrowski, 2021)</ref>. Although person means of perceived partner responsiveness were not associated with parenthood regret at follow-up at the between-person level, within-person results</p><p>showed that momentary fluctuations in partner responsiveness did positively predict corresponding fluctuations in parenting joy. This pattern points to the significance of momentary emotional and relational dynamics in shaping parents' experiences, and, over time, their evaluations related to the parenting role. Such results highlight the dynamic and temporally extended nature of parenting experiences, where affective and relational states may crystallize into more stable perceptions of parenting (dis)satisfaction and identification. They also suggest a mechanism whereby parenting joy, fostered by feeling understood and supported by a partner, may P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d</p><p>gradually buffer against the emergence or persistence of regret. This result aligns with <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fredrickson's (2004)</ref> broaden-and-build theory, which suggests that positive emotions might not only serve an immediate hedonic function but may also contribute to the accumulation of psychological and relational resources over time. In the context of parenting, such resources may include emotional resilience, adaptive parenting practices, as well as strengthened partnerships and parent-child relationships, all of which may serve to mitigate the longer-term development of parenthood regret. This perspective is also consistent with Reis's (2001) proposition that distal "downstream consequences" of partner responsiveness emerge from the accumulation of moments of supportive social interactions.</p><p>Regarding the influence of sociodemographic factors on parenthood regret, previous studies have linked parents' younger ages, greater financial strain, and the presence of special needs in children to increased levels of parenthood regret <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Piotrowski, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">YouGov, 2021)</ref>. In our study, however, only the presence of special needs in children (among the variables of parental gender, age, socioeconomic status, and special needs in children) emerged as a meaningful predictor of parenthood regret at baseline. This association did not hold over time though: After accounting for baseline levels of parenthood regret, the presence of special needs did not predict parenthood regret at follow-up. However, higher parental age and being a mother were associated with lower person means in perceived partner responsiveness, whereas parents of children with special needs experienced lower levels of parenting joy across the Christmas season. These results suggest that sociodemographic variables may exert their influence indirectly, shaping the quality of the parenting experience rather than regret itself. Overall, it is encouraging that parental gender, age, and socioeconomic status did not, in and of themselves, increase the extent to which parents experienced parenthood regret. This finding challenges deficit-based assumptions often associated P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d with these demographic groups and suggests that parenthood regret is not rooted in sociodemographic disadvantage. Yet, the elevated levels of parenthood regret observed at baseline among parents of children with special needs stress the acute emotional and practical challenges these families face. Although these difficulties might not result in a sustained increase in parenthood regret over time, the initial vulnerability remains substantial. This trend points to an important window of opportunity for early intervention. There is a need for tailored, sustained support systems that address the specific emotional, logistical, and relational demands experienced by caregivers of children with special needs. Such interventions are essential not only for reducing immediate distress but also for preventing the entrenchment of negative self-evaluations related to the parenting role.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Practical Implications</head><p>The results of this study have important practical implications. Partner responsiveness may serve as an affective scaffold for parenting joy in everyday life. Experiencing parenting joy may additionally function as a psychological buffer against parenthood regret for a longer time period.</p><p>These results suggest that parents, particularly those struggling with their parenting role, may benefit from a partner's understanding, validation, and genuine care. Practitioners in family consultation and therapy can support parents and families by helping couples develop practical strategies that increase their emotional awareness, attunement to cues for connection and support needs, and the ability to show empathy and engage in warm and constructive communication.</p><p>Strengthening these relational and emotional skills enables parents to create a secure family climate characterized by mutual understanding and shared coping. Such a climate not only amplifies the experience of parenting joy but also serves as a protective factor against negative appraisals of the parenting role. Regret is a common and deeply human emotion, even in the P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d context of parenting <ref type="bibr">(Piotrowski et al., 2023</ref><ref type="bibr">(Piotrowski et al., , 2024))</ref>. However, discussions of parenthood regret remain largely taboo, often silenced by social norms that idealize parenting as exclusively a joyful experience. We call for greater media, political, and scientific attention to be paid to parenthood regret. Creating space for parents to voice their experiences and reflect on their evolving parental identity can foster a more compassionate and flexible appraisal of parenting challenges. Rather than reinforcing self-critical or fatalistic interpretations, such open dialogue can normalize ambivalence, reduce isolation, and build emotional resilience.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations and Future Directions</head><p>Several limitations warrant consideration and point to future research directions. First, this study was conducted during the Christmas season, which may limit the generalizability of the findings to more general or less intense parenting contexts throughout the year. Second, the sample was relatively small and geographically restricted to U.K. parents, which may further constrain the extent to which the results generalize to more diverse populations. Third, parenthood regret is a socially sensitive and potentially taboo topic. The reliance on self-report measures may be susceptible to social desirability bias, particularly in the context of normative beliefs about the parenting role. Future studies may consider including a social desirability scale specific to parenting to statistically account for this influence or implement indirect or implicit assessment methods to reduce such bias. Future studies should also move beyond examining global levels of parenthood regret and instead differentiate between its cognitive and emotional components. In the broader literature on regret, as well as in recent work on parenthood regret specifically <ref type="bibr">(Piotrowski et al., 2023)</ref>, scholars have emphasized that regret entails both the evaluative judgment that one's past decision was a mistake and the emotional experience of sorrow, anger, or selfblame that accompanies this judgment. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>In the present study, we employed state-of-the-art methodologies to capture parenting joy and perceived partner responsiveness in parents' natural environment during the Christmas season.</p><p>By examining dynamic within-person associations, we revealed a unidirectional spillover effect from perceived partner responsiveness to parenting joy, highlighting the emotion-enhancing role of partner responsiveness. In addition, parenting joy emerged as a protective factor that dampened the longer-term development of parenthood regret at the between-person level. Practically, the identified moderating effect suggests that even small, everyday adjustments in family interactions can meaningfully shape parental identity. Taken together, these findings advance our understanding of resilience factors that buffer against parenthood regret and point to actionable strategies for strengthening family well-being.</p><p>P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2024 and consisted of three phases: a baseline survey (November 17), a 35-day experience sampling period (November 30 -January 3), and a follow-up survey (January 15), covering the pre-Christmas, Christmas, and post-Christmas periods. During the experience sampling period, P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d participants received three random prompts per day between 08:00 and 20:00 via the MindSampler app (for procedural details, seeTeuber et al., 2025). Participants were excluded from the final data analytic sample if they had missing data on all key study variables across all three periods.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 depicts the conceptual DSEM model. The upper left panel of Figure 1 shows the</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>by placing a circle over the path. The residual variances are also modeled as person-specific, meaning that the volatility or reactivity of the time series is heterogeneous across individuals. The right panel of Figure 1 shows the between-person model. The upper portion of the right panel shows the fixed effects for the plausible values of the person means, the residual variances, and the within-person coefficients. The ψ terms capture the between-person heterogeneity in these quantities. The residual variances are preceded by "ln" to indicate that the natural log was applied, which indicates a log-linear model to ensure that the variances were larger than 0. The bottom portion of the between-person model shows the structural model. Parenthood</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>It remains an open question whether protective factors such P r e p r i n t n o t p e e r r e v i e w e d as parenting joy and partner responsiveness exert distinct effects on these components. For instance, parenting joy may primarily buffer against the emotional intensity of regret by fostering positive affect and meaning-making in the parental role, whereas partner responsiveness may reduce the cognitive reconsideration of the decision to become a parent by reinforcing the perception of shared commitment and relational security. Clarifying these potentially divergent pathways would not only refine the theoretical model of parenthood regret but also inform more targeted interventions aimed at supporting parents who struggle with doubts and ambivalent feelings. Last but not least, we used DSEM as a powerful framework to disentangle between-and within-person components. Missing prompts were treated as missing at random in our model. More methodological efforts are needed to understand the mechanisms underlying missing values in intensive longitudinal data to ensure the robustness of parameter estimates.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 1 Figure 2</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Means (M), Standard Deviations (SD), and Correlations of Variables of Interest After Latent Decomposition Using Mplus (TYPE = Note. Needs = the presence of special needs in children. ESM = measured during the experience sampling period. Latent decomposition was performed only for the experience sampling measures.</figDesc><table><row><cell>TWOLEVEL)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Mean and SD</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Correlations</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Between</cell><cell>Within</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Between</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Within</cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>M (SD)</cell><cell>M (SD)</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>1 Mother</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2 Needs</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.04.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3 Income</cell><cell>7.05 (2.59)</cell><cell></cell><cell>-.01</cell><cell>-.12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4 Regret baseline</cell><cell>1.54 (1.06)</cell><cell></cell><cell>.03</cell><cell>.14*</cell><cell>-.05</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>5 Regret follow-up</cell><cell>1.50 (.97)</cell><cell></cell><cell>.03</cell><cell>.10</cell><cell>-.04</cell><cell>.87***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6 Joy ESM</cell><cell>5.44 (2.33)</cell><cell>0 (.81)</cell><cell>-.05</cell><cell>-.13</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell cols="2">-.48*** -.54***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">7 Responsiveness ESM 5.20 (2.28)</cell><cell>0 (.80)</cell><cell>-.17**</cell><cell>-.04</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell cols="3">-.25*** -.32*** .46***</cell><cell>.26***</cell></row></table><note><p>* p &lt; .05. ** p &lt; .01. *** p &lt; .001.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Teuber, Z., Botes, E., Reiter, <rs type="person">J., Greiff</rs>, <rs type="person">S., Aunola</rs>, <rs type="person">K.</rs>, <rs type="person">&amp; McNeish</rs>, D. (2025). Unwrapping the <rs type="institution">Dynamics of Parental Burnout</rs> and <rs type="projectName">Genuine Expression During the Festive Season: A Dynamic Structural Equation Modeling Approach</rs>. Research Square. https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-7004466/v1</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_uR3gTXQ">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Genuine Expression During the Festive Season: A Dynamic Structural Equation Modeling Approach</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr">Piotrowski, K., Mikolajczak, M., &amp; Roskam, I. (2023)</ref><p>. I should not have had a child: Development and validation of the Parenthood Regret Scale. Journal of Family <ref type="bibr">Psychology,</ref><ref type="bibr">37(8)</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Responsiveness in romantic partners&apos; interactions. Current Opinion in Psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Arican-Dinc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gable</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.copsyc.2023.101652</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copsyc.2023.101652" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101652</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Latent variable centering of predictors and mediators in multilevel and time-series models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asparouhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian estimation of single and multilevel models with latent variable interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asparouhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="328" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive crossover: Parent perceived partner responsiveness and health of youth with asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bierstetel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Farrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Tobin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Imami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zilioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Slatcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/pere.12467</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/pere.12467" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personal Relationships</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="566" to="582" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Loneliness Among Parents in Sweden Who Regret Having Children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bodin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fängström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10826-024-02988-8</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10826-024-02988-8" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Child and Family Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="244" />
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">General methods for monitoring convergence of iterative simulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="434" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied multiple regression/correlation analysis for the behavioral sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Aiken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regretting Motherhood: A Sociopolitical Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Donath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/678145</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1086/678145" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Signs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Enders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Applied missing data analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Guilford</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Missing data: An update on the state of the art</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Enders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/met0000563</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/met0000563" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="322" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A New Look at Social Support: A Theoretical Perspective on Thriving Through Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Feeney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1088868314544222</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1088868314544222" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The broaden-and-build theory of positive emotions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fredrickson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2004.1512</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2004.1512" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">359</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1367" to="1378" />
			<date type="published" when="1449">2004. 1449</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Daily fluctuation of emotions and memories thereof: Design and methods of an experience sampling study of major depression, social phobia, and controls</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Gloster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Miché</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wersebe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mikoteit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hoyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Imboden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hatzinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lieb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/mpr.1578</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/mpr.1578" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Methods in Psychiatric Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1578</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do girls really experience more anxiety in mathematics?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Goetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bieg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Lüdtke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pekrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0956797613486989</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797613486989" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2079" to="2087" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why researchers should think &quot;within-person&quot;: A paradigmatic rationale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of research methods for studying daily life</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The Guilford Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="61" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">At the Frontiers of Modeling Intensive Longitudinal Data: Dynamic Structural Equation Models for the Affective Measurements from the COGITO Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asparouhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schmiedek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00273171.2018.1446819</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00273171.2018.1446819" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multivariate Behavioral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="820" to="841" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic structural equation modeling as a combination of time series modeling, multilevel modeling, and structural equation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asparouhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The handbook of structural equation modeling</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hoyle</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Guilford</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="576" to="597" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling within-level latent interaction effects in multilevel vector-autoregressive models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holtmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koslowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavior Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">277</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is psychological research producing the kind of knowledge clinicians find useful?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hopwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Aafjes-Van Doorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Békés</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ringwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G C</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/amp0001538</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/amp0001538" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Psychologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to foster perceived partner responsiveness: High-quality listening is key</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Itzchakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Reis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/spc3.12648</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/spc3.12648" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social and Personality Psychology Compass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12648</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How many plausible values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jewsbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mccaffrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jedm.70000</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/jedm.70000" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Educational Measurement</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parenting and Emotions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leerkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Augustine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Parenting</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The multilevel latent covariate model: A new, more reliable approach to group-level effects in contextual studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Lüdtke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Robitzsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Trautwein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Asparouhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0012869</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0012869" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating and interpreting latent variable interactions: A tutorial for applying the latent moderated structural equations method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Maslowsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hemken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Behavioral Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two-level dynamic structural equation models with small samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mcneish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structural Equation Modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="948" to="966" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Primer on Intensive Longitudinal Psychometrics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mcneish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://osf.io/https://osf.io/dmpwc" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A primer on two-level dynamic structural equation models for intensive longitudinal data in Mplus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mcneish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/met0000250</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/met0000250" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="635" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Responsiveness, Social Connection, Hope, and Life Satisfaction in Everyday Social Interaction: An Experience Sampling Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Merolla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Neubauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Otmar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10902-024-00710-5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10902-024-00710-5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Happiness Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Christmas: An anthropological lens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.14318/hau7.3.027</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.14318/hau7.3.027" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">HAU: Journal of Ethnographic Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomization-based inference about latent variables from complex samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mislevy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Many Shopping Days Until Christmas? A Preliminary Investigation of Time Pressures, Deadlines, and Planning Levels on Holiday Gift Purchases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Miyazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in Consumer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What Do Parents Regret About Having Children? Communicating Regrets Online</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Abetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0192513X18811388</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0192513X18811388" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Family Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="412" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Parents Fare: Mothers&apos; and Fathers&apos; Subjective Well-Being in Time with Children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Musick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Meier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Flood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0003122416663917</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0003122416663917" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1095" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mplus 8.11. Muthén &amp; Muthén</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jrp.2016.06.020</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jrp.2016.06.020" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biases in dynamic models with fixed effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nickell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica : Journal of the Econometric Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1417" to="1426" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An Ode to Joy: Judaism and Happiness in the Thought of Rabbi Lord Jonathan Sacks and Beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Novick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-031-28229-4_44</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-28229-4_44" />
		<editor>E. Brown &amp; S. Weiss</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="365" />
			<pubPlace>Nature Switzerland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Joy and Parenting: Partners or Paradox?</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Average household income</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/personalandhouseholdfinances/incomeandwealth/bulletins/householddisposableincomeandinequality/financialyearending2023" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Office for National Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>UK -Office for National Statistics</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Merry Christmas and Happy New Year! The impact of Christmas rituals on subjective well-being and family&apos;s emotional climate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Páez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Á</forename><surname>Bilbao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bobowik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Campos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Basabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1174/021347411797361347</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1174/021347411797361347" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Psychology: Revista de Psicología Social</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How many parents regret having children and how it is linked to their personality and health: Two studies with national samples in Poland</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Piotrowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0254163</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781003258582-17" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">d sociability: Understanding human attachment</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="257" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unveiling the Uniqueness of Parental Burnout and Parenthood Regret: Impact on Parents and Children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Roskam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mikolajczak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Piotrowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/21677026251347526</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/21677026251347526" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025. 21677026251347526</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multiple imputation for nonresponse in surveys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parental Self-Efficacy and Intra-and Extra-Familial Relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-E</forename><surname>Salo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Junttila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vauras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10826-022-02380-4</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10826-022-02380-4" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Child and Family Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2714" to="2729" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who is afraid of Christmas? The effect of Christmas and Easter holidays on psychiatric hospitalizations and emergencies-Systematic review and single center experience from 2012 to 2021</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Liwinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Imfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brühl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpsyt.2022.1049935</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2022.1049935" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement error and person-specific reliability in multilevel autoregressive modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Schuurman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/met0000188</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/met0000188" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">All I want for Christmas is recovery -changes in employee affective well-being before and after vacation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Syrek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Weigelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kühnel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02678373.2018.1427816</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02678373.2018.1427816" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Work &amp; Stress</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting adaptation to parenthood: The role of responsiveness, gratitude, and trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ter Kuile</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kluwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Finkenauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Van Der Lippe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/pere.12202</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/pere.12202" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personal Relationships</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="663" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yougov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://yougov.de/politics/articles/16036-regretting-parenthood-wenn-eltern-ihre-kinder-lieb" />
		<title level="m">Regretting Parenthood&quot;: Wenn Eltern ihre Kinder lieben-Das Kinderkriegen aber bereuen</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yougov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://yougov.co.uk/society/articles/36590-one-twelve-parents-say-they-regret-having-children" />
		<title level="m">One in twelve parents say they regret having children</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of crying over spilled milk: A note on the rationality and functionality of regret</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zeelenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/095150899105800</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/095150899105800" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experience-sampling research methods and their potential for education research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zirkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3102/0013189X14566879</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3102/0013189X14566879" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Educational Researcher</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moderated mediation in multilevel structural equation models: Decomposing effects of race on math achievement within versus between high schools in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zyphur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Preacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bird</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0000115-021</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0000115-021" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The handbook of multilevel theory, measurement, and analysis</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Humphrey</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lebreton</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Psychological Association</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="494" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
