<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8C7E85D0B8366FB3A7CEA54274E75A9B</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T02:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>§ 549 adult members of the public recruited through volunteer sampling (75.8% female); § Adequate statistical power; age range between 18 and 76 yearsold (M = 39.57, SD = 12.95).</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Key Findings</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Influence of Perpetrator Personality Pathology</head><p>§ A one-way MANOVA found a small, significant difference in perceptions of the hypothetical stalking incident based on perpetrator personality pathology (p &lt; .001, η 2 p = .04).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Perceived Stalking Severity</head><p>§ Assessed via four questions measuring to what extent the incident i) constituted stalking, ii) required Police intervention, iii) caused the victim alarm, and iv) caused the victim fear of violence. § One-way ANOVAs &amp; post-hoc comparisons found consistent, small-moderate significant differences in perceptions: § Perpetrator with dissocial personality difficulties consistently perceived to be the most serious; detachment the least serious.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Perpetrator Predictability &amp; Mental Health Difficulties</head><p>§ No significant difference in perceived predictability of the perpetrator's behaviour (p = .307, η 2 p = .01). § The perpetrator exhibiting negative affectivity was perceived to experience the greatest mental health and personality difficulties; the control condition the least (p &lt; .001, η 2 p = .04; p &lt; .001, η 2 p = .03).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>§ Novel finding: perpetrator personality pathology does differentially bias perceptions of stalking. Crucially, it influenced how harmful stalking was perceived to be, and recommendations for support. § Detachment, a key trait in psychopathy, perceived least seriously.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implications &amp; Recommendations</head><p>§ Professionals should consider the potential for personality-related misperceptions of stalking to bias the recorded history of those in contact with the CJS, and the accurate assessment of stalking risk. § Stalking victims more readily seek support from family and friends 18 ; these findings inform continued attempts to improve the recognition of and support for victims of stalking (e.g., via public education). § The victims in this study were strangers to participants; future research may benefit from replicating findings in situations with additional contextual information (e.g., with close family/friends). § Personality is socially-and culturally-specific; future research should replicate findings cross-culturally, with different victim-perpetrator sex compositions (e.g., male victims), and with a representative sample.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Implications &amp; Recommendations</head><p>The influence of perpetrator personality pathology on perceptions of relational stalking</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Alfred Vaughan, Dr Simon Duff, &amp; Dr Elizabeth Paddock</head><p>Centre for Forensic and Family Psychology, University of Nottingham</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stalking Victimisation</head><p>§ National survey estimates indicate that 3% of men and 5% of women experience stalking annually in England and Wales 1 ; § True incident rates are likely higher than estimates 2 , in-part consequent to underreporting 3 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(Mis)perceptions of Stalking</head><p>§ Under UK law, the identification of stalking is a legally subjective process 4 often determined by the perceptions of those involved 5 ; § Misperceptions of stalking are prevalent 6 and prevent victims and support structures from intervening in stalking victimisation 7, 8 ; § Ex-partner (relational) stalkers are perceived to present the least threat 9 , despite being the most prevalent 10 and violent 11 stalkers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stalking &amp; Personality Pathology</head><p>§ Most stalking perpetrators meet diagnostic criteria for 'personality disorder' <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr">[14]</ref> . This group are also twice as likely to victimise expartners than strangers 15 , and thus present the greatest risk 16 . § Despite this, experimental research has not yet examined the influence of a perpetrator's personality on perceptions of stalking.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction 2. Methodology</head><p>Aim &amp; Rationale § Aim: to examine the influence of perpetrator personality pathology on perceptions of relational stalking. § Rationale: to increase understanding of (mis)perceptions of relational stalking and inform attempts to improve the recognition of, and provision of support for, stalking victimisation. § Non-directional hypothesis: expected perpetrator personality pathology to influence perceptions of relational stalking.</p><p>References: Please scan the QR code for a reference list.</p><p>Notes: The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. We would like to thank Kate Vaughan and Emma Blomfield for their support with participant recruitment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design, Materials, &amp; Measures</head><p>§ Online vignette study using a betweenparticipants experimental design. § Participants randomly allocated to read one of six accounts of an identical relational stalking incident (male perpetrator, female victim); § Five conditions described perpetrator personality difficulties concordant with the ICD-11 'PD' trait domain qualifiers; § Control did not describe their personality. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>§</head><label></label><figDesc>Between 85 &amp; 102 participants in each condition. § Perceptions measured through seven 11-point Likert-scale questions, which assessed: § Perceived incident severity 17 ; § Predictableness of perpetrator behaviour;§ Presence of perpetrator mental health and personality difficulties. 001, η 2 p = .07 p &lt; .001, η 2 p = .06 p &lt; .001, η 2 p = .05 p &lt; .001, η 2 p = .07</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
