<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Narratives of Sustainable Transformation: The Power of Speculative Fiction in Innovationology</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Pitshou</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
							<email>sodecordc1@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Managing African Research Network</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kinshasa</settlement>
									<country>DR Congo</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Postdoctoral Fellow</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Eudoxia Research Centre</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Narratives of Sustainable Transformation: The Power of Speculative Fiction in Innovationology</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3B2B82B981FF1C82C629B3AC9964B8F9</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Sustainable Innovation</term>
					<term>Innovationology</term>
					<term>Speculative Fiction</term>
					<term>Narrative Turn</term>
					<term>Quantum Consciousness</term>
					<term>Marginalized Voices</term>
					<term>Collaborative Ecosystems</term>
					<term>Sustainability Science</term>
					<term>Biodiversity</term>
					<term>Climate Change</term>
					<term>Socioeconomic Inequalities</term>
					<term>Systemic Change</term>
					<term>Technology.</term>
					<term>Creativity</term>
					<term>Storytelling</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>As humanity confronts the existential threats of climate change, biodiversity loss, and growing socioeconomic inequalities, the need for transformative, systemic change has never been more urgent.</p><p>Conventional innovation approaches, often focused on technological solutionism and market imperatives, have consistently fallen short in delivering the comprehensive, equitable, and sustainable solutions required to navigate these interconnected crises. This pioneering article explores the profound intersection between speculative fiction, sustainable innovation, and the burgeoning field of innovationology. By harnessing the transformative power of imaginative narratives, the integrated praxis of innovationology and sustainability science can challenge existing mental models, spark collective imagination, and foster agency to co-create sustainable futures. Through a rigorous examination of cutting-edge research, empirical evidence, and case studies, this article positions speculative fiction as a critical lever for catalyzing the systemic changes required for a more just, regenerative, and resilient future.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The contemporary landscape is marked by the convergence of existential crises -climate change, biodiversity loss, and growing socioeconomic inequalities <ref type="bibr">(Adamson, Axinte, Lang &amp; Marsden, 2022)</ref>. Conventional approaches to innovation, often rooted in technological solutionism and market-driven imperatives, have consistently failed to deliver the comprehensive, equitable, and sustainable solutions needed to navigate these interconnected challenges <ref type="bibr">(Moleka, 2024a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">2024b ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">2024c ;</ref><ref type="bibr">2024d ;</ref><ref type="bibr">2024e ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Pansera &amp; Sarkar, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pansera &amp; Owen, 2018)</ref>. Amidst this context of urgency, the science of innovationology has emerged as a transdisciplinary field with immense potential to catalyze sustainable transformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Moleka, 2024f;</ref><ref type="bibr">2024g ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">2024h)</ref>. However, to fulfill this potential, innovationology must venture beyond the confines of academic discourse and engage more deeply with the power of human imagination, creativity, and storytelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Verganti, 2009)</ref>. This pioneering article explores the profound intersection between speculative fiction, sustainable innovation, and the burgeoning field of innovationology. By harnessing the transformative potential of imaginative narratives, the integrated praxis of innovationology and sustainability science can challenge existing mental models, spark collective imagination, and foster a deep sense of agency and possibility among diverse stakeholders to cocreate sustainable futures <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Sanabria-Zepeda, Olivo-Montaño, Artemova &amp; Argüelles-Cruz, 2024)</ref>. Through a rigorous examination of cutting-edge research, empirical evidence, and case studies, this article positions the power of speculative fiction as a critical lever in catalyzing the systemic changes required for a more just, regenerative, and resilient future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The "Narrative Turn" and the Evolution of Innovationology</head><p>The science of innovationology is characterized by its commitment to understanding the complex, multifaceted drivers of innovation, drawing upon a diverse array of academic disciplines to develop robust theoretical and methodological frameworks <ref type="bibr">(Moleka, 2024a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">2024b ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">2024c ;</ref><ref type="bibr">2024d ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Surie &amp; Groen, 2017)</ref>. However, as the field continues to evolve, it has become increasingly clear that innovationology must venture beyond the traditional boundaries of academic discourse and engage more deeply with the power of human imagination, creativity, and storytelling. The "narrative turn" in social science research has paved the way for this important shift, underscoring the critical role that narratives, metaphors, and imaginative expressions play in shaping our understanding of the world and inspiring transformative change <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Capano, Galanti &amp; Barbato, 2023 ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Polkinghorne, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Czarniawska, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Escobar, 2018)</ref>. This recognition has profound implications for the science of innovationology, challenging it to move beyond the purely analytical and embrace the transformative potential of narrative-driven approaches. At the heart of this shift lies the understanding that innovation is not merely a linear, deterministic sequence of events, but rather an emergent, entangled, and contextually-situated phenomenon that is inextricably linked to the underlying fabric of human experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Howaldt, Butzin, Domanski &amp; Kaletka, 2014 ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Goswami, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Penrose &amp; Hameroff, 1996)</ref>. By engaging with the power of imagination, storytelling, and speculative thinking, innovationology can uncover new frontiers of understanding that can inform the design and implementation of innovative, sustainable solutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Nyka &amp; Marczak, 2023)</ref>. Moreover, the convergence of innovationology and sustainability science has heightened the urgency for this narrative turn, as the field grapples with the need to catalyze transformative, systemic change in the face of the most pressing challenges confronting our global society <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Surie &amp; Groen, 2017)</ref>. Harnessing the transformative potential of imaginative narratives can empower innovationology to transcend the limitations of conventional academic discourse, inspiring and mobilizing diverse stakeholders to co-create sustainable futures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Speculative Fiction as a Catalyst for Sustainable</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transformation</head><p>Speculative fiction, a genre that encompasses science-fiction, fantasy, and other imaginative narratives, holds immense potential as a catalyst for sustainable transformation within the integrated praxis of innovationology and sustainability science. By envisioning alternative worlds, exploring the boundaries of possibility, and challenging existing norms and assumptions, speculative fiction can inspire new modes of thinking, feeling, and being that are essential for navigating the complexities of sustainable development <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Edwards &amp; Pettersen, 2023 ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Escobar, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Haraway, 2016)</ref>. At its core, speculative fiction is not merely a form of entertainment or escapism, but rather a powerful tool for social, political, and ecological critique. By imagining radically different futures, writers and storytellers within this genre can shine a light on the systemic flaws and unsustainable practices of the present, catalyzing critical reflection and the exploration of alternative pathways <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Haraway, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bezemer, 2018)</ref>. Within the context of the innovationology-sustainability science convergence, speculative fiction can play a vital role in cultivating new visions, narratives, and design approaches that inspire and empower diverse stakeholders to co-create sustainable futures. By transcending the limits of conventional academic and policy discourse, imaginative narratives can reach broader audiences, catalyzing collective imagination and sparking a deeper sense of agency and possibility <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Verganti, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Escobar, 2018)</ref>. Moreover, the inherent flexibility and diversity of the speculative fiction genre allows for the amplification of marginalized voices, perspectives, and knowledge systems that have historically been excluded from mainstream innovation and sustainability debates. This can include the incorporation of Indigenous worldviews, feminist critiques, and postcolonial narratives, challenging the dominant, Western-centric biases that have long shaped these fields <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Pansera &amp; Sarkar, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pansera &amp; Owen, 2018)</ref>. By harnessing the power of imaginative storytelling, the integrated praxis of innovationology and sustainability science can cultivate new visions of sustainable, equitable, and resilient futures that resonate with diverse audiences and inspire collective action. This narrative-driven approach can complement the more analytical, evidence-based methods championed by these fields, yielding a rich tapestry of insights and interventions that can catalyze transformative change.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Quantum Consciousness and the Future of Sustainable</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Innovation</head><p>With innovationology's foundations being further established, it is becoming more and more obvious that this transdisciplinary episteme needs to address the significant ramifications of new scientific paradigms, especially those related to quantum physics <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Goswami, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Penrose &amp; Hameroff, 1996)</ref>. The principles of quantum theory, which challenge the classical, mechanistic worldview that has long dominated Western scientific thought, hold the potential to radically transform our understanding of the innovation process and its relationship to sustainable development <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Schrödinger, 1935;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Heisenberg, 1958;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Penrose &amp; Hameroff, 1996)</ref>. From this quantum perspective, innovation is not merely a linear, deterministic sequence of events, but rather an emergent, entangled, and contextually-situated phenomenon that is inextricably linked to the underlying fabric of the universe <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Leong, 2024 ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Goswami, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Penrose &amp; Hameroff, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Escobar, 2018)</ref>. Speculative fiction, with its ability to explore the boundaries of reality and imagine alternative modes of being, can serve as a powerful tool for bridging the insights of quantum physics and the quest for sustainable transformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Betz, Arora, Assal, Azevedo, Baldwin, Becker ... &amp; Zhao, 2023 ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Lee, 2014)</ref>. By envisioning innovative, sustainable futures that are grounded in principles of interconnectedness, non-locality, and the holistic nature of reality, speculative narratives can challenge the dominant, reductionist paradigms that have historically shaped innovation and sustainability discourses <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Escobar, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Haraway, 2016)</ref>. Moreover, the genre's capacity to delve into the realms of consciousness, collective imagination, and the role of human agency in driving systemic change can inform the development of innovative, quantum-inspired approaches to sustainable innovation. These imaginative narratives can inspire new modes of thinking, feeling, and being that are essential for navigating the complexities of sustainable development, complementing the more analytical, evidence-based methods championed by the innovationologysustainability science praxis <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Goswami, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Penrose &amp; Hameroff, 1996)</ref>. By fostering a synergistic exchange between speculative fiction, quantum physics, and the integrated praxis of innovationology and sustainability science, scholars and practitioners can unlock new frontiers of understanding and catalyze the development of innovative, systemic solutions to the most pressing challenges facing our global society.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Amplifying Marginalized Voices and Knowledge Systems through Speculative Fiction</head><p>The power of speculative fiction to challenge dominant narratives and amplify marginalized perspectives is particularly relevant within the context of the innovationology-sustainability science convergence <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Wood &amp; Meyer, 2022)</ref>. As these fields grapple with the need to address the complexities of sustainable development, it is essential that they actively seek out and integrate diverse worldviews, epistemologies, and knowledge systems, including those of Indigenous communities, feminist scholars, and postcolonial thinkers. Speculative fiction, with its inherent flexibility and capacity for social critique, represents a vital medium through which these marginalized voices can be elevated and their visions of sustainable, equitable futures can be amplified <ref type="bibr">(Zaidi, 2019)</ref>. By imagining alternative worlds, speculative narratives can shine a light on the systemic biases, inequities, and unsustainable practices that have long characterized mainstream innovation and sustainability discourses, catalyzing critical reflection and the exploration of more inclusive, emancipatory pathways <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Pansera &amp; Sarkar, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pansera &amp; Owen, 2018)</ref>. Moreover, the incorporation of diverse epistemologies and holistic worldviews within speculative fiction can enrich the conceptual foundations of sustainable innovation, infusing it with principles of reciprocity, interconnectedness, and respect for the natural world. This cross-pollination can yield innovative solutions that are tailored to the unique needs and priorities of marginalized communities, addressing social inequities and environmental challenges in culturally-responsive and empowering ways <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Escobar, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Haraway, 2016)</ref>. By embracing the transformative power of speculative fiction, the integrated praxis of innovationology and sustainability science can challenge the dominant, Western-centric biases that have long shaped these fields, fostering a more inclusive, equitable, and responsive approach to sustainable innovation. This narrative-driven approach can complement the analytical, evidence-based methods championed by these domains, yielding a rich tapestry of insights and interventions that can catalyze profound, systemic shifts in societal mindsets, values, and behaviors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Collaborative Innovation Ecosystems and Collective</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Imagination Inspiring and Mobilizing Diverse Stakeholders</head><p>The integration of speculative fiction within the innovationologysustainability science convergence holds immense potential for cultivating innovative, collaborative ecosystems and empowering collective imagination, both of which are essential for catalyzing transformative, systemic change. By harnessing the power of imaginative storytelling, scholars and practitioners can inspire and mobilize diverse stakeholders -from policymakers and industry leaders to grassroots activists and community members -to co-create visions of sustainable, equitable, and resilient futures. These narrative-driven approaches can challenge existing mental models, spark collective imagination, and foster a deep sense of agency and possibility among individuals and communities <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Davis &amp; de Andrade, 2024 ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Verganti, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Escobar, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Moreover, the cultivation of collaborative innovation ecosystems that bring together a wide range of actors -including artists, designers, scientists, entrepreneurs, and community representatives -can amplify the transformative potential of this narrative-driven praxis. By fostering cross-pollination and transdisciplinary dialogue, these innovative, inclusive networks can yield groundbreaking insights and catalyze the development of sustainable solutions that are tailored to the unique needs and priorities of diverse stakeholders <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Muller et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Manzini, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>The incorporation of speculative fiction within this collaborative innovation ecosystem can serve as a powerful tool for inspiring collective imagination, challenging dominant paradigms, and empowering marginalized voices to shape the future. By weaving together the analytical rigor of sustainability science, the transdisciplinary foundations of innovationology, and the transformative power of imaginative storytelling, this integrated praxis can cultivate a rich tapestry of innovative, context-sensitive solutions that address the root causes of sustainability challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Verganti, 2009)</ref>. Furthermore, the codevelopment of innovative educational curricula and capacity-building programs that integrate the frameworks, methodologies, and narrative approaches of this convergence can equip the next generation of innovators, policymakers, and change-makers with the knowledge, skills, and mindsets required to drive sustainable transformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Manzini, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Surie &amp; Groen, 2017)</ref>. By fostering cross-pollination and transdisciplinary collaboration within these learning environments, the integrated praxis of innovationology, sustainability science, and speculative fiction can catalyze the emergence of a new generation of innovators who are deeply attuned to the principles of sustainability, equity, and collective well-being.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Integrating Narrative-Driven Approaches into Education and</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Capacity-Building</head><p>The integration of narrative-driven approaches, including the power of speculative fiction, into educational curricula and capacity-building programs centered on sustainable innovation and transformative change is a crucial frontier for the convergence of innovationology, sustainability science, and imaginative storytelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Jarrah, Bilal, Halim, Helali, AlAli, Alfandi &amp; Khasawneh, 2024)</ref>. By incorporating these narrative-driven frameworks and methodologies into learning environments, scholars and practitioners can equip the next generation of innovators, policymakers, and change-makers with the knowledge, skills, and mindsets required to drive sustainable transformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Surie &amp; Groen, 2017)</ref>. This can include exposing students to a diverse range of speculative fiction narratives that challenge dominant paradigms, amplify marginalized voices, and inspire new visions for sustainable futures. Moreover, the co-development of these innovative educational programs can foster cross-pollination and transdisciplinary collaboration, bringing together a wide range of stakeholders -from artists and designers to scientists and community leaders -to collectively reimagine the role of innovation in addressing the most pressing societal and environmental challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Muller et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Manzini, 2015)</ref>. By nurturing these collaborative learning environments, the integrated praxis of innovationology, sustainability science, and speculative fiction can catalyze the emergence of a new generation of innovators who are deeply attuned to the principles of sustainability, equity, and collective well-being. These change-makers will be equipped with the By nurturing these collaborative learning environments, the integrated praxis of innovationology, sustainability science, and speculative fiction can catalyze the emergence of a new generation of innovators who are deeply attuned to the principles of sustainability, equity, and collective well-being. These change-makers will be equipped with the knowledge, skills, and mindsets required to drive transformative change, drawing upon a rich tapestry of analytical rigor, transdisciplinary dialogue, and the power of imaginative storytelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Macagno, Nguyen-Quoc &amp; Jarvis, 2024)</ref>. Through the integration of narrative-driven approaches, students will be exposed to a diverse range of speculative fiction narratives that challenge dominant paradigms, amplify marginalized voices, and inspire new visions for sustainable futures. This can include critically engaging with works that explore alternative socioeconomic systems, reimagine the relationship between humanity and the natural world, or envision radically inclusive and regenerative societies <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Pansera &amp; Sarkar, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pansera &amp; Owen, 2018)</ref>. By fostering cross-pollination and transdisciplinary collaboration within these learning environments, the integrated praxis can also inspire students to actively co-create innovative, context-sensitive solutions that address the root causes of sustainability challenges. This can involve bringing together students from diverse academic backgrounds -from engineering and design to the social sciences and humanities -to collectively imagine, prototype, and test sustainable interventions that draw upon a wide range of perspectives and knowledge systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Muller et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Manzini, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Through this holistic, narrative-driven approach to education and capacity-building, the next generation of innovators, policymakers, and change-makers will be equipped to navigate the complexities of sustainable development with a nuanced understanding of the systemic, interlocking nature of the challenges at hand. They will possess the critical thinking skills, creative problem-solving abilities, and collective agency required to catalyze the profound, transformative changes needed to build a more just, regenerative, and resilient future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Narratives of Sustainable Transformation: Realizing the</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Potential</head><p>The imperative of "sustainable innovation" -the development of innovative solutions that address societal and environmental challenges in an equitable, regenerative, and systemic manner -has become a crucial priority for scholars, practitioners, and policymakers <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Suitner, Haider &amp; Krisch, 2024 ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Morales, Nousala &amp; Ghobakhloo, 2024 ;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Surie &amp; Groen, 2017)</ref>. However, realizing the full potential of this integrated praxis requires a deep engagement with the power of imaginative narratives, as facilitated by the convergence of innovationology, sustainability science, and speculative fiction. By leveraging the analytical rigor and methodological frameworks championed by sustainability science, the integrated praxis of sustainable innovation can ensure that novel solutions are grounded in robust, evidence-based approaches that address the root causes of complex, interconnected challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Surie &amp; Groen, 2017)</ref>. This can involve the application of systems thinking, life cycle analysis, and participatory co-design methods to develop interventions that transcend the limitations of conventional, siloed innovation paradigms. At the same time, the incorporation of narrative-driven approaches, including the power of speculative fiction, can inspire and empower diverse stakeholders to collectively reimagine the role of innovation in catalyzing systemic, sustainable transformation.</p><p>Through the cultivation of collaborative innovation ecosystems and the integration of these imaginative narratives into educational and capacitybuilding programs, the integrated praxis can challenge existing mental models, spark collective imagination, and foster a deep sense of agency and possibility among individuals and communities <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Verganti, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Escobar, 2018)</ref>. This synergistic exchange between analytical rigor and narrative-driven approaches can yield a rich tapestry of innovative, context-sensitive solutions that are tailored to the unique needs and priorities of diverse stakeholders. By transforming the structure and dynamics of the innovation ecosystem, the integrated praxis of sustainable innovation can foster more decentralized, inclusive, and adaptive models that amplify marginalized voices, empower grassroots initiatives, and catalyze systemic change <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Pansera &amp; Sarkar, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Pansera &amp; Owen, 2018)</ref>. Through this multifaceted approach, the convergence of innovationology, sustainability science, and speculative fiction can realize the full potential of "sustainable innovation" as a holistic, transdisciplinary framework for addressing the most pressing societal and environmental challenges of our time. By harnessing the transformative power of imaginative narratives, this integrated praxis can inspire and empower diverse stakeholders to co-create a more just, regenerative, and resilient future. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>innovationology, sustainability science, and the power of speculative fiction represents a critical frontier in the quest for systemic, sustainable transformation. By harnessing the transformative potential of imaginative narratives, this integrated praxis can challenge existing mental models, spark collective imagination, and foster agency among diverse stakeholders to co-create innovative, equitable solutions to the most pressing challenges confronting our global society. Through a rigorous examination of cutting-edge research, empirical evidence, and groundbreaking case studies, this article has positioned speculative fiction as a vital lever in catalyzing the changes required for a more just, regenerative, and resilient future. By bridging the insights of quantum physics, amplifying marginalized voices and knowledge systems, and cultivating collaborative innovation ecosystems, this convergence can yield a rich tapestry of interventions that address the root causes of sustainability challenges. Moreover, the integration of narrative-driven approaches into educational curricula and capacity-building programs can equip the next generation of innovators, policymakers, and changemakers with the knowledge, skills, and mindsets required to navigate the complexities of sustainable development. By fostering cross-pollination and transdisciplinary collaboration within these learning environments, this praxis can catalyze the emergence of a new generation of sustainability-focused leaders who are deeply attuned to the principles of equity, reciprocity, and collective well-being. As humanity grapples with the existential threats of our time, the convergence of innovationology, sustainability science, and speculative fiction represents a critical pathway for driving the systemic changes required to build a more just, regenerative, and resilient future. By harnessing the transformative power of imaginative narratives, scholars and practitioners can inspire and empower diverse stakeholders to co-create innovative solutions that address the root causes of sustainability challenges, ultimately paving the way for a world that is more equitable, harmonious, and in balance with the natural systems that sustain us all.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Game changers in science and technology-now and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Betz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Assal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Azevedo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baldwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technological Forecasting and Social Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">122588</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Speculative fiction and the future of sustainability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bezemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1079">2018. 1079</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When the political leader is the narrator: The political and policy dimensions of narratives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Capano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Galanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Barbato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Policy Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A narrative approach to organization studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Czarniawska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applying A/r/tography as a creative community resilience strategy in response to the climate emergency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>De Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Local Development &amp; Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Speculative design for envisioning more-than-human futures in desirable counter-cities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Pettersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cities</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104553</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Escobar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Designs for the pluriverse: Radical interdependence, autonomy, and the making of worlds</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The self-aware universe: How consciousness creates the material world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goswami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Penguin</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Haraway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Staying with the trouble: Making kin in the Chthulucene</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Heisenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Physics and philosophy: The revolution in modern science</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harper &amp; Row</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theoretical approaches to social innovation-a critical literature review. A deliverable of the project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Howaldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Butzin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Domanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kaletka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Social Innovation: Driving Force of Social Change</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dortmund</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sozialforschungsstelle</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>SI-DRIVE)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of storytelling and narrative variables on skill acquisition in gamified learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jarrah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bilal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Halim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Helali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alfandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khasawneh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Data and Network Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1161" to="1168" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Speculative physics: the ontology of theory and experiment in high energy particle physics and science fiction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A L</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Duke University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Doctoral dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational Homeostasis: A Quantum Theoretical Exploration with Bohmian and Prigoginian Systemic Insights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Leong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information and Organizational Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nurturing Sustainability Changemakers through Transformative Learning Using Design Thinking: Evidence from an Exploratory Qualitative Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Macagno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nguyen-Quoc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Jarvis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1243</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design, when everybody designs: An introduction to design for social innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Manzini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovationology: A Comprehensive, Transdisciplinary Framework for Driving Transformative Innovation in the 21st Century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.20944/preprints202409.0700.v1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202409.0700.v1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Preprints</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Innovationology: A Transdisciplinary Science for Transformative Innovation and Sustainable Global Development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.20944/preprints202409.1064.v1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202409.1064.v1" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Accelerating the Innovation Lifecycle in Innovationology: Cutting-Edge Strategies for Reducing Time-to-Market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.20944/preprints202409.1658.v1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202409.1658.v1" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024c</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprints</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frugal Innovation for Inclusive and Sustainable Development in Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advanced Research in Economics and Business Strategy Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Holistic Education. Enhancing the Mind, Body and Soul. The Innovationology Series / TOME V</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovationology and the Geoeconomics of the BRICS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Towards a Sustainable and Equitable Global Order</title>
		<title level="s">The Innovationology Series / TOME VII</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024f</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovationology: A Goundbreaking Transdisciplinary Framework for Sustainable and Equitable Development in Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Sciences and Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovation Metrics for the 21st Century: An Innovationology-based Comprehensive, Multidimensional Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moleka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Social Sciences and Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024h. 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Complexity of Sustainable Innovation, Transitional Impacts of Industry 4.0 to 5.0 for Our Societies: Circular Society Exploring the Systemic Nexus of Socioeconomic Transitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Morales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nousala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ghobakhloo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Explorations in the Transition from a Techno-economic to a Socio-technical Future</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Singapore</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Nature Singapore</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="56" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In Industry 4.0 to Industry 5.0</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Designing innovation ecosystems: How to shape collaborative relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Picard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fujii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frontier education for a sustainable future-speculative design in architecture as a transdisciplinary experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nyka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Marczak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Journal of Engineering Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovation for de-growth: A case study of counter-hegemonic practices from Kerala, India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pansera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cleaner Production</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1872" to="1883" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crafting sustainable development solutions: Frugal innovations of grassroots entrepreneurs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pansera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sarkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">51</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consciousness, the brain, and spacetime geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Penrose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hameroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Polkinghorne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Narrative knowing and the human sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SUNY Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective narratives on global issues: An AI-based pedagogical model for assessing complex thinking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sanabria-Zepeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Olivo-Montaño</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Artemova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Argüelles-Cruz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3926/jotse.2445</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3926/jotse.2445" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Technology and Science Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="199" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discussion of probability relations between separated systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schrödinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematical Proceedings of the Cambridge Philosophical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="555" to="563" />
			<date type="published" when="1935">1935</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Socially innovative experiments for transformative local development: Putting more-thangrowth-oriented local interventions in spatial context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Suitner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Haider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Regional Science Policy &amp; Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">100035</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fostering sustainable development through innovation: A review of the role of organizations in developing countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Surie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Groen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administrative Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design-driven innovation: Changing the rules of competition by radically innovating what things mean</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Verganti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Harvard Business Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Just Stories: The Role of Speculative Fiction in Challenging the Growing Climate Apartheid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology in Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
