<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-10">October 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Ewens</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xavier</forename><surname>Giroud</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Luis</forename><surname>Garicano</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Guadalupe</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Prat</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Esteban</forename><surname>Rossi-Hansberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">LSE</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">NBER Organizational Economics Meetings</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">the University of Houston</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Rice University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>SKEMA</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">INSEAD</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">HEC, PolyU</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University of Oxford (Said)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">University of Bristol</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nova</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Georgia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Purdue University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">the University of Warwick</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">University of Porto</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-10">October 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7BFE3A7EDC5EAB967DC75D940799237D</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-19T16:56+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We introduce a novel measure of corporate hierarchies for over 3,100 U.S. public firms. This measure is obtained from online resumes of 7 million employees and a network estimation technique that allows us to identify hierarchical layers. Equipped with this measure, we document several facts about corporate hierarchies. Firms have on average ten hierarchical layers and a pyramidal organizational structure. More hierarchical firms have a more educated workforce, higher internal promotion rates, and longer employee tenure. Their operating performance is higher, but they face higher administrative costs. They are more active acquirers and produce more patents, but not higher-quality patents. They exhibit lower stock return volatility and operating asset volatility. We also examine how companies adjust their hierarchies in response to demand and knowledge shocks. We find that pharmaceutical companies increased their number of layers following the Covid-19 pandemic, while companies flattened their hierarchies following the adoption of artificial intelligence (AI) technologies. These findings are consistent with the theoretical predictions of existing models of corporate hierarchies.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Corporate hierarchies come in many shapes. While some companies adopt vertical, multilayered hierarchies (e.g., IBM, GE), others prefer flatter organizational structures (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Netflix)</ref>. Anecdotal evidence abounds with potential pros and cons of different hierarchical structures. For example, it is often argued that vertical hierarchies benefit from clearly defined roles, responsibilities, and accountability, which might enable them to achieve the organization's strategic goals more effectively. On the other hand, these advantages might come at the cost of reduced flexibility and slower decision-making (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">McKinsey, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>The theoretical literature provides several frameworks that help conceptualize hierarchies.</p><p>The early literature sees hierarchies as a form of governance that allows managers to monitor their subordinates better and hence align their incentives with the firm's objective (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Williamson, 1967;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alchian and Demsetz, 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Calvo and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Wellisz, 1978, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Rosen, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Qian, 1994)</ref>. Other models highlight the role of hierarchies in processing and communicating information within the boundaries of the firm (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Radner, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bolton and Dewatripont, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Stein, 2002)</ref>. In these models, a manager's span of control is limited by how much information she can process, which induces a need for hierarchical layers. Layers are costly, however, since they distort the transmission of information within the firm. In a similar spirit, the literature on "knowledge hierarchies" (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Garicano and Rossi-Hansberg, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Caliendo, Monte, and Rossi-Hansberg, 2015)</ref> argues that hierarchies allow workers and managers to specialize and communicate, allowing managers to solve the more complex problems faced by the production workers. In these models, by adding a hierarchical layer, the company invests in a manager who acts as a "problem solver" for the workers under her supervision. The manager is costly, however, since she does not engage in production and has a fixed training cost. Ultimately, the decision to add a layer is driven by the trade-off between the benefits and costs of adding more problem solvers to the organization.</p><p>While the theoretical literature provides helpful guidance in thinking about corporate hierarchies, there is surprisingly little empirical work that aims to understand the determinants and implications of different organizational structures. The existing evidence comes primarily from middle-sized firms in Europe with relatively straightforward organizational forms (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Caliendo, Monte, and Rossi-Hansberg, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Caliendo, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Gumpert, Steimer, and Antoni, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bias, Lochner, Obernberger, and Sevilir, 2024)</ref>. 1 In contrast, much less is known about 1 Moreover, most of this work characterizes organizational forms based on occupation codes (rather than the hierarchies of more complex organizations such as U.S. public companies. In this regard, the main evidence to date has been gathered by <ref type="bibr">Rajan and Wulf (2006)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Guadalupe and Wulf (2010)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Guadalupe, Li, and Wulf (2014)</ref>, who rely on survey data from the consulting firm Hewitt Associates for a sample of about 300 U.S. firms over the years <ref type="bibr">[1986]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1987]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1988]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1989]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1990]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1991]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1992]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1993]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1994]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1995]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1996]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1997]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1998]</ref><ref type="bibr">[1999]</ref>. These data provide information on the number of managers under the supervision of the CEO and other C-suite executives. While these data allow them to study the top layers of the organizational chart, they only capture a subset of the hierarchy. This scarcity of empirical evidence is due to the lack of comprehensive data on corporate hierarchies. Even the most granular datasets available to date-such as the Longitudinal Employer-Household Dynamics (LEHD) of the U.S. Census Bureau that contains employeremployee matched data for U.S. firms-do not allow researchers to characterize hierarchies.</p><p>In the LEHD, information is available on each employee's salary, along with employee characteristics (such as gender, race, and highest educational degree). Still, no information is collected on the employee's role and rank within the organization. This makes it challenging to construct informative metrics of corporate hierarchies.</p><p>In this paper, we propose a novel measure of corporate hierarchy that can be used to study publicly traded U.S. companies. Equipped with this measure, we then explore the role of hierarchies for corporate decision-making and a wide range of outcomes, guided by the various theories of corporate hierarchies.</p><p>To construct our hierarchy measure, we combine data on worker job histories with a network estimation technique that allows us to infer corporate structures. A large sample of online resumes matched to public firms provides a view of the firm's internal labor market, allowing us to track job transitions and title changes. We use these primary inputs to determine the number of hierarchical layers using the network estimation methodology of <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Huitfeldt, Kostøl, Nimczik, and Weber (2023)</ref>. Intuitively, job transitions within a firm help estimate job ranks. The estimated job ranks come with statistical uncertainty because transitions can be promotions, demotions, and lateral moves. Identifying the most likely set of lateral moves provides information to infer the layers of the corporate hierarchy.</p><p>The variable construction leverages online resume data of over 16 million workers at U.S. public firms from 2016 to 2023. The measure we obtain, which captures the number of hierarchical layers, indicates that the average firm has ten layers, and that hierarchies have become flatter over time.</p><p>job titles or ranks), which need not capture hierarchies per se.</p><p>We start our analysis by validating our hierarchy measure. We validate it in several ways.</p><p>First, we show that the layers group workers into reasonably homogeneous groups based on their title, work experience, and education. Second, while the <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Huitfeldt, Kostøl, Nimczik, and Weber (2023)</ref> methodology does not restrict the layers' shape, we nevertheless find that the average firm's hierarchy is pyramidal (i.e., more workers on the bottom layers). This is reassuring, as most models of firm hierarchy predict this shape. Third, the fraction of workers with "manager" in their title increases significantly as we move up to higher layers. This is again consistent with the models of firm hierarchy in which employees at higher layers are more likely to engage in managerial activities. Fourth, we show that our measure of hierarchical layers performs well when benchmarked against a small set of firms with known hierarchical layers. Overall, these patterns reassure us that our new measure captures the inherent features of corporate hierarchies.</p><p>We then show that firms with more hierarchical layers have a more educated workforce, and that advanced degrees are more prevalent the higher the hierarchical layer. This echoes the models of knowledge hierarchies, in which the layers add more "problem solvers" that require higher training costs. We further show that employees in high-layers firms have longer tenure, with promotions playing a greater role in transitions relative to outside hires, consistent with the notion that hierarchies provide employees with a clearer career trajectory and promotion path.</p><p>Next, we examine the relationship between hierarchies and a variety of outcomes. First we show that high-layers firms are more profitable-as captured by the return on assets <ref type="bibr">(ROA)</ref> and net profit margin (NPM)-but generate lower revenues per employee. They also have higher overhead costs (SG&amp;A) and wages, consistent with the higher costs of maintaining hierarchies. We further show that high-layer firms generate more patents and do more acquisitions. However, there is no significant difference in patent quality (as measured by patent citations) and their propensity to make diversifying acquisitions.</p><p>Second, we show that high-layer firms exhibit lower stock volatility. This lower volatility is paired with lower operating asset volatility rather than lower financial risk (e.g., leverage).</p><p>These differences echo well with the models of knowledge hierarchies, in which high-layer firms have more specialist managers-that is, problem solvers-who reduce the firm's operating volatility through their problem-solving activities.</p><p>In the last part of the paper, we flip the regression specification and examine the determinants of corporate hierarchies. One prediction of the models of knowledge hierarchies is that companies would add layers in response to positive demand shocks (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Caliendo, Monte, and Rossi-Hansberg, 2015)</ref>. The intuition is that additional layers add managers (that is, problem solvers), allowing lower-level employees to narrow the knowledge they must master in production. To test this prediction, we examine the evolution of hierarchies at bio-pharmaceutical companies around the Covid-19 pandemic, which induced a spike in demand for their products. Consistent with theory, we find that bio-pharmaceutical companies significantly increased their number of hierarchical layers following the pandemic.</p><p>Finally, a common prediction of the models of corporate hierarchies is that a decrease in the cost of knowledge acquisition and information processing reduces the need for layers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Radner, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bolton and Dewatripont, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano, 2000)</ref>. Consistent with this prediction, we find that companies decrease their layers after adopting artificial intelligence (AI) technologies. Overall, these results are consistent with the models of corporate hierarchies, and indicate that the cross section of hierarchies observed in the data is a complex outcome of firm-specific shocks.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. Section 2 discusses the theoretical underpinnings and our conceptualization of hierarchical layers. Section 3 reviews existing measures of hierarchy. Section 4 introduces our novel measure. Section 5 describes the data. Section 6 provides a validation of our metric. Section 7 presents the analysis of firm outcomes. Section 8 examines the determinants of corporate hierarchies. Finally, Section 9 offers conclusion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Corporate hierarchy: theory</head><p>This section summarizes the theoretical literature on corporate hierarchy that guides our variable construction, variable validations, and empirical tests. For comprehensive surveys of corporate hierarchy theory, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Garicano and Zandt (2012)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Malenko (2024)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Models of corporate hierarchy</head><p>It is useful to start with a summary of how economists view the organization. Caliendo (2020) write that the organization must "determine how much each employee knows, how many employees to hire, and how many layers of management to use in production" (p. 4213). <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano (2000)</ref> argues that organizations exist "to solve coordination problems in the presence of specialization" (p. 874). Given that most firms' production depends on the skills of their workforce, the organizational problem can be viewed as a means to allow workers to combine their time and knowledge, which allows workers to gain the help of other workers in production <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Garicano and Rossi-Hansberg, 2006)</ref>.</p><p>One class of models views the firm as a "knowledge hierarchy" (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Garicano and Rossi-Hansberg, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Caliendo, Monte, and Rossi-Hansberg, 2015)</ref>. In these models, workers must contribute time and knowledge to produce, and workers depend on the output of other workers to complete production. A knowledge hierarchy divides tasks-or the knowledge space-among workers. Layers emerge with managers who act as problem solvers and handle exceptions from the layers below. Adding layers thus adds specialists to the workforce, allowing the firm to leverage worker knowledge at the lower levels better. The hierarchy ensures that managers deal with the least common problems, leaving the more common ones to the lower layers of the firm. As <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Caliendo and Rossi-Hansberg (2012)</ref> summarize, when we observe an organizational structure, we can infer the agents' knowledge, how information flows within the firm, and the communication paths.</p><p>These benefits of hierarchy come with costs. The first is the fixed cost of training managers, as they must learn how to solve problems regardless of how the firm uses the knowledge. The second is the communication required between managers and workers that does not generate output. Accordingly, when a firm adds a layer to its hierarchy (and hence another set of problem solvers), it weighs the gains from specialization against the cost of coordination and loast production time. Ultimately, firms choose a structure-the number of layers and the share of workers in each layer-to best match problems to knowledge. The organization then tries to economize on the knowledge of managers to solve problems.</p><p>The main ideas from the models of knowledge hierarchy echo well with a second class of models, which we refer to as "information hierarchy" (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Radner, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bolton and Dewatripont, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Stein, 2002)</ref>. In these models, the span of control of the CEO is restricted by the CEO's ability to process information, which induces a need for delegation in the form of hierarchical layers. As in the models of knowledge hierarchy, adding layers gives rise to a tradeoff between the gains from specialization and the costs of communication. In these models, specialized workers collect information (within their layer), which they then communicate to managers (across layers). If the costs of communication are high, multilayered hierarchies become less attractive.</p><p>Finally, a third class of models sees hierarchies as a form of governance that allows managers to better align their subordinates' incentives with the firm's objective (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Williamson, 1967;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Alchian and Demsetz, 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Calvo and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Wellisz, 1978, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Rosen, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Qian, 1994)</ref>. In particular, one subset of these governance models, which we refer to as "incentive hierarchy," argue that, because much of the employees' incentives are provided through promotions, their effectiveness depends on the career path within the organization's hierarchy. In these models, multilayered hierarchies provide a career path that is conducive to internal promotions and hence contribute to employees' incentives (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lazear and Rosen, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Malcomson, 1984)</ref>.</p><p>Our analysis studies whether empirical analogs of these models' assumptions can be found in our sample, and then explores the empirical relevance of these models for firm decisions and outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">What is a layer?</head><p>Before introducing our hierarchy measure, we describe how we conceptualize hierarchical layers throughout the paper. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Caliendo and Rossi-Hansberg (2012)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Caliendo, Monte, and Rossi-Hansberg (2015)</ref> define a layer as a group of employees with similar knowledge levels performing tasks at a comparable level of authority. In keeping with this definition, our measure of hierarchical layers aims to capture jobs with similar complexity, tasks, and responsibilities. Another way to characterize layers is in terms of information flows between roles. For example, in the model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bolton and Dewatripont (1994)</ref>, workers in a given layer send messages to those above but not below. In the knowledge hierarchy model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano (2000)</ref>, a layer is a set of workers with the same scope of knowledge and who communicate problems to the layer above them. Since we do not observe communication flows across roles, we cannot measure layers in this fashion. Nevertheless, we believe that our measure captures similar duties and close rankings within the firm, in keeping with the above conceptualization of hierarchical layers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Existing measures of hierarchy</head><p>Our attempt to measure corporate hierarchy is not the first. Appendix Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">A1</ref> summarizes sixteen papers that capture the broad scope of empirical work in this area. The table allows us to discuss different methodologies and resulting counts of hierarchical layers.</p><p>There are three methods that researchers use to identify job rankings and levels. The first approach is to use direct reports or surveys from firms or consultants (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baker, Gibbs, and Holmstrom, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Liberti and Mian, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Guadalupe and Wulf, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Guadalupe, Li, and Wulf, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano and Hubbard, 2016)</ref>. This approach minimizes measurement error but lacks external validity due to the small number of firms for which such data are available. The second and most common approach is to connect job titles to occupation codes (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Caliendo, Monte, and Rossi-Hansberg, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Gumpert, Steimer, and Antoni, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bias, Lochner, Obernberger, and Sevilir, 2024)</ref>. The key assumption underlying this method is that the occupation codes reflect job or task complexity, and such complexity correlates with rank.</p><p>The unique number of occupational codes limits this approach, however. Appendix Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">A1</ref> shows that the number of levels based on occupation codes does not exceed 4. Finally, the third approach, which is the one we implement in this paper, uses observed transitions between jobs to infer rankings. One can then infer levels by using an algorithm that captures the "clustering" of jobs into promotions. This approach leverages the dynamics of a firm's internal labor market. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baker, Gibbs, and Holmstrom (1994)</ref> were the first to implement this approach and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Huitfeldt, Kostøl, Nimczik, and Weber (2023)</ref> introduce a formal algorithm to create hierarchical layers.</p><p>While each method and approach has strengths and weaknesses, we believe the internal labor markets method is ideal for public firms. First, alternative methods have too few layers to capture the complex structure of large public firms. Second, it is unclear whether a general mapping between occupation codes and job titles would provide a "one size fits all" that is suitable for a wide variety of public firms across different industries. Using revealed transitions in an internal labor market at the firm level circumvents this limitation, as this approach does not rely on a general mapping and classification system. Finally, the data that are obtained as a by-product of the internal labor markets approach are helpful as they capture promotion rates, work experience, and other human capital measures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">A new measure of hierarchy 4.1 Internal labor markets: an algorithm</head><p>We aim to create a firm-year measure of the number of hierarchical layers. Suppose we have data on worker resumes over a 5-to 8-year horizon, where resumes reveal titles, start dates by title, and transitions between jobs. Further, assume that titles are standardized within the firm. This data provides a view of a firm's internal labor market and the inputs we need to implement the method of <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Huitfeldt, Kostøl, Nimczik, and Weber (2023)</ref>. 2 There are two critical pieces of intuition for this method. First, job transitions ("worker flows") reveal the ranking of jobs <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Clauset, Arbesman, and Larremore, 2015)</ref>. Second, a layer in a firm is a collection of roles that are more likely to have lateral moves between them rather than promotion or demotion (Bonhomme, Lamadon, and Manresa, 2022). 3   The first step is to identify the connected jobs in the firm, or internal labor markets (ILMs).</p><p>The method requires tracking connections between roles over the sample period, effectively finding the largest connected roles in the firm. Firms can have multiple ILMs if they have separate divisions where job roles never transition to one another (e.g., a diversified firm that produces jet engines and financial services). Ideally, a firm has few ILMs, or the largest ILM comprises a large fraction of worker-years. Our analysis will focus on the largest ILM in the firm. Fortunately, this ILM comprises over 70% of the worker-years for the median firm in our sample (see Section 6.1). One cost of this focus is related to multi-divisional firms, as the method can only summarize the layers of the largest division. Nevertheless, this is unlikely to be a concern for our analysis as long as firms structure their divisions-controlling for size-in a similar fashion.</p><p>The second step leverages the worker transitions in the largest ILM to create a role ranking.</p><p>Note that all these steps are performed at the firm level. We use all years available in the resume data (see Section 5). Intuitively, if role A is followed by role B (50%) and role C (50%), while role C only transitions to A 5% of the time, the ranking would put B and C above A. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Huitfeldt, Kostøl, Nimczik, and Weber (2023)</ref> introduces a minimum violation ranking (MVR) to account for the noise in resume data and job transitions. The algorithm starts by ranking roles based on the promotions they receive. The method then swaps ranks of connected (or random) role pairs and checks whether the implied ranking has the same or a higher number of promotions (accepting it if it does). This procedure likely has many ties, so the final ranking is the average of optimal ranks. The uncertainty of a given rank-the standard deviation-is used in the final step.</p><p>Once roles are ranked, we put them into hierarchical levels. The estimated mean rank and rank standard deviation inform the clustering of roles and the number of layers. The algorithm clusters ranks and uses the estimation uncertainty to select the number of clusters K. A high standard deviation suggests that a role could move up or down the ranking in a series of optimal rankings. This flexibility is a sign of lateral moves between roles and, thus, a layer. Technically, as <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Huitfeldt, Kostøl, Nimczik, and Weber (2023)</ref> write (p. 11):</p><p>Given a number of clusters [layers] K, the k-means algorithm assigns each occupation [role] to a hierarchy level such that the sum of the within-level squared distances in estimated ranks is minimized. The choice of the number of hierarchy levels for each internal labor market is determined by the uncertainty in the rank estimation.</p><p>We describe our final measure of hierarchical layers in Section 6 after discussing the data inputs in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">LinkedIn data</head><p>We leverage data on worker resumes provided by CoreSignal. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">4</ref> The data provider extracts resume data-including work histories, job titles, employers, and educational backgroundfrom publicly available profiles of U.S.-based workers from 2016 to 2023. While our analysis focuses on workers who are active during the sample period, we use their complete work history that is available on LinkedIn. Thus, we have a much longer view of the firms' job ladders than the final sample period.</p><p>We exclude temporary or part-time workers using titles such as "intern," "consultant," etc. These profiles are self-filled by individuals, and while the online resume site does require some structure, there are few requirements for titles or accuracy of job timing. Admittedly, it is challenging to assess the coverage of the actual set of workers at firms or the sample selection within firms. We speculate that the managerial class and upper management are more likely to create and manage their profiles.</p><p>A comparison of headcounts between our data and Compustat reveals that coverage is below 50% for most firms (see Section 6.1). However, this likely understates the actual coverage since the Compustat headcount includes temporary workers and non-U.S. employees.</p><p>Importantly, the algorithm to measure hierarchical layers described below is largely robust to over-or under-representation of a given title. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">5</ref> Rather, all we require is that the titles occur at least once in the data and that a promotion or demotion exists between titles.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">6</ref> In the final sample described below, we have 8,753,665 job transitions from 2017 to 2023.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">7</ref> Again, we caution that we do not have a means of directly assessing whether we have complete coverage of titles or transitions. To validate our data, we rely on an extensive set of validation tests that demonstrate the data capture features of hierarchies predicted by theory and consistent with industry practice (see Section 6.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1">Title cleaning, clustering, and roles</head><p>One caveat of using worker-submitted resumes is that they feature a large set of often idiosyncratic titles. Indeed, the average firm in the resume data has an average of 1,033 unique titles (median 254) across the sample period. Although our methodology does not directly map jobs to occupational codes, the large number of titles makes it challenging to classify transitions accurately. We thus implement a cleaning and clustering method to reduce the number of titles within each firm. The cleaning step removes commonly added suffixes and prefixes, normalizes abbreviations, and removes rare words where "rare" is defined across and within firms. Additionally, we apply stemming (i.e., reducing words to their primary part) to titles to standardize different forms of the same role; for instance, "Software Engineer" and "Software Engineering" are both stemmed to "Software Engin." This cleaning step alone reduces the average number of titles per firm to 929 (median 217).</p><p>The next step recognizes that individuals may use multiple descriptions for the same role, often sharing common keywords. Our clustering algorithm identifies common phrases across titles within firms based on the frequency of strings or bi-grams. Specifically, it captures the top 25% of strings and bi-grams by frequency for each firm, prioritizing bi-grams within a title. For example, consider a firm with only two titles over the years: "Software Engin, UX" and "Software Engin, backend." For individual strings, the algorithm would detect "Software" and "Engin" each appearing twice, while "UX" and "backend" appear once each.</p><p>For bi-grams, "Software Engin" would appear twice, and "Engin UX" and "Engin backend" would each appear once. Since the algorithm prioritizes bi-grams over individual strings, both titles would map to the single role "Software Engin." If a title does not map to a common phrase, the algorithm maps it to a common string using the most common role in the set. This process results in a meaningful reduction in the number of titles, now classified as roles, with an average of 259 roles (median 99) per firm. Each role encompasses approximately three raw titles (2.3 cleaned titles).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Public firm data</head><p>We merge the resume data with data on U.S. publicly-traded firms from Standard &amp; Poor's Compustat. This merge is facilitated by the availability of the company's website (URL), which is reported in both datasets. As there are still many false positives and negatives, we supplement the merge with a fuzzy string comparison of firm names and a manual review of hundreds of potential matches. In total, we match 7,277 firms to the resume site data (across all years and industries) before filters and additional data cleaning. These firms have over 16 million unique workers in all years (again, before cleaning). After filtering from data cleaning and implementing the algorithm, we are left with nearly seven million unique workers.</p><p>The final sample of firms includes those in Compustat as of 2015 or later that have at least one year of measured hierarchical layers. We exclude firms in the following industries based on SIC codes: 4900-4999 (regulated utilities), 5200 and 5300-5399 (retail, with many part-time workers), 7100-7299 (service firms with poor LinkedIn coverage), and 4400-4599 (airlines and shipping, with a large fraction of firms with near-zero coverage on LinkedIn).</p><p>Any remaining firms after these filters, whose LinkedIn employee count is less than 15% of Compustat employees (Compustat item "emp") or with less than 25% of worker-years in the largest internal labor market are dropped. With these criteria, we are left with 3,128 firms (though the sample size varies depending on the regression). Over 2,000 firms outside the filtered industry codes lack a hierarchical layer measure, have no employees listed on the resume website, or have insufficient coverage. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> compares the two samples. In-sample firms tend to be larger (based on total assets), have higher leverage, and higher profitability (based on ROA). These are all characteristics of large firms, which confirms that our sample tilts toward larger companies.</p><p>We use several other datasets in the paper, which we briefly introduce here. The stock price data are obtained from CRSP and merged using the CRSP-Compustat bridge maintained by WRDS. Execucomp provides information on the top executives (the C-suite) that we combine with the resume data, along with information on their compensation. BoardEx provides information on board size. Finally, we use the patent data of DISCERN <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Arora, Belenzon, and Sheer, 2021)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Kogan, Papanikolaou, Seru, and Stoffman (2017)</ref>, as well as the data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Babina, Fedyk, He, and Hodson (2024)</ref> on public firms' use of artificial intelligence (AI).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Hierarchical layers</head><p>This section describes the measure of hierarchical layers and presents a series of validation tests motivated by the theory literature reviewed in Section 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Summarizing the data</head><p>What do corporate hierarchies look like over time and across firms? Panel A of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> reports summary statistics on layers and other characteristics. The unit of observation is a firm observed in the most recent year of its observable hierarchy. Recall that the clustering algorithm (see Section 4) identifies the firms' internal labor markets (ILMs) from job transitions and infers hierarchical layers from the largest ILM. Panel A shows that the average firm has 149 ILMs. While this may seem large, this count is driven by rare one-off titles or job cycles that are typical in the user-inputted LinkedIn data. The hierarchical layers measure focuses on the largest ILM, which contains 129 unique roles on average (recall that titles are mapped to roles). On average, there are 196 roles in a firm.</p><p>Two statistics provide comfort that the largest ILM captures most roles and workers.</p><p>Specifically, for the median firm, 60% of the roles and 73% of the worker-years are found in the largest ILM. That is, nearly three-quarters of the workers help identify a firm's corporate hierarchy. The table also reports the number of employees recorded in Compustat and those found in LinkedIn. The former includes part-time, seasonal, and non-US employees. The LinkedIn data includes US-based employees with public profiles. As can be seen, the LinkedIn data covers 49% of the number of Compustat employees for the median firm. While this is an inherent limitation of the LinkedIn data, this is less of limitation for our algorithm since it only needs to capture job transitions across roles within the firm.</p><p>The average number of hierarchical layers across all firms is 9.5 (median 8). This exceeds the number of layers-typically 4-obtained in the studies reviewed in Appendix Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">A1</ref>.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">8</ref> </p><p>The higher number of layers at U.S. public firms is not surprising, since they are larger than most firms considered in the prior literature. Importantly, this higher number of hierarchical layers suggests that the existing methods (e.g., those based on occupational codes that have a built-in cap on the number of layers) may be too coarse to capture the rich organizational structure of publicly traded firms.</p><p>The last three variables in Panel A report different versions of the "hierarchization" measure of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bias, Lochner, Obernberger, and Sevilir (2024)</ref> that captures the relative share of employees in each layer. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_7">9</ref> The first two measures use their partition based on occupation codes. We construct these two measures by mapping job titles to occupation codes (using the German Classification of Occupations and the ONet occupation codes, respectively). The third measure uses our definition of layers. The average of 0.75 is higher, which is expected since this variable increases in the number of layers. Note that all three exceed the 0.41 average in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bias, Lochner, Obernberger, and Sevilir (2024)</ref>, who study the hierarchization of German firms before and after going public. Their firms are substantially smaller than the U.S. public firms in our sample, which likely explains the lower degree of hierarchization.</p><p>Panel B reports the statistics from Panel A for the complete set of firm-year observations. These statistics mirror those from Panel A.</p><p>Moving to the time series evidence, Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows that the average and median number of layers for U.S. public firms has declined over the sample period. Thus, the flattening of the firm-first documented in <ref type="bibr">Rajan and Wulf (2006)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Guadalupe and Wulf (2010)</ref> for the top of the hierarchies-applies to later years among a much larger sample of public firms, taking into account a more complete characterization of their hierarchy.</p><p>Finally, Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows that hierarchical layers vary substantially across industries, as well as across firms within industries (Panel A), while there is less variation within industries over time (Panel B). The latter further shows that many industries experience a flattening of their hierarchies, in keeping with the broader evidence from Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.1">Within-firm variation</head><p>Baker, Gibbs, and Holmstrom (1994)'s analysis of a single medium-sized services firm from 1969-1988 showed stability in the organizational form. As they note (p. 893), "the hierarchy was surprisingly stable over time. With few exceptions, titles important in 1969 were similarly important in 1988." We observe similar stability among U.S. public firms in our sample.</p><p>During our sample period from 2016-2023, only 18% of firms experienced a change in layers, and this occurred in 3.9% of firm-years. When layers do change, they increase three-quarters of the time, and the median change is a one-layer increase. This stability limits our ability to study within-firm changes and thus leaves much of what follows as cross-sectional results.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_8">10</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Validation</head><p>In this section, we present a series of tests to validate our proposed measure of corporate hierarchy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.1">Ranks, titles, and promotion</head><p>Ultimately, a measure of hierarchy should correctly rank workers and jobs. The first set of validation tests examines whether layers have the expected titles, work experience, and connections via promotion.</p><p>In Table <ref type="table">3</ref>, we report the most commonly occurring titles in the top and bottom layers of the hierarchy. While firms with different total layers are difficult to compare, it is reassuring to see that the titles closely capture those that would naturally be associated with the top (e.g., "Vice President," "Director") and bottom (e.g., "Sales Associate," "Driver," "Cashier") levels of the hierarchy.</p><p>Relatedly, Appendix Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">A2</ref> shows that titles that include the strings "director" and "president" are increasingly more prevalent higher up in the hierarchy, while titles that include the strings "sales" and "engineer" are increasingly more prevalent in lower layers. The hierarchical layer's rank also positively correlates with other measures of levels. Appendix Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">A1</ref> reports the average ranking for titles by layer after mapping the titles to the ONet classification system.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_9">11</ref> As can be seen, we observe a weakly positive relationship between a title's hierarchical layer and the one to five ranking in ONet.</p><p>A hierarchical structure should also group workers into experience buckets. Workers in the lower layers should have fewer years of work experience either because they have not yet been promoted or because being at higher levels requires more know-how that takes time to accumulate. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> shows that work experience-measured since the worker graduates or their first job-increases with the hierarchical layer. As experience tends to coincide with higher pay, this pattern is consistent with most theory models of hierarchies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lazear and Rosen, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Malcomson, 1984)</ref>. Overall, the characteristics of titles and worker experience across layers confirm that our measure captures meaningful features of firm hierarchies.</p><p>The theory literature reviewed in Section 2 guides the remainder of the validation tests that are based on firm size, the shape of the hierarchy, and the distribution of managers across layers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.2">Firm size</head><p>Most models of corporate hierarchies predict that, as a firm grows in scale, the number of layers increases (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Calvo and Wellisz, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr">Caliendo, Monte, and Rossi-Hansberg, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> shows how the distribution of hierarchical layers varies across size quintiles. This figure focuses on the manufacturing sector in 2023 for ease of exposition, but similar patterns are found across all other sectors. As shown, we find evidence for a strong, positive relationship between size (captured by total assets in Panel A and the number of employees in Panel B) and the number of hierarchical layers.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">4</ref> further investigates the connection between firm size-measured in eight different ways (using total assets, employment, revenues, the number of business segments, the number of U.S. subsidiaries, the number of executives, board size, as well as firm age)-and the number of layers. The dependent variable is the log of the number of layers in year t, while all righthand variables are measured in year t -1. As can be seen, all size proxies strongly correlate with a firm's layer count. Indeed, the R-squared in several regressions exceeds 70%. The fit is highest for employment, as theory would predict-as firms add employees (without a commensurate increase in output), they are more likely to alter their organizational structure through additional layers. Importantly, the regression in the last column, which includes all size controls, shows that size does not fully explain the variation in hierarchical layers. That is, there is enough variation in hierarchies that cannot be explained by size alone. This is the variation that we exploit in our empirical analysis.</p><p>In sum, the evidence from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">4</ref> confirms the strong association between the number of layers and firm size, as one would expect from theory. Moreover, this strong association motivates the inclusion of size controls in all our regressions to ensure that our results do not merely capture differences in size that are correlated with the number of layers. In our preferred specification, we will include granular size controls in the form of asset decile fixed effects (see Section 7).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.3">Firm shape</head><p>Next, we turn to the shape of the firm's organizational structure. Most theories predict that the corporate structure will be pyramidal, that is, higher layers will have a smaller share of employees. For example, this follows from the models of information hierarchy where hierarchies divide workers into those specializing in tasks and those coordinating them (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bolton and Dewatripont, 1994)</ref>, the models of knowledge hierarchy where hierarchies distribute problem solvers across layers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano, 2000)</ref>, and the models of incentive hierarchy where promotion incentives rely on having fewer employees at higher layers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lazear and Rosen, 1981)</ref>.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_10">12</ref> Note that the pyramidal shape is not imposed when constructing our measure of hierarchical layers. Thus, evidence that firms are pyramidal on average would provide additional validation in light of the different theories of corporate hierarchy. We investigate firm shape using the share of employees in a layer, or in a layer quantile, measured using the number of employees in our LinkedIn data. As discussed in Section 5.1, LinkedIn does not capture all employees, and we speculate that LinkedIn over-samples middle to upper-middle management. Such over-sampling does not impact the hierarchy variable construction per se, but does impact employee shares. Thus, estimating firm shapes entails some measurement error.</p><p>There are two ways in which we can compare firms' shapes. We can condition on the number of layers, or we can split the firm hierarchy into quintiles (or similar) to pool firms in one analysis. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref> follows the second approach, showing the share by hierarchy quintile for firms with at least five layers. In each industry sector, we observe a monotonic decrease in the share of employees as one moves into higher layers. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref> follows the first approach, reporting the average shape of firms with five (Panel A) and eight layers (Panel B) where the shares are averaged across all firm-years. As can be seen, the evidence is again generally consistent with a pyramidal shape.</p><p>Finally, an indirect view of a firm's shape can be obtained from how workers move between layers. Promotion in our data is a change in a worker's role to a new one with a higher rank.</p><p>Recall that layers are collections of roles, and both layers and roles are ranked. In a pyramidal organization where workers can be promoted, there are fewer positions at the next (higherranked) layer than at the current layer. This should result in a longer time to promotion higher up in the hierarchy (along with any additional experience requirements as a worker moves up the firm). This is indeed what we observe in Appendix Figure <ref type="figure">A2</ref>, which shows that the time to next-layer promotions tends to increase as we move up the firm's hierarchy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.4">Worker characteristics</head><p>The next set of validation tests aims to confirm that worker characteristics across layers vary as one would expect from theory. In particular, the knowledge hierarchy models posit that higher layers are management layers, while lower layers are mostly populated by production workers.</p><p>In this spirit, we expect to see an increase in the share of managers as we move up the firm's hierarchy. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref> reports the share of workers in each layer with the string "manager" in their title for groups of firms that have the same number of layers. Conditioning on the number of layers ensures we are comparing the same layers across firms. As can be seen, the share of managers tends to increase as we move up the firm's hierarchy. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_11">13</ref> This higher prevalence of managers-or "problem solvers" in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano (2000)</ref>'s terminology-confirms that our measure captures meaningful features of the firm's organizational structure, in keeping with existing models of corporate hierarchy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.5">Additional validation</head><p>In the Appendix, we provide additional validation. In Appendix A1, we show that our measure of hierarchical layers performs well when benchmarked against a small set of firms with known hierarchical layers. In Appendix A2, we provide support for the algorithm's assumptions about the nature of job transitions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.6">Summary</head><p>In sum, the validation tests provided in this section indicate that publicly available resume data can be used to build meaningful proxies for corporate hierarchies consistent with a large body of theoretical work on organizations. In Sections 7 and 8, we use our measure to explore the role of hierarchies for corporate decision-making and a wide range of outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Title measurement issues</head><p>Before moving to the empirical analysis, we discuss potential measurement issues in job titles.</p><p>As mentioned in Section 4, our hierarchy measure requires the identification of unique roles and promotion paths within the firm. The LinkedIn resume data provide imperfect information on both, which could bias our measure of hierarchy, as the firms' specific titles and promotion paths may not align with the economic mechanisms we consider. In particular, issues such as title inflation documented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Cohen, Gurun, and Ozel (2023)</ref> could produce too many managers or promotions that are not connected to decision-making or job tasks. This could, in turn, bias upward the number of layers.</p><p>Nevertheless, title inflation is unlikely to significantly impact the estimated number of hierarchical layers. This is because the algorithm creates a new layer only when there are substantial outbound promotions from a specific title to higher-level roles, and "fake" or superfluous titles-often found at lower echelons (e.g., "Director of Customer Service" or "Assistant Manager")-typically lack such promotional pathways. The title-to-role algorithm, designed to reduce dimensionality, tends to aggregate these less influential titles rather than separating them into distinct layers.</p><p>The evidence presented so far also indicates that title inflation is unlikely to be a firstorder concern for our analysis. In particular, title inflation would predict an increase in the number of layers over time, while we found the opposite pattern in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Moreover, title inflation would predict a surge of (alleged) managerial roles at lower levels of the hierarchy, which is contrary to what we observed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Corporate hierarchy and firm outcomes</head><p>Now that we have demonstrated that our measure of hierarchical layers captures expected patterns in firm organization, we ask whether hierarchical layers help explain firm outcomes.</p><p>To do so, we estimate regressions of the outcome of interest Y it (such as ROA or the number of patents) for firm i in year t on log(# layers) it-1 , that is, the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers of firm i in year t -1. The regressions include year, industry (based on 4-digit SIC codes), and size decile fixed effects (based on the firm's assets at t -1). That is, we compare firms in the same year, same industry, and of similar size, that differ based on their number of layers.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_12">14</ref> When estimating these regressions, we cluster standard errors at the company level.</p><p>Our regressions aim to characterize how corporate hierarchies correlate with a series of outcome variables. Accordingly, we caution that our results are correlational and hence need not warrant a causal interpretation. Breaking ground on the latter would require exogenous variation in corporate hierarchy, which is difficult to obtain given the inherent endogeneity of organizational structures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Human capital</head><p>We first examine how the number of layers correlates with measures that capture different dimensions of the firm's human capital. We consider two dimensions: education and career paths.</p><p>In the theories of corporate hierarchies, additional layers require employees with managerial skills that are costly to acquire. For example, in the models of <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Rosen (1982)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano (2000)</ref>, this is captured by a fixed cost of knowledge acquisition. We thus expect firms with more layers to have a more educated workforce. To examine whether this is the case, we use the educational histories of employees from their online resumes. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_13">15</ref>Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> presents the percent of workers in each layer who have a post-graduate degree.</p><p>Each line represents the average percent of workers for firms with the same total number of layers. As can be seen, post-graduate degrees tend to be more prevalent as we move up the firm's hierarchy, consistent with the above arguments.</p><p>Next, we examine the relationship between the number of layers and the extent to which workers build their careers within the firm's internal labor market. A large literature highlights the importance of intrafirm labor mobility for employees' incentives and their willingness to invest in firm-specific human capital (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lazear and Rosen, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Waldman, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baker, Gibbs, and Holmstrom, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Lazear and Oyer, 2004)</ref>. Accordingly, the provision of a clear career path ("job ladders") in multi-layer firms is likely to affect employees in multiple ways.</p><p>In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">5</ref>, we examine several dimensions related to the firm's human capital. The first two columns show that high-layer firms are less likely to bring in external hires (column 1) and have higher internal promotion rates (column 2). These patterns confirm that the job ladders of promotion are more prevalent in high-layer firms. The higher promotion rates, combined with the longer tenure observed in columns 3 (referring to the "non-new" employees, that is, excluding employees who joined during the year) and 4 (referring to all employees), show that the average employee in high-layer firms has more experience within the firm, consistent with the notion that employees have stronger incentives to invest in firm-specific human capital in high-layer firms. 16   In column 5, we further explore the extent to which high-layer firms provide employee stock option plans (ESOPs) to their employees. ESOPs are commonly used as a way to enhance employee retention and long-term commitment to the firm (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Jones and Kato, 1995)</ref>. To the extent that high-layer firms are more reliant on internal job ladders and firmspecific human capital investments, one might expect a higher prevalence of ESOPs among them. We collect data on ESOPs from the firms' filings of Form 5500 that we match to our sample of public firms. 17 As can be seen, we find that firms with more layers are indeed significantly more likely to offer ESOPs to their employees.</p><p>An important part of the firm's internal labor market is the top executive team. In columns 6 to 8 of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">5</ref>, we examine features of the CEO. First, in keeping with our finding of higher internal promotion rates and tenure, we find that high-layer firms are more likely to appoint internal CEOs. Turning to CEO compensation, we find that CEOs of high-layer firms have higher compensation. Moreover, multi-layer firms have higher wage inequality, as captured by the CEO pay ratio (that is, the ratio of the CEO's pay to the median worker's pay). These findings are consistent with several models of corporate hierarchy. In particular, they are consistent with the tournament-type models, in which higher rewards are provided 16 In the Appendix, we complement these findings in two ways. First, Appendix Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">A3</ref> plots the average tenure in a given layer quintile for groups of firms that have the same total number of layers. As can be seen, the average tenure within a layer quintile tends to increase as we move up the hierarchy. Moreover, firms with more layers tend to have higher tenure by layer across the hierarchy. Second, Appendix Table <ref type="table">A3</ref> provides additional perspective on the hiring and promotion patterns. Specifically, we consider all role switches and all new external hires as the set of employee-year observations. We then show that, within a firm, the probability of external hiring is monotonically decreasing as we move up the hierarchy. (The estimates capture the probability of an external hire in a given layer quintile relative to the lowest layer quintile as base group.) This pattern is consistent with the predictions of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baker, Gibbs, and Holmstrom (1994)</ref> who argue that, as higher layers demand more firm-specific human capital, external hires are more difficult to find.</p><p>17 Form 5500 filings are annual reports required for employee benefit plans subject to the Employee Retirement Income Security Act (ERISA)-including retirement plans such as 401(k)s, as well as certain welfare benefit plans-in order to provide the Department of Labor (DOL) and the IRS with key information about a plan's financial condition, investments, operations, and compliance with federal regulations. Using these data, we construct an indicator variable ("ESOP") equal to one if the firm has an employee stock option plan or employee stock bonuses.</p><p>at the top of the job ladder (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Lazear and Rosen, 1981)</ref>, and the models of knowledge hierarchy in which higher-level problem-solvers require skills that are increasingly more costly (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Garicano and Rossi-Hansberg, 2006)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Firm productivity and costs</head><p>Arguably, how firms organize production with workers in their hierarchy should impact firm productivity. Large, persistent differences in firm productivity have been documented across countries and time (see the survey of <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Syverson, 2011)</ref>. These differences can be partially explained by market structure, technology, demand, diversification, and exposure to trade, among others. Organizational structure is likely to be another determinant of firm productivity.</p><p>Many models highlight how organizational structures can contribute to productivity. For example, in the models of knowledge hierarchy, adding a layer brings in more managers ("problem solvers") who contribute to productivity by solving complex problems faced by the production workers at lower layers. This benefit comes at a cost since managers spend their time problem-solving rather than producing (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Garicano and Zandt, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Caliendo, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>The left-hand panel of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref> explores the relationship between the number of layers and four measures of productivity. Columns 1-3 show that an increase in the number of layers is associated with a higher return on assets (ROA), gross profit margin, and net profit margin. These findings indicate that multi-layer firms achieve higher operating performance.</p><p>Interestingly, column 4 shows that high-layer firms have a lower revenue-to-employee ratio. This echoes the argument that high-layer firms have more managers who are not directly involved in the production process.</p><p>The right-hand panel of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref> explores cost measures (scaled by total assets). In column 5, we consider selling, general, and administrative expenses (SG&amp;A). SG&amp;A is often considered a measure of organizational capital. As can be seen, SG&amp;A is substantially higher for high-layer firms, consistent with the higher cost of maintaining more complex hierarchies.</p><p>Finally, in column 6, we examine wages. The point estimate is positive and significant, indicating that firms with more hierarchical layers have more expensive human capital. This again points to the higher cost of maintaining multilayered hierarchies, and aligns with the theories of corporate hierarchies in which additional layers require employees with managerial skills (or the ability to solve more complex problems in the models of knowledge hierarchies) whose human capital is likely more costly.</p><p>Next, we examine two major types of firm investment: acquisitions and innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Acquisitions</head><p>One of the most significant investments that public firms make over their life cycle are acquisitions of other firms. Empirical evidence suggests that acquisitions are often value-destroying (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Alexandridis, Antypas, and Travlos, 2017)</ref>, while there is mixed evidence on the value gains from diversifying acquisitions (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Eckbo, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Why would we expect a firm's hierarchical structure to matter for the firm's acquisition activity? To our knowledge, no model of hierarchies offers direct prediction about acquisition activities. From a theoretical perspective, the prediction could go either way. On one hand, to the extent that high-layer firms have more specialized employees-as in the models of knowledge and information-based hierarchies-they might be better able to identify suitable targets and potential synergies. On the other hand, the multi-layer structure may complicate the integration of other firms and their workforce.</p><p>Table 7 studies whether our measure of hierarchical layers predicts acquisition activity and the type of acquisitions. We measure acquisition activity using SDC Platinum and the Compustat-SDC merge from <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ewens, Peters, and Wang (2024)</ref>. In column 1, the dependent variable is an indicator variable equal to one if the firm had at least one acquisition during the year. As can be seen, firms with more layers are significantly more likely to engage in acquisitions. In column 2, we obtain similar results if we only consider "large" deals (that is, deals with reported valuations). These results also hold if we consider the count of acquisitions (column 3) and the sum of the (reported) valuations across all acquisitions made by the firm (column 4). Overall, these results indicate that high-layer firms are significantly more active in the acquisition market.</p><p>Column 5 of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">7</ref> examines whether the type of acquisition differs. Following Gormley and Matsa (2016), we define a diversifying acquisition as one where none of the target's SIC code matches the acquirer's primary SIC code. As can be seen, we find no evidence that high-layer firms differ along this dimension. This indicates that, although high-layer firms are more likely to engage in acquisitions, they do not favor diversifying acquisitions, as those might be harder to integrate into a multi-layered structure.</p><p>Overall, we conclude from these results that the number of hierarchical layers has meaningful predictive power for acquisition activity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4">Innovation</head><p>A common refrain about large, public firms is that they are at a disadvantage in producing high-impact innovation. The small, high-growth startups are considered critical suppliers of such innovation. This supposed advantage of startups could reflect the startup's size, flexibility, and quick decision-making. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Ewens and Marx (2024)</ref> show that younger firms produce higher-impact patents. Relatedly, in his analysis of newly-public firms, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Bernstein (2015)</ref> shows that the firm's innovation productivity decreases after the IPO. Our data allow us to explore how hierarchical structures can explain heterogeneity in public firms' innovation.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">8</ref> provides regression estimates of patenting activity and quality. Investments in innovation often start with R&amp;D. Column 1 shows that firms with more layers invest more in R&amp;D (as a ratio of total assets), although the point estimate is not significant at conventional levels. The Poisson estimate in column 2 shows that this higher R&amp;D investment corresponds with a significant increase in the number of patents. This finding is confirmed in column 3 where we use OLS (instead of Poisson) and code the dependent variable as the IHS (inverse hyperbolic sine) of the number of patents.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_14">18</ref> Do these patents differ in quality? To examine this question, we use the average number of citations per patent as dependent variable. As can be seen from columns 4 (Poisson) and 5 (OLS with the IHS transform), we find little evidence of an association between hierarchical layers and this proxy for patent quality. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_15">19</ref>Overall, these innovation outcomes show that multi-layer hierarchies are not detrimental to innovation production-in fact, they tend to produce more innovation-and do not face a disadvantage in generating high-quality patents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5">Firm risk</head><p>While the theories of corporate hierarchy do not provide explicit predictions for firm risk, there are many reasons to expect hierarchies to matter along this dimension. In particular, in the models of knowledge hierarchy, the addition of layers increases the firms' ability to "solve problems," which may enhance their ability to manage risks and adjust to unexpected shocks. This, in turn, would reduce the volatility of the firms' cash flows.</p><p>In columns 1 and 2 of of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">9</ref>, we examine the relationship between the number of layers and the firm's stock volatility, measured as the square root of the sum of squared daily stock returns (from CRSP) over the year. Column 1 refers to the raw measure, while it is winsorized at the 5% level in column 2. As can be seen, both estimates indicate that more layers are associated with lower stock volatility.</p><p>In columns 3 to 6, we refine this analysis by asking whether the lower stock volatility reflects lower business and/or financial risk. In columns 3 and 4, we consider measures of operating asset volatility and cash flow volatility, respectively, which we compute as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Gormley and Matsa (2016)</ref>. As is shown, firms with more layers have lower business risk based on these two metrics. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_16">20</ref> In columns 5 and 6, we examine leverage (the debt-to-asset ratio) and cash holdings (the cash-to-asset ratio) and find that the number of layers has little predicting power for these variables. If at all, the evidence in column 5 suggests that high-layer firms use higher leverage at the margin (corresponding to higher financial risk). Overall, these findings indicate that the lower stock volatility of high-layer firms is due to lower business risk rather than financial risk.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6">Stock returns</head><p>So far, our analysis shows that high-layer firms have higher operating performance (Section 7.2) and lower risk (Section 7.5). Another dimension of firm performance is the firm's stock returns. To examine the stock market performance of high-vs. low-layer firms, we build long-short portfolios using the hierarchical layers as the sorting characteristic for 2016 to 2023. Each year, firms are sorted, and the portfolio goes long in the top quartile and short in the bottom quartile. The portfolio is rebalanced each year. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">10</ref> reports the excess returns (alpha) that are achieved by this trading strategy under different asset pricing models.</p><p>As can be seen, we find evidence for an insignificant alpha in all columns.</p><p>The insignificant alpha indicates that stock market investors correctly anticipate the benefits and costs of having multiple layers. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_17">21</ref> Leaving the alpha aside, a look at the factor loadings is informative. In particular, the profitability factor loads positively, which is consistent with our profitability results (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref>). Moreover, the full 6-factor model in column 6 shows that high-layer stocks behave like large-cap, "quality" stocks. The latter feature signals stability and resiliency, which echoes well with what we found in the volatility analysis (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">9</ref>).</p><p>While we are unaware of organizational theories tied to these results, it is reassuring to see that they match the correlational tests above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">What explains firms' hierarchical layers</head><p>The analysis presented so far indicates that corporate hierarchy-as measured by the number of layers-has predictive power for a series of outcomes in a way that is consistent with various theories of firm organization. That being said, the results presented so far tell us little about how firms choose their layers. In what follows, we turn to this question by exploring potential determinants of the firms' decision to add or remove hierarchical layers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.1">Corporate life cycle</head><p>As a starting point, we examine how firms adjust their hierarchies over their life cycle, focusing on the transition to becoming a public firm in the IPO. This analysis echoes the work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bias, Lochner, Obernberger, and Sevilir (2024)</ref>, who explore the shift in hierarchization among German IPOs using the Rajan (2012) framework.</p><p>We examine a similar question for U.S. public firms whose IPOs occurred during our sample period and for which we can observe worker resumes in the years prior. As the transition to being public increases the complexity of the firm's operations and imposes additional reporting requirements, we expect firms to increase their hierarchical layers. Firms may also expand their layers if going public increases the size of the organization, in keeping with the strong relationship between firm size and the count of layers documented in Section 6.2.2.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref> presents regression coefficient estimates from a simple event study analysis for firms that had their IPO during our sample period. Consistent with the above arguments, we find that the number of layers increases substantially post-IPO. Note that the number of layers already increased two years before the IPO, likely because the firm was preparing for the listing. 22</p><p>22 We caution that these results are correlational due to the endogenous nature of the decision to go public.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2">The Covid pandemic</head><p>The Covid pandemic provides a source of variation for studying how firms respond to shocks.</p><p>Consider the set of firms in the pharmaceutical industry. For these firms, the pandemic represents a twofold shock. First, they were forced to solve the vaccine problem for a novel disease in a rapid amount of time. Second, they likely anticipated a huge spike in demand (conditional on a successful vaccine).</p><p>In the models of <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano (2000)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Caliendo, Monte, and Rossi-Hansberg (2015)</ref>, firms respond to demand shocks and shocks to "complexity" by adding layers. The rationale is that additional layers add managers (problem solvers), allowing lower-level workers to narrow the knowledge they must master in production. This, in turn, increases the organization's ability to address higher demand and the higher complexity of their environment. Accordingly, through the lens of these models, we would expect pharmaceutical firms to add layers following the Covid shock.</p><p>To study this question, we consider the set of firms in the 4-digit SIC code 2834 (that is, firms that manufacture, fabricate, or process drugs in pharmaceutical preparations-in short, pharmaceutical firms). The dependent variable is the current year's log number of hierarchical layers. The analysis considers firm-year observations from 2017-2022 (that is, around the Covid shock). As control firms, we consider either (i) all firms outside SIC code 2834 or (ii) all firms outside SIC code 2834 and outside the so-called "Covid industries" that were directly impacted by Covid such as lodging or cruise ships (the list of Covid industries is obtained from <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Fahlenbrach, Rageth, and Stulz, 2021)</ref>. We then estimate a difference-in-differences specification in which "Covid" and "post" are indicator variables equal to one for the treated firms (SIC code 2834) and the post-Covid years (that is, 2020-2022), respectively. The specification further includes firm and year fixed effects. The firm fixed effects are important since we are interested in within-firm changes in hierarchical layers around the Covid shock. As we noted in Section 6.1.1, the number of layers has limited within-firm variation. Hence, a caveat of including firm fixed effects is that it reduces the power of our tests. Nevertheless, given the magnitude of the Covid shock for pharmaceutical firms, we might still detect significant changes in the number of layers around that specific shock. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_18">23</ref>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">11</ref> presents the results. Column 1 shows that the number of layers increased by about 4% among the treated firms in the post-Covid years. Column 2 introduces a dynamic specification. As can be seen, the response starts in 2020 and is stronger in 2021-2022, when most vaccines were released. In columns 3 and 4, we find that the results are similar if we include size decile fixed effects. Finally, in columns 5 and 6, our results continue to hold if we exclude firms in the Covid industries from the control group. Note that, in all specifications, the pre-treatment coefficients are small and insignificant, which mitigates the possibility of pre-trends that could confound our estimates. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_19">24</ref>Overall, the evidence from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">11</ref> indicates that firms respond to demand and complexity shocks by adding hierarchical layers. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_20">25</ref> These responses further suggest that a firm's hierarchical structure is shaped by the shocks the firm has faced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3">Artificial intelligence</head><p>Artificial intelligence (AI) reduces the cost of knowledge acquisition and information processing. From a theoretical perspective, we would expect hierarchies to flatten following the adoption of AI. For example, in the models of knowledge hierarchy, lowering the cost of knowledge acquisition allows workers to solve a wider range of problems, which reduces the demand for problem solvers and hence the need for hierarchical layers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Garicano, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Garicano and Zandt, 2012)</ref>. Similarly, in the information-based model of hierarchies, the better ability to process information reduces the need for delegation through additional layers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Radner, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Bolton and Dewatripont, 1994)</ref>.</p><p>The recent rise in the adoption of AI provides an opportunity to evaluate these predictions.</p><p>To do so, we regress the log number of hierarchical layers on the measures of AI adoption proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Babina, Fedyk, He, and Hodson (2024)</ref> based on the number of AI job postings.</p><p>The regressions also include firm, year, and size decile fixed effects. The inclusion of firm fixed effects is important since we are interested in how firms adjust their hierarchies upon adopting AI. As discussed in Section 6.1.1, a limitation is that the firm fixed effects reduce the power of our tests due to the limited within-firm variation in hierarchical layers.</p><p>The results are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">12</ref>. We consider four different metrics of AI adoption: the share of AI job postings, broadly (column 1) and narrowly (column 2) defined, the average share of AI skills (column 3), and the average maximum share of AI skills (column 4). As can be seen, we find evidence for a reduction in the number of layers in all four columns, as predicted by theory. Although the tests are under-powered, we find that the point estimates are significant at the 10% level regardless of the metric of AI adoption. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_21">26</ref>To obtain more within-firm variation in the number of layers, we also ran a specification using long differences, that is, regressing the change in log(# layers) for a given firm over all available years on the corresponding change in AI (as well as year and size decile fixed effects). Doing so yields estimates that are similar to those in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">12</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">Conclusion</head><p>We propose a measure of corporate hierarchy for U.S. public firms that is obtained from online resumes of seven million employees and a network estimation technique that allows us to identify hierarchical layers. After validating this measure, we document several facts pertaining to corporate hierarchies that we link to existing theories of firm organization. In particular, we show that more hierarchical firms have a more educated workforce, higher internal promotion rates, and longer employee tenure. Their operating performance is higher, but they face higher administrative costs. They are more active acquirers and produce more patents, but not higher-quality patents. They exhibit lower stock return volatility and have lower business risk (i.e., operating asset volatility). Turning to the determinants of corporate hierarchies, we find that pharmaceutical companies increased their number of layers following the Covid-19 pandemic, while companies flattened their hierarchies following the adoption of AI technologies. These findings are consistent with the theoretical predictions of existing models of corporate hierarchies, especially those that conceptualize hierarchical layers as a way to bring in "problem solvers" whose knowledge helps solve the more complex problems faced by lower-layer workers.</p><p>In their characterization of the literature on hierarchies and internal labor markets, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Baker and Holmstrom (1995)</ref> noted that the literature has "too many theories, too few facts" (p. 255). What was true in 1995 remains true 30 years later, especially for U.S. public firms, as there is no available data on their hierarchy. This study aimed to fill this gap, by providing a measure of hierarchy that can be used to gain insights into the determinants and implications of hierarchies. In this spirit, we will release the hierarchy data to other researchers, in the hope that they will spur future work on this exciting topic. 27</p><p>27 The data will be posted on a public repository. For now, researchers interested in using the data should email the authors to obtain the most updated version of the data.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figures and Tables</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2: Organizational layers by industry</head><p>Panel A displays the box plot of the number of hierarchy layers across firms for the major industries in the sample. For each firm, the number of layers is recorded in the last year in which the firm's corporate hierarchy is observed. Panel B plots the average number of hierarchical layers by industry-year using all firm-year observations.      This figure reports the fraction of employees with the string "manager" in their title within a given layer. Each line represents a group of firms with the same number of layers (i.e., longer lines correspond to groups of firms with more layers). The figure includes firms in our sample whose number of layers is between 4 and 14, which corresponds to the interquartile range across all firms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 8: Advanced degrees by hierarchical layer</head><p>This figure reports the percentage of workers with an advanced degree (i.e., postgraduates) within a given layer. Each line represents a group of firms with the same number of layers (i.e., longer lines correspond to groups of firms with more layers). The figure includes firms in our sample whose number of layers is between 4 and 14, which corresponds to the interquartile range across all firms. </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">β k × 1(k years since IPO) + δi + γt + ϵit,</formula><p>where i indexes firms and t indexes years for the set of firms that had an IPO during the sample period; log(# layers it ) is the natural logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers; 1(k years since IPO) is an indicator variable equal to one if the observation is recorded k years after (or before when k &lt; 0) the firm's IPO; δi is a firm fixed effect; and γt is a year fixed effect. The excluded year is the year of the IPO. Standard errors are clustered at the firm level. This table reports differences in observables between the firms that are in the final sample ("In sample") and those that are not ("Out of sample") within the set of Compustat firms. Each firm is recoded once in 2015 or in the first available year during our sample period <ref type="bibr">(2016)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2017)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2018)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2019)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2020)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2021)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2022)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2023)</ref>. The table reports the sample mean in each group and the difference-in-means (with the corresponding standard error in parentheses). All variables are from Compustat. "Assets" is the book value of total assets (Compustat item "at"); "Total liabilities" is the sum of all liabilities (item "lt"); "PPE (net)" is the net property, plant, and equipment (item "ppent"), "Debt / equity" is the ratio of total liabilities to total equity (item "teq"); "Cash" is cash and marketable securities (item "che"); "Revenue" is total revenue (item "revt"); "Net income" is the firm's net income (item "ni"); "EBIT" is the firm's earnings before interest and taxes (item "ebit"); and ROA (return on assets) is the ratio of operating income before depreciation (item "oibdp") to assets. All ratios are winsorized at the 5% level. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively.  This table reports regression estimates using observations at the firm-year level. The dependent variable is the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers. On the right-hand side, the regressions include various measures of firm size, lagged by one year. "Assets" is the book value of total assets (Compustat item "at"); "employees" is the number of employees in thousands (item "emp"); "revenue" is total revenue (item "revt"); "firm age" is the number of year since the firm went public; "business segments" is the count of historical business segments reported in the segment file of Compustat; "# US subsidiaries" is the count of subsidiaries from the WRDS subsidiaries data (set to one if missing); "# execs in Execucomp" is the count of executives in Execucomp; "board size" is the size of the board from BoardEx. This table reports regression estimates using observations at the firm-year level. In column 1, the dependent variable is the fraction of new LinkedIn employees during the year ("% new"). In column 2, it is the fraction of existing LinkedIn employees who are promoted during the year ("% promote"). In columns 3 and 4, it is the logarithm of the average tenure of the firm's employees (in year). In column 3, this variable is constructed excluding employees who joined during the year ("Non-new"), while in column 4 it includes all employees ("All"). In column 5, "ESOP" is an indicator variable equal to one if the firm has an employee stock option plan or employee stock bonuses. In column 6, "Internal CEO" is an indicator variable equal to one if the firm appoints a new CEO who had worked at the firm before starting the CEO position (the sample consists of all CEO turnover events). In column 7, "CEO pay" is the logarithm of the total compensation (salary and bonus) of the CEO. In column 8, "CEO pay ratio" is the ratio of the CEO's pay to the median worker's pay. In all regressions, the right-hand side variable is "log # layers (t -1)," which is the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers in the previous year.  This table reports regression estimates using observations at the firm-year level. In columns 1-4, the dependent variables are measures of profitability and productivity. "ROA" is the ratio of operating income before depreciation (Compustat item "oibdp") to total assets (item "at"); "Gross margin" is the ratio of gross profits (item "gp") to total revenue (item "revt"); "Net margin" is the ratio of net income (item "ni") to total revenue; "Rev/emp." is the ratio of total revenue to the number of employees (item "emp"). The dependent variables in columns 5 and 6 are cost measures. "SG&amp;A" is the ratio of selling, general &amp; administrative expense (item "xsga") to total assets; and "Wages" is the ratio of staff expense (item "xlr") to total assets. All these variables are winsorized at the 5% level. In all regressions, the right-hand side variable is "log # layers (t -1)," which is the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers in the previous year.  This table reports regression estimates using observations at the firm-year level. In column 1, the dependent variable is the ratio of R&amp;D expenses (Compustat item "xrd") to total assets (item "at"), winsorized at the 5% level. In columns 2 and 3, the dependent variable is the number of patents applied for by the firm in a given year. In columns 4 and 5, the dependent variable is the number of citations received by these patents. Citations are computed as the average number of citations received by the end of the sample across all patents of the firm in a given year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Log number of layers</head><p>Columns 2 and 4 provide estimates from Poisson regressions. Columns 3 and 5 provide estimates using the IHS (inverse hyperbolic sine) transform of the dependent variable. In all regressions, the right-hand side variable is "log # layers (t -1)," which is the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers in the previous year. This table reports regression estimates using observations at the firm-year level. In columns 1 and 2, the dependent variable is the square root of the sum of squared daily stock returns over the year. The raw measure is used in column 1, while it is winsorized at the 5% level in column 2.</p><p>In columns 3 and 4, the dependent variables are operating asset volatility and cash flow volatility, respectively. These measures are computed as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Gormley and Matsa (2016)</ref>. In column 5, the dependent variable is the debt-to-asset ratio (leverage), which is computed as the ratio of total debt (Compustat item "dt") to total assets (item "at"). In column 6, the dependent variable is the cash-to-asset ratio, which is computed as the ratio of cash and marketable securities (item "che") to total assets. Both ratios are winsorized at the 5% level. In all regressions, the righthand side variable is "log # layers (t -1)," which is the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers in the previous year. This table presents multi-factor regressions of the monthly returns of portfolios sorted by the lagged number of hierarchical layers from 2016 to 2023 (96 months). In each year, we sort firms by the number of layers and construct a long-short portfolio that goes long in the top quartile and short in the bottom quartile of firms. The right-hand side variables include a constant (α) and the six factors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Fama and French (2018)</ref>, which are obtained from Kenneth French's website. R m -r f is the market risk factor, "SMB" is the size factor, "HML" is the growth factor, "RMW" is the profitability factor, "CMA" is the investment factor, and "Momentum" is the momentum factor. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively.</p><p>( This table reports regression estimates using observations at the firm-year level. The sample period spans the years 2017-2022 (three years before and three years after the Covid-19 pandemic). The dependent variable is the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers. On the right-hand side, "Covid" is an indicator variable equal to one for firms in SIC code 2834 (pharmaceutical companies), and "Post" is an indicator variable equal to one for the post-Covid years (2020-2022).</p><p>In columns 1-4, the control group includes all firms outside SIC code 2834. In columns 5 and 6, it includes all firms outside SIC code 2834 and outside the "Covid industries" identified by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Fahlenbrach, Rageth, and Stulz (2021)</ref> that were directly impacted by Covid. In columns 2, 4, and 6, "Post" is replaced with a set of year dummies (using 2019 as base year) that characterize the dynamics of the treatment effect. Size decile fixed effects are based on the firm's total assets in the previous year. This table reports regression estimates using observations at the firm-year level. The dependent variable is the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers. The right-hand side variables are various measures of AI adoption based on job posting data, obtained from <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Babina, Fedyk, He, and Hodson (2024)</ref>. They include the share of AI job postings, broadly (column 1) and narrowly (column 2) defined, the average share of AI skills (column 3), and the average maximum share of AI skills (column 4). Size decile fixed effects are based on the firm's total assets in the previous year. These validation tests reassure that the LinkedIn and promotion data reveal the deeper corporate hierarchy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A2 Job transitions</head><p>An assumption of our algorithm is that observed role changes in a worker's job history are a promotion or a lateral change in their position at the firm. Confirming this is challenging and thus rests on the assumption that individuals rarely stay at firms where they are demoted. If</p><p>this assumption is valid, individuals who move between firms should be more likely to move to a lower position on the hierarchy than a higher one. To test this and allow for comparisons of ranks across firms, we split firm hierarchies into quintiles. For all workers who move between firms (between the largest internal labor market of each), we identify the quintile they move to relative to the quintile of their previous position. Appendix Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">A4</ref> presents the transition matrix. As can be seen, for those outside of the first quintile, more than half of the moves are to the same quintile and below in each transition. In unreported results, we also find that movers who experience promotions across firms move to larger firms, while those who have no change or are demoted move to smaller firms. We interpret these patterns as support for our central assumption that within-firm role changes are promotions. Table <ref type="table">A3</ref>: Where external employees join in the hierarchy</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A3 Figures and Tables</head><p>This table reports regression estimates where the dependent variable is an indicator for whether a worker joined the firm from another firm in the last year (columns 1-2) or the last two years (columns 3-4). The sample includes all such workers, as well as those workers who stayed at the firm but switched layers. The unit of observation is a worker-year in which any of these moves occurred. The right-hand side variables are indicator variables for the quintile of the hierarchy where the individual moved to or was promoted to. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1: Organizational layers by year</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1: Organizational layers by year</figDesc><graphic coords="36,85.04,188.89,449.20,326.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Panel A: Hierarchical layers by major industry Panel B: Hierarchical layers by major industry over time</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Work experience across the firm hierarchy</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Variation in organizational layers by size</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Share of employees by hierarchy layer quintile</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Share of employees by hierarchy layer</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Managers by hierarchical layer</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Change in the number of hierarchical layers around the IPO</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure A1 :</head><label>A1</label><figDesc>Figure A1: ONet "ranking" and hierarchy layers</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="43,85.04,184.02,441.92,321.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="60,85.04,183.51,449.20,326.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="61,85.04,163.34,449.20,326.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Comparison of firms in and out of the sample</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Summary statisticsThis table reports summary statistics for the hierarchy variables. "Number of internal labor markets" is the count of internal labor markets (ILMs) within the firm that are identified by the algorithm described in Section 4. "Size of largest ILM" is the number of roles in the firm's largest ILM. "Number of unique roles" is the number of unique roles within the firm. "% role in largest ILM" is the fraction of all roles in the firm found in the largest ILM. "% workeryears in largest ILM" is the fraction of all worker-years whose role is in the firm's largest ILM. "Employees (Compustat)" is the number of employees in Compustat (in thousands). "Number employees (LinkedIn)" is the number of employees in the LinkedIn data (in thousands). "Number hierarchy layers" is the number of hierarchical layers of the firm. "Hierarchization" is the metric of hierarchization from<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bias, Lochner, Obernberger, and Sevilir (2024)</ref>, computed using layers based on the occupation codes of the German Classification of Occupations, the occupation codes of ONet, and our measure of hierarchical layers, respectively. Panel A considers the cross-section of firms using the last year in which the firm's corporate hierarchy is observed. Panel B considers all firm-year observations.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">In sample Out of sample</cell><cell>Diff.</cell><cell>s.e.</cell><cell>obs.</cell></row><row><cell>Assets</cell><cell>16626.42</cell><cell>5166.11</cell><cell cols="3">11460.30  *  *  *  (2471.57) 7,147</cell></row><row><cell>Total liabilities</cell><cell>13855.65</cell><cell>3823.59</cell><cell cols="3">10032.05  *  *  *  (2300.21) 7,138</cell></row><row><cell>PPE (net)</cell><cell>1413.81</cell><cell>811.69</cell><cell>602.12  *  *  *</cell><cell cols="2">(183.41) 6,980</cell></row><row><cell>Debt / equity</cell><cell>2.37</cell><cell>1.79</cell><cell>0.58  *  *  *</cell><cell>(0.09)</cell><cell>7,127</cell></row><row><cell>Cash</cell><cell>1581.45</cell><cell>400.10</cell><cell>1181.36  *  *  *</cell><cell cols="2">(388.86) 6,524</cell></row><row><cell>Cash / assets</cell><cell>0.25</cell><cell>0.25</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>6,480</cell></row><row><cell>Revenue (m)</cell><cell>4114.69</cell><cell>2461.89</cell><cell>1652.79  *  *  *</cell><cell cols="2">(429.23) 7,094</cell></row><row><cell>Net income</cell><cell>84.36</cell><cell>46.48</cell><cell>37.88  *  *  *</cell><cell>(6.17)</cell><cell>6,474</cell></row><row><cell>EBIT</cell><cell>636.69</cell><cell>297.26</cell><cell>339.42  *  *  *</cell><cell cols="2">(100.73) 6,472</cell></row><row><cell>Net income / revenue</cell><cell>-0.08</cell><cell>-0.10</cell><cell>0.02  *</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>4,879</cell></row><row><cell>ROA</cell><cell>-0.13</cell><cell>-0.36</cell><cell>0.23  *  *  *</cell><cell>(0.02)</cell><cell>6,265</cell></row><row><cell>Firms</cell><cell>3,128</cell><cell>4,019</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Regressions of the number of hierarchical layers on measures of firm size</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Industry fixed effects are based on 4-digit SIC industries. Standard errors, clustered at the firm level, are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively. Differences in hiring, promotions, and tenure</figDesc><table><row><cell>Log number of layers</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Industry fixed effects are based on 4-digit SIC industries. Size decile fixed effects are based on the firm's total assets in the previous year. Standard errors, clustered at the firm level, are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Employees</cell><cell cols="2">Tenure (log years)</cell><cell cols="2">ESOP? Internal</cell><cell>CEO</cell><cell>CEO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>% new</cell><cell cols="2">% promote Non-new</cell><cell>All</cell><cell></cell><cell>CEO</cell><cell>pay</cell><cell>pay ratio</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>(6)</cell><cell>(7)</cell><cell>(8)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">log # layers (t -1) -0.046  *  *  *</cell><cell>0.048  *  *  *</cell><cell>0.053  *  *</cell><cell cols="4">0.086  *  *  *  0.059  *  *  *  0.18  *  *  *  0.37  *  *  *</cell><cell>33.8  *  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0058)</cell><cell>(0.0052)</cell><cell>(0.024)</cell><cell>(0.026)</cell><cell>(0.019)</cell><cell cols="2">(0.053) (0.051)</cell><cell>(4.73)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>9,023</cell><cell>9,020</cell><cell>9,020</cell><cell>9,023</cell><cell>8,845</cell><cell>749</cell><cell>7,989</cell><cell>6,162</cell></row><row><cell># firms</cell><cell>1,354</cell><cell>1,354</cell><cell>1,354</cell><cell>1,354</cell><cell>1,685</cell><cell>571</cell><cell>1,125</cell><cell>1,554</cell></row><row><cell>Mean dep. var.</cell><cell>0.14</cell><cell>0.18</cell><cell>1.72</cell><cell>1.63</cell><cell>0.14</cell><cell>0.59</cell><cell>8.60</cell><cell>101.54</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.04</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.04</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.37</cell><cell>0.33</cell></row><row><cell>Size decile FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Industry FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Firm productivity and costs</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Industry fixed effects are based on 4-digit SIC industries. Size decile fixed effects are based on the firm's total assets in the previous year. Standard errors, clustered at the firm level, are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>ROA</cell><cell cols="3">Gross margin Net margin Rev/emp.</cell><cell>SG&amp;A</cell><cell>Wages</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>(6)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">log # layers (t -1) 0.0227  *  *  *</cell><cell>0.0700  *  *  *</cell><cell>0.339  *  *  *</cell><cell cols="3">-171.9  *  *  *  0.0804  *  *  *  0.0146  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.00679)</cell><cell>(0.0253)</cell><cell>(0.0705)</cell><cell>(21.95)</cell><cell cols="2">(0.00930) (0.00574)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>15,670</cell><cell>15,473</cell><cell>15,473</cell><cell>17,323</cell><cell>14,080</cell><cell>4,062</cell></row><row><cell># firms</cell><cell>2,670</cell><cell>2,883</cell><cell>2,883</cell><cell>2,882</cell><cell>2,658</cell><cell>625</cell></row><row><cell>Mean dep. var.</cell><cell>-0.02</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>-0.69</cell><cell>585.90</cell><cell>0.31</cell><cell>0.08</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.58</cell><cell>0.46</cell><cell>0.44</cell><cell>0.64</cell><cell>0.59</cell><cell>0.75</cell></row><row><cell>Within-R 2</cell><cell>0.25</cell><cell>0.04</cell><cell>0.11</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>0.31</cell><cell>0.11</cell></row><row><cell>Size decile FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Industry FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Acquisition activityThis table reports regression estimates using observations at the firm-year level. The dependent variable in column 1 is an indicator of whether the firm has an acquisition (of any type) in SDC during the year. Column 2 only considers acquisitions with reported valuations, which tend to be public targets or larger acquisitions. Column 3 reports Poisson estimates for the total number of acquisitions during the year. In column 4, the dependent variable is the logarithm of the sum of the reported valuations across all acquisitions made by the firm during the year. In column 5, the dependent variable is an indicator variable equal to one if the acquirer's primary SIC code in SDC does not match any of the SIC codes of the target. In all regressions, the right-hand side variable is "log # layers (t -1)," which is the logarithm of the number of hierarchical layers in the previous year. Industry fixed effects are based on 4-digit SIC industries. Size decile fixed effects are based on the firm's total assets in the previous year. Standard errors, clustered at the firm level, are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Acq.?</cell><cell cols="4">Acq. w/ # Acq. log( V ) Diversify?</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>value?</cell><cell>(all)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>log # layers (t -1)</cell><cell>0.010  *</cell><cell>0.0083  *  *</cell><cell>0.21  *</cell><cell>0.33  *  *</cell><cell>0.043</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(0.0055) (0.0042)</cell><cell>(0.11)</cell><cell>(0.14)</cell><cell>(0.042)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>18,489</cell><cell>18,489</cell><cell>11,656</cell><cell>998</cell><cell>1,689</cell></row><row><cell># firms</cell><cell>3,009</cell><cell>3,009</cell><cell>1,958</cell><cell>511</cell><cell>657</cell></row><row><cell>Mean dep. var.</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>0.24</cell><cell>4.80</cell><cell>0.62</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.37</cell><cell>0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Pseudo-R 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Model</cell><cell>OLS</cell><cell>OLS</cell><cell>Poisson</cell><cell>OLS</cell><cell>OLS</cell></row><row><cell>Size decile FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Industry FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Firm patenting</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Industry fixed effects are based on 4-digit SIC industries. Size decile fixed effects are based on the firm's total assets in the previous year. Standard errors, clustered at the firm level, are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively. Stock and firm volatility</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R&amp;D</cell><cell cols="2"># patents</cell><cell cols="2"># cites</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Poisson</cell><cell>IHS</cell><cell>Poisson</cell><cell>IHS</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">log # layers (t -1) 0.0053</cell><cell cols="2">2.44  *  *  *  0.19  *  *  *</cell><cell>0.29</cell><cell>0.13  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">(0.0069) (0.59) (0.032) (0.19) (0.070)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>10,325</cell><cell cols="2">13,479 16,462</cell><cell>2,597</cell><cell>2,650</cell></row><row><cell># firms</cell><cell>1,803</cell><cell>2,447</cell><cell>3,000</cell><cell>587</cell><cell>607</cell></row><row><cell>Mean dep. var.</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell>16.10</cell><cell>0.48</cell><cell>0.97</cell><cell>0.54</cell></row><row><cell>Pseudo-R 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.86</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.32</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.39</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.36</cell></row><row><cell>Size decile FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Industry FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Industry fixed effects are based on 4-digit SIC industries. Size decile fixed effects are based on the firm's total assets in the previous year. Standard errors, clustered at the firm level, are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively. Stock market performance of hierarchy-sorted portfolios</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Stock σ</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Operations and financial</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Wins.</cell><cell>σ(OA)</cell><cell>σ(CF)</cell><cell>Debt Assets</cell><cell>Cash Assets</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>(6)</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">log # layers (t -1) -0.042  *  *  *  -0.042  *  *  *  -0.051  *  *  *  -0.0038</cell><cell>0.015  *</cell><cell>-0.0060</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.010)</cell><cell>(0.0089)</cell><cell cols="4">(0.015) (0.0041) (0.0081) (0.0068)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>16,095</cell><cell>16,095</cell><cell>14,318</cell><cell>12,357</cell><cell>14,780</cell><cell>16,092</cell></row><row><cell># firms</cell><cell>2,766</cell><cell>2,766</cell><cell>2,750</cell><cell>2,269</cell><cell>2,638</cell><cell>2,991</cell></row><row><cell>Mean dep. var.</cell><cell>0.55</cell><cell>0.55</cell><cell>0.47</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>0.26</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.20</cell><cell>0.24</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell>0.10</cell></row><row><cell>Size decile FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Industry FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>* * -0.79 * * * -0.90 * * * -0.89 * * * -0.78 * * * Hierarchical layers in the pharmaceutical industry following Covid-19</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>(6)</cell></row><row><cell>α</cell><cell cols="2">-0.00020 -0.0026</cell><cell>-0.0033</cell><cell>-0.0024</cell><cell>-0.0026</cell><cell>-0.0031</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="6">(0.0039) (0.0027) (0.0027) (0.0025) (0.0027) (0.0026)</cell></row><row><cell>R m -r f</cell><cell>-0.084</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>0.090</cell><cell>0.10</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>0.085</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.11)</cell><cell>(0.069)</cell><cell>(0.068)</cell><cell>(0.065)</cell><cell>(0.072)</cell><cell>(0.067)</cell></row><row><cell>SMB</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.89  (0.090)</cell><cell>(0.11)</cell><cell>(0.090)</cell><cell>(0.093)</cell><cell>(0.12)</cell></row><row><cell>HML</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.090</cell><cell>-0.13  *</cell><cell>-0.035</cell><cell>-0.088</cell><cell>-0.057</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.076)</cell><cell>(0.075)</cell><cell>(0.14)</cell><cell>(0.078)</cell><cell>(0.15)</cell></row><row><cell>RMW</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.22  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.24  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.11)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.12)</cell></row><row><cell>CMA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.12</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.15</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.18)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.20)</cell></row><row><cell>Momentum</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.011</cell><cell>0.047</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.067)</cell><cell>(0.075)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>96</cell><cell>96</cell><cell>96</cell><cell>96</cell><cell>96</cell><cell>96</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>-0.01</cell><cell>0.53</cell><cell>0.54</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.53</cell></row></table><note><p>*  </p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Standard errors, clustered at the industry level (4-digit SIC), are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively. Firm response to AI: number of hierarchical layers</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Log # layers</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>(6)</cell></row><row><cell>Covid × Post</cell><cell>0.040  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.028  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.025  *  *</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0090)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0100)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Covid × 2017</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.019  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.0080</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.0068</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0090)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0085)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0097)</cell></row><row><cell>Covid × 2018</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.00069</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.00066</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.00044</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0058)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0048)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0056)</cell></row><row><cell>Covid × 2020</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.020  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.013  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.011  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0030)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0042)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0043)</cell></row><row><cell>Covid × 2022</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.034  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.022  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.020  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0055)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0077)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0079)</cell></row><row><cell>Covid × 2023</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.051  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.043  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.041  *  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0065)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0076)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0083)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>14,931</cell><cell>14,931</cell><cell>14,681</cell><cell>14,681</cell><cell>12,375</cell><cell>12,375</cell></row><row><cell># firms</cell><cell>2,827</cell><cell>2,827</cell><cell>2,809</cell><cell>2,809</cell><cell>2,364</cell><cell>2,364</cell></row><row><cell>Mean dep. var.</cell><cell>2.03</cell><cell>2.03</cell><cell>2.03</cell><cell>2.03</cell><cell>1.96</cell><cell>1.96</cell></row><row><cell>Within-R 2</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.04</cell><cell>0.04</cell></row><row><cell>Size decile FE?</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Firm FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Standard errors, clustered at the firm level, are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Log # layers</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell></row><row><cell>Share job postings AI</cell><cell>-0.61  *</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.34)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Share job postings AI (narrow)</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.75  *</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.40)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Average share (skills)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.68  *</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.36)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Avg max share</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.14  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.074)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell cols="3">5,505 5,505 5,505</cell><cell>5,505</cell></row><row><cell># firms</cell><cell cols="3">1,491 1,491 1,491</cell><cell>1,491</cell></row><row><cell>Mean dep. var.</cell><cell>2.41</cell><cell>2.41</cell><cell>2.41</cell><cell>2.41</cell></row><row><cell>Within R 2</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Size decile FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Firm FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The excluded quintile (base group) is the bottommost quintile. Size decile fixed effects are based on the firm's total assets in the previous year. Standard errors, clustered at the firm level, are reported in parentheses. *, **, and *** denotes significance at the 10%, 5%, and 1% level, respectively.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Joined t -1 to t</cell><cell cols="2">Joined t -2 to t</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell></row><row><cell>Quintile 2</cell><cell cols="4">-0.029  *  *  *  -0.029  *  *  *  -0.081  *  *  *  -0.081  *  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0028)</cell><cell>(0.0028)</cell><cell>(0.0084)</cell><cell>(0.0084)</cell></row><row><cell>Quintile 3</cell><cell cols="2">-0.038  *  *  *  -0.038  *  *  *</cell><cell>-0.11  *  *  *</cell><cell>-0.11  *  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0022)</cell><cell>(0.0022)</cell><cell>(0.0073)</cell><cell>(0.0074)</cell></row><row><cell>Quintile 4</cell><cell cols="2">-0.041  *  *  *  -0.041  *  *  *</cell><cell>-0.11  *  *  *</cell><cell>-0.11  *  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0034)</cell><cell>(0.0034)</cell><cell>(0.015)</cell><cell>(0.016)</cell></row><row><cell>Quintile 5</cell><cell cols="2">-0.050  *  *  *  -0.050  *  *  *</cell><cell>-0.15  *  *  *</cell><cell>-0.15  *  *  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0034)</cell><cell>(0.0034)</cell><cell>(0.014)</cell><cell>(0.014)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell cols="4">1,502,037 1,493,506 1,657,456 1,648,142</cell></row><row><cell># workers</cell><cell cols="4">1,258,578 1,252,008 1,303,957 1,298,748</cell></row><row><cell># firms</cell><cell>1,692</cell><cell>1,692</cell><cell>1,693</cell><cell>1,693</cell></row><row><cell>Mean dep. var.</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>0.33</cell><cell>0.32</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Firm FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Size decile FE?</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE?</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>An earlier formulation of a similar methodology is found in<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baker, Gibbs, and Holmstrom (1994)</ref>.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1"><p>What follows is a high-level summary of their method. Interested readers should consult<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Huitfeldt, Kostøl, Nimczik, and Weber (2023)</ref> for more details.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_2"><p>See https://coresignal.com/.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Our data cleaning of the LinkedIn data removes extremely rare titles and transitions that would have very high rank uncertainty and thus have large impacts on the layer partition.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Due to this criterion, we lose over 150 firms when we implement the algorithm because there are too few transitions between jobs in the resume data.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_5"><p>We need to start in 2017 because a transition is measured relative to the previous year.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_6"><p>The exception is<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adhvaryu, Bassi, Nyshadham, Tamayo, and Torres (2023)</ref>, who identify 16 layers in their study of an Argentinean automotive working group.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_7"><p>This measure is constructed as follows. Suppose a firm has K layers and βij is the share of employees in layer j for firm i. Hierarchization is then 1 -K j=1 β 2 ij . Thus, a flat firm has a value of 0 and a firm with equal shares across K layers approaches 1 as K increases.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_8"><p>Note that we may still detect meaningful changes in the aggregate, given the changing number of public firms over the sample period.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="11" xml:id="foot_9"><p>In Appendix FigureA1, as well as all other figures in which we plot layer-by-layer statistics for groups of firms with the same number of layers, we consider firms whose number of layers is between 4 and 14. These cutoffs correspond to the 25th and 75th percentiles of the distribution of the number of layers across all firms in our sample.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_10"><p>Relatedly, Hart and Moore (2005)  shows that the pyramidal form is optimal.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_11"><p>Note that the pattern is not monotonic. Toward the top of the hierarchy, the share of managers decreases, which likely reflects the different terminology used to refer to upper-echelon managerial roles (e.g., "director," "president").</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="14" xml:id="foot_12"><p>We obtain qualitatively similar results throughout if the size decile fixed effects are based on the number of employees. We also obtain similar results if we include age decile fixed effects, where age is measured as the number of years since the firm went public.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="15" xml:id="foot_13"><p>Since the employees' educational histories are sometimes unreported or incomplete, this analysis is based on a smaller sample.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="18" xml:id="foot_14"><p>The IHS(y) transform is preferred over the log(y) transform as it behaves similarly to the logarithm but allows to retain zero-valued observations without having to arbitrarily rescale y in the logarithm operator (e.g., by adding one). See<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bellemare and Wichman (2019)</ref> for more details.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="19" xml:id="foot_15"><p>In additional analyses, we considered other proxies for patent quality such as novelty and the number of right-tail patents. We found no significant differences in these measures between firms with different hierarchical layers.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="20" xml:id="foot_16"><p>Note that the point estimate for cash flow volatility is not significant at conventional levels. However, since this metric is based on the standard deviation of only four quarterly cash flows (from Compustat's quarterly file), it is inherently noisy, which limits our ability to detect a statistically significant relationship, even if one exists.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="21" xml:id="foot_17"><p>Consistent with this interpretation, when looking at analysts' EPS (earnings per share) forecasts from the IBES (Institutional Brokers' Estimate System) database, we find no evidence that analysts systematically over-or under-estimate the performance of high-vs. low-layer firms.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="23" xml:id="foot_18"><p>Note that, since the treatment assignment is at the industry level, we cluster standard errors along this dimension (4-digit SIC).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="24" xml:id="foot_19"><p>The only exception is the 2017 pre-treatment coefficient in column 2. However, this estimate is not robust. Once we account for size decile fixed effects in column 4 and the finer control group in column 6, the corresponding estimate is small and insignificant.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="25" xml:id="foot_20"><p>One potential concern with this analysis is that, as pharmaceutical firms hire more employees to accommodate the demand for vaccines, this might mechanically trigger a higher number of layers. However, when we re-run the regressions in Table11controlling for contemporaneous changes in employment, we find that the point estimates remain large and statistically significant. That is, the increase in the number of layers is not merely reflecting an increase in the firms' workforce.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="26" xml:id="foot_21"><p>The evidence in Table12is related to the finding of<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Babina, Fedyk, He, and Hodson (2025)</ref> that firms with more AI postings tend to have a higher share of employees in junior vs. senior positions. To the extent that flatter hierarchies have a higher share of junior positions, their finding is consistent with our evidence.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="28" xml:id="foot_22"><p>Some of the largest and well-known investment banks are also in the data. We find that the ranking of investment bank titles and layers behaves similarly to these two examples. However, the expansive set of noninvestment bank roles with similar titles makes it challenging to create a clean sample for a narrow analysis of one job role.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This table reports the most common titles across all firms and years in their top layer (left-hand panel) and bottom layer (right-hand panel). We rely on LinkedIn's representativeness regarding title distribution and promotion reporting.</p><p>Ideally, we could compare a firm's final corporate hierarchy-the number of layers and titles within each-to a self-reported organizational chart. Those charts are unfortunately unavailable in any 10-K filing that we have searched or on company websites. Instead, we explore an industry with a fairly standardized job ladder for a major job role: investment banks and bankers. The titles in this career path should be ranked as expected and be separated into different hierarchical layers.</p><p>The exercise proceeds in three steps. Firstly, we identify the titles and rank ordering of investment banking career paths of investment banks. Next, we assess whether these titles (i) have the expected ranks in our data and (ii) are separated into different layers. Thirdly, we consider only the individuals with investment banking roles and re-run the ranking and clustering algorithm. This final step is a check for whether the data and algorithm can see the hierarchy without different firm roles. We implement this test on Jeffries and Lazard. 28</p><p>Jeffries' investment bank titles are analyst, associate, director, and president. The data correctly ranks these roles with analyst at the bottom and president at the top. In the final data, 74% of titles with "analyst" are in the first layer (as expected). The remaining 26% include operations, business, and other non-banking analysts in the second layer. Most individuals (87%) with "associate" in their title are in the eighth layer. The large gap between analysts and associates is because of the rich set of roles at the lower layers in the firm that are not directly working in banking. Indeed, when we narrow the set of analyst jobs to those with clear investment banking roles (step 3), the associates are in layer three. We find directors are in layer 9 (one above associates) and presidents in layer 10. After conditioning on investment banking roles, these layers are five and six. Thus, the data and clustering algorithm correctly ranks and separates the investment bankers. We repeated the same exercise for Lazard and found similar results. Most importantly, when we condition on investment bankers and rerun the algorithm, Lazard has five layers with "analyst" at the lowest level and "president" at the top.</p><p>This figure reports the average number of years that a promoted worker spends in a given layer before the promotion. Each line represents a group of firms with the same number of layers (i.e., longer lines correspond to groups of firms with more layers). The figure includes firms in our sample whose number of layers is between 4 and 14, which corresponds to the interquartile range across all firms.</p><p>This figure reports the average number of years in a role for all workers who switch roles within the firm over the sample period. The averages are reported within a layer quintile. Each line represents a different group of firms that has the same total number of layers.   </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Achyuta</forename><surname>Adhvaryu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vittorio</forename><surname>Bassi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anant</forename><surname>Nyshadham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jorge</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tamayo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicolas</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Organizational responses to product cycles, NBER Working Paper 31582</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production, information costs, and economic organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Armen</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alchian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harold</forename><surname>Demsetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="777" to="795" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Value creation from M&amp;As: New evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Alexandridis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Nikolaos Antypas, and Nickolaos Travlos</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="632" to="650" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matching patents to Compustat firms, 1980-2015: Dynamic reassignment, name changes, and ownership structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ashish</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sharon</forename><surname>Belenzon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lia</forename><surname>Sheer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 104217</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Artificial intelligence, firm growth, and product innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tania</forename><surname>Babina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anastassia</forename><surname>Fedyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alex</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Hodson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103745</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Firm investments in artificial intelligence technologies and changes in workforce composition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tania</forename><surname>Babina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anastassia</forename><surname>Fedyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alex</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Hodson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">NBER Volume on Technology, Productivity, and Economic Growth</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Susanto</forename><surname>Basu</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lucy</forename><surname>Eldridge</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Haltiwanger</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erich</forename><surname>Strassner</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="117" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The internal economics of the firm: Evidence from personnel data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Gibbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bengt</forename><surname>Holmstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="881" to="919" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Internal labor markets: Too many theories, too few facts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bengt</forename><surname>Holmstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="259" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elasticities and the inverse hyperbolic sine transformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marc</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bellemare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Casey</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wichman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does going public affect innovation?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shai</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1365" to="1403" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Going public and the internal organization of the firm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Bias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><surname>Lochner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Obernberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Merih</forename><surname>Sevilir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Working Paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The organization of firms across countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Raffaella</forename><surname>Sadun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Van Reenen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1663" to="1705" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The firm as a communication network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><surname>Bolton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mathias</forename><surname>Dewatripont</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="809" to="839" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discretizing unobserved heterogeneity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stéphane</forename><surname>Bonhomme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thibaut</forename><surname>Lamadon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><surname>Manresa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="643" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Productivity and organization in Portuguese firms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lorenzo</forename><surname>Caliendo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4211" to="4257" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The anatomy of French production hierarchies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monte</forename><surname>Ferdinando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Esteban</forename><surname>Rossi-Hansberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="809" to="852" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of trade on organization and productivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lorenzo</forename><surname>Caliendo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Esteban</forename><surname>Rossi-Hansberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1393" to="1467" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supervision, loss of control, and the optimum size of the firm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Guillermo</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Calvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stanislaw</forename><surname>Wellisz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="991" to="1010" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978. 1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Political Economy</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic inequality and hierarchy in faculty hiring networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aaron</forename><surname>Clauset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Samuel</forename><surname>Arbesman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Larremore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Advances</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1400005</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Too many managers: The strategic use of titles to avoid overtime payments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lauren</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Umit</forename><surname>Gurun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Bugra</forename><surname>Ozel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">NBER Working Paper 30826</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Corporate takeovers and economic efficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Eckbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Espen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Financial Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Ewens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matt</forename><surname>Marx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Startup patents</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Working Paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ewens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ryan</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Michael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sean</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Measuring intangible capital with market prices</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="427" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How valuable is financial flexibility when revenue stops? Evidence from the COVID-19 crisis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rüdiger</forename><surname>Fahlenbrach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Rageth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">René</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Financial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5474" to="5521" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Choosing factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eugene</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Fama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kenneth</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>French</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trade shocks, firm hierarchies, and wage inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Friedrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="652" to="667" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchies and the organization of knowledge in production</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luis</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Garicano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hubbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Law, Economics, and Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="653" to="684" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Political Economy</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organization and inequality in a knowledge economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luis</forename><surname>Garicano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Esteban</forename><surname>Rossi-Hansberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1383" to="1435" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchies and the division of labor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luis</forename><surname>Garicano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><surname>Van Zandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Organizational Economics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Gibbons</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="604" to="654" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Playing it safe? Managerial preferences, risk, and agency conflicts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Todd</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gormley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Matsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who lives in the C-suite? Organizational structure and the division of labor in top management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Guadalupe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hongyi</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julie</forename><surname>Wulf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="824" to="844" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The flattening firm and product market competition: The effect of trade liberalization on corporate hierarchies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Guadalupe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julie</forename><surname>Wulf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Journal: Applied Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Firm organization with multiple establishments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Gumpert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Henrike</forename><surname>Steimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Manfred</forename><surname>Antoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1091" to="1138" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the design of hierarchies: Coordination versus specialization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oliver</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="675" to="702" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Internal labor markets: A worker flow approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><surname>Huitfeldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kostøl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Nimczik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">233</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="688" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The productivity effects of employee stock-ownership plans and bonuses: Evidence from Japanese panel data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Derek</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Takao</forename><surname>Kato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="414" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technological innovation, resource allocation, and growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leonid</forename><surname>Kogan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dimitris</forename><surname>Papanikolaou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amit</forename><surname>Seru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Noah</forename><surname>Stoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="665" to="712" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Internal and external labor markets: A personnel economics approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edward</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lazear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Oyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Labour Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="554" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rank-order tournaments as optimum labor contracts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edward</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lazear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sherwin</forename><surname>Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="864" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the effect of hierarchies on information use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jose</forename><surname>Liberti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Atif</forename><surname>Mian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Financial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4057" to="4090" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Work incentives, hierarchy, and internal labor markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Malcomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="507" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information flows, organizational structure, and corporate governance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nadya</forename><surname>Malenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Corporate Finance</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Denis</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Edward Elgar Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="546" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fitter, flatter, faster: How unstructuring your organization can unlock massive value</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mckinsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">McKinsey &amp; Company</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-08-24">2020. August 24, 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incentives and loss of control in an optimal hierarchy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yingyi</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="544" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The organization of decentralized information processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roy</forename><surname>Radner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1109" to="1146" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The flattening firm: Evidence from panel data on the changing nature of corporate hierarchies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Raghuram</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julie</forename><surname>Wulf</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="759" to="773" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2012. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Finance</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authority, control, and the distribution of earnings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sherwin</forename><surname>Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bell Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="323" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How organizational hierarchy affects information production</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Janis</forename><surname>Skrastins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vikrant</forename><surname>Vig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Financial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="564" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information production and capital allocation: Decentralized versus hierarchical firms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeremy</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1891" to="1921" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What determines productivity?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chad</forename><surname>Syverson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic literature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="365" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchies and entrepreneurship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joacim</forename><surname>Tag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Astebro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Job assignments, signalling, and efficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Waldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RAND Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchical control and optimum firm size</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oliver</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
