<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">D R A F T</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-07-28">July 28, 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Nusrat</forename><surname>Molla</surname></persName>
							<email>nusrat.molla@princeton.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elke</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 45 46 47 48 49 50 51 52 53 54 55 56 57 58 59</addrLine>
									<postCode>60 61 62</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Environment</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Princeton University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<address>
									<postBox>125 126 127 128 129 130 131 132 133 134 135 136 137 138 139 140 141 142 143 144 145 146 147 148 149 150 151 152 153 154 155 156 157 158 159 160 161 162 163 164 165 166 167 168 169 170 171 172 173 174 175 176 177 178 179 180 181 182 183 184 185 186</postBox>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">D R A F T</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-07-28">July 28, 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">22015EE4665AE92BF6AC2BAD2F96D338</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:55+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Communities reliant on extractive industries face a paradox: despite the promise of economic growth from lucrative, well-paying industries, they often experience poor socio-economic outcomes. While the so-called "resource curse" has been debated and studied extensively in a variety of disciplines, understanding when and why the resource curse occurs, and whether it is possible to escape it, remains a challenge. This study examines these questions through a dynamical systems model that incorporates theories from the literature about how extractive industries interact with institutions and the communities in which they're based. The model reveals that both the resource curse and a more diversified economy are possible, depending on the initial level of community capital. It also reveals how various factors, such as declining commodity prices, can trigger an abrupt and irreversible transition from the diversified equilibrium to the resource curse. A generalized version of the model further suggests that socio-political dynamics are critical in determining the occurrence of this type of transition. The results illustrate the difficulty of escaping the resource curse, identify potential leverage points or change, and highlight the critical role of institutional dynamics in producing and perpetuating extractive dynamics in these regions. Sustainable development | Critical transitions | resource curse | institutions</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>F rom the oil wells of Nigeria, Venezuela, and the Congo to the United States' Appalachian coalfields and the Canadian tar sands, the regions and countries from which fossil fuels and other raw materials that fuel modern life are extracted are diverse but tend to share a common dilemma: despite the incredible wealth generated by these enterprises and the promise of economic development often pitched by extractive industries, the purported long-term economic benefits of extractive industries often fail to materialize. Instead, these regions face not only environmental destruction and adverse health impacts, but also higher poverty rates and slower economic growth <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(3)</ref>. Understanding this contradiction, often referred to as the "resource curse", why it occurs in some contexts and not others, and whether it can be reversed, remains an open challenge <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(4)</ref>. This is in large part because extractive industries are deeply intertwined with the development of the regions in which they are based, leading to two-way feedbacks that the disciplines typically studying this phenomena are ill-suited to account for. Understanding the complex interactions between extractive industries and communities gains particular importance as the energy transition is poised to shift the geography of extraction, and the many places economically reliant on fossil-fuel extraction face the prospects of economic decline and depopulation, while the drive for critical minerals opens up new frontiers of extraction. This study offers a new approach to understanding this phenomena through a stylized model formalizing theories about the socio-political feedbacks associated with extractive industries.</p><p>The resource curse has long been studied in a variety of disciplines, including economics, political science, sociology, and geography. The main explanations for the resource curse center either on how extractive industries interact with non-extractive sectors of the economy, or on how they interact with institutions. The first class of theories, based mostly in the macroeconomic literature, focuses on the "crowding out" effect of extractive industries, where they divert resources from activities that support long-run growth, especially during resource booms <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(5)</ref>. Similarly, the over-adaptation hypothesis suggests that resource-extracting regions become excessively adapted to a certain form of extraction, making them unable to adapt to changing circumstances <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6)</ref>. Therefore, when the extractive industry shuts down, the region may be left with specialized infrastructure that is not useful for other types of economic</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Significance Statement</head><p>Many places that rely on extractive industries experience long-term economic and social harm, despite the wealth these industries bring. This paradox-known as the "resource curse"-is widespread, but why it occurs in some regions and not others remains unclear. This study presents a theoretical model capturing feedbacks between extractive industries, communities, and institutions. It reveals how communities often become trapped in extraction-dependent economies as industries decline, but also identifies opportunities for escape if action is taken earlier. These findings shed new light on the structural dynamics that entrench the resource curse and highlight the critical role of institutions in enabling more resilient and diversified economic futures for affected communities.</p><p>activity and ancillary businesses that are no longer linked to anything <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6)</ref>. This specialization is exacerbated by the high wages paid by extractive industries, which discourages workers from local entrepreneurship or pursuing further education or training <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6)</ref>.</p><p>The other class of theories centers on how resource extraction interacts with institutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">8)</ref>. While there is a consensus on the need for strong institutions in order to prevent the resource curse <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">9)</ref>, whether the presence of extractive industries itself influences the strength of institutions has been a matter of debate, with some arguing that extractive industries undermine the development of strong institutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7)</ref>. For example, the point-source nature of natural resources like minerals is hypothesized to make them easily controlled by small groups, leading to inequality and rentier effects in which resource rents allow governments to avoid accountability and silence critics and maintain power through patronage or repression <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10)</ref>. The micro-scale impact of extractive industries on institutions, including informal institutions has also been well documented in rural sociology, with a focus on the social disruption and fragmentation of community relationships and institutions caused by extractive industries. For example, the influx of workers during resource booms can lead to a strain on existing services and infrastructure, and social tensions and conflict with existing residents, altering community dynamics and cultural norms <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(13)</ref>. The introduction of powerful external actors such as multinational corporations and government agencies, can reshape local power structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15)</ref>. Additionally, the economic benefits of resource extraction are often unequally distributed, leading to increased economic inequality and social stratification within a community <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(16)</ref>. In the long term, extractive industries can be powerful not only economically, but also in shaping a community's culture and norms. The fact that these industries typically employ a large proportion of workers in the community, and often multiple generations of workers, and the often long hours and harsh conditions characterizing the work, means that these industries can become embedded in the social fabric and identity of a community <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18)</ref>. This tendency is often exploited by extractive industries, which actively amplify the centrality of extraction to the identity of a community or region to maintain power even as their economic importance may be declining <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20)</ref>.</p><p>While these theories are supported by decades of empirical research, the heterogeneity of contexts and multi-dimensional nature of the resource curse means that understanding why the resource curse occurs in some contexts and not others, and whether it is possible to escape once caught in the resource curse, remains a challenge. The macroeconomics and and political-economic literature, in relying on regression analyses and meta-analyses, offer generalizable insight, but are limited to measuring uni-directional impacts and thus struggle with complex feedbacks, such as the one between institutions and extraction, that make it difficult to determine cause and effect. Qualitative case studies, which offer insights into complex dynamics in a contextualized manner, but can be challenging to extend to the diverse contexts in which these communities exist throughout the world. Complex systems models can incorporate the complex feedbacks that generate qualitatively different outcomes in different contexts, allowing them to build on existing contextual, qualitative work while contributing to more general theories about when and why the resource curse occurs. Such models exist for understanding numerous other socio-political phenomena, such as the development and maintenance of institutions for managing the commons in small-scale agriculture <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22)</ref> and escaping the "poverty trap" <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24)</ref>. Yet, the resource curse, despite its ubiquity throughout the world, numerous theories in multiple disciplines, and its importance in determining the development of entire regions and nations, has not received the same attention from modelers. Existing models of communities reliant on extractive industries address aspects of them, such as the migratory and boom-bust dynamics of these communities <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(25)</ref> and the co-existence of extractive industries with other resource-based livelihoods <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(26)</ref>. However, the mechanisms leading to the resource curse have yet to be formalized in a mathematical model. By incorporating existing theories about the underlying dynamics of how extractive industries interact with institutions into a complex systems model, this study allows for systematically exploring prospects for extraction-dependent places to break the resource curse and transition towards more diversified, equitable, and sustainable forms of development.</p><p>This study proceeds in two main parts: 1) Developing and analyzing a dynamical systems model linking extractive industries, community capital, institutional strength, and economic diversity to understand the possible long-term outcomes, or equilibria, generated by these dynamics, and the conditions under which the system can transition between these equilibria, and 2) Analyzing a more general version of the model from the first section to verify that results are robust to different model structures, and identify the processes that are most influential in determining whether the resource curse occurs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>Dynamical systems modeling allows for modeling complex feedbacks by mathematically operationalizing how key variables in a system evolve over time through interaction with each other. These variables that track the state of the system over time are called state variables, and their interdependencies are often visualized through causal loop diagrams like in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref> and mathematically operationalized through a system of ordinary differential equations.</p><p>This study focuses on the feedback at the heart of explanations of the resource curse: extractive industries shape communities' natural, human, and social capital, in both positive and negative ways, which in turn shapes the prospects for non-extractive sectors and livelihoods to prosper (crowding out and overadaptation hypotheses). The ways and extent in which extractive industries impact communities are mediated by institutions, but the quality or strength of these institutions is itself influenced by how dominant the extractive industry is (institutional quality hypotheses). Thus, a positive feedback loop, or lock-in effect, can occur with the extractive industry becoming more economically dominant, weakening the institutions that would regulate them, allowing them to become or remain profitable and further entrenching their dominance.</p><p>This dynamic is operationalized in a model with three state variables: extractive industry capital (K), community capital (C), and the population working in non-extractive industries (Ln). These variables interact with each other through intermediary variables, such as economic diversity and institutional quality. Each of the state variables and the processes associated with them is described in more detail below and depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>.</p><p>Extractive Industry Capital and Production. The dynamics of extractive industry capital are modeled similarly to the formulation in Lopez 2010, with investment increasing proportional to the profit and depreciating at a fixed rate, with the added dynamic of institutions imposing a cost on extractive industries and thus reducing their profit. Thus, the extractive industry capital K, in dollars, is modeled by</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">K = ϕ ∂Q ∂K 1 -I Ln Ln + Lm -µK, [1a]</formula><p>where ϕ is the rate of capital reallocation ($/time), Q is the profit before the costs imposed by taxes and regulations, Lm is the extractive industry labor (in number of workers), Ln is the labor in a non-extractive industry (in number of workers), and µ is the depreciation rate. In another departure from Lopez 2010, we use the derivative of the profit with respect to K to represent firms acting on the expected profit rather than the current profit.</p><p>The feedback between extractive industries and institutions is captured abstractly through I (dimensionless), representing the fraction of extractive industry profits captured by the community through taxes and regulations. Rather than modeling a specific mechanism through which extractive industries undermine institutional strength (i.e. rentier effects, social disruption), I, is directly a function of economic diversity, or the fraction of the workforce in a non-extractive industry fn = Ln Ln + Lm . Lower economic diversity, corresponding with the extractive industry being more dominant economically and politically and fewer interests to contest it, leads to weaker institutions. Thus, a lower cost is imposed on the industry, leading to increased mining activity, creating a positive feedback loop.</p><p>In the specific model, I is modeled as a linear function of the economic diversity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">I = bfn,</formula><p>where b ≤ 1 is a constant factor. Production is modeled using a Leontief production function,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">P = a • min K, Lm ψ , where</formula><p>Lm is mining labor, and ψ is the ratio of labor to capital. Because extractive industries pay high wages compared to other rural livelihoods and rely on a fairly mobile workforce, we assume that K will be the limiting factor to production, and that the dynamics of the mining labor move more quickly than the dynamics in the model so that mining always has the necessary labor. Hence, Lm = ψK and P = aK. The pre-tax profit, Q, then simplifies to</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Q = paK -wLm,</formula><p>where a is the factor productivity of input capital, p is the price of the extracted resource, w is the wage. Assuming the mining industry is not anticipating the institutional dynamics modeled here, changes in mining investment are based on the marginal gain in profit (pre-tax) of additional investment ∂Q ∂K , which makes</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">K = ϕ ((pa -wψ) (1 -bfn)) -µK. [1b]</formula><p>Community Capital. The extractive industry is linked to the rest of the local economy in part through its impact on community capital. Community capital encompasses the natural, social, human, financial, and built capital that is critical for successful communities <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28)</ref>. Natural capital encompasses the environmental assets and ecosystem services present in a community, such as land, water, biodiversity, and scenic beauty, whereas cultural capital reflects the shared values, traditions, and identities that shape how community members interact and make decisions. Human capital refers to the skills, knowledge, health, and leadership capacity of individuals. Social capital denotes the networks, trust, and norms that facilitate cooperation and collective action. Financial capital comprises the monetary resources available for investment and development. Built capital includes the physical infrastructure that supports community activities, such as transportation, utilities, and buildings. Especially in the remote places where natural resources extraction typically takes place, extractive industries have enormous influence on each of these dimensions of community capital. The environmental damage they cause has long-term impacts on soil and water quality and dramatic effects on the landscape and scenic beauty of a region. As noted earlier, they also have a significant influence on human and social capital, such as by disrupting existing social networks with an influx of workers during a resource boom <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(15)</ref>, and due to their high wages with little educational requirements, dis-incentivizing developing education and other forms of human capital <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6)</ref>. However, with strong institutions in place, they can also benefit community capital. Tax revenue from extractive industries is often used to fund education, and they often build roads and other infrastructure necessary for the development of other industries <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(29)</ref>. Thus the ability to capture the benefits of extractive industries while mitigating their impacts on community capital is critical in shaping prospects for alternative development pathways in the future. These different dimensions of how mining impacts community capital (in $) are modeled by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Ċ = -F (P ) + G (I(fn) • (pP -wψK)) + H(Ln) -δC, [2a]</formula><p>where F represents the damage from extraction as a function of production, P , G represents the contribution of extractive industries to community capital, based on the proportion of profit transferred to the community through I, H represents the contribution of non-extractive industries to C, and δ represents a decay/depreciation rate. The net effect of the extractive industry on community capital thus results from the balance between the inevitable destructive impacts of the industry and the benefits that are able to be captured from the industry based on the strength of institutions. Thus, in the case of weak institutions, this captures the "crowding out" and over-adaptation effects of extractive industries. Each of the functions in Equation 2a is currently modeled as a linear function, making where η, b, and α represent scalings on the loss due to extractive industries, gain from transferring wealth from extractive industries, and gain from non-extractive industries, respectively.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Ċ = -ηaK + τ bfn(apK -wψK) + αLn -δC, [2b] D R A F T</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Non-Extractive Industry Labor and Population Dynamics.</head><p>The extractive industry is also linked to the rest of the local economy through the distribution of workers. Workers in the community move between working in the extractive industry, in non-extractive industries, and leaving the region altogether based on the opportunities or payoff associated with each of the options at the time, in line with assumptions in prior models of migration <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">31)</ref>. The flows of workers between these options is modeled based on evolutionary game theory approaches for modeling how agents switch between options based on pairwise comparisons of their fitness <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(32)</ref>. Since community capital is important in shaping the types of non-extractive sectors that emerge -higher levels of human and social capital, for example, may lead to more white collar jobs -the individual payoff from working in it is assumed to be a function of C (denoted by E(C)). As noted earlier, the extractive industry always satisfies its labor needs, so the extractive industry labor is determined by the mining capital. The non-extractive labor dynamics is modeled as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">Ln = Ln [c1Lm [E(C) -w] + c2 [E(C) -π] -c3Ln] , [3a]</formula><p>where π is the payoff that can be expected outside of the community and c1, c2, and c3 are constants associated with the rates of flows between the non-extractive industry and extractive industry, external opportunities, and unemployment, respectively. The individual payoff from working in a non-extractive industry, E(C), is assumed to be a linear function of C, making Ln = Ln (c1ψK(λC -w) + c2(λC -π) -c3Ln) .</p><p>[3b] System Summary. This makes the overall system</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">K = ϕ (pa -wψ) 1 -b Ln Ln + ψK -µK, Ċ = -ηaK + τ b Ln Ln + ψK (apK -wψK) + αLn -δC, Ln = Ln (c1ψK(λC -w) + c2(λC -π) -c3Ln) .</formula><p>and the corresponding partially generalized model  </p><formula xml:id="formula_9">K = ϕ ∂ ∂K ρP (K, Lm(K)) -wLm(K) [1 -I(fn)] -µK, Ċ = -F (P ) + G (I(fn) • (pP -wψK)) + H(Ln) -δC Ln = Ln [c1Lm(K) [E(C) -w] + c2 [E(C) -π] -c3Ln] .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>For feasible parameterizations, the system exhibits up to two possible stable equilibria: one in which the extractive industry dominates with weak institutions and no community physical/natural infrastructure or non-extractive industries, and one in which the extractive industry exists at lower levels alongside non-extractive industries, stronger institutions and community physical/natural infrastructure (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>). The first equilibrium demonstrates all of the qualities of the resource curse: the initial rise in community natural and physical capital from gain from the extractive industry is quickly reversed as institutions are weakened and the community bears most of the damage rather than the benefits from the extractive industry. While the total absence of non- extractive industries is unlikely since extractive industries are usually accompanied by auxiliary industries, this equilibrium represents the crowding out effect of the extractive industry on industries that can independently sustain themselves and communities after the decline of the extractive industry.</p><p>The second equilibrium, on the other hand, represents an alternative to the resource curse in which the maintenance of strong institutions throughout the expansion of the extractive industries ensures that the benefits of the extractive industry are used to develop non-extractive industries, fulfilling the promise of economic development that extractive industries often make. Crucially, extraction takes place at lower levels in this scenario because of the higher costs imposed on it. As revealed by the phase portraits (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3b</ref>) and visualization of the basin of attractions for the two equilibria (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>), once there is a sufficiently high level of economic activity, whether extractive or non-extractive, the initial community capital is the main important determinant of whether a community will reach the diversified equilibrium. Unsurprisingly, communities with initially high community capital reach the diversified equilibrium, suggesting that the communities most in need of the economic development promised by extractive industries are least likely to have that promise fulfilled <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6)</ref>.</p><p>Crucially, this bistability is only possible when taking into account the feedback between the economic dominance of the extractive industry and the institutional strength. Making the transfer of wealth between the mining industry and community capital based on a fixed parameter scaling rather than a function of economic diversity, for example, leads to a single equilibrium (see Supplementary Information). This reinforces the necessity of taking into account the underlying institutional dynamics of extractive industries to understand how they entrench themselves in the resource curse, as well as how alternative outcomes can arise. changes as parameters change, allowing understanding how the system responds to exogenous perturbations or shocks. The bifurcation diagrams reveal that at certain parameter values the diversified equilibrium loses stability through a fold or saddle-node bifurcation (see Supplementary Information for calculation of the system equilibria). For example, as the price of the extracted resource declines -as may be expected if the demand declines -the diversified equilibrium loses stability (Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>). This leads the system to experience a sudden transition to the resource curse equilibrium. The resource curse equilibrium, on the other hand, remains stable even as the parameter returns to its original value, leading the transition to be irreversible. While it may seem unintuitive that lower commodity prices would lead to the extractive industry becoming more dominant, reduced profits by the extractive industry also means reduced contributions to community physical and natural infrastructure, reducing prospects for non-extractive industry as well and leading to low economic diversity and weak institutions. In practice, this manifests as industries extracting concessions in the form of tax breaks or loosening of regulations from communities that are desperate to avoid mine or plant closures and mass layoffs (6). Freudenberg's 1992 landmark paper on the addictive tendencies of communities reliant on extractive industries gives such an example of a community in remote northwestern Colorado that successfully ensured that the shale oil, and later coal, industries in the area would bear the costs of development and minimize environmental impact. This approach -an illustration of the diversified equilibrium -allowed the community to withstand the commodity price shocks of the late 1980s that ravaged many other rural communities. However, just a decade later as the industry was overall becoming less profitable in the region, this same community agreed to cover a significant portion of the developer's costs in the hopes of turning a marginal investment into a profitable one <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6)</ref>. Thus, it is precisely when extractive industries are in decline and it is most important for communities to develop diversified livelihoods that they are least able to. Looking at how the basins of attraction for the two equilibria (Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>) paints a more hopeful picture, however. The basin of attraction indicates the resilience of different stable equilibria to perturbations. For higher values of the price, the basin of attraction for the resource curse equilibrium is much narrower than that of the diversified equilibrium, meaning that there is a smaller range of initial conditions leading to the resource curse equilibrium and small stochastic perturbations can push the system to the diversified equilibrium. The basin of attraction for the diversified equilibrium does narrow as the system approaches the bifurcation point, as is common close to a critical transition. Overall though, under the conditions in which the diversified equilibrium is stable, there is a high chance of reaching that equilibrium or perturbing the system from the resource curse equilibrium to the diversified equilibrium.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bifurcation diagrams show how the stability landscape</head><p>As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>, a critical transition occurs within the range of feasible parameter values for most of the parameters in the model. In addition to when the price drops, this transition occurs when the scaling of the damage to community capital with extraction increases (6a), suggesting, unsurprisingly, that more damaging forms of extraction contribute to the resource curse, through, for example, undermining other land-based industries like farming. The transition is also triggered when wages increase (6c), making working in the extractive industry more attractive than alternatives. This paradoxical effect of well-paying jobs in extractive industries holds up in the empirical literature, where the ability to make high wages with no higher education </p><formula xml:id="formula_10">1 2<label>3 1) 2) 3)</label></formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>. Illustrative bifurcation diagram with respect to the commodity price (p). The dashed line indicates an unstable equilibrium while the solid lines represent stable equilibria. The arrows denote which equilibrium the system would reach.</p><p>and little training disincentivizes young people from gaining education or developing skills that could develop other industries <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6)</ref>. This is in contrast to farming, for example, which pays significantly lower wages and as a result, relatively few children of farmers go into farming. A similar effect exists for when the labor-capital ratio increases (6d), making more jobs available in the extractive industry. It also occurs when the rate at which the industry invests capital based on profit decreases (6f), leading to lower rates of extractive industry growth, and when the rate of depreciation of community capital increases (6g). Reduced mobility of workers between the extractive industry and non-extractive industry (6h), and between nonextractive industry and leaving the community altogether (6i) also increases the likelihood of transition. This is likely because the model assumes the mining industry is always able to fulfill its labor requirements, while the non-extractive sector relies on workers switching to it from mining or migrating in, so reduced mobility mostly reflects inertia in willingness to take non-extractive industry jobs. This is realistic in cases where the extractive industry is culturally embedded or  where there's a greater barrier to switching between extractive and non-extractive jobs. Finally, and unsurprisingly, it also occurs when the rate at which community capital translates to per-capita benefits from working in non-extractive sectors decreases (6k), the rate at which workers are unable to find work in non-extractive industry increases (6m), and when the scaling of institutional strength with economic diversity decreases (6n). While for many of these, the fact that they lead to a transition to the resource curse equilibrium is unsurprising, some of the mechanisms leading to a transition are less intuitive. It's not immediately obvious, for example, why declining commodity prices or decreasing rate of capital investment by the industry would make a transition to the resource curse occur without accounting for how it is the wealth generated by the extractive industry that enables diversification. While the bifurcation diagrams reveals that many factors can trigger a sudden and irreversible transition to the resource curse equilibrium, we want to know whether a similar transition in the other direction is possible. In order for a transition from the resource curse equilibrium to the diversified equilibrium, the resource curse equilibrium must lose stability. The resource curse equilibrium is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">) c) d) e) f ) g) h) i) j) k) l) m) n)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">K * = ϕ (pa -wψ) µ L * n = 0 C * = - ηaK δ = - ηa δ ϕ (pa -wψ) µ</formula><p>We can check whether this equilibrium is stable by computing the eigenvalues of the Jacobian at this equilibrium (see Supplementary Information for the full Jacobian). When L * n = 0, the Jacobian (with variables ordered as K, Ln, and C) reduces to</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">J = -µ 0 0 0 c1ψK(λC -w) + c2(λC -π) 0 -ηa α -δ</formula><p>Since the Jacobian is lower-triangular, the eigenvalues are simply the diagonal entries ( -µ, -δ, and c1ψK(λC -w) + c2(λC -π)). Since all coefficients in the model are positive, we just need to check that c1ψK(λC -w) + c2(λC -π) &lt; 0. equilibrium, c1ψK(λC -w) + c2(λC -π) is always negative and the system is always stable. This means that the resource curse equilibrium is extremely self-reinforcing and resistant to perturbations in control parameters, which is perhaps unsurprising given how common an outcome it is empirically. Thus, in the absence of either an external perturbation to the state of the system to push the system out of the basin of attraction for the resource curse, or some change in the structure of the dynamics, the system cannot transition from the resource curse equilibrium to the diversified equilibrium. Generalized modeling allows for exploring the implications of different functional forms because the functional forms of the ODEs themselves become parameters. In particular, the Jacobian can be written in terms of exponent parameters, which represent the elasticity of a process to a particular variable. For example, ∂p ∂k = K * P * ∂P ∂K represents the elasticity of extractive industry production to capital, which conveniently corresponds to the output elasticity parameter in Cobbs-Douglas production functions. This parameter is called an exponent parameter because its value is an indication of the non-linearity of the process (e.g. a value of 1 represents a linear relationship between labor and production, while a value of 2 represents a quadratic, or more generally, a super-linear relationship). In order to explore how different exponent parameters shape the stability landscape, we analyze the bifurcations with respect to these parameters. Instead of plotting how the steady state -which cannot be computed without specifying functional forms -changes with respect to model, this analysis focuses on determining when the abrupt transition from the diversified to resource curse equilibrium depicted in Figures <ref type="figure">5</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> occurs. We analyze when this transition occurs by using the Routh-Hurwitz conditions for a 3x3 matrix to determine when the diversified equilibrium changes stability. By plotting its stability with respect to the exponent parameters, we can see which dynamics are most important in determining when the transition to the resource curse occurs. For ease of interpretation, we show selected bifurcations with respect to varying two exponent parameters at a time (see Supplementary Information for comprehensive 3D bifurcations). In practice, a particular specification of the functional forms, such as the one presented earlier, does not occupy a single point on the diagram because other parameters in the generalized model change when the functional forms change. Thus, rather than being used to determine whether the diversified equilibrium will be stable for a given set of functional forms, these diagrams reveal which functional forms are important in determining when the transition to the resource curse occurs and for which functional forms this transitions occurs earlier or later.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Generalized Modeling</head><p>As shown by Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>(a), the elasticity of production to capital ( ∂p ∂k , or link 1 in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>) is relatively less influential over stability, and interestingly has a non-monotonic relationship with stability. Since ∂p ∂k + ∂p ∂lm = 1 for constant elasticity of substitution production functions, this indicates that a balance between capital and labor in production is best for stability of the diversified equilibrium. The elasticity of institutional strength to economic diversity (link 2) is more influential, and lower values of that elasticity -i.e. institutional strength that scales sub-linearly with economic diversity -are better for diversified equilibrium stability.</p><p>In short, the diversified equilibrium is more stable when the strength of institutions is less responsive to economic diversity. This would achieved by, for example, safeguards that make public institutions less susceptible to influence by extractive industries.</p><p>Additionally, a lower elasticity of the community capital benefit from extractive industry to the proportion of profits transferred to the community, such as through taxes, ( ∂g ∂ [i • q] or link 4) is better for diversified equilibrium stability. In practice, this would be achieved by relying less on the taxes collected from extractive industries, which is often unlikely in the remote and rural communities where extractive industries are often based. Similarly, the elasticity of nonextractive industry to community capital ( ∂e ∂c or link 6) is influential, with lower elasticities being better for the diversified equilibrium. However, non-extractive industries that don't rely heavily on community capital are likely less desirable as livelihoods (e.g. involving low-wage or dangerous jobs). Thus, while non-extractive industry being less sensitive to community capital might be better for the stability of the diversified equilibrium, that equilibrium may be less desirable. Finally, the elasticity of damage to community capital from extractive industry production (link 3), and the elasticity of benefit to community capital from non-extractive industry have little effect on stability (link 5) (see Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref> for full results). This analysis reveals that the results of the model analyzed earlier are not contingent on the specific assumptions of functional forms and that there's a wide range of functional forms for which the transition from the diversified equilibrium to resource curse occurs. Additionally, the dynamics that are most important in determining when this transition occurs are largely those that have to do with the specific relationship between economic diversity, institutional strength, and how extractive industries contribute to community capital. It's clear, then, that the question of when the resource curse occurs cannot be determined purely in terms of economic dynamics, but rather these institutional and sociological dynamics that are more difficult to quantify.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>The dynamics of communities that are the site of extractive industries and their tendency to experience poor outcomes and economic reliance on these industries have long been the subject of study in economics and rural sociology, but determining when or why the so-called resource curse occurs has remained a challenge. This study develops a theoretical model incorporating how extractive industries entrench themselves by undermining the public institutions that regulate their impact on community capital, and thus the possibilities for non-extractive industries to develop. This feedback between extractive industries and institutional strength produces a resource curse equilibrium and a diversified equilibrium. However, as the bifurcation analysis reveals, the diversified equilibrium can lose stability in response to exogenous changes, such as drops in commodity prices or increases in extractive industry wages relative to non-extractive wages, leading to an abrupt and irreversible transition to the resource curse equilibrium. In particular, this transition is likely to occur when the extractive industry is declining in a region, at the precise moment when diversification is most critical. Additionally, the mathematical stability analysis shows that the resource curse equilibrium never loses stability. On the other hand, far from the critical transition, the basin of attraction for the resource curse is narrow, so stochasticity induced transitions are likely in practice, offering some hope for escape from the resource curse. This analysis helps explains why the resource curse can be so difficult to break out of, and reveals the importance of avoiding the transition to the resource curse in the first place <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29)</ref>.</p><p>Analysis of the generalized version of the model reveals that these results largely generalize to a range of functional forms, representing different technologies, types of resources, or socio-political contexts. It also reveals that the dynamics that are most important in determining when the transition occurs are those associated with how economic diversity influences institutional strength, how institutional strength determines the impact of extractive industries on community capital, and how community capital shapes the growth of non-extractive industries. In particular, weakening the link between economic diversity and institutional quality -such as through democratic safeguards that ensure that institutional quality is not overly susceptible to influence from whatever industry is dominant economically -is critical in preventing the transition to the resource curse.</p><p>Ultimately, this study suggests transitioning away from the resource curse is challenging in the absence of a large exogenous intervention or a transformation in the structure of the system itself. However, there remain numerous leverage points at which to help predict or prevent the resource curse in the first place. This work thus complements existing work on these communities by providing additional support for hypotheses from the empirical literature for why the resource curse occurs and suggesting new dynamics and variables on which to focus future empirical research. Better understanding these underlying mechanisms of the resource curse will be crucial for helping places impacted by extractive industries navigate the inherent challenges and inequities associated with them to more just and sustainable forms of development.</p><p>From Equation (3):</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">C = c 1 wψK + c 2 π + c 3 L n (c 1 ψK + c 2 )λ</formula><p>Substituting into (2), starting with C and L n ψK + L n :</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">0 = -ηaK + b L n ψK + L n (ap -wψ)K + αL n -δC 0 = -ηaK + b 1 b 1 - µK ϕ(ap -wψ) (ap -wψ)K + αL n -δ c 1 wψK + c 2 π + c 3 L n (c 1 ψK + c 2 )λ 0 = -ηaK + (ap -wψ) - µ ϕ K K -δ c 1 wψK + c 2 π (c 1 ψK + c 2 )λ + α - δc 3 (c 1 ψK + c 2 )λ L n</formula><p>Now substituting in our L n :</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">0 = -ηaK + (ap -wψ) - µ ϕ K K -δ c 1 wψK + c 2 π (c 1 ψK + c 2 )λ + α - δc 3 (c 1 ψK + c 2 )λ ψK b 1 - µK ϕ(pa -wψ) -1</formula><p>It is not possible to solve this expression for K, so we plot this expression implicitly for the bifurcation analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Jacobian</head><p>Let x = (K, L n , C). Then the Jacobian matrix of f (x) with respect to x is given by ∂f ∂x where row i, column j contains ∂f i ∂x j .</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">J =       ϕ(pa -wψ)b ψL n (L n + ψK) 2 -µ -ϕ(pa -wψ)b ψK (L n + ψK) 2 0 c 1 ψ(λC -w)L n c 1 ψK(λC -w) + c 2 (λC -π) -2c 3 L n L n (c 1 ψKλ + c 2 λ) -ηa + 2K(τ b(ap -wψ)) 2 L n L n + ψK 3 2(τ b(ap -wψ)) 2 ψK 3 L n L n + ψK 1 (L n + ψK) 2 + α -δ       1.3 Removing Economic Diversity-Institutional Strength feedback K = ϕ(pa -wψ)(1 -b) -µK Ċ = -ηaK + (b(pa -wψ)K) + αL n -δC Ln = L n (c 1 ψK(λC -w) + c 2 (λC -π) -c 3 L n )</formula><p>The resource curse equilibrium remains the same as in the original system. Solving for steady state if L n ̸ = 0 (diversified equilibrium):</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">(1) 0 = ϕ(pa -wψ)(1 -b) -µK (2) 0 = -ηaK + (b(pa -wψ)K) + αL n -δC<label>(</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">3) 0 = L n (c 1 ψK(λC -w) + c 2 (λC -π) -c 3 L n )</formula><p>Taking (1):</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">µK = ϕ(pa -wψ)(1 -b) K = ϕ(pa -wψ)(1 -b) µ</formula><p>This is the same as the mining-dominated equilibrium when b = 0.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">Generalized Model Analysis</head><p>The generalized model equations are as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">K = ϕ ∂ ∂K ρP (K, L m (K)) -wL m (K) [1 -I(f n )] -µK,<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">Ċ = -F (P ) + G(I(f n ) • (pP -wψK)) + H(L n ) -δC (2) Ln = L n [c 1 L m (K)[E(C) -w] + c 2 [E(C) -π] -c 3 L n ].<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Generalized modeling allows for determining stability and identifying bifurcations without specifying functional forms. Unlike traditional dynamical systems analysis, it is not possible to compute the location and number of equilibria. The generalized modeling process involves 1) normalization of the variables and functions in terms of the unknown steady state, 2) defining unknown quantities from the normalization process as scale parameters, 3) computing the Jacobian in terms of these parameters, 4) in the case that the Jacobian is not tractable analytically for calculating the Routh-Hurwitz conditions, parameterizing and numerically computing the Routh-Hurwitz conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Normalization</head><p>We define normalized state variables as</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">k = K K * c = C C * l n = L n L * n</formula><p>the normalized functions for equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(1)</ref> as</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">l m (r, k) := 1 L * m L m (R * r, K * k) p(r, k, l m ) := 1 P * P(R * r, K * k, L * m l m ) f n := 1 F * n L n L n + L m = 1 F * n L * n l n L * n l n + L * m l m = 1 F * n L * n L * m l n L * n L * m l n + l m i(f n ) := 1 I * I(F * n f n ) q := 1 Q * Q = 1 Q * [ρP -wL m -H] = 1 Q * P * ρp -w L * m P * l m - H * P * h</formula><p>the normalized functions for equation ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">d(p) := 1 D * D(P * p) b(qi) := 1 B * B(Q * I * • qi) h(l n ) := 1 H * H(L n * l n )</formula><p>and finally, the normalized functions for equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">e(c):= 1 E * E(C * c)</formula><p>This makes the normalized equations</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">k = ϕ 1 K * ∂Q ∂K (1 -I * i) - µK * K * k = ϕ P * K * ρ ∂p ∂k + ∂p ∂l m ∂l m ∂k - L * m P * w ∂l m ∂k 1 K * - I * K * i -µk (4) ċ = -D * C * d + B * C * b + F * C * f -δc (5) ln = E * L * m c 1 l n l m e + E * c 2 l n e -L * m c 1 wl n l m -c 2 l n π -c 3 L n * l n 2<label>(6)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Define Parameters</head><p>Since we are considering the system at steady state, we can then define scale parameters based on these normalized quantities. Scale parameters typically indicate time scales or the relative importance of different processes. For Equation ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>), we get the following scale parameter:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">α k = ϕ ∂Q ∂K * K * [1 -I * ] = µ</formula><p>For Equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>), we get scale parameters</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">α c = D * C * + δ = B * C * + F * C * β c = 1 α c D * C * β c = δ α c = 1 -β c η c = 1 α c B * C * η c = 1 α c F * C * = 1 -η c making the equation ċ = α c (-β c d + η c b + (1 -η c )f -(1 -β c )c).</formula><p>Finally, for Equation (6), we get </p><formula xml:id="formula_30">0 = E * L * m c 1 + E * c 2 -L * m c 1 w -c 2 π -c 3 L n * α Ln = E * L * m c 1 + E * c 2 = L * m c 1 w + c 2 π + c 3 L n * β Ln = 1 α Ln L * m c 1 w β Ln = 1 α Ln c 2 π β Ln = 1 α Ln c 3 L * n η Ln = 1 α Ln E * L * m c 1 η Ln = 1 α Ln E * c 2 = 1 -η Ln</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Computing the Jacobian</head><p>Using the normalized equation, we can now compute the Jacobian.  Once the Jacobian is defined, we can conduct stability and bifurcation analysis as usual by parameterizing the Jacobian for a particular equilibrium.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_31">∂ k ∂k = ϕ P * K * 1 K * ρ ∂ 2 p ∂k 2 + ∂ 2 p ∂l m ∂k ∂l m ∂k + ∂p ∂l m ∂ 2 l m ∂k 2 - L * m P * w ∂ 2 l</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Generalized Modeling Parameterization</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symbol</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>ηαλπ</head><label></label><figDesc>Scaling of damage to C with extraction $ M T Scaling of benefit to C with non-extractive industry $ Scaling of per-capita payoff from non-extractive industry to C 1 N Payoff of leaving community $ N c1 Responsiveness of workers to payoff difference between working in extractive and non-extractive industry 1 T $ c2 Responsiveness of workers to payoff difference between leaving the community and non-extractive industry 1 T $ c3 Rate of workers being unable to find employment in non-extractive industry (due to saturation) 1 T N</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Graphical representation of the system. The variables in bold are the state variables, and the italicized variables represent intermediary variables. Each link represents a process in the model, and is marked by whether it is a positive or negative interaction. The numbered links represent those that are analyzed in their generalized form in the second part of the study.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,91.15,185.23,169.93,77.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Time series of trajectories for the state variables.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Trajectories in the a) the 3-d phase space, b) the 2-d projection in the K-C plane (i.e. a top-down view) and c) a 2-d projection in the K-Ln plane (i.e. front view).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig.4. Visualization of the basins of attraction for the two equilibria, with points color-coded by which equilibrium they lead to. The red points indicate points that lead to the resource curse equilibrium (denoted by a red star) while blue points indicate points that lead to the diversified equilibrium (denoted by the blue star).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Bifurcation diagrams illustrating how equilibrium K values vary with respect to each parameter in the model. The curves are computed analytically (see Supplementary Information). Dashed lines indicate unstable equilibria, and solid lines indicate stable equilibria. The red line indicates the resource curse equilibrium, while the blue line indicates the diversified equilibrium.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Since C = -ηa δ ϕ(pa-wψ) µand is thus negative itself at this</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Gain in non-extractive industry to community capital (link 6) 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 7. 2-D bifurcation diagrams with respect to exponent parameters of the generalized model. The region in light blue indicates where the diversified equilibrium exists alongside the resource curse equilibrium, and the region in red indicates where only the resource curse equilibrium exists.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>making the equation ln = α Ln η Ln l n l m e + η Ln l n e -β Ln l n l m -β Ln l n -β Ln l n 2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Ln (η Ln l n e -β Ln l n ) ∂l m ∂k = α Ln (η Ln -β Ln ) ∂l m ∂k ∂ ln ∂c = α Ln (η Ln l n l m + η Ln l n ) ∂e ∂c = α Ln (η Ln + η Ln ) ∂e ∂c = α Ln ∂e ∂c ∂ ln ∂l n = α Ln η Ln l m e + η Ln e -β Ln l m -β Ln -2 β Ln l n = α Ln η Ln + η Ln -β Ln -β Ln -2 β Ln = -α Ln β Ln</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure S1 :</head><label>S1</label><figDesc>Figure S1: Bifurcation plots with respect to all combinations of three parameters. The surface represents the surface at which the determinant is equal to 0 and thus indicates where the diversified equilibrium changes stability.</figDesc><graphic coords="19,72.00,107.57,529.20,378.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Definitions and dimensions of the variables and parameters for the specific model.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>-www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Molla et al.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>PNAS -July 28, 2025 -vol. XXX -no. XX -3</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_2"><p>-www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Molla et al.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Molla et al.PNAS -July 28, 2025 -vol. XXX -no. XX -5</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_4"><p>-www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Molla et al.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_5"><p>-www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Molla et al.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_6"><p>Molla et al. PNAS -July 28, 2025 -vol. XXX -no. XX -9</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_7"><p>-www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.XXXXXXXXXX Molla et al.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Computing the steady state for the case where L n = 0 (the resource curse equilibrium): Taking Equation (1):</p><p>Taking Equation ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>):</p><p>Computing the steady state for the case where L n ̸ = 0 (the diversified equilibrium):</p><p>We use equations ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and (3) to put (2) in terms of K. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R A F T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1117 1118 1119 1120 1121 1122 1123 1124 1125 1126 1127 1128 1129 1130 1131 1132 1133 1134 1135 1136 1137 1138 1139 1140 1141 1142 1143 1144 1145 1146 1147 1148 1149 1150 1151 1152 1153 1154 1155 1156 1157 1158 1159 1160 1161 1162 1163 1164 1165 1166 1167 1168 1169 1170 1171 1172 1173 1174 1175 1176 1177 1178</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The curse of natural resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jd Sachs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Warner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. Econ. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="827" to="838" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Auty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Sustaining Development in Mineral Economies: The Resource Curse Thesis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Routledge, London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resource intensity, institutions, and development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Eh Bulte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Damania</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rt Deacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1029" to="1044" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Resource Curse -What Have We Learned from Two Decades of Intensive Research: Introduction to the Special Issue</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Papyrakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The J. Dev. Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tvdv</forename><surname>Cavalcanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mohaddes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Raissi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Growth, development and natural resources: New evidence using a heterogeneous panel analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="318" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Addictive Economies: Extractive Industries and Vulnerable Localities in a Changing World Economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Freudenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1549-0831.1992.tb00467.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/j.1549-0831.1992.tb00467.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rural. Sociol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does Mother Nature Corrupt? Natural Resources, Corruption, and Economic Growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Cal Weidmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IMF</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Institutions and the Resource Curse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mehlum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Moene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Torvik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Econ. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Quality of Political Institutions and the Curse of Natural Resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cabrales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hauk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Econ. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Varieties of Resource Experience: Natural Resource Export Structures and the Political Economy of Economic Growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Isham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The World Bank Econ. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Boom, bust, action! How communities can cope with boom-bust cycles in unconventional oil and gas development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/ropr.12490</idno>
		<ptr target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/ropr.12490" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Policy Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="569" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resource Dependence and Socioeconomic Well-being</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lawrie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tonts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Boomtowns</forename><surname>Plummer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aust. Geogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking social structure, fragmentation, and substance abuse in a resource-based community</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Parkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Work. &amp; Fam</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Community</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extractive industries and development: The resource curse at the micro, meso and macro levels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gilberthorpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Papyrakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Extr. Ind. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="390" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Anthropology of Extraction: Critical Perspectives on the Resource Curse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">,</forename><surname>Gilberthorpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rajak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00220388.2016.1160064</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00220388.2016.1160064" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The J. Dev. Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Publisher: Routledge eprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resiliency and resource-based communities: a Canadian case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Deacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lamanes</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Istanbul, Turkey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="724" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community Economic Identity: The Coal Industry and Ideology Construction in West Virginia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>York</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1549-0831.2009.00004.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/j.1549-0831.2009.00004.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rural. Sociol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">eprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Institutional Bases of Identity Construction and Reproduction: The Case of Underground Coal Mining</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wicks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1468-0432.00162</idno>
		<ptr target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/1468-0432.00162" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Work. &amp; Organ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<pubPlace>Gender</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A just transition for whom? Politics, contestation, and social identity in the disruption of coal in the Powder River Basin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Res. &amp; Soc. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101657</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Where Appalachia Went Right: White Masculinities, Nature, and Pro-Coal Politics in an Era of Climate Change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Schwartzman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of infrastructure design on commons dilemmas in socialecological system dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Qubbaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Muneepeerakul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Anderies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13207" to="13212" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The emergence and resilience of self-organized governance in coupled infrastructure systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Muneepeerakul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Anderies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>Natl. Acad. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>National Academy of Sciences Section: Social Sciences</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4617" to="4622" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">G Engstr öm, M Schl üter, Resilience offers escape from trapped thinking on poverty alleviation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Haider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1603043</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">M Schl üter, Implications of poverty traps across levels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Radosavljevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Haider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sj Lade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105437</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics of resilience-equity interactions in resource-based communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Molla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Deionno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. Earth &amp; Environ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Nature Publishing Group</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Number: 1 Publisher</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sustainable economic development: on the coexistence of resource-dependent and resource-impacting industries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lopez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ. Dev. Econ. Camb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="705" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Measurement of Community Capitals through Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bregendahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Flora</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Online J. Rural. Res. &amp; Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Emery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Flora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Spiraling-Up: Mapping Community Transformation with Community Capitals Framework in 50 Years of Community Development Vol I. (Routledge)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Num Pages</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mining the Past: Historical Context and the Changing Implications of Natural Resource Extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Frickel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Freudenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategic behaviors and governance challenges in social-ecological systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Muneepeerakul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Anderies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth&apos;s Futur</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="865" to="876" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Migration, Unemployment and Development: A Two-Sector Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Todaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Am. Econ. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Replicator dynamics in Evolutionary Games and Population Dynamics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hofbauer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Sigmund</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="85" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
