<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Right-wing Populism in a Global Perspective: The Necessity for an Integrative Theory</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Springer International Publishing</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Springer International Publishing</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A Hamed</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
							<email>hamed.hosseini@newcastle.edu.au</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Saha</surname></persName>
							<email>lawrence.saha@anu.edu.au</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><surname>Adamczyk</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Human and Social Futures</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Newcastle</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Arts &amp; Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Australian National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<region>ACT</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">College of Engineering, Science and Environment</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Newcastle</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Right-wing Populism in a Global Perspective: The Necessity for an Integrative Theory</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">The Palgrave Handbook of Global Social Change</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Springer International Publishing</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="24"/>
							<date type="published" when="2022" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C655445D870DA4BEB1909E8C4AFBD01F</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-030-87624-1_7-1</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Right-wing Populism</term>
					<term>Ethnocentric nationalism</term>
					<term>Radical right</term>
					<term>Integrative social theory</term>
					<term>Authoritarian neoliberalism</term>
					<term>Post-globalism</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This chapter not only presents a critical review of the contemporary academic literature regarding the "social nature" (basic characteristics), "social manifestations," and "social nurtures" (determining factors, roots, bases, and impacts) of Right-Wing Populism (RWP), but also initiates a conversation to pursue a new consolidative line of theorization of RWP. It starts by addressing the existing</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>This chapter draws attention to the challenges of theorizing right-wing populism (RWP) in social sciences through a critical-comparative review and mapping of the literature on this subject. The ultimate aim is to initiate a productive conversation on how to overcome these challenges. As a contribution to the debate, we will also discuss and make recommendations on the ways an integrative approach can be pursued for addressing the theoretical complexities and difficulties revealed by the review. The literature on RWP has been fast-growing, particularly since the upsurge in anti-globalist responses to the 2008 Global Financial Crisis, the "Brexit" and the rise of Trump(ism), also in the return of right-wing authoritarianism to power in Latin America post-Pink Tide and the electoral victories of radical nationalists in most Eastern European countries, as well as in few large economies in the "global South" (e.g., Brazil, India, and the Philippines), and even in the European Parliament. Associated with the escalation of the radical right movements that have reinvented themselves to gain more popular bases by toning down their radical rhetoric (e.g., Front National in France), longstanding centrist political parties in many countries have also witnessed a significant further shift toward more ethnocentric and nationalist standings in both rhetoric and policy (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Britain, China, France, Greece, Israel, South Africa, and Turkey)</ref>. This global shift in politics has resulted in a sudden growth in scholarly efforts to explain the changes. However, and for several reasons explained below, as a result, the literature has become more diversified, complicated, and thus ambiguous. This poses challenges for researchers interested in developing broad theoretical frameworks to grasp the totality and paradoxes of the global shift.</p><p>Our review exposes major cleavages in the literature that are formed generally around three axes. The first axis of discord relates to the conceptual approaches to characterize the core nature of the phenomenon, which appear to be highly diverse despite some significant overlaps. A range of alternative concepts have been used in the literature to refer to an arrangement of phenomena that are closely related or sufficiently commensurable (if not almost identical). This long list includes terms like "radical right," "far-right," "(new) populism," "right populism," "plutocratic populism," "ethnonationalist populism," "ultra-nationalism," "ethnocentrism," "authoritarian neoliberalism," "illiberalism," "nativism," "neo-fascism," and "racial supremacy." We do not suggest that the differences between these notionsno matter how subtle they may be in some casesshould be overlooked. Rather, we argue that a focus on those sections of the literature that have directly used the concept of "RWP" provides a primary intellectual base that can be further extended, applied, and assessed when dealing with the alternative terminologies in other sectors of the literature. Nevertheless, the review of the literature remains challenging when we narrow the scope of the review only to a single term like RWP even in its varied uses, a variation that seems to emerge in the different approaches of analysts and authors to what characterizes "populism." Thus, even in focusing on RWP specifically to make the argument manageable still leaves its own challenges that are delineated later in this chapter.</p><p>The second axis of controversy and division among scholars originates from the ways RWP is described regarding its social manifestationsi.e., the various ways in which RWP has manifested in different domains of social reality, and how its strains are classified or distinguished. This is partly determined by the various scholars' disciplinary backgrounds. For instance, political scientists typically concentrate on the phenomenon's manifestations as a political force, and so analyze it in terms of party politics, illiberal democracy, elections, and so on <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">(Vormann &amp; Weinman, 2021)</ref>. In contrast, sociocultural studies theorize RWP mostly as a cultural shift, emphasizing social value systems, ideologies, identity politics, and political culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cover, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Norocel et al., 2020)</ref>, and political sociologists theorize RWP as a social movement, drawing on social movement theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Jansen, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Kincaid, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Rydgren, 2004)</ref>. Disputes are present even within each disciplinary account. For instance, questions are raised by political scientists about the "thinness" or "thickness" of populism as an ideology among those who focus on its ideational aspects (an aspect which will be explored in detail in the next section on "the nature" of RWP).</p><p>The third axis of division is exhibited in the causal explanations of RWP that we coin here as the social nurtures of RWP, i.e., the theories that locate RWP in path dependencies (the sociohistorical origins, contextual factors, and social bases of the trajectories of the evolution and impacts of RWP over time). In this axis, some authors highlight macro-social factors such as the failures or contradictions of globalization, particularly neoliberal globalism or a global legitimacy crisis of liberal democracy (O'Byrne, 2019), while others emphasize meso-and micro-social psychological factors such as the impact of socioeconomic deprivations, collective resentment, or authoritarian personalities, <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">(TenHouten, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>This chapter is structured into three sections, around the three axes, respectively, to explore and explain the sources of divisions. Through this, we will argue that despite divisions it is both possible and indeed necessary for social scientists to develop encompassing yet flexible schemes for the theorization of RWP, which can then be adapted, assessed, and revisited for different cases and contexts according to their specificities. In conclusion, the chapter will make general recommendations on how best to develop an integrative theoretical framework with the capacity to address any unnecessary conceptual inconsistencies and divisions that exist and to synthesize the currently unrelated explanatory efforts at the macro-, meso-, and microlevels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2</head><p>The Distinct Nature of RWP: Conceptual Confusions and Terminological Inconsistencies</p><p>Sources of the conceptual and terminological ambiguities around what fundamentally constitutes RWP in the literature are varied. Above all, are the following three. First, the lack of consent around the term "populism" seems to have affected the characterization of the nature of RWP. Up until the 1950s, the term "populism" was used predominantly in referring to (self-claimed populist) agrarian movements in North America of the late nineteenth century <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Fuentes, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Moffitt, 2017)</ref>. Since then, the use of the term "populism" has grown widely and diversely in political discourses and scholarly debates. The recent increase in the use of "populism" in both media and academia to refer only to the radical right nationalist movements, however, has muddied the waters more greatly <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Betz, 2018)</ref>. While associating "radical right" with "populism" to improve terminological clarity can help increase precision in terms of ideological direction (right vs. left), it does not necessarily eliminate ambiguity. As such, it will be helpful here to briefly discuss the phenomenon of "populism" as the defining element of RWP. Due to a significant lack of ideological structure, as discussed later in this chapter, populist movements manifest elusive, manipulative, and paradoxical features. Indeed, the incoherence of reality is the second source of conceptual ambiguity in the literature. As Fuentes (2020, p. 49) explains: "One of the paradoxical characteristics of these movements lies in the fact that . . . its anti-elitist, anti-status quo, or anti-establishment nature is embodied by an elite that speaks on behalf of the people." Moreover, the recent global rise of new (mostly radical right) populist movements in different regions and the emergence of coalitions and transnational networks of mutual support in itself is a phenomenon that requires social scientists to go beyond their "academic ghettoization" and separate case studies <ref type="bibr">(Moffitt, 2017, p. 4</ref>). However, despite the subjective ambiguities in existing theoretical attempts and the absence of an "objective" or singular reality -"objective fuzziness"it is still possible to focus on the most common denominators to create some level of conceptual certainty necessary for constructing middle-range theories.</p><p>Populism is widely conceptualized as a sociopolitical phenomenon that assumes an idealized, harmonious population of like-minded ordinary citizens whose popular preferences must be given priority in policy processes. This phenomenon in itself can potentially be a step forward in a democratic society where the elite or the ruling class are out of touch, especially when populism appears in the form of grassroots movements to keep the elite and powerful in check, or to demand the protection and satisfaction of basic rights and needs (security, welfare, employment, housing, and so on) for a significant segment of the population. Most colorful examples of such populist functions can be found in the cases of anti-colonialist revolutionary mass movements in the "third world" in the past century. Populism furthermore frequently appears as a movement to defend the national sovereignty of a nation against foreign economic or political interventions through imbalanced trade agreements or loosely regulated international transactions, such as the anti-free trade, anti-corporate movements of the 1990s in Latin America.</p><p>Many populist movements tend to use conventional democratic means such as elections to influence politics, and some movements may even maintain some level of democracy after gaining power in promoting fairer redistribution of resources toward disadvantaged social strata. However, populism does not appear as a rather well-articulated doctrine with few detectable rigid ideological principles, an issue referred to as the "ideological thinness" of populism. More specifically, in the case of RWP, populism often emerges in the form of popular rhetoric that taps into a population's anger or fear and advocates quick fixes without a proper understanding of the root causes of major social problems and the complexities of social institutions; stark examples are the populist responses to the complex refugee crisis in Europe and Brexit in the UK. It is therefore more apt to develop simplistic understandings of society and its social ills. For example, it is often easier for the lesseducated, anxious, and/or forgotten sections of a population to become enchanted by those political discourses that blame a culturally weak or racially different minority group for economic problems and to demonize the malfunctioning government institutions (under the general title of "establishment"), rather than questioning the unjust capitalist relations that have promoted a highly destructive competitive individualistic condition in the first place <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Colgan &amp; Keohane, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Viviani, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Populism, contrary to what Isaiah Berlin believes, is not a "Cinderella's shoe" <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Berlin, 2013</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Berlin, [1967]]</ref>); due to its ideological thinness, it can fit many kinds of feet. Radical right populists, depending on the context, may draw on a mixture of quasisocialist, conservative, racist, or even liberal ideals in order to gain support. They may evolve into an extreme form known as "fascism," which gained global momentum in the early twentieth century. There thus are justified concerns that history may repeat itself in this century <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Campani, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Peters, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Indeed, many of the recent efforts to outline the key characteristics of populism draw more on right-wing political tendencies (de la <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Torre, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Finchelstein, 2014)</ref>. Several core features that are generally attributed to RWP movements in the literature are:</p><p>1. Disrespect of political and cultural pluralism, manifested in their view of the people as a subject with a unitary will and/or historical origin, and conception of political rivals as enemies or the proxies of enemies <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(M체ller, 2016)</ref>. 2. An understanding of the leader(s) as a "charismatic embodiment" of the desires of the imagined nation. 3. Strong dismissal of independent legislative and judicial branches of government (if especially they are structured based on liberal/pluralist values and/or human rights) or more generally the rejection of "the separation of powers" principle. 4. Ethnocentric or exclusionist type of nationalism. 5. Pragmatist attachment to a vertical form of the electoral democratic structure where elections are seen as only the means for winning power and holding to it; in other words, electoral processes are considered legitimate only when they lead to the desired outcome.</p><p>We believe that identifying RWP by this cluster of features can potentially reduce conceptual confusion. As Fuchs explains, RWP is often associated with tendencies that conceive of "the people" as an "undifferentiated unity," and appeal to "popular prejudices" in denying class conflicts or reducing them to "crude and simplified antagonisms" <ref type="bibr">(Fuchs, 2018, p. 781)</ref>. Right-wing populist political culture can therefore often be directed toward undervaluing diversity and promoting a consecrated image of the nation mixed with a nostalgic craving for a return to a fantasized golden age in the past.</p><p>Other widely attributed features such as the anti-establishment tendency, as explained below, are not unique to RWP and thus should not be used to distinguish it from other types of movements (whether populist or non-populist) that evidence the same characteristic. As noted, being anti-establishment, as well as anti-elitist, is often widely attributed to RWP. However, these characteristics are not exclusive to the right-wing populist agenda since they are also commonly shared among the so-called left-populist political movements <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Laclau, 1979)</ref> and parties as well as many other marginalized non-populist groups. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Mansbridge and Macedo (2019)</ref> argue that anti-elitism is the most common feature across this spectrum. Moreover, alliances and policy orientation overlaps can be found between the radical right populist movements and some sections of the major center-right parties, for example, between Brexiters and the Conservative Party in the UK and the Tea party and the Republican party in the USA.</p><p>The reason that we here focus only on RWP, as opposed to Left-Wing Populism (LWP), is more than due to the manageability and coherency of argument. While we agree that the ideological thinness of "populism" as a discourse or political style enables it to flexibly borrow from, or to be borrowed by, other ideologies (and therefore we can think of both the right and the left versions) we are not comfortable with treating many new (/neo-) socialist (/leftist) movements in the same way simply because they have gained a popular social base or pursued a popular anti-elitist cause. As manifested in history multiple times, the left is indeed as susceptible as the right to be influenced by ethno-nationalist or authoritarian values. However, there are significantly different features that determine many of the new movements on the left, making the universal application of the term populism problematic. Thus, to include the literature on LWP in this reviewdue to the problematic attribution of a loosely defined notion of "populism" to many examples that are profoundly different to RWP and thus require different theoretical frameworkswould add to conceptual confusion.</p><p>For instance, many of these new (neo-) socialist movements are ethnically or culturally more inclusive and more genuinely committed to grassroots democracy with "popular" social bases that are very different to those on the right. Therefore, simply holding an anti-establishment position and a popular base of support does not entitle a movement to be characterized as populist if they do not also evidence a strong racially, culturally, or ideologically homogenizing way of idealizing their own identity and the identity of the ruling class. Recent examples of left-wing movements have emerged in Latin America in the 2000s (such as the Pink Tide), and more recently in Greece (SYRIZA), Spain (Podemos), and Europe-wide (DiEM25). There are also many relatively radical left-wing movements (like the Progressive International, Party of the European Left, Left Party in Germany, and Movement for Socialism in Bolivia) with some key defining elements of general populism such as the admiration of "the people" against a delegitimized elite, but without the preference of "the general will" over any rights and representation in their ideology (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Mudde &amp; Rovira Kaltwasser, 2017</ref>, for a detailed description of these three key elements). Moreover, in the so-called age of rising right-wing populism, most of these movements are either in decline or face significant barriers, which itself indicates a substantively different underlying dynamism. Their "popular" bases are far more diverse, constituted predominantly by the young, educated, female, immigrant, ethnic minorities, and a precariat class where their perception of the establishment is not fixed nor mixed with anti-intellectualism or conspiracy theories. Thus, even broadening the concept of "populism," to include socialist or radical democratic movements simply because of their emphasis on "the people" as against the elite, makes it more confusing, less rigorous, and less useful.</p><p>As emphasized, the choice of terminology is defined by what the investigators consider as the nature of the phenomenon (i.e., the first axis of controversy in the literature). However, the difficulty is not only about the definition of populism. Concerning the sociohistorical bases, historical roots, and dynamism (i.e., the third axis) that govern the rise and demise of these oppositional movements, there are enough significant differences to question the plausibility of developing a theoretical approach equally applicable to both sides of the spectrum. For example, "welfare chauvinism" (of say, the Danish People's Party in Denmark and the French National Front) can be distinguished from the above-mentioned new popular socialist orientations to the extent that the pursuit of welfare provisions is seen to be restricted to citizens and denied to immigrants or other social groups, thus constituting a type of right-wing state nationalism with its unique historical roots and dynamics.</p><p>The third source of conceptual plurality (including the unnecessary confusions) is comprised of the disparities among scholars and researchers in terms of the social values that underpin their theoretical approaches, as well as the ontological, epistemological, and methodological assumptions that guide their studies of the subject.</p><p>The differences in such meta-theoretical standings determine what aspects of RWP are highlighted, from what angle, and with what normative position the phenomenon is approached or subjectively evaluated. For instance, while there is a tendency to equate RWP with political authoritarianism or suppressive communitarianism <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Crewe &amp; Sanders, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Germani, 2019)</ref>, reducing RWP to authoritarianism can be confusing <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(McKay et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Riedel, 2017)</ref>. Authoritarianism sees the ultimate source of legitimacy to lie in a leader's authority and it is from there that legitimacy cascades down to those submitted to this supremacy. In contrast, right-wing populists place legitimacy in "the people" and its fetishized source of uniting identity. Leaders are normally perceived as the embodiment of this identity. RWP, therefore, remains dependent on quasi-democratic mechanisms that directly transfer this legitimacy from the masses upward to the leaders. Their relationship with democracy, though, under certain radicalizing conditions, can devolve further into antidemocratic violent reactions (e.g., Trumpists' violent insurgency post-2020 election), authoritarianism in power, or even further into an extreme version of it (i.e., totalitarianism or fascism).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">The Multifaceted and Multiscalar Manifestations of RWP</head><p>In what major social forms is RWP manifested? Responses to this question vary across the literature. RWP is widely understood as a social construct, a mode of political practice <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bart &amp; Noam, 2016)</ref>, a discourse, a grassroots social movement, or a constellation of closely related top-down political movements interested in party politics and power concentration, and finally a discursive and stylistic repertoire <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Brubaker, 2017)</ref>. RWP has also been conceptualized in many ways: as a social attitude, a set of social norms and values, a style of thought or a political style <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Moffitt, 2017)</ref>, a political current, a strategy of politicization of the rift between society and politics <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(Viviani, 2017)</ref>, and a historical moment or process <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(Riveros, 2018)</ref>. RWP can be all the above and thus is a multifaceted phenomenon. Each of these descriptors may have strong implications for the theorization of the phenomenon. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Moffitt (2017)</ref> considers RWP a globalizing "political style" with common features that can be found across different contexts. RWP, according to Moffitt, is not a genuine ideology because it relies much less on stable principles. He makes the argument for considering RWP as a political style rather than other commonly used conceptions of it such as a "thin ideology," or a social ideational phenomenon <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Mudde &amp; Rovira Kaltwasser, 2017)</ref>, a political strategy, a political logic, or a discourse/rhetoric. It is a "style" since, for populists, the way the message is delivered is more important than the message itself. It therefore cannot always exclusively represent a potential threat to formal or electoral democracy as it partially depends on such mechanisms to gain and maintain power but may pose a potentially serious threat to those democracies that safeguard individual and minority rights <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(M체ller, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Despite the lack of consensus, more engaging conversations of RWP around its social manifestations, especially across different scholarly traditions, are needed. RWP manifests itself in various ways; the point is that no one way should be treated as a universally primary feature or be reduced to another in our analyses. Manifestations of RWP can be in the forms of electoral support and behavior, social activism, discourse, ideology, social grievances, attitudinal qualities, normative and value systems, psychological appeal, cultural practices, party politics, and political style. RWP is intrinsically multifaceted and a focus on any one facet does not necessarily require the exclusion of others.</p><p>There thus remain many important questions that have not received adequate attention or are the subject of disputed answers. For instance, can we differentiate between sociocultural populism, political populism, economic populism, and even ecological populism? How nationalist, internationalist, imperialist, authoritarian, neocolonialist, neoliberal, or libertarian can these movements be? Is RWP a legitimate or understandable outburst of anger or reaction toward the failures of globalism or neoliberalism, or a manipulated move toward a more authoritarian version of neoliberalism? Is this a movement to protect and serve material interests? Whose interests exist at the movement's elite level, and whose interests exist at the movement's grassroots level? Or is this a movement to release accumulated social anxieties in the form of social resentment? What are the inconsistencies between the movement's rhetoric, frames, and practices? And, is the movement to protect the interests of the national capital, in alliance with conservative politicians, against the global capital in a growingly polarized world? In the remainder of this section, we argue that the multifaceted manifestations of RWP necessitate integrative theorization.</p><p>As we have explained so far (right-wing) populism in its most general sense refers to shifted values and mobilized collective actions toward the political, cultural, and economic entitlements and preferences of the populace (the so-called "the people") against those particular social groups or communities whose identities or interests are perceived to differ from the widely idealized image of a typical countryperson. In the case of RWP, these targeted groups include not only sectors of the (liberal) elite, government, globalist corporations, foreign powers (except those who can be strategic allies), but also intellectuals, mainstream and alternative progressive media, secular scientific bodies, ethnic and religious minorities, immigrants, and refugees. As discussed profoundly in many parts of the literature, (right-wing) populism, as a thin ideology, does not always materialize in society as a well-articulated doctrine or a coherent group attitude with several detectable rigid guiding principles.</p><p>An established tradition in the literature argues that RWP commonly "emerges" in the form of macroscale movements and popular rhetoric that taps into a population's collective emotions at the micro-and meso-levels and advocates quick solutions without a proper understanding of the root causes of the problems and the complexities of social institutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aslanidis, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Neuner &amp; Wratil, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Stanley, 2008)</ref>. RWP constantly draws on anger, frustration, and resentment of the social groups abandoned by centrist politics to construct enemies to its cause, invoking peoples' fears and using these imagined enemies to scapegoat the structural flaws of the system.</p><p>When seen from this perspective, the major macro-, meso-, and micromanifestations of RWP must be taken into account and the interrelations between the mechanisms that connect these manifestations be theorized and investigated. However, there are significant chasms in the literature between the macro-, meso-, and microlevel descriptions of the nature of the phenomenon. This multiscalar nature of the phenomenon corresponds also to the multilevel processes and path dependencies, or what we call the nurtures of RWP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4</head><p>The Distinct Nurtures of RWP: On the Plausibility of Developing Integrative Theoretical Frameworks</p><p>By "the nurtures" of RWP we mean not only the determining factors and sociohistorical roots that nurture (i.e., give rise to, and influence) RWP including its multifarious social bases, but also whatever is nurtured by RWP, e.g., its impacts on, and relationships with, democracy, politics, global forces, and societies. The idea that we pursue here is that the deep entanglement of the "nurtures" of RWP, from macro-to microlevels, necessitates the development of integrative approaches to theorizing the process and phenomenon. The following subsections will argue for this necessity in detail through a critical assessment of both the promises and problems of the main analytical traditions at the macro-sociological level and offer suggestions on how best to pursue an approach of integrative theorization while maintaining some flexibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Regarding the Multifarious and Intersectional Social Bases of RWP</head><p>A growing section of the literature attempts to feature the social bases of RWP in different contexts. Comparisons indicate some level of commonality. The questions that are often asked are: (1) What are the driving forces of right-wing populism?; and</p><p>(2) What social agents mobilize resources and where are the social bases of these movements? The issue of social class appears to be central to both. Is the base comprised of a new social class with false class consciousness (i.e., unable to understand that their support of RWP contradicts their class interest at least in the long run <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Hacker &amp; Pierson, 2020</ref>)), or, does it consist of a multitude of social bases with underlying consolidating factors? We can typically classify the grassroots supporters of populist parties into three main categories. First, there are those who devotedly vote for and support populist parties and movements with which they share almost similar social values and political causes. These people are normally more ideologically committed and active in promoting right-wing populism and stay faithful for a long period. The main driving factors for these supporters are their core social values, political beliefs, and ideologies that are shaped historically over a long period as a result of their social status or social origin. In the case of Trump's populist support, this includes Tea Party supporters, members of the Ku Klux Klan (KKK), neo-fascist, racist, and white supremacist advocates, and similar groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Crowson &amp; Brandes, 2017)</ref>. There is therefore a multi-temporal dimension to RWP in how the allegiance of these individuals and groups to the rightwing populist movement/leader comes about as a momentary materialization of a long-term allegiance to values.</p><p>The second base of support consists of those who assume that a right-wing populist party and its leaders are more capable of representing their concerns and resolving their problems. They are disenfranchised with any existing mainstream political and economic institution (the so-called "establishment") since they may (rightfully or wrongfully) feel neglected or left behind as a result of the economic policy reforms adopted by many countries to promote corporate globalization <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Kurer, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">McQuarrie, 2017)</ref>. This base includes <ref type="bibr">Lipset's (1960, p. 170</ref>) "declining 'liberal' classes living in declining areas." In the absence of viable, strong, or popular socialist alternatives, racially white, less-educated, male, blue-collar working class (some with past unionist backgrounds) as well as small-city precariat (people suffering from unstable or unpredictable circumstances) are more liable to become enchanted with the idea of nationalist protectionism; as the protection of traditional manufacturing and extractivist manual-labor jobs, against the so-called rival immigrant workers or overseas manual labor employed in offshore jobs <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Kurer &amp; Palier, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Ost, 2018)</ref>. Unlike the first group, they do not essentially endorse ethnocentric values, but to them, their social concerns appear to be more promisingly addressed and acknowledged by right-wing populist movements. This group offers their support mainly for pragmatic reasons during the election seasons. These allies may later either become more loyal or withdraw their backing, depending on how successfully their expectations are satisfied by the populist party and leaders in power or how satisfying the populist performances are either economically or rhetorically (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fraser, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>The third base consists of those who vote for populist parties for personal, tactical, or emotional reasons unrelated to their political beliefs or values if they persistently hold any. Some people may vote for populist candidates/parties, not necessarily because they have read and agreed with their policies, but rather because they find those populist leaders charismatic. They may support right-wing leaders like Trump who appear to be charismatic for their perceived character, e.g., as "successful businessmen" who can save the nation's economy, despite being politically incorrect or inexperienced in many ways <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Lubbers et al., 2002)</ref>. This popular perception that a self-interested businessman (a capitalist/owner of the means of production) can herald a solution for the masses (the ones exploited for the very success of that capitalist person) in "saving a nation's economy," is a clear example of "false class consciousness" (from a Marxian point of view) that the populist elite exploit. For instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Mason (2010)</ref> argues that the charismatic character of both Sarah Palin (US) and Pauline Hanson (Australia), in combination with the social aspect of women's vulnerability, was one of the prime reasons for their political success. Alternatively, some may choose to vote for right-wing populist parties purely for tactical reasons, such as to avoid voting for anti-nationalist parties, to disapprove of the government in power (disapproval or protest vote), or to push for a non-centrist party in politics.</p><p>It is thus reasonable to differentiate between RWP as a political movement and the (right-wing) "populist support," particularly those who vote populist. This is because many who support right-wing populist agendas through elections may not necessarily be wedded to all populist values and may change their vote in the next round of elections. It is however imperative to understand how populist parties are sometimes able to achieve such a high degree of support, large enough to turn them into strong players or even to pave their way to power. An important point to bear in mind is that both the incentives and the underlying social factors might be different the populist elite compared to their rank-and-file supporters even though they share the same mindset or political cause.</p><p>In discussing the social basis of RWP as one of the nurturing factors, we here have limited our scope to its political domain. However, even within this limited scope, we realize that substantial differences exist between the social, and social psychological, mechanisms behind distinct popular support. While for some socioeconomic factors such as class are influential, for other sectors of the population cultural views and social psychological aspects may play a greater role. As an example, there is enough evidence to show that the bases of support for Trump in both the 2016 and 2020 elections evidence intersections between race, age, gender, religious orientation, educational qualification, residential status, and social class <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Frey, 2021</ref>). Yet, the literature and journalistic material on this matter generally remain divided between those who stress the preeminence of cultural factors (e.g., identity politics) over socioeconomic factors (class politics), and those who take what might be seen as an opposite position, although interestingly both sides refer to empirical data <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Bhambra, 2017)</ref>. Taking the "intersectionality" of the support base in this case, and other similar cases, may offer a resolution to the above bifurcation and seeming impasse. This is another reason why more integrative but flexible theoretical frameworks are required.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Regarding the Macrostructural Factors</head><p>Alongside the growth in the number of theoretical perspectives and disciplinary approaches to studying (right-wing) populism, the inconsistency in the literature on how to "explain" this contested phenomenon has also grown. Significant efforts have also recently been made to facilitate comparisons across case studies and thereby draw generalizable ideas. However, genuine interdisciplinary works are lacking and the literature remains divided <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abromeit, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Populism is multifaceted since it emerges and evolves in different interrelated layers: the individual, the collective, the institutional, and the social. Each of these layers has been well studied and theorized. However, little has been done to theorize how these layers are interconnected, how they are related to one another, and how changes in one affect changes in another. The literature can be divided between at least three strata of explanation: (1) the macrostructural; where studies of the socioeconomic, sociohistorical, and political-economic accounts of populist ideologies, movements, and/or politics are located <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Judis, 2016)</ref>; (2) the meso-institutional; where studies of populism as a fundamentally political phenomenon and its interaction with other political forces and social institutions are situated (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">M체ller, 2016)</ref> and the social psychological mechanisms that mediate between the macro-and microdynamics are counted; and (3) the micro psycho-anthropological and psychological, where the emotional and psychological underpinning of populist attitudes and affective support for populist parties are investigated. However, there is not much dialogue or collaboration between accounts located in these three strata. For example, psychological accounts of populist sentiments and behaviors are largely either dismissed or downplayed by the researchers in the first and second strata, and vice versa.</p><p>When explaining the (global) rise or spread of right-wing populism as a macrosocial phenomenon (e.g., in the form of sociopolitical movements), macro-social structural changes, especially the political-economic transformations, appear to be the primary factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Caiani &amp; Graziano, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Flew, 2020)</ref>. These factors function in association with other primary sociodemographic determinants (such as age, regional or rural residential status, ethnicity, gender, education, religion, and/or occupation). This association occurs only in a relative sense (e.g., a relative decline in the middle-class and traditional working-class status as compared to lower-or under-class status) and is strengthened in the new context of fast-evolving communication and information landscape <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Kr채mer, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Moffitt, 2017, p. 3)</ref>.</p><p>Moreover, social psychological factors such as social anxiety, sense of insecurity, resentment, uncertainty, humility, and ressentiment (i.e., the "affects" associated with decreasing "white privileges" in a globalization context) mediate the relationship between macro factors such as economic liberalization and austerity regimes and meso-level or collective sociopolitical actions, such as electoral behaviors and institutional settings, in favor of populist parties, populist protests, and support <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Pettigrew, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Rydgren, 2003)</ref>. Furthermore, the sociohistorical residues of centuries of colonial-settler or patriarchal cultures such as class-racial discrimination, patriotism, misogyny, and racism, alongside personality factors like dogmatism, closed-mindedness <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Hosseini &amp; Saha, 2018)</ref>, social dominance, and authoritarianist personalities play a role in the translation of macrostructural changes and political discourses into personal and group actions and attitudes <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Rydgren, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>We now, due to the limited capacity of this chapter, focus on a few key explanations of RWP through macroscale social-scientific lenses. In doing so, we aim to highlight not only the advantages but also the perils of isolating macroanalyses from the two other strata and thereby in the next subsection emphasize the necessity of incorporating explanations from the other two strata.</p><p>The macrodynamics analyzed in the literature to explain the nurtures of RWP are mostly related to key social institutional shifts such as changes in democratic institutions due to adopting more authoritarian approaches to governance. The structure of economic activities and the relations between multiple social classes appear to be central. Similarly, political-economic structural shifts, and in particular the socio-ecological crises of capitalism faced at the systemic level and the challenges they pose to the material foundations of quality of life and the cultural sources of social integrity, are among the essential elements of such theorizations. Another macro factor is the perceived challenges that rapid demographic shifts, such as a sudden increase in the intake of foreign workers and flows of mass refugee immigration, pose to the social homogeneity of society and national social security in the eyes of the mainstream population, which can then ignite communitarian reactions. In the context of economic austerity, widely adopted as a neoliberal response to economic crises, such collective anxieties can quickly translate into xenophobic responses and demands for welfare chauvinism <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Marx &amp; Naumann, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>The literature highlights several interrelated social transformations in the contemporary global settings, which provide the macrostructural causes behind the rise and evolution of populist phenomena. The major factors that are widely discussed are:</p><p>1. The economic crisis of capitalism under neoliberal/corporate globalization, economic uncertainties or fluctuations, inequality (especially the "declining middle", particularly the lower middle classes) due to transforming employment structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Kurer, 2020)</ref>. 2. The political crises of globalism such as a decline in national sovereignties over internal affairs and economic independence and associated rising global insecurity, terror, and crime <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Flew, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Goldstein &amp; Gulotty, 2019)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The crisis of liberal democracy in the (post-) neoliberal context in both the "global</head><p>North" and "global South" <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Kaul, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">McKay et al., 2020)</ref>. 4. The crisis of Post-Gulf-War imperialism, contested American dominance, and Western expansionism <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">(Regilme Jr. &amp; Parisot, 2020)</ref>. 5. The crisis of multiculturalism and Eurocentric cosmopolitanism as value systems in the neoliberal context that gives way to the re-racialization of society, a process that can be traced back to the imagined "orient" (popular orientalism and its new form, Islamophobia) in persisting colonialist mentalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Kirtsoglou &amp; Tsimouris, 2018)</ref>. 6. The less-visible authoritarian nature of neoliberal globalism <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">(Tansel, 2017)</ref>. 7. The spatial, regional, or geographical imbalances of capitalist development and ethnic compositions <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(McQuarrie, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b80">van Wijk et al., 2020)</ref>. 8. The rise of a multi-polar international capitalist system, especially the more recently heightened conflicts between the old poles (the West) and the new poles (China and Russia), the 2022 Ukraine crisis being the latest stark example.</p><p>As discussed previously, these broad global shifts influence the social relationships between different sectors of society. A key factor is the change in socioeconomic status as perhaps the most discussed element in the literature. But there are also other related factors and their characterizations, such as age, regional, or rural residential status, ethnicity (white), gender (male), education (lower), and occupation (industrial). These factors are highly intertwined and thus require theories of intersectionality, originated by intersectional feminists <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Dietze et al., 2020)</ref>, to be incorporated.</p><p>Since the early 1980s, many countries began to adopt economic liberalization policies according to which they had to open their economies to more free trade, flows of capital, foreign investment, information, and immigration. However, these changes, despite their association with cycles of greater economic growth captured in indices like GDP, have also increased social divides within and between countries (Chase-Dunn, 2020; <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Hosseini et al., 2020)</ref>. Countries have adopted a policy focus to facilitate investment in areas in which they had a greater advantage over others.</p><p>Such policies create disparities between different sectors and regions of an economy. Some industries have gained greater leverage (high-tech industries and the finance sector) while others witnessed a decline in regional economies of advanced capitalist societies. Most importantly the manufacturing sector in the USA, UK, and Australia has been increasingly offshored to other countries with cheaper labor and resources, and weaker safety standards and environmental regulations. Relatedly, white-collar, information, financial, and advanced producer services have grown rapidly in urban areas in these countries. As the result of this globalization (increased interconnection and integration) between economies, metropolitan areas have flourished economically while nonmetropolitan rural and old industrial zones have suffered from these changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Harvey, 2005)</ref>.</p><p>Governments have generally changed their roles from the protectors, planners, and regulators of the economy to the facilitators of free-market activities. The growing sense of relative deprivation among the ex-beneficiaries of the nationally planned economies of the pre-neoliberal era, who increasingly have found themselves abandoned by the new globalist economic changes and centrist parties, is theorized as a major socioeconomic factor behind the rise of RWP (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Rooduijn &amp; Burgoon, 2017)</ref>. The relative deprivation was arguably not painful enough in the advanced capitalist societies of the 1980s and 1990s to instigate mass support for RWP, as the global economy, despite some challenges, could still cater for the hardworking, heavily indebted working classes in the "global North." The 2008 global financial crisis (GFC) however, accelerated the rate of financialization and thus the decline of the manufacturing sector in these countries, resulting in higher levels of relative deprivation <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Jetten et al., 2015)</ref>.</p><p>The literature suggests that the widely adopted reductions in corporate tax rates and the taxation of upper middle classes have been encouraged by neoliberal policies to improve economic growth and investment <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Kostigen, 2011)</ref>. This has however adversely affected state revenues (many becoming more dependent on debt than tax income) and capacities to fund public services and social security programs necessary for maintaining a level of equality <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Ostry et al., 2016)</ref>. The reduction in social spending means that those sectors of society that have witnessed a decline in their socioeconomic status as the result of changes under economic globalization, can hardly be compensated or even retrained and redeployed in the newly emerging sectors.</p><p>The economic/capitalist globalization processes accelerated under neoliberal and free trade regimes faced a financial "crash" in 2008. The crisis shook the debtdependent social status of many middle-class families, including many who had initially benefitted from earlier waves of economic liberalization. Governments generally responded to the crisis by cutting public spending under austerity measures, increasing their public debt to be repaid by their citizens in generations to come, and quantitative easing to increase the money supply with the effect of saving the "too big to fail" enterprises, most of them being the same corporations responsible for the crisis in the first place <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Patom채ki, 2009)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Judis (2016)</ref> defines the new (right-wing) populism as discontent with neoliberal policy and a sign of a society in the crisis that arises under particular political-economic conditions, i.e., the failure of neoliberalism. Indeed, the 2008 GFC discredited neoliberalism in the eyes of many, including some of its previous advocates. However, the rising populist parties in both the "global North" and "global South" reveal a much stronger willingness, compared to social democratic forces, to politicize their criticisms of central elements of neoliberal economics, such as free trade and to embrace more protectionist measures <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Judis, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>As a result of the growing social divide within globalized economies, the middle class has shrunk in size <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Kurer, 2020)</ref>. Since then, members of the middle class find themselves unable to fulfill their dreams. Interestingly, however, it is largely the middle-class white men (in the global North), with lower educational levels and employed in weakened manufacturing sectors, who are most attracted to populist movements <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(McQuarrie, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Rydgren, 2013)</ref>. While younger generations in metropolitan areas, immigrant workers, and women of color have suffered more severely from economic globalization, they are less attracted to RWP. This can be explained by considering the impact of greater education and contact/experience of other cultures/societies through traveling, living in cosmopolitan urban areas, experiencing ethnic marginalization, and access to a broader range of news and information sources.</p><p>In sum, RWP gives disenchanted masses simple answerssuch as blaming "the immigrants"to complex socioeconomic problems. Limited access to better quality (higher) education, counter-cosmopolitan worldviews developed as the result of lower engagement with the outside world, and a lack of detailed knowledge about the complex root causes of their socioeconomic decline, make individuals more prone to adopt right-wing populist sentiments and reasoning. Here again, socioeconomic status, though in close relation with other sources of social division/s, comes into the equation as one of the primary factors driving an individual's alignment with collective RWP movements. Education, communication, and knowledge (social consciousness) require resources, of which many community members in nonmetropolitan areas and deindustrialized urban spaces are often deprived.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5</head><p>Discussion: Indicative Insights into an Integrative Theory of RWP</p><p>As Jonathan H. <ref type="bibr">Turner (2010, p. viii)</ref> reminds us, "the social universe unfolds at the macro-, meso-, and micro-levels; and although these are analytical distinctions, they denote how the social world is actually structured." RWP, like any other transformative movement, is manifested at all levelsfrom the affective-psychological realm to collective-behavioral to communal-organizational to political-institutional domains and even intersocietal relations and conflicts. Scholarly accounts of the macrodynamics of RWP are useful in demonstrating how RWP at the macro-level can be understood in terms of forces like the shifts in (inter)national systemic relations in politics, economy, and culture, in associations with changes in social stratifications and hierarchies.</p><p>Understanding the macrodynamics of RWP is likely to provide us with a general overview applicable to multiple specific contexts because such factors have been commonly experienced under the effects of the globalization of capitalism, neoliberalism, and modernity. But such understandings fail to explicate why and how different groups, communities, and individuals within the same settings and/or exposed to the same macro-forces encounter populism differently. Further, it is essential to understand why the groups or individuals that experience the same emotional strain, as a result of the same macroscale shifts, and even may belong to the same social categories, do not necessarily always react by supporting RWP. Sociological explanations of the macrodynamics of RWP are inadequate as they do not illuminate how macrostructural changes translate into individual and group behaviors and attitudes (i.e., the so-called "downward causation"), and vice versa. They, therefore, need to be complemented with studies of emotional and social psychological mechanisms, as well as studies of collective actions and movements.</p><p>An example of the above is that there is no robust correlation between unemployment or low welfare provision and popular support for populist parties. Meanwhile, populist parties do not incessantly or ubiquitously derive their support from those negatively affected by economic liberalization or globalization; not all the male blue-collar workers of any given deindustrialized area (categorically or continuously) support RWP <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Kiss et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Walley, 2017)</ref>. Macrostructural accounts alone cannot explain all the variations in right-wing voting. Inconsistencies in the structural approach require us to bring the mediating psychological, collective, and attitudinal factors into the picture. Among the most reliable attitudinal factors attributed in the literature to the right-wing populist upsurge in politics are antiimmigrant attitudes, perceptions of ethnic threat, in-group favoritism, authoritarian personality, general political orientation and past party preferences, and political distrust and dissatisfaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">An Integrative Way Forward</head><p>We now narrow our argument to some key aspects of RWP to elaborate how the three strata are intertwined and thus how an integrative effort can begin to unravel the complexity of the phenomenon. In many micro accounts of rising right-wing populism, individual and collective disillusionment with democratic institutions is considered to be one of the major social psychological factors. Attention to these microlevel characteristics could bring us closer to explanations of why some people are right-wing populists, while others are not. But they are still inadequate given that disillusionment or resentment does not exclusively lead to a right-wing populist backlash. A response can manifest itself in many forms: from political apathy and disenfranchisement to violent insurgency, and from limited justice activisms (like the Occupy movements and Black Lives Matter movements) to the sudden outbursts of street protests and mass uprisings. For disillusionment to be translated into a sustainable political movement with long-term impacts on inter/national politics in the populist direction, the involvement of mediating meso-level mechanisms is required. Among these mechanisms are the dissident political parties and groupings that can facilitate the translation of collective resentment into electoral behaviors that can then result in the formation of new political discourses and meso-level institutional changes.</p><p>As parts of the literature argue, regarding the issue of resentment as a motive, many of the far-right movements like the Tea Party in America have been renowned for supporting social hierarchy or social inequality in general <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Rosenthal, 2020)</ref>. Consequently, the growing popularity of right-wing populist parties is most likely influential on those groups that share conservative values but also have experienced a relative decline in their status due to the new shifts in the (neoliberal) economy <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">(Swank &amp; Betz, 2003)</ref>. Right-wing populist groups tend to oversimplify complex problems as an effective tactic to communicate with less-educated groups and to blame bigger issues on already marginalized communities, to restore the traditional social hierarchies around race, gender, sexual orientations, and so on. This has led to racial hysteria among older generations living in regional areas and among the lesseducated working-class Americans. The social bases of many populist parties however have been fast expanding into metropolitan areas, thanks to underfunded public education systems. Further, new communication technologies have rekindled traditional discriminatory beliefs through innovative means <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(Ranieri, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>It is therefore important to know why and how the resentment caused by the contradictions in capitalist democratic societies, between an idealized perception of democracy and of the inability of an economic system to deliver those promises, translates into a communitarian or radical right-wing backlash rather than a more progressive response.</p><p>The question of why some people support radical right movements rather than progressive socialist movements must be answered by focusing on their "character structure" as a mediating factor. This would require us, as <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Fuchs (2018)</ref> argues, to draw on critical psychology combined with political economy and ideology critique. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abromeit (2017)</ref> argues that Frankfurt School Critical Theorists pioneered an interdisciplinary approach that can be adapted today to develop a more comprehensive explanation of RWP. Critical Theory combines the critique of capitalism, critical social psychology, and media and discourse analyses, as well as political theory. For instance, according to Franz L. Neumann <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Neumann &amp; Marcuse, 1957)</ref>, one of the associates of the Frankfurt School, destructive collective anxiety generates large-scale support for far-right movements when six conditions coincide: destructive competition, social alienation, the alienation of labor, political alienation, psychological alienation and persecutory anxiety, and finally the institutionalization of anxiety. Indeed, both the rise and demise of neoliberalism can be seen as the main source of the realization of these six preconditions of today's politics of anxiety <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Fuchs, 2017</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Fuchs, , 2018))</ref>.</p><p>It is reasonable to believe, as macro-sociological accounts tell us, that the inability of the State in reducing social inequalities and fulfilling the dreams of the middleclass has played a decisive role as a cause in the context of rising RWP in America. However, the disillusioned white male working class people of the rust belt states who allegedly showed their anger and anxiety for losing their status by voting for the populist candidate (Trump), could equally have voted for Bernie Sanders (as a social democrat who presented a greater capacity to address such social concerns in his campaign) had he been supported and nominated by his own party's establishment in the 2016 election. Seemingly, the lack of a strong alternative to a populist solution from the Left side of politics was a significant factor in this context. In the case of Greece's SYRIZA, for example, where the left alternative gained momentum in 2015, right-wing populism did not appear strong. This clearly indicates how mesolevel mechanisms like party politics can make a difference and mediate the translation of microlevel processes to macro-level ones.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusion</head><p>In this exploratory chapter, we set out to bring the study of RWP, as a concept, a movement phenomenon, a set of loosely articulated ideological discourses, and as a composition of attitudinal, affective, and behavioral characteristics, into the field of social inquiry. In so doing, we have demonstrated the multilevel nature and interrelated nurtures of right-wing populism, and the importance of developing integrative frameworks of inquiry based on a more precisely defined notion of RWP that would make studies not only more commensurable but also more complementary. We see RWP as a multilevel phenomenon manifested in the structural, institutional, and social psychological levels of society. We, therefore, differentiate between a universal "grand theory" of everything (called right-wing populist) and an integrative theorization of RWP. We consider the latter a realistic solution to the challenges of studying the phenomenon and overcoming unproductive chasms in the literature. We agree with <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">Wodak (2015)</ref> that the contingency of different contexts, where populist resurgence occurs, disallows any single overarching explanation. However, this does not automatically prohibit the possibility of developing a flexible integrative theoretical framework using pragmatically selective methodological approaches that, when applied in different contexts, allow for differences and contingencies to be included in the equation. This framework can be based on what <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Mudde and Rovira Kaltwasser (2017)</ref> consider to be a minimal definition of right populism that grasps its common features across space and time.</p><p>Fortuitously, while many sociologists have abandoned grand theory construction, integrative efforts to create meta-theoretical frameworks for multilevel analyses have been expanding <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Knorr-Cetina &amp; Cicourel, 2014)</ref>. There is no one single way of meta-theorization. The integrative approach, however, can provide us with many exemplars; from classical theories in sociology, to mid-twentieth century efforts like the Frankfurt School, to more contemporary ones like Giddens' structuration theory, Luhmann's social system theory, Actor-Network Theory, Emergence theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">(Sawyer, 2001</ref><ref type="bibr">), and Hosseini's constructuralism (2011</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">, 2012)</ref>. Developing such integrative frameworks, therefore, remains an open, yet inevitable, quest for those committed to non-reductionist approaches. Only when we can study RWP in this way, will it become an important and highly relevant part of growing interdisciplinary endeavors in understanding further this very important modern social phenomenon. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Social change in the smart cities era: revisiting tensions between technocracy and populism  Emotions as Societal Responses in the Age of Globalization  Modern Right-wing activism in Japan  Social Movements and Social Change in the Early 21st Century  The Necessity for an Integrative Theory of Right-Wing Populism in the 21st Century  Remove your knee from my neck: A radical call to collapse the politics of race through the Black Lives Matter Movement in the USA and beyond  The rise of post-populist conservatism in Turkey: an initial glance  Neoliberal Globalization, Class Conflict, and Social Change</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Right-wing Populism in a Global Perspective: The Necessity for. . .</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A critical review of recent literature on populism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Abromeit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.17645/pag.v5i4.1146</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.17645/pag.v5i4.1146" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Politics and Governance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is populism an ideology? A refutation and a new perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Aslanidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-9248.12224</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-9248.12224" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Noam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The populist style in American politics: Presidential campaign discourse</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1593" to="1621" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Berlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://berlin.wolf.ox.ac.uk/lists/bibliography/bib111bLSE.pdf" />
		<title level="m">To Define Populism</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1967">2013. 1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The radical right and populism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Betz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Oxford handbook of the radical right</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rydgren</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="164" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brexit, trump, and &apos;Methodological Whiteness&apos;: On the misrecognition of race and class</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bhambra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1468-4446.12317</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1468-4446.12317" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The British Journal of Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">Suppl 1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why populism?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brubaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11186-017-9301-7</idno>
		<idno>11186-017-9301-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theory and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding varieties of populism in times of crises</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Caiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Graziano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01402382.2019.1598062</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01402382.2019.1598062" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">West European Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1141" to="1158" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The blurred borders of racism, neo-fascism and national populism. asopis za kritiko znanosti</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Campani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">260</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twenty-first century Deglobalization and the struggle for global justice in the world revolution of 20xx</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chase-Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Routledge handbook of transformative global studies</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Motta</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gills</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="43" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Colgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Keohane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Liberal order is rigged</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Foreign Affairs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">36</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vulnerability and the discourse of &apos;forgotten people&apos;: Populism, population and cultural change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10304312.2020.1798875</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10304312.2020.1798875" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Continuum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="749" to="762" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Authoritarian populism and liberal democracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Crewe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sanders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-030-17997-7</idno>
		<ptr target="http://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-3-030-17997-7" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Palgrave Macmillan</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differentiating between Donald Trump and Hillary Clinton voters using facets of right-wing authoritarianism and social-dominance orientation: A brief report</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Crowson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0033294117697089</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0033294117697089" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="373" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The promise and perils of populism global perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>De La Torre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>The University Press of Kentucky</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Right-wing populism and gender: European perspectives and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dietze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Walter De Gruyter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Co</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<pubPlace>Wetzlar</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>transcript</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Returning populism to history</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Finchelstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-8675.12131</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-8675.12131" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Constellations: An International Journal of Critical &amp; Democratic Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="482" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Globalization, neo-globalization and post-globalization: The challenge of populism and the return of the national</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Flew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1742766519900329</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1742766519900329" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Media and Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Post-populism in Zambia: Michael Sata&apos;s rise, demise and legacy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0192512117720809</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0192512117720809" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Political Science Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="456" to="472" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exit Polls Show Both Familiar and New Voting Blocs Sealed Biden&apos;s Win</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.brookings.edu/research/2020-exit-polls-show-a-scrambling-of-democrats-and-republicans-traditional-bases/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-02-03">2021. 3 February 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Donald Trump: A critical theory-perspective on authoritarian capitalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Triplec-Communication Capitalism &amp; Critique</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authoritarian capitalism, authoritarian movements and authoritarian communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0163443718772147</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0163443718772147" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Media Culture &amp; Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="779" to="791" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Populism the timeline of a concept</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Fuentes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3167/choc.2020.150103</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3167/choc.2020.150103" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contributions to the History of Concepts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Germani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Authoritarianism, fascism, and National Populism</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The globalisation crisis: Populism and the rise of an anti-trade coalition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gulotty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3224/eris.v6i3.04</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3224/eris.v6i3.04" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ERIS -European Review of International Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Let them eat tweets: How the right rules in an age of extreme inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hacker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pierson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Liveright Publishing Corporation</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Spaces of Neoliberalization: Towards a theory of uneven geographical development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Harvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Franz Steiner</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Alternative globalizations: An integrative approach to studying dissident knowledge in the global justice movement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper Back edition ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theorizing social ideations: Beyond the divide between humanities and social sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id쩌2015482" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of the Humanities</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How &apos;Critically Open-Minded&apos; Are We? An Australian Perspective through the World Values Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Saha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11205-017-1608-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-017-1608-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Indicators Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1211" to="1236" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Motta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Routledge handbook of transformative global studies</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Populist mobilization: A new theoretical approach to populism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-9558.2011.01388.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9558.2011.01388.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relative deprivation and relative wealth enhances antiimmigrant sentiments: The V-curve re-examined</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mols</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Postmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0139156</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0139156" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139156" to="e139156" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The populist explosion: How the great recession transformed American and European politics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Judis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Columbia Global Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Populism and the crisis of liberalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kaul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0191453718774951</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0191453718774951" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophy &amp; Social Criticism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theorizing the radical right: Directions for social movements research on the right-wing social movements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kincaid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/soc4.12469</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/soc4.12469" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociology Compass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Migration, crisis, liberalism: The cultural and racial politics of islamophobia and &quot;radical alterity&quot; in modern Greece</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kirtsoglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tsimouris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01419870.2018.1400681</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01419870.2018.1400681" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ethnic and Racial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1874" to="1892" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Right-wing populism in a Metropolis: Personal financial stress, conservative attitudes, and Rob Ford&apos;s Toronto</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M L</forename><surname>Perrella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Spicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/07352166.2019.1657021</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/07352166.2019.1657021" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Urban Affairs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1028" to="1046" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Advances in social theory and methodology: Toward an integration of micro-and macro-sociologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Knorr-Cetina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Cicourel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The big handout: How government subsidies and corporate welfare corrupt the world we live in and wreak havoc on our food bills</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kostigen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Rodale</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Populist online practices: The function of the internet in right-wing populism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kr채mer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/1369118X.2017.1328520</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2017.1328520" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information, Communication &amp; Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1293" to="1309" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The declining middle: Occupational change, social status, and the populist right</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kurer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0010414020912283</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0010414020912283" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10-11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1798" to="1835" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shrinking and shouting: The political revolt of the declining middle in times of employment polarization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kurer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Palier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/2053168019831164</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/2053168019831164" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research &amp; Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">205316801983116</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Politics and ideology in Marxist theory: Capitalismfascismpopulism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Laclau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Political man: The social bases of politics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Verso</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lipset</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Heinemann</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1960">1979. 1960</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extreme right-wing voting in Western Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lubbers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gijsberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scheepers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Political Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Populism and democratic theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mansbridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Macedo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-lawsocsci-101518-042843</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-lawsocsci-101518-042843" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Law and Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do right-wing parties Foster welfare chauvinistic attitudes? A longitudinal study of the 2015 &apos;refugee crisis&apos; in Germany</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Marx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Naumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.electstud.2018.01.011</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.electstud.2018.01.011" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electoral Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">&apos;Pitbulls&apos; and populist politicians: Sarah Palin, Pauline Hanson and the use of gendered nostalgia in electoral campaigns</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative American Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="199" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authoritarianism, populism, nationalism and resistance in the Agrarian South</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mckay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D L T</forename><surname>Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02255189.2020.1814707</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02255189.2020.1814707" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian Journal of Development Studies / Revue canadienne d&apos;챕tudes du d챕veloppement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="347" to="362" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The revolt of the Rust Belt: Place and politics in the age of anger</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcquarrie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1468-4446.12328</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1468-4446.12328" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="S152" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The global rise of populism: Performance, political style, and representation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moffitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.11126/stanford/9780804796132.001.0001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.11126/stanford/9780804796132.001.0001" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Populism: A very short introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mudde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rovira Kaltwasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>still image</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/actrade/9780190234874.001.0001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/actrade/9780190234874.001.0001" />
		<title level="m">Retrieved from Very short introductions</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">What is populism?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>M체ller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Marcuse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The democratic and the authoritarian state: Essays in political and legal theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Neuner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wratil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11109-020-09629-y</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11109-020-09629-y" />
		<title level="m">The populist marketplace: Unpacking the role of &quot;thin&quot; and &quot;thick&quot; ideology. Political Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Norocel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hellstr철m</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>J첩rgensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nostalgia and Hope: Intersections between politics of culture, welfare, and migration in Europe</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The rise of populism, the demise of the neoliberal and neoconservative globalist projects, and the war on human rights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/21598282.2019.1613917</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/21598282.2019.1613917" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Critical Thought</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="268" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Workers and the radical right in Poland</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/S0147547917000345</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0147547917000345" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Labor and Working-Class History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ostry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Loungani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Furceri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fandd/2016/06/pdf/ostry.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Neoliberalism: Oversold? Finance and Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="41" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neoliberalism and the global financial crisis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Patom채ki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/07393140903322497</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/07393140903322497" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The fascism in our heads&apos;: Reich, Fromm, Foucault, Deleuze and Guattari -The social pathology of fascism in the 21st century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00131857.2020.1727403</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00131857.2020.1727403" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Educational Philosophy and Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In pursuit of three theories: Authoritarianism, relative deprivation, and intergroup contact</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Pettigrew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-psych-122414-033327</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-psych-122414-033327" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Populism, media and education: Challenging discrimination in contemporary digital societies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ranieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contested American dominance: Global order in an era of rising powers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S F</forename><surname>Regilme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Parisot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Routledge handbook of transformative global studies</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A H</forename><surname>Hosseini</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Motta</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gills</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="193" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Populism and its democratic, non-democratic, and anti-democratic potential</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Riedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Polish Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The populist process: A theoretical contribution to the debate of the phenomenon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Riveros</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Izquierdas</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The paradox of well-being: Do unfavorable socioeconomic and sociocultural contexts deepen or dampen radical left and right voting among the less welloff?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rooduijn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Burgoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0010414017720707</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0010414017720707" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1720" to="1753" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Empire of resentment: Populism&apos;s toxic embrace of nationalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rosenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>The New Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meso-level reasons for racism and xenophobia: Some converging and diverging effects of radical right populism in France and Sweden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rydgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1368431003006001560</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1368431003006001560" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Explaining the emergence of radical right-wing populist parties: The case of Denmark</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rydgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/0140238042000228103</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/0140238042000228103" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">West European Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="474" to="502" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Class politics and the radical right</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rydgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">London</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emergence in sociology: Contemporary philosophy of mind and some implications for sociological theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sawyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/338780</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/338780" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="585" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The thin ideology of populism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13569310701822289</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13569310701822289" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Ideologies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Globalization, the welfare state and right-wing populism in Western Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Swank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-G</forename><surname>Betz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/soceco/1.2.215</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/soceco/1.2.215" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Socio-Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">States of discipline: Authoritarian neoliberalism and the contested reproduction of capitalist order</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tansel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Rowman &amp; Littlefield International</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anger: From primordial rage to the politics of hatred and resentment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tenhouten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Nova Science Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Theoretical principles of sociology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Where does ethnic concentration matter for populist radical right support? An analysis of geographical scale and the halo effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tolsma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.polgeo.2019.102097</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.polgeo.2019.102097" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Geography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102097</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A political sociology of populism and leadership</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Viviani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.13128/Smp-20860</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.13128/Smp-20860" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Societamutamentopolitica-Rivista Italiana Di Sociologia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="303" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The emergence of illiberalism: Understanding a global phenomenon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vormann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weinman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trump&apos;s election and the &quot;white working class&quot;: What we missed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Walley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/amet.12473</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/amet.12473" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Ethnologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The politics of fear: What right-wing populist discourses mean</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wodak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>SAGE Publications Ltd</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
