<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">How Much Do Citizens Care About Ethnic Wealth Gaps? Inequality and Support for Financial Market Stabilization in Times of Crisis *</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Research and Impact Fund at the London School of Economics</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">LSE</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_SenrzMf #_33t8Nrw #_grmccFp">
					<orgName type="full">Systemic Risk Centre</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">SRC</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Systemic Risk Centre at the London School of Economics</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Economic and Social Research Council</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">ESRC</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-06-30">30 June 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Björn</forename><surname>Bremer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Political Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central European University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><surname>Chwieroth</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of International Relations</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Economics § School of Social and Political Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Licia</forename><surname>Bobzien</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lea</forename><surname>Kaftan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Patricia</forename><surname>Posey</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lukas</forename><forename type="middle">Stötzer Robin</forename><surname>Hetzel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joe</forename><surname>Higton</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">the University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">the University of Vienna</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">the University of Zurich</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Witten</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Herdecke University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">How Much Do Citizens Care About Ethnic Wealth Gaps? Inequality and Support for Financial Market Stabilization in Times of Crisis *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-06-30">30 June 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3E0A36250F54B6781C6E0D0CFBCB5C2C</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:14+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Ethnic wealth gaps</term>
					<term>wealth inequality</term>
					<term>financial crises</term>
					<term>stabilization policies</term>
					<term>multi-ethnic societies</term>
					<term>survey experiments</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>People value household wealth as a source of private insurance, investment, and social status, which is reflected in their policy preferences. These preferences encourage governments to stabilize financial markets and protect private wealth during major economic crises. However, such policies often exacerbate wealth inequality, including between dominant and subordinate ethnic groups. We explore how citizens evaluate this trade-off by using information treatment and conjoint survey experiments in Australia and the UK in the wake of the COVID crisis. We find that information on ethnic wealth disparities has little, if any, effect on financial stabilization policy preferences, whereas information on ethnicity-neutral wealth inequality reduces support for such stabilization. Additionally, the conjoint experiment reveals greater acceptance of targeted interventions that reduce general wealth disparities than of targeted interventions to alleviate ethnic inequality. Our findings reveal a critical political economy constraint on contemporary policy efforts to address enduring inequities in multiethnic societies.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Debate over the inequities of "racialized capitalism" in advanced democracies has recently moved to center stage <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">(Melamed 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b93">Robinson 1983)</ref>. As <ref type="bibr">Darity (2022, p. 402)</ref> explains, this form of social stratification means that "[m]embers of a subordinate group can do all 'the right things'...and still not receive the level of rewards received by similarly accomplished members of a dominant group" (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">DeSante 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Large wealth gaps result from and reproduce such stratification (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Addo and Darity 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Darity 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Derenoncourt et al. 2022)</ref>. Most scholarly attention to "ethnic" wealth inequality, which we define as a systematic absolute difference in the median household net wealth of dominant and historically subordinate ethnic groups, 1 has focused on the United States (US), with its large and persistent ethnic wealth divides. 2 Although systematic comparison is hampered by large data gaps, there are similarly large ethnic wealth disparities in other advanced democracies <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Chatterjee, Czajka, and Gethin 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Karagiannaki 2023)</ref>. 3 For example, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> shows that Indigenous Australian and Black British households have far lower median levels of wealth than majority White households, comparable with Black-White wealth inequality in the US.</p><p>Research points to historical legacies, market structures, and societal and policy biases as sources of persistent large wealth gaps and policies that reproduce them. In the US case, these include the racialized allocation of credit and its effects on the distribution of housing assets <ref type="bibr" target="#b106">(Thurston 2018</ref>) and health outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Hamil-Luker and O'Rand 2023)</ref>, the legacies of the G.I. Bill <ref type="bibr" target="#b108">(Turner and Bound 2003)</ref> and redlining in housing markets <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">(Rothstein 2017)</ref>, labor market stratification <ref type="bibr">(Chetty et al. 2024)</ref>, and biases in personal bankruptcy and welfare regimes <ref type="bibr" target="#b112">(Wiedemann and Wise 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b115">Wise 2020)</ref>. In Europe, the 1. The terms "race" and "ethnicity" overlap. We use the latter throughout, as it is the more dominant term. Since "White" and "Black" are common shorthands for dominant and subordinate groups in many advanced democracies, we also use them accordingly (see <ref type="bibr">Finney et al. 2023, pp. 1-10)</ref>.</p><p>2. Across each quintile of the wealth distribution the White-to-Black ratio of median household net worth is ten to one or higher <ref type="bibr">(Darity, Addo, and Smith 2021, p. 6)</ref>.</p><p>3. Most European national statistical agencies do not compile statistics on race or ethnicity <ref type="bibr">(Balestra and Fleischer 2018, p. 15)</ref>. Others, such as Canada, do not collect data on household wealth by race or ethnicity.  literature on "welfare chauvinism" has shown how anti-immigrant bias reduces support for redistribution (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Avdagic and Savage 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Magni 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b96">Rueda 2018)</ref>.</p><p>We are not primarily interested in testing public attitudes towards redistribution and welfare policy. Instead, we investigate attitudes towards other policies that have powerful (indirect) consequences for wealth inequality: those that protect private wealth during economic crises. People value personal wealth as a form of private insurance against shocks, for retirement, as sources of investment in human and business capital, as collateral for borrowing, and for social status (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ansell 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Iversen and Rehm 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b111">Wiedemann 2021)</ref>. During the Global Financial Crisis (GFC) and the COVID-19 pandemic, governments supported household incomes, wealth, and continued access to credit markets by stabilizing financial markets and boosting the value of financial assets and housing (see Figure <ref type="figure">A</ref>.1 in the Appendix). These interventions benefited many middle-class and poorer households, but wealthier households captured most of the wealth benefits. For example, in the United Kingdom (UK) and the US, the wealth share of the poorest 50 percent of households (in which subordinate ethnic groups are disproportionately represented) fell after the GFC, while those in the top decile increased.</p><p>In the US, the wealth of subordinate ethnic group households experienced larger declines than those of White households during the Great Recession and its immediate aftermath <ref type="bibr">(2007)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2008)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2009)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2010)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2011)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2012)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2013)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Credit Suisse 2022)</ref>.</p><p>Financial market stabilization may be necessary in complex, financialized economies to prevent cascading defaults and economic collapse that would negatively affect most peo-</p><p>ple. Yet it often increases wealth inequality because supporting asset prices disproportionately benefits the already wealthy -an instance of the so-called "Matthew effect". 4   Since wealth inequality is typically much higher than income inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Fagereng et al. 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Gomez 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr">Greenwald et al. 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wolff 2022)</ref>, and dominant ethnic groups hold an outsized share of market-traded assets <ref type="bibr">(Crossley, Fisher, and</ref>  The actions you need to take to protect everyone cause the equity markets to 4. "For to everyone who has will more be given, and he will have abundance; but from him who has not, even what he has will be taken away" (Matthew 25:29, RSV).</p><p>go up, and those that own the equities benefit more.' Ethnic wealth inequality is longstanding, but this policy trade-off is a comparatively recent phenomenon. The political salience of ethnic disadvantage increased with the Black Lives Matter (BLM) protests after the murder of George Floyd in March 2020.</p><p>The COVID-19 pandemic also increased sympathy for disadvantaged ethnic minorities by highlighting their role in front-line health and other service sector jobs. Among advanced democracies, disparities between ethnic groups are considered among the most concerning forms of inequality in Canada, the Netherlands, Australia, the UK, and the US, especially among the young <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Duffy et al. 2021</ref>; see also <ref type="bibr">Benson et al. 2021, pp. 23-27)</ref>.</p><p>In addition, only since the 1970s have governments consistently acted to protect household wealth during crises <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Chwieroth and Walter 2019)</ref>. Before World War Two, crises associated with plagues, wars, revolutions, and state collapse often drove sustained reductions in economic inequality by destroying the wealth of the rich <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">(Scheidel 2017)</ref>. Since then, the rise of mass middle-class wealth has made it virtually impossible for governments not to intervene to prevent widespread wealth destruction.</p><p>How then do citizens evaluate this modern policy trade-off between crisis interventions and reducing ethnic wealth inequality? Do they favor addressing ethnic wealth inequality during crises if this puts their own wealth at greater risk? This question is a crucial test of the strength of support for financial stabilization policies. It is also a hard test of the strength of inequality aversion and of the <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">Meltzer and Richard (1981)</ref> argument that as inequality grows, most voters will favor more redistribution.</p><p>We address these issues by examining attitudes in Australia and the UK, two multiethnic countries with high ethnic wealth inequality that have received limited scholarly attention.</p><p>We fielded a large online survey in both countries in early 2022 (n=5,096). We used an information treatment experiment to test whether informing people of large ethnic wealth gaps and the effect of crisis interventions on them influenced their support for financial stabilization policies. To provide a benchmark, we also used an information treatment that highlights the impact of financial stabilization policies on "ethnicity-neutral" wealth inequality (that is, referring only to wealth deciles). This allowed us to determine whether aversion to ethnic wealth inequality differs from aversion to ethnicity-neutral inequality.</p><p>We then used a conjoint survey experiment to test whether people favored mitigating the regressive impact of financial stabilization policies by providing targeted direct assistance to ethnic minorities, comparing this to support for assistance to "poor" households.</p><p>We find that most people, unsurprisingly, support financial stabilization policies in crises.</p><p>Wealth inequality aversion is also apparent but, strikingly, only when framed in ethnicityneutral terms. Thus, our core finding is that most people give little weight to the regressive consequences of such policies for ethnic inequality. The conjoint survey experiment also shows that, on average, respondents support compensation for poor households but oppose it for disadvantaged ethnic groups. The results of both experiments are robust to a series of different specifications and tests. Further analysis indicates that respondents are less averse to ethnic wealth inequality than to ethnicity-neutral wealth inequality due to strong in-/out-group dynamics, ethnic resentment, merit-based beliefs about inequality, and right-wing partisanship.</p><p>We see these results as substantively important. Contemporary wealth inequality is high and persistent, especially between dominant and subordinate ethnic groups. By undertaking financial stabilization in crises, governments are doing what is broadly popular, but this can reproduce one of the most pernicious inequalities in contemporary capitalist democracies. Persisting ethnic inequality dampens growth and poverty reduction by limiting opportunities for disadvantaged citizens, increasing their financial vulnerability, eroding democratic institutions and norms <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Bartels 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Burgoon et al. 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Darvas and Midões 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Hacker and Pierson 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b94">Rodrik 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Silverman and Moise 2021)</ref>, and reducing support for public goods provision <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Busemeyer and Iversen 2020)</ref>.</p><p>The next section situates our questions in existing research and develops our empirical expectations. Section three discusses our cases, data, and research methods. Section four describes our information treatment experiment and summarizes its results. Section five describes our conjoint experiment and its results. Section six addresses some significant heterogeneous treatment effects, and the final section considers the wider implications of our findings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theory</head><p>Today, especially in advanced economies, governments and central banks use a growing policy arsenal to limit losses from financial crises. This includes interest rate reductions, bank recapitalizations, central bank asset purchases and liquidity provision, asset and liability guarantees, and debt rescheduling and reduction. All were used during the GFC and the COVID-19 pandemic, directly or indirectly supporting the prices of financial and housing assets that dominate household wealth <ref type="bibr">(Chwieroth and Walter 2019, pp. 165-184)</ref>. These policies also maintain private sector access to credit, allowing firms to maintain output and employment, and households to refinance leveraged assets such as housing at lower cost and to borrow to invest in education and skills <ref type="bibr" target="#b111">(Wiedemann 2021)</ref>.</p><p>During the pandemic, many governments introduced explicit household debt relief and rescheduling policies, while others encouraged banks to allow struggling borrowers to delay repayments. 5 These financial stabilization policies differ in principle from unemployment insurance, but the line is blurred because leveraged households use income to service debt and thus to preserve asset ownership and credit access.</p><p>We set aside the question of government policy motivations and focus on voter preferences. Many households have a strong material interest in financial stabilization policies.</p><p>Those with high net wealth face significant financial risks, particularly when it is illiquid <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Jensen and Wiedemann 2023)</ref>. In recent decades, middle-class voters have gained significant wealth in the form of property and pensions, and their participation in financial markets has grown, including via credit. Adverse market movements threaten retirement 5. Household debt relief policies were comparatively modest during the GFC, such as the Obama administration's HAMP program.</p><p>prospects due to the general shift from defined benefit to defined contribution pensions.</p><p>Less wealthy households also have a growing stake in financial stabilization due to dependence on credit to cope with shocks, to retain control of leveraged housing assets, and to maintain consumption of goods and services such as education and healthcare <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Ahlquist and Ansell 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Crouch 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">OECD 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b111">Wiedemann 2021)</ref>. Lastly, households may support financial stabilization policies to prevent adverse sociotropic effects resulting from financial sector collapse and mass unemployment. These considerations suggest that risks to household wealth will shape voters' preferences on financial stabilization, as in other domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Ahlquist and Ansell 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ansell 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Chwieroth and Walter 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Hariri, Jensen, and Lassen 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b80">Margalit and Shayo 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Markgraf and Rosas 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b111">Wiedemann 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The regressive effects of financial stabilization</head><p>Financial stabilization is problematic from another perspective because it disproportionately benefits the wealthiest households, among which ethnic minority groups are often under-represented. Low net wealth held by disadvantaged ethnic minorities has multiple causes, including historically racialized credit allocation that hampered access to housing <ref type="bibr" target="#b106">(Thurston 2018)</ref>, and low household income, pension and financial market access, and low intergenerational transfers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Addo and Darity 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Darity 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Derenoncourt et al. 2022)</ref>. Hence, crisis policies that boost market asset values disproportionately benefit wealthier households. Disadvantaged ethnic minority households with financialized assets can benefit in absolute terms but lose in relative terms because of their lower net wealth than dominant groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Bourquin, Brewer, and Wernham 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Crossley, Fisher, and Low 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Kanabar 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b109">Weller and Figueroa 2021)</ref>. These regressive effects have not gone unnoticed. During the COVID pandemic, some progressive politicians called on governments and central banks to assist disadvantaged ethnic groups by undertaking bold wealth and income redistribution. In introducing legislation to require the US Federal Reserve to tackle racial gaps in employment, income, and wealth, Senator Elizabeth Warren insisted that "systemic racism and inequality is...a result of specific policy choices and the Fed must take deliberate action to fix it." 6 There have been similar calls on other governments to reduce ethnic wealth inequality, including in the UK <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Khan 2020)</ref> and Australia <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">(McIlwraith 2024)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluating preferences for financial stabilization</head><p>How do people evaluate the trade-off between financial stabilization and addressing high ethnic inequality? Many people are concerned about distributional fairness and exhibit "inequality aversion" <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Cavaillé and Trump 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Dimick, Rueda, and Stegmueller 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Gilens and Thal 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">McCall and Kenworthy 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Scheve and Stasavage 2017, pp. 463-464)</ref>. If inequality is seen as the result of structural disadvantage and luck rather than variations in personal effort, support for redistribution tends to be higher <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Alesina and Angeletos 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Ballard-Rosa, Martin, and Scheve 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Cappelen et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Gilens 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b82">McCall 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Petersen 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b90">Petersen et al. 2011)</ref>. Such inequality aversion can also influence assessments of crisis interventions. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Limberg (2020)</ref> shows that GFC policy interventions were often perceived as unfairly benefiting wealthier residents, increasing support for progressive redistribution.</p><p>However, we expect that general inequality aversion will not substantially dampen demand for financial stabilization policies for three reasons. First, as explained above, most households across the wealth distribution have a material interest in financial stabilization policies. These patterns of household wealth and indebtedness can erode their support for redistribution, dampening the effect of inequality aversion <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Ahlquist and Ansell 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Ansell 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b111">Wiedemann 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Second, as household wealth rises, inequality aversion likely falls. This may be because people are prone to motivated reasoning (Bénabou and Tirole 2016; Epley and Gilovich 6. Source: https://financialservices.house.gov/news/documentsingle.aspx?DocumentID=407678 2016). The relatively wealthy are more likely to adopt an individualist view of inequality as due primarily to variations in merit and effort, reducing their support for wealth redistribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Alesina and Angeletos 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Ballard-Rosa, Martin, and Scheve 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Cappelen et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Gualtieri, Nicolini, and Sabatini 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b82">McCall 2013)</ref>. Individuals' opinions about inequality can also be shaped by their partisan values <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Culpepper et al. 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b76">Lindqvist 2024)</ref>.</p><p>Third, attitudes toward redistribution can be shaped by ethnic and racial biases <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Harell, Soroka, and Iyengar 2016)</ref>. Individuals in dominant ethnic groups can oppose redistribution if they perceive subordinate groups as disproportionate or undeserving beneficiaries.</p><p>Such "welfare ethnocentrism" <ref type="bibr">(Ford 2016, p. 633)</ref> may offset concerns about the regressive effects of financial stabilization policies. Thus, we expect the following: Hypothesis 1. Support for financial stabilization policies will be widespread in assetrich, financialized economies.</p><p>However, support for stabilization policies could depend on people's access to information linking the consequences of financial stabilization to a fairness narrative <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Culpepper et al. 2024)</ref>. The distributive consequences of these policies are complex and difficult to understand. Moreover, many people in practice underestimate inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Gimpelson and Treisman 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">Xu and Garand 2010)</ref>. This suggests that providing information about the impact of stabilization could alter their policy preferences. However, research shows that such information often has little impact on redistribution preferences <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Ciani, Louis, and Manfredi 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Kuziemko et al. 2015)</ref>. 7 Thus, we expect that: Hypothesis 2a. Informing respondents about the distributive consequences of financial stabilization policies will reduce but not eliminate support for these policies.</p><p>Nevertheless, some voters are likely to be sensitive to the regressive impact of stabiliza-7. Direct exposure to local inequality can have significant effects. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">Sands (2017)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b99">Sands and Kadt (2020)</ref>. tion policies. Inequality aversion might manifest itself in support for targeted assistance for underprivileged groups disadvantaged by financial stabilization policies. Such assistance could include direct transfers, subsidies, or preferential treatment for groups lacking wealth <ref type="bibr">(Wheeler 2021, p. 12)</ref>. Some voters may view targeted measures as more efficient than generalized redistribution and/or may prefer them to the indirect solution of curtailing financial stabilization policies. This produces a further expectation: Hypothesis 2b. On average, citizens will prefer a combination of generalized financial stabilization and targeted support for disadvantaged groups.</p><p>We also expect that some voters will be less concerned about the regressive impact of financial stabilization policies when they are framed in ethnic rather than general terms.</p><p>Inequality favoring one's in-group is more likely to be perceived as fair and merit-based <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Becker 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b107">Trump 2020)</ref>. Ethnic divides reduce support for redistribution in the US. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Alesina, Ferroni, and Stantcheva 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Elkjaer and Iversen 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Gilens 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b78">Luttmer 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b87">Myrdal 1944</ref>) and in societies with stronger redistributive traditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Alesina and Glaeser 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Alesina and Stantcheva 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Harell, Soroka, and Iyengar 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">Lieberman 2003)</ref>. Attitudes toward Indigenous peoples in settler societies, including the US, Canada, Australia, and New Zealand, also limit support for redistribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Beauvais 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Harell, Soroka, and Ladner 2014)</ref>.</p><p>These attitudes differ, at least in appearance, from "old-fashioned racism" (OFR) based on notions of innate racial hierarchy. Today, prejudice often manifests as "symbolic" resentment toward groups that are perceived to violate meritocratic norms (Cramer 2020; Kam and Burge 2018). 8 For example, some US voters viewed sub-prime mortgage defaults after 2007 as caused by poor initial purchase and borrowing decisions by particular groups, and thus as undeserving of public assistance <ref type="bibr" target="#b104">(Skocpol and Williamson 2016)</ref>. In fact, economic crises often exacerbate pre-existing social divides, amplifying the tendency of individuals to discriminate against outgroups <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Gidron and Mijs 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sambanis, Nikolova, 8</ref>. Others find OFR remains important in American politics: <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Huddy and Feldman (2009)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Knuckey and Kim (2015)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Tesler (2012)</ref>.</p><p>and Schultz 2022). In the extreme, ethnicity-neutral public assistance can be unpopular among in-groups if they exhibit welfare ethnocentrism or chauvinism (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Magni 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b96">Rueda 2018)</ref>. This can even apply to the poor in a dominant ethnic group <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Kuziemko et al. 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Therefore, we expect that informing people that poorer members of their society (which we call a "class" framing) are negatively affected by a policy intervention will have a stronger effect on preferences than informing them that disadvantaged ethnic subgroups are negatively affected. 9 Similarly, targeted assistance to disadvantaged ethnic minorities should be less popular than targeted assistance to the generalized "poor". This can be summarized as follows:</p><p>Hypothesis 3a. Informing respondents about the distributive consequences of financial stabilization policies will moderate support for these policies more when framed in class terms than when framed in ethnic group terms.</p><p>Hypothesis 3b. On average, citizens will prefer to complement financial stabilization measures with targeted support for poor households rather than with targeted support for ethnic minorities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Our Cases</head><p>To test our expectations, we focus on Australia and the UK, two countries relatively underexplored in the literature on ethnic wealth inequality. Unlike most countries, both collect data on ethnic wealth inequality, which is large and persistent. Like the US, they have wealthier white majorities and longstanding histories of discrimination against and 9. We define class in "economic" rather than "sociological" terms, focusing on the position of groups in the income and wealth distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Goldthorpe 2010)</ref>.</p><p>disadvantage among some ethnic minority groups. Both have fraught histories of imperialism, settler colonialism, immigration, and racism that remain politically salient, as demonstrated by recent controversies over the treatment of Britain's "Windrush" generation of immigrants from the Caribbean and by the failed "Voice to Parliament" for Indigenous Australians referendum in 2023. Australia and the UK are less tainted by the legacy of slavery than the US, upon which much social science literature has focused (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Alesina, Ferroni, and Stantcheva 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Alesina and Glaeser 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">DeSante 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Engstrom and Huckfeldt 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Gilens 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Haney-López 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Schram, Soss, and Fording 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Silverman and Moise 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b114">Winter 2006</ref>). 10 Neither country relied as heavily as the US on affirmative action programs as mechanisms of redistribution, nor have they experienced as strong a backlash against them <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">(Rieder 1987)</ref>. Both Australia and the UK also had more typical economic experiences during the pandemic than the United States, which had an exceptionally strong recovery that substantially benefited lower-income households.</p><p>Australia and the UK share other common characteristics that assist comparison, including political culture, institutions, economic development, welfare regimes emphasizing targeted rather than universal social insurance, comparable wealth inequality, and attitudes toward redistribution. Compared to the US, proportionally more citizens in Australia and the UK share the view that luck rather than merit determine individuals' economic circumstances, with the UK somewhat closer to a more "pessimistic" European norm. 11</p><p>The two countries also differ in relevant ways. Both have become more ethnically diverse in recent decades, but Australia has a very disadvantaged minority Indigenous population (Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders, hereafter "ATSI") and since the 1970s experienced rapid growth in immigration from East Asia. The UK's imperial experience means that its rising ethnic diversity, including its now significant Black British and South Asian 10. However, Britain's role in modern slavery before and after its phased abolition by parliament in 1833 has received considerable attention. E.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Huzzey (2012)</ref>.</p><p>11. See data from the International Social Survey Program and the World Values Survey shown in Appendix B. ethnic group population, is primarily due to immigration from former colonies. 12 We focus on ATSI and Black British ethnic groups rather than other minority ethnic groups because of their especially disadvantaged positions. These groups constitute similar proportions of the total population -about 3.3 and 4 percent respectively in Australia and the UK. Our two-country survey allows us to explore the possibility that different national attitudes and experiences shape policy preferences on financial stabilization and targeted compensation. Importantly, financial stabilization policies likely contributed to increasing wealth inequality in Australia and the UK, which was already politically salient before the pandemic. 13 In Australia over 2020-2021, the real net wealth of households in the wealthiest decile rose by an estimated average of $900,000, compared to $276,000 for the next three deciles and $66,000 for the bottom six. 14 In the UK, the net wealth of the richest decile of households increased from February 2020 to May 2021 by over £44,000, compared to £6,500 for the fifth decile and £0 for the bottom three. 15 12. We follow the terminology of both countries' national statistical agencies. 13. In Australia, the federal Senate initiated an inquiry on inequality in 2014. The UK Parliament appointed a Commission on Race and Ethnic Disparities (CRED) in 2020.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Governments in</head><p>14. In proportional terms, households in the bottom six deciles did slightly better than higher deciles <ref type="bibr">(Davidson and Bradbury 2022, pp. 26-27)</ref>.</p><p>15. The fifth decile gained most in proportional terms <ref type="bibr">(Leslie and Shah 2021, p. 35)</ref>. Basis points </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Monetary policy reductions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Our Survey</head><p>We worked with the survey company Qualtrics to recruit a high-quality sample of around 2,550 respondents from each country. We restricted the sample to eligible voters (citizens aged 18 or older) and used crossed quotas for age, gender, and education to obtain a representative general population sample. 16 The final version of the survey was fielded in both countries in March 2022. Data collection and the subsequent analyses were preregistered and received Institutional Review Board (IRB) approval. 17 were designed to elicit preferences towards financial stabilization. The lived experience of many respondents with these policies likely helped them to understand our questions, but we also prefaced each experiment with simple explanations to ensure that they had 16. We had pre-tested the survey among a convenience sample of students, using their feedback to refine it. 17. IRB approval was granted by the Research Ethics Committee of the London School of <ref type="bibr">Economics (ref. 43119)</ref>. The pre-analysis plan is available online at https://osf.io/gdmh5. We discuss ethical considerations in Appendix A.</p><p>sufficient knowledge to answer our questions.</p><p>The information treatment experiments randomly exposed subgroups to additional information on wealth inequality and the distributive effects of financial stabilization policies.</p><p>We provided two treatments to investigate whether information about policy effects on "ethnic" and "class" inequality had different effects on preferences. Our survey is distinctive but related to that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Alesina, Ferroni, and Stantcheva (2021)</ref>, who investigate the effect of providing a factual account of the causes and consequences of structural racism on US respondents' policy preferences.</p><p>Our conjoint experiment measured levels of support for a randomized set of alternative policies that many governments implemented during deep economic crises in recent decades. These include general financial stabilization policies as well as targeted assistance to disadvantaged households. This allows us to test whether respondents would support mitigating the regressive impact of financial stabilization policies by combining them with assistance for disadvantaged groups, defined either in class or ethnic terms. 18   Information treatment experiment: Financial stabilization policies and ethnic inequality</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental design and methods</head><p>We first showed an introductory vignette to all respondents that briefly explained the rationale and design of financial stabilization policies used by governments and central banks to mitigate wealth losses in an economic crisis. Then we randomly assigned two groups of respondents to different additional information treatments. The full text that 18. Wealth taxes are a theoretical alternative to targeted assistance. However, we excluded this option because it would not have allowed us to discriminate between aversion to higher inequality and personal loss aversion.</p><p>respondents received in each experimental group is shown in Appendix B. 19 These described respectively the effect of financial stabilization policies on the wealth distribution between ethnic groups ("the ethnicity frame") and between rich and poor groups ("the class frame"). A control group received no information about the distributive effects of these policies. This design enabled us to test how respondents reacted to the prospect of increasing inequality, and whether the ethnicity or class treatments were more powerful.</p><p>The ethnicity frame described the trade-off in which we are primarily interested. It first compared the average level and portfolio composition of household wealth for ATSI and non-ATSI households in Australia and Black and White British households in the UK, and the average levels of indebtedness of each group. Then it explained why high exante ethnic wealth inequality means that financial stabilization policies often increase this inequality.</p><p>The class frame compared the average levels and portfolio composition of wealth for households in the bottom ten percent and the top ten percent of the wealth distribution with the "typical" (median) household. It also compared the average levels of indebtedness of each group. Finally, it explained why financial stabilization policies often increase wealth inequality by disproportionately benefiting households with more property, pension, and financial assets. If judgments about the fairness of inequality depend on the availability of comparative information, then our treatments should mitigate any cognitive biases related to the lack of available information. 20   After being shown the information treatment (or none for the control group), respondents were asked: (1) to rate on a Likert scale from 0 to 10 how supportive they were of financial stabilization policies ("support variable") and (2) whether they would implement financial stabilization policies after a crisis if they had a say ("choice variable"), giving them three answer categories ("yes", "no", "don't know").</p><p>19. We used authoritative data on each country's wealth distribution from national statistical agencies and other respected surveys.</p><p>20. Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Culpepper et al. (2024)</ref>, we strive to maintain politically neutral language, but recognize that the impact of the treatment might be partially driven by some respondents' belief that merely raising the issue of inequality reflects left-wing bias.</p><p>We use these as our main dependent variables, employing linear regressions to calculate the average treatment effects (ATEs) of the frames on support for financial stabilization policies. To facilitate comparison of the results across the two dependent variables, we re-scaled the linear "support" variable measured on the Likert scale so that it ranges from 0 to 1. Moreover, since we are interested in support for financial stabilization, we transform the choice variable into a binary variable where 1 means support and 0 means no support (opposition or don't know).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">3</ref> shows that in the control group, support for financial stabilization policies is We also asked respondents about their support for individual stabilization policies. Figure  21 This could indicate that the preferences of some respondents are less strongly anchored because these respondents lack information about the effects of these policies. Therefore, we next analyze the effect of our information treatments.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> shows, as we expected, that providing information about the regressive effects of financial stabilization policies reduces support for them. The "class" treatment lowers support for financial stabilization by 5.7 percentage points compared to the control group (Model 1). Moreover, respondents exposed to this treatment are 10.5 percent less likely to answer that they would favor using financial stabilization policies in the next crisis compared to the control group (Model 4). These effects are statistically significant and remain stable when we include country-fixed effects (Models 2 and 5) and additional individual-level covariates (Models 3 and 6). 22</p><p>21. Poorer respondents tend to register a higher level of uncertainty than wealthier respondents and constitute roughly half of those who fail to articulate a clear preference. This may be because these respondents are less able to bear the costs of acquiring detailed information about financial sector stabilization policies. For a similar view regarding inheritance taxation, see <ref type="bibr">(Elkjaer et al. 2023)</ref>.</p><p>22. In the next section, we show that the treatments do not influence uncertainty.</p><p>The "ethnicity" treatment has a much smaller effect, reducing support for financial stabilization policies by only 1.9 percentage points (Model 1). More remarkably, the treatment has no statistically significant effect on respondents' choice to implement financial stabilization policies (Model 4). These effects are stable if we include country-fixed effects (Models 2 and 5) and individual-level covariates (Models 3 and 6).</p><p>Overall, the results are consistent with Hypotheses 2a and 3a. Only ethnicity-neutral information treatments highlighting the regressive impact of financial stabilization policies substantially reduce support for these policies. Thus, our respondents appear willing to forgo some of the benefits of interventions to avoid worsening class inequality, but collectively they are less concerned about higher ethnic inequality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Robustness tests</head><p>To probe the robustness of these results, we first used different regression models to estimate the treatment effects. We recoded the linear "support" variable into a dummy, which does not change the effects. Then we treated the "decision" variable as categorical and used multinomial probit regression models. The results confirm that the ethnicity treatment does not affect the choice to implement financial stabilization: it neither affects the likelihood to favor or oppose these policies nor the likelihood to answer "don't know"</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(see Figure A.10 in Appendix D).</formula><p>Second, we re-ran the analyses by country. <ref type="bibr">Figure A.11</ref> shows the resulting heterogeneous treatment effects (HTEs). It confirms that the class treatment has a negative effect in both countries. This effect is slightly larger in the UK, but the difference is not statistically significant. In contrast, the ethnicity treatment has no effect in either country.</p><p>Third, we used a manipulation check to test whether respondents receiving the treatment read our vignette carefully. Specifically, we asked respondents in our two treatment groups the following question: "Earlier we provided you with information comparing the Finally, we also asked respondents if they believe that financial stabilization policies would be effective for different social groups. These questions came after the primary dependent variables used above and included two questions about the effect of these policies on poor and ethnic minority households in each country. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> shows that both treatments reduce respondents' belief that such policies benefit ATSI and Black British households.</p><p>This signals that respondents, on average, understood the implications of our treatments.</p><p>Once again, in the case of the ethnicity treatment, this did not affect their support for financial stabilization policies, which further supports our inference that most respondents do not sufficiently weigh concerns about ethnic wealth inequality to change their policy preferences. Although respondents do not weigh concerns about ethnic inequality highly, they may support both generalized financial stabilization and targeted compensation to ethnic minorities. To test support for this combination, we use the conjoint survey experiment, in which we gave respondents detailed information about different policies that governments routinely implement during economic crises. We then asked them to decide between pairs of randomly created policy packages.</p><p>Specifically, we presented respondents with policy packages that included five policy interventions (attributes) with levels that randomly vary across pairings. This includes income support, policies protecting asset values, debt relief, and targeted support for specific social groups. 23 Table <ref type="table">3</ref> shows the wording of all attributes and levels in the conjoint experiment.</p><p>Each respondent was confronted with five pairs of policy packages and after each pair, 23. For each respondent, we randomized the order in which the respondent viewed the sets of policy tools. increase. The highest support is for wage replacement of 100 percent of the pre-crisis average wage. Yet we also find high support for financial stabilization policies, including protecting assets in bank accounts, in pensions, and in private property compared to no protection. It is stronger than support for policies protecting bond and share prices.</p><p>As noted earlier, one of the main components of household wealth, housing, is often leveraged. Many households require income to sustain mortgage and other debt payments, making it difficult to distinguish demand for income protection and for financial stabilization. However, most respondents also support policies facilitating the restructuring of mortgage and other personal debts, including credit card debt. The restructuring of student debt is the least popular, but still more popular than no debt restructuring. The patterns are similar for debt rescheduling.</p><p>Overall, this is strong additional evidence that many Australian and British citizens favor financial stabilization policies. Do they also support combining financial stabilization with targeted support for disadvantaged groups?</p><p>To answer this question, we included targeted support for ethnic minority and poor households, respectively, as our main attribute of interest in the conjoint experiment.</p><p>We frame our question in a way most likely to induce generosity, by avoiding saying that targeted support will be financed by taxes or borrowing. The results suggest that respondents prefer a combination of financial stabilization and targeted support to poorer groups, consistent with Hypothesis 2b. However, they are strikingly divided on the desirability of targeted policies based on class and ethnicity. Most favor targeted support for "poor" groups but oppose targeted support for ATSI and Black British ethnic groups -both compared to no targeted support. This is consistent with Hypothesis 3b.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Robustness Tests</head><p>To probe the robustness of these results, we first repeated the analysis using respondents' rating of each package as a dependent variable, instead of the choice variable. As shown in Figure A.12, this does not change our results.</p><p>Second, we analyzed the conjoint experiment by country. Following Leeper, Hobolt, and Tilley (2020), we report the conditional marginal means in Figure A.13. It shows that country differences are minimal, except for reported preferences on targeted support for different groups. Opposition to targeted protection for disadvantaged ethnic households was significantly lower in Australia than in the UK. However, in both countries, there was much stronger support for targeted protection based on class (in line with Hypothesis 3b).</p><p>That these results are consistent across our two country samples increases our confidence in the external validity of this central finding.</p><p>Third, we used a priming experiment before the conjoint to test whether respondents oppose targeted assistance to ethnic minorities because they know little about the extent of their disadvantage. Do they change their preferences if they are informed about the size of the ethnic wealth gap? 24 Contrary to our pre-registered expectations, the answer is no: informed respondents also strongly oppose targeted assistance to wealth-poor ethnic minorities. 25 This could suggest that at least some respondents' views about the relative desirability of ethnicity-based redistribution are ingrained and relatively resistant to information provision, as <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Alesina, Ferroni, and Stantcheva (2021)</ref> also found in the US context.</p><p>Finally, we conducted several standard robustness tests for conjoint survey experiments.</p><p>We find no carry-over effects, i.e., respondents did not evaluate packages differently across the five rounds of conjoint tasks (see <ref type="bibr">Figure A.16</ref>). Nor did profile order alter our estimated effects <ref type="bibr">(Figure A.17)</ref>. Finally, the response to the conjoint experiment neither meaningfully varied by respondents' screen size <ref type="bibr">(Figure A.18)</ref> nor by respondents' survey completion time <ref type="bibr">(Figure A.19)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heterogeneous treatment effects</head><p>Why are respondents less averse to the regressive effects of financial stabilization on ethnic wealth inequality than on class inequality? We explore this question by investigating heterogeneous treatment effects (HTEs).</p><p>First, we find little evidence that respondents' preferences are shaped by variation in their material position in asset and credit markets, which is contrary to our pre-registered expectations. In an economy in which wealth increasingly influences policy preferences, even less financialized respondents appear to view the costs of worsening inequality as insufficient to outweigh the benefits of financialization stabilization policies. The level of financialization (measured variously) does not influence responses to the information treatment experiment <ref type="bibr">(Figure A.8)</ref>. However, in the conjoint experiment, people with more net wealth are more strongly opposed to targeted support for ethnic minorities 24. Appendix D includes more information about the priming example and its design. 25. The primes did not influence responses to the information treatment experiment, either.</p><p>(Figure A.9). We find somewhat smaller differences regarding targeted support for poor households; instead, people with more net wealth are more likely to favor no targeted support.</p><p>The weak effect of financialization variables implies that wider material considerations may drive overall support for financial stabilization. This could be because stabilization provides both personal and sociotropic benefits to households by protecting personal wealth and preventing wider economic and societal losses, including unemployment.</p><p>Treatment effects vary more strongly by other variables. As the upper-left panel of Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows, Black/ATSI respondents respond to the ethnic inequality treatment more than others. For Black/ATSI respondents, the information reduces their support for financial stabilization policies by 7.5 percentage points, while it has no effect on the majority. 26</p><p>This is mirrored by the results from the conjoint experiment (Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>, upper-left panel),</p><p>where Black/ATSI respondents are equally supportive of targeted support for ethnic minorities and poor households. Respondents from the majority strongly prefer support for poor households. Black/ATSI respondents are also more strongly opposed to no targeted support than other respondents; the latter even prefer no targeted support to targeted support for Black households.</p><p>This suggests that the majority of respondents are opposed to ethnicity-based redistribution due to strong in-/out-group dynamics, whereas outgroups view inequality and redistribution more through the lens of ethnicity. It is consistent with the interpretation that egalitarian values in liberal democracies are more strongly associated with notions of class rather than ethnic divides. It is also notable that despite their divergence from the majority position on the trade-off, Black/ATSI respondents still support financial stabilization policies in crises like the ethnic majority. This likely helps to sustain political support for financial stabilization policies.</p><p>26. Interestingly, Black/ATSI respondents do not, on average, respond to the class inequality information treatment. Other respondents respond only to the class treatment. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Partisanship</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>: HTEs in the information treatment experiment by ethnic group, ethnic resentment, inequality beliefs, and partisanship.</p><p>Note: The figure shows HTEs of the information treatments on the linear "support" variable as the dependent variable (recoded to range from 0-1); controls for country fixed effects and covariates included.</p><p>This dynamic is clearly influenced by ethnic resentment. 27 People exhibiting higher levels of ethnic resentment should care less about the regressive effects of financial market stabilization policies when framed in ethnic terms. This is exactly what we find. The ethnic information treatment reduces support for financial stabilization among people with low ethnic resentment, but not for people with medium or high resentment (Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>, upper-right panel). Interestingly, respondents with low ethnic resentment are also more responsive to the class treatment, suggesting that ethnic resentment may be correlated 27. We follow the literature and use an ethnic resentment index based on four common questions, the wording of which is shown in the Appendix. with a higher tolerance for inequality. Similarly, in the conjoint experiment, respondents exhibiting greater ethnic resentment are both more strongly opposed to ethnicity-based targeting and, perhaps more interestingly, more supportive of class-based targeting compared to people with low ethnic resentment. The former are also much more supportive of no targeted assistance compared to the latter. Ethnic resentment thus plausibly explains why some individuals are not concerned about the regressive effects of financial market stabilization policies on ethnic minorities and oppose redistribution along ethnic lines.</p><p>Most people, however, exhibit less ethnic resentment and their preference for class-based redistribution could derive from a view that it is the fairest option precisely because it is "colorblind". The similar results in both Australia and the UK increase our confidence that this result is not due to majority animosity towards either Indigenous or immigrant groups specifically.</p><p>Support for redistribution on ethnic lines may also be influenced by people's beliefs about social stratification. Respondents who believe that inequality is primarily due to bad luck (structuralism) respond to both information treatments, whereas those who believe that inequality is primarily due to differences in individual effort respond to the class inequality treatment and not to the ethnic inequality treatment (Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>, bottom-left panel). Inequality beliefs also influence responses to the conjoint experiment (Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>, bottom-left panel). People who hold structuralist views are less opposed to targeted support for ethnic households and more opposed to no targeted support than people who hold individualist beliefs. However, people who hold structuralist beliefs still clearly favor class-based redistribution and even oppose ethnicity-based support more than no targeted support.</p><p>Beliefs about social stratification are also related to partisanship. Left partisans are more likely to hold structural beliefs and are more egalitarian than right partisans. Since this may not translate into equally strong support for redistribution to out-groups, we examine how partisanship moderates our treatment effects. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> (bottom-right panel)</p><p>shows that left-wing respondents react to both the ethnicity and class frames, while right-wing respondents do not. One interpretation of this evidence is that opinions on inequality divide along familiar ideological lines because inequality is an easily accessible partisan issue. However, even left-wing respondents react much more strongly to the class frame. The conjoint experiment confirms these findings (Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>, bottom-right panel).</p><p>Left partisans are less opposed to ethnicity-based targeted support, consistent with the findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Alesina, Ferroni, and Stantcheva (2021)</ref>. They are also more opposed to no targeted support than right partisans but, interestingly, they are no more supportive of class-based compensation. Although right-wing respondents do not alter their support for financial market stabilization when they are informed about its regressive distributive consequences (as shown by the information treatment experiment), they seem ready to combine it with targeted support for poor households.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Household wealth and access to credit serve as important sources of self-insurance, investments in human capital, and social status. Adverse asset and credit market shocks play an increasingly central role in shaping public opinion and citizen behavior in contemporary unequal and racialized political economies. Our analysis shows how people evaluate the trade-off between financial stabilization during crises and reducing wealth inequality of different kinds. Most weight financial stabilization more highly than wealth redistribution. This suggests that the accumulation and financialization of wealth pushes strongly against societal support for redistribution, even as inequality grows in democracies. This is consistent with observed growth in crisis interventions in recent decades.</p><p>Yet by benefiting wealthier households most, these interventions can worsen societal inequality, especially between ethnic groups. Although this may help to entrench racialized capitalism in complex, financialized democracies, respondents in Australia and the UK appear relatively unmoved. Highlighting the impact of financial stabilization policies on class inequality somewhat reduces support for them, but highlighting the effects on ethnic inequality does not. We also found that respondents were much more likely to support a combination of financial stabilization policies and compensatory targeted interventions when the latter assist the generically "poor" than when they assist poor ethnic minorities.</p><p>These findings suggest that in both countries, most respondents are more likely to modify their support for financial stabilization due to its effects on class inequality than on ethnic group inequality. Ethnic majority respondents, those with high ethnic resentment, those with merit-based views of inequality, and those of right-wing political orientation seem to care least about ethnic wealth inequality. These groups have a strong preference for prioritizing financial stabilization. At the other end of the spectrum, ethnic minority respondents perceive an acute trade-off between these two policy goals and have a stronger preference for reducing ethnic wealth inequality. Ultimately, despite the BLM movement and the highlighting of ethnic inequalities during the pandemic, most people appear not to favor compensating poor ethnic groups during economic crises.</p><p>In many democracies, politics is decided in the middle ground rather than at the extremes. Although most citizens seem reluctant to base judgments about fairness and appropriate redistribution on ethnic or racial categories, they retain a significant aversion to the regressive impact of crisis interventions. Those with low to modest levels of ethnic resentment still strongly prefer ethnicity-neutral fairness rationales for tempering these regressive effects. These citizens give fairness considerations significant weight when evaluating policy choices, favoring targeted support to disadvantaged groups. Yet they do not favor the use of ethnicity frames in determining redistributive policies, perhaps because they see class-based redistribution as fairer (on grounds that the poor are found in all ethnic groups). This aligns with previous experimental studies of the United States <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Alesina, Ferroni, and Stantcheva 2021)</ref>. It also aligns with recent public opinion surveys <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Duffy et al. 2021</ref>; see also <ref type="bibr">Benson et al. 2021, pp. 23-27)</ref> showing that although some voters see these gaps as unfair and important, most prefer that governments pursue only class-based redistributive policies.</p><p>This interpretation has important implications. William Julius <ref type="bibr" target="#b113">Wilson (2011)</ref> argued that both race/ethnicity-based and class-based affirmative action was still needed to reduce the persistent socioeconomic disadvantage of underprivileged ethnic minorities. Since then, there have been growing calls for bolder, targeted ethnicity-based redistribution from progressive politicians and activists. Yet our results suggest that there is limited appetite in liberal democracies to tackle long-standing, large ethnic wealth gaps during periods of crisis when the policy trade-offs are most acute.</p><p>This majority preference may in turn intensify the incentives for credit dependency among marginalized ethnic groups, heightening their financial vulnerability and their disproportionate usage of the higher-cost fringe credit industry <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Adami 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b91">Posey 2023)</ref>. It could encourage a ratchet effect, whereby new crisis interventions leave subordinate ethnic groups facing higher levels of wealth inequality and credit dependence. There are few signs to date that most voters are willing to support targeted redistribution sufficient to forestall this outcome. Our findings thus point to a major ethical and practical downside of financial sector stabilization policies -one that highlights a morally hazardous dilemma in bailouts that is less commonly emphasized but to which policymakers should pay greater attention.  A.2  A.3 A.4</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.2 Further information on our survey</head><p>Our survey was conducted among citizens over the age of 18 in Australia and the United Kingdom (UK). The survey fieldwork was conducted by Qualtrics using their online panels in Australia (N=2,549) and the UK (N=2,547). Fieldwork took place between 2 and 29 March 2022. The survey was designed to take around 20 minutes and the median response time was 20.25 minutes in Australia and 18.9 minutes in the UK.</p><p>Sampling We used quotas on age and gender (interlocked) and education in both countries to ensure that the samples are as representative of the population as possible. Quality control The survey included two attention checks. Qualtrics eliminated any respondents that failed these checks, as well as those for whom there was evidence of duplication, of "flatlining" answers across questions, of inserting gibberish in open-text answers, and who completed the survey in less than a third of the median response time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pre-tests</head><p>The survey also included manipulation checks, which we use in robustness tests.</p><p>Survey flow Figure A.4 describes the survey flow. Upon agreeing to take the survey, respondents first answered questions about basic demographic information, which we used for quota-based sampling. We then asked respondents a set of questions to elicit information that we use as moderators and covariates. This included a battery of questions asking respondents about their inequality aversion and their resentment towards other ethnic groups.</p><p>Thereafter, respondents were informed about the rationale and design of financial stabilization policies used by governments and central banks to mitigate wealth losses in response to an economic crisis. They were then asked to evaluate different policy packages in a conjoint survey experiment. Before the conjoint experiment, respondents were split into a control group and two treatment groups. In the treatment groups, respondents were either exposed to an ethnic wealth prime or a class wealth prime, while the control group only received the common vignette containing basic information about financial market stabilization policies.</p><p>After the conjoint experiment, respondents were again split into three different treatment groups. One third of our respondents was exposed to information highlighting the effects of financial stabilization policies on ethnic inequality, while another third of our respondents was exposed to information highlighting class inequality. The remaining third was the control group, receiving no further information. To assign respondents to the groups in this information treatment experiment, we used block randomization, based on the group to which they were assigned in the first manipulation. For example, a third of people who were in the treatment group for the priming experiment were assigned to the A.9</p><p>All households may be ranked from poorest to richest in their total wealth and split into different groups, as shown in the figure below.</p><p>[</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PAGE BREAK]</head><p>As shown below, the Household, Income, Labour Dynamics in Australia Survey estimates that the wealth of the average household in the top 10% is $3,310,000. This is 6 times more wealth than the typical household in the middle, which has $502,002; and 5,900 times more wealth than the average household in the bottom 10%, which has $562.</p><p>This also means that households in the top 10% also hold 44% of all wealth in Australia, while typical household in the middle holds 5% and those in the bottom 10% hold less than 1%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>[PAGE BREAK]</head><p>As shown below, the sources of wealth for these three groups are also quite different. Households in the bottom 10% hold most of their wealth in physical assets (household contents, possessions, and valuables), whereas typical households in the middle and those in the top 10% hold most of their wealth in property. As shown below, the average household in the bottom 10% has debt that is 125% of its wealth. By contrast, the typical household in the middle has debt that is 33% of its wealth. The average household in the top 10% has debt that is 9% of its wealth.</p><p>For these reasons, policies limiting wealth losses after a crisis often increase wealth inequality in Australia. This is because these policies mainly support the value of assets (property, private pensions, shares, bonds, and deposits in bank accounts) that are primarily owned by very wealthy households.</p><p>As shown below, the Household, Income, Labour Dynamics in Australia (HILDA) Survey estimates that the wealth of the average non-Indigenous Australian household is $520,000. This is eight times more wealth than that of the average Indigenous Australian (Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander) household, which is $66,250.</p><p>[</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PAGE BREAK]</head><p>As shown below, the sources of wealth for these two groups are also quite different. Indigenous households hold most of their wealth in superannuation followed by physical assets (household contents, possessions, and valuables), whereas non-Indigenous households hold most of their wealth in property and superannuation.</p><p>[</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PAGE BREAK]</head><p>The average Indigenous Australian household has zero net property wealth because it has a lowerthan-average rate of home ownership and a larger mortgage relative to the value of its property.</p><p>Nearly 51% of Indigenous households have more personal loans, credit card and student debt than savings compared to 30% of households of non-Indigenous Australians.</p><p>For these reasons, policies limiting wealth losses after a crisis often increase inequality between ethnic groups in Australia. These policies mainly support the value of assets (property, private pensions, shares, bonds, and deposits in bank accounts) that are primarily owned by non-Indigenous Australian households.</p><p>B.4.2 Wording of the Australian "ethnic" information treatment</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.12</head><p>All households may be ranked from poorest to richest in their total wealth and split into different groups, as shown in the figure below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>[PAGE BREAK]</head><p>As shown below, the UK Office of National Statistics indicates that the wealth of the average household in the top 10% is £1,899,100. This is 8 times more wealth than the typical household in the middle, which has £235,600, and 404 times more wealth than the average household in the bottom 10%, which has £4,700.</p><p>This also means that households in the top 10% hold 45% of all wealth in the United Kingdom, while typical households in the middle hold 4% and those in the bottom 10% hold less than 1%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>[PAGE BREAK]</head><p>As shown below, the sources of wealth for these three groups are also quite different. Households in the bottom 10% hold most of their wealth in physical assets (household contents, possessions, and valuables), whereas typical households in the middle hold most of their wealth in property. Households in the top 10% hold most of their wealth in pensions. The sources of wealth for these two groups are also quite different. Black British households hold most of their wealth in physical assets (household contents, possessions, and valuables), whereas White British households hold most of their wealth in property and pensions.</p><p>[</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PAGE BREAK]</head><p>The average Black household has zero net property wealth. This is because it has a lower-thanaverage rate of home ownership and a larger mortgage relative to the value of its property.</p><p>Nearly 40% of Black households have more personal loans, credit card and student debt than savings, compared to 22% of White households.</p><p>For these reasons, policies limiting wealth losses after a crisis often increase inequality between ethnic groups in the United Kingdom. These policies mainly support the value of assets (property, private pensions, shares, bonds, and deposits in bank accounts) that are primarily owned by White households.</p><p>B.4.4 Wording of the British "ethnic" information treatment</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.15</head><p>Household wealth is the value of all assets owned by a household minus the value of all its debt.</p><p>Here is a breakdown of some typical household assets and debts: Economic crises can often have negative consequences for household wealth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assets</head><p>Asset prices fall. Property values, share and bond prices, and the value of private pensions often decline, while bank deposits may suffer losses.</p><p>Also, households may borrow more to maintain payments for essential items like food, education and childcare, health, rent and mortgage payments.</p><p>The result is that many households experience wealth losses during crises.</p><p>Policymakers may use various policies to limit wealth losses for households during economic crises, including:</p><p>Support incomes by providing benefits that replace lost income, enabling households to continue making payments, including on their debts. A 25% "replacement rate" means that households receive 25% of their previous income. Support asset prices by preventing the fall of property, share, bond, and pension values, and by guaranteeing the value of deposits in bank accounts.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">$</formula><p>Reschedule debts by allowing debtors to delay or extend the period of repayment.</p><p>Reduce debts owed by households to lenders. A.19  Note: The figure shows the results of a multinomial regression model, using the "choice" variable as the dependent variable. Controls for country fixed effects and covariates included. The left panel shows the HTEs for the linear "support" variable as the dependent variable (recoded to range from 0-1); the right panel shows HTEs for the categorical "choice" variable. Controls for country fixed effects and covariates included.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.2 Full regression table for Table 1</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Ratio of majority-to-minority median household wealth.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Median household wealth and ratio of white to black median household wealth in Australia, the UK, and the US (national currencies) Note: Ethnic majority comprises Non-Indigenous Australian, White British, and White US households. Ethnic minority comprises Indigenous Australian, Black Caribbean and Black African in the UK, and African-American households in the US. Source: The Household, Income and Labour Dynamics in Australia (HILDA) wave 18 (2018); UK Office of National Statistics Wealth and Assets Survey April 2016-March 2018; US Federal Reserve Board Survey of Consumer Finances 2019.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Australia and the UK, as in many countries, undertook extensive policy interventions in response to the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020-2021 and the deep economic crises it induced. According to an IMF study, there were 69 policy interventions (including policy revisions) in Australia and 70 in the UK in 2020 alone, including some that directly and indirectly supported asset prices and debt servicing by households and businesses. As Figure 2 indicates, these were extraordinary in size and scope, overshadowing those undertaken during the GFC. Many citizens were substantially affected by these interventions, which received extensive media coverage from early 2020 through the period of our surveys. The timing of our surveys enabled us to take advantage of the recent lived experience of citizens with the interventions we analyze.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Fiscal measures, central bank credit facilities, central bank asset purchase programs (percent of GDP), and monetary policy basis point reductions: Australia and UK initiated in 2020 Source: Kirti et al. (2022).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure A. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure A.4 presents an overview of our survey design, which is explained in more detail in Appendix B. Its central elements, an information treatment and a conjoint experiment,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Support for financial stabilization policies, pooled. Note: The left panel of the figure shows the distribution of respondents for a continuous measure of support for financial stabilization policies. The right panel of the figure shows the distribution of responses to a hypothetical choice question. Question wording in Table A.1. Only data from the control group shown.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Results from the manipulation check Note: The left panel shows the share of respondents in each treatment group who passed our manipulation check; the right panel shows the average treatment effects excluding all respondents who failed the manipulation check. Country fixed effects and covariates included.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: AMCEs from conjoint survey experiment, pooled. Note: The figure shows the average marginal component effects (AMCEs) of a change in the value of one of our five dimensions on the probability that the respondent chooses the policy package.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Wolff, Edward N. 2022. "The Stock Market and the Evolution of Top Wealth Shares in the United States." The Journal of Economic Inequality 20 (1): 53-66. Xu, Ping, and James C Garand. 2010. "Economic Context and Americans' Perceptions of Income Inequality." Social Science Quarterly 91 (5): 1220-1241.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure A. 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure A.1: Development of asset values in Australia, the UK, and the US from 2017 until 2022 Source: Google Finance, Bank of International Settlements.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) Average views on inequality and progressive taxes. (b) Average views on what is important for getting ahead in life.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure A. 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure A.2: Views on inequality in Australia, the UK, and the US Note: The top panel shows responses to the question "Please cross one box for each of these to show how important you think it is for getting ahead in life..." The bottom panel shows agreement with the statements "Differences in income in Australia are too large" and "It is the responsibility of the government to reduce the differences in income between people with high incomes" as well as answers to the question "Do you think people with high incomes should pay a larger share of their income in taxes than those with low incomes, the same share, or a smaller share?" All answers are recorded on a scale from 1 to 5, where higher values indicate more progressive views. Source: International Social Survey Program, Wave 2019.</figDesc><graphic coords="50,94.57,362.10,406.14,253.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure A. 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure A.3: Average views on inequality and progressive taxes Note: The figure shows average responses to the question "How would you place your views on this scale?" Incomes should be made more equal (1) vs. There should be greater incentives for individual effort (10). Answers are recorded on a scale from 1 to 10. Source: World Value Survey, Wave 7, 2017-2022.</figDesc><graphic coords="51,94.57,258.60,406.14,253.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure A.5: Support for financial stabilization by country.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure A. 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure A.10: Average treatment effects on choice variable estimated using multinomial logit regressions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure A.11: HTEs by country in the information treatment experiment Note:The left panel shows the HTEs for the linear "support" variable as the dependent variable (recoded to range from 0-1); the right panel shows HTEs for the categorical "choice" variable. Controls for country fixed effects and covariates included.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="53,72.00,169.72,451.27,350.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="58,97.83,106.82,399.44,186.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="61,108.93,124.28,377.41,211.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="62,142.83,391.23,309.18,179.42" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Average treatment effect on support for stabilization policies.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Support variable</cell><cell cols="3">Choice variable</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>M1</cell><cell>M2</cell><cell>M3</cell><cell>M4</cell><cell>M5</cell><cell>M6</cell></row><row><cell>(Intercept)</cell><cell cols="6">0.658*** 0.668*** 0.694*** 0.695*** 0.734*** 0.853***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell>(0.014)</cell><cell>(0.016)</cell><cell>(0.026)</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Ethnic inequality treatment -0.019* -0.019* -0.019* -0.016</cell><cell>-0.016</cell><cell>-0.008</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.019)</cell><cell>(0.019)</cell><cell>(0.019)</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Class inequality treatment -0.057*** -0.057*** -0.056*** -0.105*** -0.105*** -0.102***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.019)</cell><cell>(0.019)</cell><cell>(0.019)</cell></row><row><cell>Country fixed effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Covariates</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Num.Obs.</cell><cell>4519</cell><cell>4519</cell><cell>4300</cell><cell>3654</cell><cell>3654</cell><cell>3503</cell></row><row><cell>R2</cell><cell>0.012</cell><cell>0.014</cell><cell>0.022</cell><cell>0.009</cell><cell>0.016</cell><cell>0.036</cell></row><row><cell>R2 Adj.</cell><cell>0.011</cell><cell>0.013</cell><cell>0.020</cell><cell>0.009</cell><cell>0.015</cell><cell>0.034</cell></row></table><note><p>+ p &lt; 0.1, * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001 A.6 in Appendix C.1 shows that most respondents support several policies, including those that boost asset prices and policies that reschedule or reduce debt. Overall, this is evidence in favor of Hypothesis 1: people generally support financial stabilization policies, although a sizeable group is uncertain.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Average treatment effect on perceived effectiveness of stabilization policies.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Poor</cell><cell>Black</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>We used extensive pre-tests to develop the survey instrument. First, we tested our survey among a convenience sample of university students at [OMITTED FOR PEER REVIEW]. This pre-test allowed us to test responses to our survey experiment and to solicit feedback (via open answer questions) on all elements of our survey. Second, we implemented a soft launch to test our survey among a small sample representative of the Qualtrics panels. This further allowed us to test the length of the survey, check our quality controls, and ensure that data collection worked as intended.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>wealth of the average White British household</head><label></label><figDesc>Wording of the British "class" information treatmentAs shown below, the UK Office of National Statistics indicates that the</figDesc><table><row><cell>B.4.3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="7">The wealth distribution of British households</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Poorest =</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Typical household</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Richest =</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Bottom 10%</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>in the middle</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Top 10%</cell></row><row><cell>0%</cell><cell>10%</cell><cell>20%</cell><cell>30%</cell><cell>40%</cell><cell>50%</cell><cell>60%</cell><cell>70%</cell><cell>80%</cell><cell>90%</cell><cell>100%</cell></row></table><note><p><p>is £313,900. This is five times more wealth than that of the average Black (Black African, Black British, Black Caribbean, other Black ethnic groups) British household, which is £60,100.</p>[PAGE BREAK]</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>For instance, imagine this simple example of a household with [£210,000 / $210,000] in total assets and [£95,000 / $95,000] in total debts. Its total wealth is [£115,000 / $115,000]:</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Debts</cell></row><row><cell>Property</cell><cell>Mortgages</cell></row><row><cell>Private pensions</cell><cell>Credit card</cell></row><row><cell>Shares</cell><cell>Student loans</cell></row><row><cell>Bonds (government and corporate)</cell><cell>Personal loans (including hire purchase,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>overdrafts, and payday loans)</cell></row><row><cell>Deposits in bank accounts</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Physical assets (household contents,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>possessions, and valuables)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>[PAGE BREAK]    </p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 2 Table A</head><label>2A</label><figDesc>Table A.4: Average treatment effect on support for wealth protection policies (full regression table). .5: Average treatment effect on effectiveness of wealth protection policies (full regression table). Table A.6: Average treatment effect on support for wealth protection policies (binary variable).</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="5">Support variable C.3 Full regression table for Poor D Robustness Tests D.1 Information treatment experiment</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Choice variable Black</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(Intercept) Class inequality</cell><cell>M1</cell><cell>M2</cell><cell cols="2">M3 0.611***</cell><cell cols="2">M4 0.546***</cell><cell>M5</cell><cell>M6</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">(Intercept) Ethnic inequality treatment Class inequality treatment UK (ref. = Australia) Age Male (ref. = female) Ethnic minority (ref. = majority) Low education (ref. = high) Medium education Low income (ref. = high) Medium income Num.Obs. R2 Num.Obs. R2 R2 Adj. Medium income Low income (ref. = high) 0.658*** 0.668*** 0.694*** 0.695*** 0.734*** 0.853*** (0.006) (0.006) (0.011) (0.014) (0.016) (0.026) -0.019* -0.019* -0.019* -0.016 -0.016 -0.008 (0.008) (0.008) (0.008) (0.019) (0.019) (0.019) -0.057*** -0.057*** -0.056*** -0.105*** -0.105*** -0.102*** (0.008) (0.008) (0.008) (0.019) (0.019) -0.020** -0.027*** (0.006) (0.007) (0.016) (0.016) 0.000+ 0.000** (0.000) (0.000) 0.018** (0.007) 0.011 (0.016) -0.015 (0.009) -0.027*** (0.007) -0.024* (0.010) -0.013 (0.009) (0.023) 4519 4519 4300 3654 3654 3503 0.012 0.014 0.022 0.009 0.016 0.036 4347 0.030 0.028 (0.022) 0.019 -0.023 0.021 (0.022) 4012 -0.053* -0.047* (0.000) (0.000) (0.017) (0.023) Age 0.000 0.000 Medium education -0.076*** -0.046* (0.011) (0.010) (0.022) (0.018) Medium income -0.017 -0.024* Low education (ref. = high) -0.051* -0.044* (0.011) (0.010) (0.036) (0.023) Low income (ref. = high) -0.046*** -0.033** Ethnic minority (ref. = majority) 0.036 -0.060** (0.008) (0.008) (0.015) (0.037) Medium education -0.023** -0.019* Male (ref. = female) 0.072*** 0.094* (0.011) (0.010) (0.000) (0.016) Low education (ref. = high) -0.030** -0.010 Age 0.000 -0.092*** Male (ref. = female) 0.037*** (0.008) Ethnic minority (ref. = majority) -0.015 (0.018) (0.016) (0.015) (0.015) -0.011 UK (ref. = Australia) -0.037* -0.059*** Average marginal effect (0.007) (0.018) (0.018) (0.018) -0.10 -0.05 0.00 0.05 0.10 0.049*** Class inequality treatment -0.127*** -0.127*** -0.126*** -0.077*** -0.076*** (0.008) (0.007) (0.018) (0.018) (0.018) (0.019) (0.013) (0.012) Ethnic inequality treatment -0.034*** -0.028*** (0.009) (0.008) Class inequality treatment -0.040*** -0.023** (0.009) (0.009) UK (ref. = Australia) -0.052*** -0.013+ M1 M2 M3 (Intercept) 0.616*** 0.634*** 0.689*** (0.013) (0.015) Ethnic inequality treatment -0.045* -0.045* -0.047* Ethnic inequality (0.025) In favor Against Treatment Don't know</cell></row><row><cell>R2 Adj.</cell><cell cols="6">0.011 + p &lt; 0.1, * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001 0.013 0.020 0.009 Num.Obs. 4519 4519</cell><cell>4300</cell><cell>0.015</cell><cell>0.034</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">+ p &lt; 0.1, * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001 R2</cell><cell>0.011</cell><cell>0.013</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.027</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R2 Adj.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.011</cell><cell>0.012</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.024</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">+ p &lt; 0.1, * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>A.20 A.25</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>For these reasons, policies limiting wealth losses after a crisis often increase wealth inequality in the United Kingdom. These policies mainly support the value of assets (property, private pensions, shares, bonds, and deposits in bank accounts) that are primarily owned by very wealthy households.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Anonymity We did not collect any personal information allowing to identify the respondents (e.g., address, name, place of residence, etc.). As a result, anonymity is guaranteed.</p><p>Funding We received funding from the <rs type="funder">Systemic Risk Centre at the London School of Economics</rs> to field the survey.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>provided excellent research assistance, and we gratefully acknowledge funding from the <rs type="funder">Research and Impact Fund at the London School of Economics (LSE)</rs> and support of the <rs type="funder">Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC)</rs> in funding the <rs type="funder">Systemic Risk Centre (SRC) at the LSE</rs> (grant numbers <rs type="grantNumber">ES/K002309/1</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">ES/R009724/1</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">ES/Y010612/1</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_SenrzMf">
					<idno type="grant-number">ES/K002309/1</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_33t8Nrw">
					<idno type="grant-number">ES/R009724/1</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_grmccFp">
					<idno type="grant-number">ES/Y010612/1</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>they were asked to (1) choose between the two policy packages (forced choice) and (2) rate each package on a Likert scale from 1 to 5. We primarily use the force choice variable, estimating OLS regressions to calculate the average marginal component effects (AMCEs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Hainmueller, Hopkins, and Yamamoto 2014)</ref>. This allows us to measure the average impact of each policy level on the probability that respondents choose a policy package. Since each respondent evaluated ten policy packages in total, we cluster standard errors by respondents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>The results of the conjoint experiment Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> show that respondents most strongly support income protection policies, with support increasing as wage replacement rates Informed and voluntary consent We designed our surveys in Qualtrics and recruited respondents via their online panel. Respondents voluntary opted into the study. At the beginning of the survey, respondents were informed about the content of the survey and informed of the following: "Your participation in this study is entirely voluntary and you can withdraw at any time. The information provided by you in this questionnaire will be used for research purposes only. It will not be used in a manner that allows identification of your individual responses and all your answers in this study will remain confidential."</p><p>We then asked respondents whether they agreed to participate in the survey and/or wanted to receive more information. Respondents who asked for more information were given a lot of additional information about the content of the study, the use of their data (for scientific purposes), and our commitment to treat their answers in a confidential manner. Respondents who had asked for this additional information were then again given the choice whether to participate in the survey or not.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Survey content and deception</head><p>The study does not use any deception. Our video treatments only included information that was accurate at the time of our fieldwork.</p><p>Risks of harm There were no risks for respondents associated with participating in this study. Respondents were remunerated by Qualtrics for successfully completing the survey.</p><p>Participant pool Our participant pool was diverse: It was representative of the general population of the United Kingdom and Australia, respectively, on basic demographic characteristics (age and gender groups as well as education). It did not include members of groups that we consider vulnerable or marginalized, and our surveys posed no harm to respondents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p>We are not aware of any conflicts of interest.</p><p>control group for the framing experiment, one third was assigned to the ethnic inequality frame, and one third was assigned to the class inequality frame.</p><p>Finally, respondents were asked additional questions about their socio-economic situation and other variables.  A.6  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.3 Variable coding, summary statistics, and variable coding</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.2.3 Priming respondents about inequality</head><p>Prior to the conjoint experiment, we had randomly split respondents into three groups: a control group that received no additional information, and two treatment groups that A.28 received an "ethnic wealth prime" and a "class wealth prime", respectively. The class wealth prime briefly explained the nature and composition of wealth in each country for households in the bottom 10 percent of the wealth distribution, while the ethnic wealth explained the nature and composition of household wealth for people of Indigenous origin in the Australia survey and Black ethnic groups in the UK survey.  In both cases, our treatments primed respondents to think about the position of minority groups by summarizing the composition of their wealth and the level of their net wealth (assets -liabilities). Again, we relied on true information derived from data from national statistical agencies and authoritative surveys in both countries. Our results show that the primes do not influence respondents' views on targeted support for the different groups. This could suggest that at least some respondents' views about the relative desirability of class-based and ethnicity-based arguments for wealth redistribution are ingrained and relatively resistant to information provision, as other researchers find in the US context <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Alesina, Ferroni, and Stantcheva 2021)</ref>.  A.31</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.2.4 Additional robustness tests for the conjoint experiment</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Financial Exclusion in the UK: Evidence on Ethnicity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roberta</forename><surname>Adami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Policy and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Online first</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disparate Recoveries: Wealth, Race, and the Working Class After the Great Recession</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fenaba</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Addo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Darity</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The ANNALS of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">695</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Taking Credit: Redistribution and Borrowing in an Age of Economic Polarization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ahlquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ben</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ansell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="640" to="675" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fairness and Redistribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alberto</forename><surname>Alesina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George-Marios</forename><surname>Angeletos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="960" to="980" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Perceptions of Racial Gaps, their Causes, and Ways to Reduce Them</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alberto</forename><surname>Alesina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matteo</forename><surname>Ferroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefanie</forename><surname>Stantcheva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">NBER Working Paper 29245</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alberto</forename><surname>Alesina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edward</forename><surname>Glaeser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fighting Poverty in the US and Europe</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diversity, Immigration, and Redistribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alberto</forename><surname>Alesina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefanie</forename><surname>Stantcheva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AEA Papers and Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Political Economy of Ownership: Housing Markets and the Welfare State</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ben</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ansell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Political Science Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does the Framing of Immigration Induce Welfare Chauvinism? The Effects of Negativity Bias and Motivated Reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sabina</forename><surname>Avdagic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lee</forename><surname>Savage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Political Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Online first</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diversity Statistics in the OECD: How do OECD Countries Collect Data on Ethnic, Racial and Indigenous Identity? OECD Statistics Working Papers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carlotta</forename><surname>Balestra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lara</forename><surname>Fleischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018/09</date>
			<publisher>OECD</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Structure of American Income Tax Policy Preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cameron</forename><surname>Ballard-Rosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lucy</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kenneth</forename><surname>Scheve</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Unequal Democracy: The Political Economy of the New Gilded Age</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Larry</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bartels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Political Consequences of Indigenous Resentment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edana</forename><surname>Beauvais</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Race, Ethnicity, and Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mind the Income Gaps? Experimental Evidence of Information&apos;s Lasting Effect on Redistributive Preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bastian</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Justice Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mindful Economics: The Production, Consumption, and Value of Beliefs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roland</forename><surname>Bénabou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jean</forename><surname>Tirole</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attitudes to Inequalities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rebecca</forename><surname>Benson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bobby</forename><surname>Duffy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rachel</forename><surname>Hesketh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kirstie</forename><surname>Hewlett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IFS Deaton Review of Inequalities. Institute for Fiscal Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends in Income and Wealth Inequalities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pascale</forename><surname>Bourquin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mike</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Wernham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IFS Deaton Review of Inequalities. Institute for Fiscal Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positional Deprivation and Support for Radical Right and Radical Left Parties*</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brian</forename><surname>Burgoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sam</forename><surname>Van Noort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthijs</forename><surname>Rooduijn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Geoffrey</forename><surname>Underhill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Welfare State with Private Alternatives: The Transformation of Popular Support for Social Insurance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marius</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Busemeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Torben</forename><surname>Iversen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="686" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Just Luck: An Experimental Study of Risk-Taking and Fairness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cappelen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Konow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erik</forename><forename type="middle">Ø</forename><surname>Sørensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bertil</forename><surname>Tungodden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1398" to="1413" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Two Facets of Social Policy Preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Charlotte</forename><surname>Cavaillé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kris-Stella</forename><surname>Trump</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="146" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Can Redistribution Keep Up with Inequality? Evidence from South Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aroop</forename><surname>Chatterjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Léo</forename><surname>Czajka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amory</forename><surname>Gethin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">2021. 1993-2019. 2021/20</date>
			<publisher>World Inequality Lab</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Working Paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Economic Impacts of COVID-19: Evidence from a New Public Database Built Using Private Sector Data*</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Raj</forename><surname>Chetty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Stepner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="889" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>and Opportunity Insights Team. 2024</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Wealth Effect: How the Great Expectations of the Middle Class Have Changed the Politics of Banking Crises</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chwieroth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Learning About Inequality and Demand for Redistribution: A Meta-Analysis of In-Survey Informational Experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emanuele</forename><surname>Ciani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fréget</forename><surname>Louis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Manfredi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>OECD Papers on Well-being and Inequalities 02</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the Role of Racism in Contemporary US Public Opinion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Katherine</forename><surname>Cramer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Global Wealth Databook 2022</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Credit</forename><surname>Suisse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Credit Suisse</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Heterogeneous and Regressive Consequences of COVID-19: Evidence from High Quality Panel Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Crossley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hamish</forename><surname>Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104334</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Privatised Keynesianism: An Unacknowledged Policy Regime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Colin</forename><surname>Crouch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The British Journal of Politics and International Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="382" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Economy is Rigged&apos;: Inequality Narratives, Fairness, and Support for Redistribution in Six Countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pepper</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Culpepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ryan</forename><surname>Shandler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jae-Hee</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Taeku</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Online first</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Subaltern Middle Class: The Case of the Missing &quot;Black Bourgeoisie&quot; in America</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Darity</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fenaba</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>William</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Imari</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Addo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contemporary Economic Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="494" to="502" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Position and Possessions: Stratification Economics and intergroup Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Darity</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Literature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="400" to="426" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zsolt</forename><surname>Darvas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Catarina</forename><surname>Midões</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Wealth Distribution and Social Mobility. Publications Office of the European Union</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Wealth Inequality Pandemic: Covid and Wealth Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bruce</forename><surname>Bradbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>Australian Council of Social Service</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ellora</forename><surname>Derenoncourt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chi</forename><forename type="middle">Hyun</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Moritz</forename><surname>Kuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Moritz</forename><surname>Schularick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Wealth of Two Nations: The U.S. Racial Wealth Gap, 1860-2020</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Working Twice as Hard to Get Half as Far: Race, Work Ethic, and America&apos;s Deserving Poor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Desante</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="356" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Altruistic Rich? Inequality and Other-Regarding Preferences for Redistribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><surname>Dimick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Rueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Stegmueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quarterly Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inequalities Around The Globe: What the World Sees as Most Serious</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bobby</forename><surname>Duffy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Murkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kirstie</forename><surname>Hewlett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rebecca</forename><surname>Benson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rachel</forename><surname>Hesketh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>The Policy Institute, King&apos;s College London</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Democratic State and Redistribution: Whose Interests Are Served?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mads</forename><surname>Elkjaer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Torben</forename><surname>Andreas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Iversen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Political Science Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Why Is It So Hard to Counteract Wealth Inequality? Evidence from the United Kingdom</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mads</forename><surname>Elkjaer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ben</forename><surname>Andreas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laure</forename><surname>Ansell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Asli</forename><surname>Bokobza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Cansunar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jacob</forename><surname>Haslberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nyrup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:186d0990-1cef-460b-9709-adf253" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023. 19195</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erik</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Engstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Huckfeldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Class, and Social Welfare</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Mechanics of Motivated Reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Epley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Gilovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Asset-Price Redistribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Fagereng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthieu</forename><surname>Gomez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Émilien</forename><surname>Gouin-Bonenfant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Holm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><surname>Moll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gisle</forename><surname>Natvik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.matthieugomez.com/files/apr.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nissa</forename><surname>Finney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Nazroo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laia</forename><surname>Bécares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dharmi</forename><surname>Kapadia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Natalie</forename><surname>Shlomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Racism and Ethnic Inequality in a Time of Crisis: Findings from the Evidence for Equality National Survey</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bristol</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Policy Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who Should We Help? An Experimental Test of Discrimination in the British Welfare State</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="630" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do Changes in Material Circumstances Drive Support for Populist Radical Parties? Panel Data Evidence from the Netherlands during the Great Recession, 2007-2015</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Noam</forename><surname>Gidron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan J B</forename><surname>Mijs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Gilens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Why Americans Hate Welfare: Race, Media, and the Politics of Antipoverty Policy</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chicago</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Doing Well and Doing Good?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Gilens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adam</forename><surname>Thal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Public Opinion Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Misperceiving inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vladimir</forename><surname>Gimpelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Treisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economics &amp; Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysing Social Inequality: A Critique of Two Recent Contributions from Economics and Epidemiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Goldthorpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="731" to="744" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthieu</forename><surname>Gomez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.matthieugomez.com/files/wealthinequality.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Wealth Inequality and Asset Prices</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hanno Lustig, and Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh. 2021. Financial and Total Wealth Inequality with Declining Interest Rates. NBER Working Paper 28613</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Greenwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matteo</forename><surname>Leombroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Repeated Shocks and Preferences for Redistribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Giovanni</forename><surname>Gualtieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marcella</forename><surname>Nicolini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fabio</forename><surname>Sabatini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">167</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Winner-take-all Politics: How Washington Made the Rich Richer -and Turned its Back on the Middle Class</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jacob</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hacker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Pierson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Simon &amp; Schuster</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal Inference in Conjoint Analysis: Understanding Multidimensional Choices via Stated Preference Experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Hainmueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hopkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Teppei</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Black/White Differences in the Relationship Between Debt and Risk of Heart Attack Across Cohorts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jenifer</forename><surname>Hamil-Luker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Angela</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>O'rand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSM-Population Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ian</forename><surname>Haney-López</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Dog Whistle Politics: Strategic Racism, Fake Populism, and the Dividing of America</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Race, Prejudice and Attitudes Toward Redistribution: A Comparative Experimental Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Allison</forename><surname>Harell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stuart</forename><surname>Soroka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shanto</forename><surname>Iyengar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Political Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="744" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Public Opinion, Prejudice and the Racialization of Welfare in Canada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Allison</forename><surname>Harell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stuart</forename><surname>Soroka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kiera</forename><surname>Ladner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ethnic and Racial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2580" to="2597" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Middle Class Without a Net: Savings, Financial Fragility, and Preferences Over Social Insurance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jacob</forename><surname>Hariri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amalie</forename><forename type="middle">Sofie</forename><surname>Gerner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lassen</forename><surname>Dreyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="892" to="922" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Assessing the Political Effects of Racial Prejudice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leonie</forename><surname>Huddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stanley</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="447" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Freedom Burning: Anti-Slavery and Empire in Victorian Britain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Huzzey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ithaca, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information and Financialization: Credit Markets as a New Source of Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Torben</forename><surname>Iversen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Philipp</forename><surname>Rehm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2349" to="2381" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-National Support for the Welfare State Under Wealth Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amalie</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Sofie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wiedemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1959" to="1995" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uncovering Reactions to the Racial Resentment Scale across the Racial Divide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cindy</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Camille</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Burge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">How has COVID-19 Affected Wealth Disparities Among Ethnic Groups in the UK? Economics Observatory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ricky</forename><surname>Kanabar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Scale and Drivers of Ethnic Wealth Gaps Across the Wealth Distribution in the UK: Evidence from Understanding Society. Working Paper 97</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eleni</forename><surname>Karagiannaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>LSE</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Colour of Money: How Racial Inequalities Obstruct a Fair and Resilient Economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Omar</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<pubPlace>Runnymede Trust</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking Economic and Financial Policies During COVID-19: An Announcement-Level Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Divya</forename><surname>Kirti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Prachi</forename><surname>Mishra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yang</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Strasky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Soledad</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peria</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IMF Working Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2022</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">114</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial Resentment, Old-Fashioned Racism, and the Vote Choice of Southern and Nonsouthern Whites in the 2012 U.S. Presidential Election*</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Knuckey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Myunghee</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="905" to="922" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Last-Place Aversion&quot;: Evidence and Redistributive Implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kuziemko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ryan</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ilyana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Taly</forename><surname>Buell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Reich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Norton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Elastic Are Preferences for Redistribution? Evidence from Randomized Survey Experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kuziemko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ilyana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emmanuel</forename><surname>Norton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefanie</forename><surname>Saez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Stantcheva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1478" to="1508" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring Subgroup Preferences in Conjoint Experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Leeper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Hobolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tilley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Wealth Gap Year: The Impact of the Coronavirus Crisis on UK Household Wealth. The Resolution Foundation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Leslie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Krishan</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Race and Regionalism in the Politics of Taxation in Brazil and South Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Evan</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What&apos;s Fair? Preferences for Tax Progressivity in the Wake of the Financial Crisis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julian</forename><surname>Limberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Urban Myth? Government Involvement in the Economy and Left-Right Politics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jesper</forename><surname>Lindqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Political Science Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hank Paulson: &apos;I think it&apos;s pretty likely we will see a recession&apos;</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edward</forename><surname>Luce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Financial Times</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-04-14">2023. April 14, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Group Loyalty and the Taste for Redistribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erzo</forename><forename type="middle">F P</forename><surname>Luttmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="500" to="528" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Economic Inequality, Immigrants and Selective Solidarity: From Perceived Lack of Opportunity to In-group Favoritism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gabriele</forename><surname>Magni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1357" to="1380" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Markets Shape Values and Political Preferences: A Field Experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yotam</forename><surname>Margalit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Moses</forename><surname>Shayo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="492" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Borrowing to Self-Insure? Credit Access and Support for Welfare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>Markgraf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Guillermo</forename><surname>Rosas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="642" to="655" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leslie</forename><surname>Mccall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Undeserving Rich: American Beliefs about Inequality, Opportunity, and Redistribution</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Americans&apos; Social Preferences in the Era of Rising Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leslie</forename><surname>Mccall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lane</forename><surname>Kenworthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspectives on Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wealth Redistribution in &apos;Australia&apos;</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Phoebe</forename><surname>Mcilwraith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Common Ground</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial Capitalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jodi</forename><surname>Melamed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Critical Ethnic Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Rational Theory of the Size of Government</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Allan</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Meltzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Scott</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Richard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="914" to="927" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gunnar</forename><surname>Myrdal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harper and Brothers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1944">1944</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Risks That Matter Survey</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>OECD Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Welfare as Small-Scale Help: Evolutionary Psychology and the Deservingness Heuristic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deservingness Versus Values in Public Opinion on Welfare: The Automaticity of the Deservingness Heuristic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rune</forename><surname>Bang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rune</forename><surname>Slothuus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lise</forename><surname>Stubager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Togeby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Political Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information Inequality: How Race and Financial Access Reflect the Information Needs of Lower-Income Individuals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Patricia</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Posey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The ANNALS of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">707</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Canarsie: the Jews and Italians of Brooklyn against Liberalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Rieder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Black Marxism: The Making of the Black Racial Tradition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cedric</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<publisher>North Carolina Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Chapel Hill, NC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why Does Globalization Fuel Populism? Economics, Culture, and the Rise of Right-Wing Populism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dani</forename><surname>Rodrik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Color of Law: A Forgotten History of How our Government Segregated America</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Rothstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Liveright Publishing</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Food Comes First, Then Morals: Redistribution Preferences, Parochial Altruism, and Immigration in Western Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Rueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Sambanis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><surname>Nikolova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Effects of Economic Austerity on Pro-Sociality: Evidence from Greece</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="589" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exposure to Inequality Affects Support for Redistribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Melissa</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sands</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="663" to="668" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local Exposure to Inequality Raises Support of People of Low Wealth for Taxing the Wealthy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Melissa</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sands</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kadt</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">586</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7828</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Great Leveler: Violence and the History of Inequality from the Stone Age to the Twenty-First Century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Walter</forename><surname>Scheidel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wealth Inequality and Democracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kenneth</forename><surname>Scheve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Stasavage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Race and the Politics of Welfare Reform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sanford</forename><surname>Schram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joe</forename><surname>Soss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Fording</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Race and Finance: America&apos;s Segregated Banking Sector</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Silverman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Imani</forename><surname>Moise</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Financial Times</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-12-13">2021. December 13, 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Tea Party and the Remaking of Republican Conservatism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Theda</forename><surname>Skocpol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vanessa</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Spillover of Racialization into Health Care: How President Obama Polarized Public Opinion by Racial Attitudes and Race</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Tesler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="690" to="704" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chloe</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Thurston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">At the Boundaries of Homeownership: Credit, Discrimination, and the American State</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When and Why is Economic Inequality Seen as Fair</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kris-Stella</forename><surname>Trump</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Behavioral Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Closing the Gap or Widening the Divide: The Effects of the G.I. Bill and World War II on the Educational Outcomes of Black Americans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sarah</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Bound</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Economic History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Wealth matters: The Black-White Wealth Gap Before and During the Pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Weller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Figueroa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Center for American Progress</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b110">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Policy Response Instrumental in Shaping the Pandemic&apos;s Impact on Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jesse</forename><surname>Wheeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b111">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Indebted Societies: Credit and Welfare in Rich Democracies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Wiedemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b112">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Dog-Whistle Politics of Personal Responsibility, Credit, and the American Welfare State</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Wiedemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tess</forename><surname>Wise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.3579128</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3579128" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b113">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Declining Significance of Race: Revisited &amp; Revised</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">William</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Julius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Daedalus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b114">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond Welfare: Framing and the Racialization of White Opinion on Social Security</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><forename type="middle">J G</forename><surname>Winter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="400" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b115">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Personal Bankruptcy and Race: When the Public-Private Welfare State is Predatory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tess</forename><surname>Wise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.3630278</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3630278" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
