<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">How eco-emotions inform decisions to live with less to protect the natural environment</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jaeger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Psychology, Speech and Hearing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<country key="NZ">New Zealand</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Psychology, Speech and Hearing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<country key="NZ">New Zealand</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Donald</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hine</surname></persName>
							<email>donald.hine@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Psychology, Speech and Hearing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<country key="NZ">New Zealand</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Psychology, Speech and Hearing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Canterbury</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Christchurch</settlement>
									<country key="NZ">New Zealand</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">How eco-emotions inform decisions to live with less to protect the natural environment</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1E63B1B7C630E84299DF6D8C675D7FAC</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>eco-emotions</term>
					<term>climate change</term>
					<term>environmental problems</term>
					<term>behavior change</term>
					<term>pro-environmental behavior</term>
					<term>environmental concern</term>
					<term>willingness to sacrifice</term>
					<term>audience segmentation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The rapid degradation of the environment is one of our greatest challenges in the 21 st century.</p><p>To avoid the worst consequences human behavior must change. The current study investigated how feelings about environmental problems (eco-emotions) predict concern for the natural environment and willingness to make sacrifices for it. Using a cross-sectional online sample of 286 New Zealand residents, latent profile analysis identified three profile groups with distinct patterns of eco-emotions: emotionally detached (40%), emotionally ambivalent (34%), and empathic alarmed (26%). Validation analyses revealed that members of the empathic-alarmed segment reported significantly higher levels of environmental concern and willingness to make sacrifices for the environment than members of the emotionally-ambivalent segment, who in turn expressed greater concern and willingness to sacrifice than members of the emotionally-detached segment. Findings from this study suggest that inducing a combination of negative eco-emotions with compassion may be effective for promoting environmental concern and pro-environmental sacrifice.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Emotions play an important role in shaping attitudes, threat appraisals, and decisionmaking processes, including those related to environmental issues such as climate change and sustainability. To avoid significant and potentially irreversible disruptions to the natural environment and human societies, we must learn to live within planetary boundaries: the limits within which humanity can safely operate to maintain a stable and resilient earth system <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2)</ref>. Recent research, however, indicates that we have already exceeded safe limits of six of nine boundaries identified by Rockström and colleagues (1): climate change, novel entities, biogeochemical flows, land-system change, freshwater use, and biosphere integrity <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref>. Historical trends are also not encouraging. Early in the 1970s, humanity's annual demand for biological resources only marginally exceeded the amount the Earth ecosystem could regenerate. By 2022 this demand exceeded the ecosystem regeneration capacity by at least 70%. Reversing this trend constitutes one of humanity's greatest challenges. In the current study, we explore how feelings about environmental problems (eco-emotions) predict concern for the natural environment and willingness to make sacrifices to save it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Eco-emotions</head><p>In response to the growing number and intensity of environmental challenges, researchers in environmental psychology and behavioral economics have become increasingly interested in situational and personal factors that influence pro-environmental behavior (PEB; 5, 6, 7). The well-established link between emotions and behavior in other domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> has prompted environmental researchers to explore the relevance of emotional responses to PEB. Eco-emotions are broadly defined as conscious and unconscious feelings towards environmental problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>. Several recent international studies have investigated the prevalence of eco-emotions and their relevance to PEB <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>. For instance, in a multinational study with 10,000 participants, Hickman and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> found that many young people experienced negative eco-emotions such as fear (67%), anxiety (61%), worry (60%), anger (57%), and guilt (50%) when thinking about climate change, while much smaller proportions felt optimistic (30%) and indifferent (29%).</p><p>Negative eco-emotions are not only common, but also have increased over time. <ref type="bibr">Leviston and colleagues (16)</ref> found that between 2010 and 2013 Australians became more ashamed and guilty when thinking about climate change and less hopeful. <ref type="bibr">Leiserowitz and colleagues (17)</ref> found a similar trend in the US, with two thirds of Americans being worried about climate change, which is an increase of approximately 10% within five years (2014 to 2019). Furthermore, the number of Americans feeling very worried (30%) about climate change tripled during this period. Overall, research suggests that people around the world exhibit a broad range of emotional responses to environmental challenges, including negative emotions such as worry, fear, and shame, but also more positive emotions such as hope and optimism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Eco-emotions and PEB</head><p>Emotions play a key role in shaping attitudes and threat appraisals, both of which have been shown to be important determinants of behavior. For example, Ajzen's theory of planned behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> posits that emotions may lead individuals to generate positive or negative attitudes, which influence intentions and behavior. Similarly, Slovic's and colleagues' affect heuristic model <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> suggests that people's affective response (general feelings of goodness or badness) towards an object, event, or behavior can influence risk appraisals, which in turn can increase or decrease the likelihood of future actions.</p><p>There is also considerable evidence to suggest that specific emotions are predictive of decisions to engage or not engage in PEB. An extensive literature on fear appeals indicates that fear can elicit behaviors to reduce external threats, particularly when accompanied by information that boosts self-efficacy <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>. Stanley and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> found that Australians who experienced higher levels of eco-anger and eco-depression were more likely to engage in climate activism. In comparison, those reporting eco-anxiety were less likely to engage in pro-environmental actions <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>. However, a multinational study <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> across 32 countries found that experiencing anxiety towards climate change was associated with proenvironmental behavior and environmental activism. The authors did also note that increased levels of climate anxiety are associated with detrimental mental health outcomes, suggesting there is a trade-off between PEB and mental health which has to be considered.</p><p>Theorists argue that emotions may facilitate PEB by serving as a mechanism to "concretize" or reduce the psychological distance of abstract environmental problems like climate change, for which the most extreme impacts are often perceived to be highly uncertain, likely to take place far in the future, in distant locations, and impacting dissimilar others <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24)</ref>. This concretization process can enhance the salience of environmental problems, feelings of perceived personal vulnerability, and empathy for affected others, all of which may further enhance PEB <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Moving beyond discrete emotions to emotion patterns</head><p>Most studies on emotions and PEB to date examined the role of how specific emotions in isolation predict human responses to environmental problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>.</p><p>However, it is important to recognize that eco-emotions often co-occur, and that the overall pattern of emotions may help us to understand why people respond or fail to respond to environmental threats. <ref type="bibr">Smith and Leiserowitz (31)</ref> found that a combination of five ecoemotions (worry, hope, interest, guilt, and disgust) explained 50% of the variance in climate change policy support, explaining PEB better than worldviews and sociodemographic variables. While this highlights the importance of eco-emotions for sustainable behavior, the way in which multiple eco-emotions combined predict PEB is complex. Ojala <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>, for instance, found that hope predicted PEB, but only for individuals who were also worried about environmental problems. One explanation for this may be that when people are hopeful, but not worried, hope is based on denial, but when people are hopeful and worried, they experience constructive hope which increases the motivation to practice PEB <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>.</p><p>Wang and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> further extended our understanding of the complex interplay of eco-emotions by evaluating whether a combination of a wider range of ecoemotions (13 emotions in total) predicted PEB. Using hierarchical cluster analysis, they identified four audience segments with distinct sets of eco-emotions which were characterized as having either strong negative emotions (scoring high on negative emotions such as anger and fear, but low on positive emotions like hope), weak negative emotions (scored similar to those with strong negative emotions, but with lower intensity), no emotions (experienced low levels of both negative and positive emotions), and ambivalent emotions (experienced both positive and negative emotions). Members of the strong negative emotions segment reported significantly higher levels of support for climate friendly policies and environmental funding compared to members of the weak negative emotions and ambivalentemotions segments. Members of the no emotions segment exhibited the lowest levels of policy and funding support.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The current study</head><p>The current study seeks to deepen our understanding of which eco-emotions tend to co-occur and how patterns of emotions predict environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice. Our study extends Wang and colleagues' (29) work both conceptually and methodologically. First, whereas Wang and colleagues focused on eco-emotions related to climate change, we focused more broadly on emotional responses towards environmental problems. Second, while they investigated how members of each eco-emotions segment differed in terms of their support for climate-friendly policies and funding, we analyzed how our identified emotions segments predict environmental concern and willingness to make a broad range of personal sacrifices related to climate change mitigation but also more general to environmental sustainability. Measuring willingness to sacrifice considers that proenvironmental decisions are often a trade-off between doing what is best for oneself versus what is best for the environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>. In contrast to behavioral measures, willingness to sacrifice is a more diverse measure as it can cover a wide range of intentions for various proenvironmental behaviors rather than assessing context specific behaviors. Third, whereas Wang and colleagues created eco-emotion segments based on a relatively restricted set of 13 emotions, we assessed a larger group of 23 discrete emotions to create a segmentation solution. Our selection of eco-emotions includes different aspects of unhappy emotions (i.e., sad, hurt, depressed, grief), fear-related emotions (i.e., anxious, afraid, worried), positive emotions (i.e., hopeful, optimistic, happy), and an empathetic emotion (i.e., compassion) which were previously not assessed in detail by Wang and colleagues. Using a larger set of eco-emotions allows us to evaluate the possible effects of emotions on environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice in a more complete and nuanced manner.</p><p>Based on Wang's and colleagues' (29) findings, we hypothesized that there would be at least three eco-emotion segments in our sample: negative eco-emotions, no emotions, and ambivalent emotions (a mix of positive and negative eco-emotions). We also predicted that the identified segments would differ significantly in their environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice, with those groups feeling stronger negative eco-emotions exhibiting the highest levels of environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice for the natural environment, and those with no eco-emotions exhibiting the lowest levels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>The study was conducted in August 2022 and used a Cint online panel sample of New Zealanders. Cint is one of the largest digital survey-based providers with access to over 500,000 panelists <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref>. To ensure survey data quality, Cint (37) uses a detection system to prevent duplicates and fraud, and suppliers adhere to industry standards <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref>. Of the 405 New Zealand residents recruited, 119 participants were excluded from the survey as they either did not complete the survey or did not pass all three attention checks. The final sample consisted of 286 participants aged 18 to 89 years (M = 43.13, SD = 17.53; Median = 40.00; S1 Table ).</p><p>Compared to 2018 census data <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref>, participants in the current sample were slightly older (median age in current study: 40.00 years; census: 37.40 years), more educated (participants holding an undergraduate degree or higher in current study: 41%; census: 25%), and consisted of more females (current study: 66%; census: 51%). In terms of ethnicity, the current sample resembled the New Zealand population (current study: 67% European, 17% Māori; census: 68% European, 15% Māori). Most participants lived in cities or suburban areas (64%), while 36% lived in rural residential, semi-rural, and rural areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedure and measures</head><p>Following a review and approval of this study by the University of Canterbury Human Ethics Committee, a Qualtrics online survey <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref> was conducted. At the beginning of the survey, participants were informed about the purpose of the study and that responses would be anonymous. Moreover, informed consent was obtained, participants were told that they could choose to withdraw at any time from the survey, and a helpline was provided in case any of the questions caused them distress.</p><p>After answering questions about their socio-demographic background, participants were asked how they feel towards environmental problems by rating 23 different types of eco-emotions (sad, hurt, angry, disgusted, frustrated, afraid, anxious, worried, ashamed, guilty, despair, depressed, grief, helpless, powerless, indifferent, bored, confused, doubtful, optimistic, hopeful, happy, compassionate). All emotion items were derived from previous research by Hickman and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> and Pihkala <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> and were measured on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = never to 5 = almost always).</p><p>Next, participants' environmental concern was measured using an amended version of the Concern for Climate Change scale applied by Jones and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>. The scale consisted of seven items, of which one item was reverse coded ("I am not overly concerned about environmental problems such as climate change as I think the impacts are probably exaggerated"). All items were measured on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = strongly disagree to 5 = strongly agree). Internal consistency for this scale was very high (Cronbach's α = .92).</p><p>Finally, participants' willingness to make sacrifices for the natural environment was assessed with a newly developed 24-item scale. As measuring PEB in real world settings is often difficult, we employed a measure of PEB intentions based on the concept of willingness to sacrifice. Willingness to sacrifice, which is "the extent to which individuals' decisions will take into account the well-being of the environment, even at the expense of immediate selfinterest, effort, or cost" (35 p259), has been found to be one of the strongest predictors of PEB, over and above knowledge, concern, and socio-economic characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>. Although several willingness to sacrifice scales exist <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35)</ref>, their focus is quite narrow. We developed a new scale to assess a broader range of sustainable behaviors related to transportation, food, electricity, and recycling, which were not assessed by existing scales.</p><p>All items were measured on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = strongly disagree to 5 = strongly agree). While exploratory factory analysis, using principal axis factoring, revealed four eigenvalues above one, the scree plot clearly indicated a one-factor solution. All solutions from one to four were subjected to promax rotations. Solutions two to four exhibited a high number of cross-loadings, and several items did not load strongly on any factor. Consistent with the scree plot, the one-factor solution was most interpretable and therefore retained to construct a unidimensional measure of willingness to sacrifice. The average of the 24 items was calculated to create a single score. Internal consistency for this scale was very high (Cronbach's α = .92). Details of the questionnaire are shown in S2 Appendix.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical methods</head><p>To analyze the data (42), SPSS 28 <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(43)</ref> was used to conduct descriptive statistical analysis and assess bivariate correlations among all study variables. To classify participants based on their eco-emotions into homogeneous segments, a latent profile analysis was then performed with MPlus 8 <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref>. To test if the segments differed significantly in their ecoemotions and in their demographic characteristics, several post-hoc one-way analyses of variance (ANOVAs) were carried out with SPSS 28. Then, a multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) was conducted with SPSS 28 to determine if the identified segments differed along a combination of environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice. The MANOVA was followed by two one-way ANOVAs to validate the segments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Descriptive statistics and bivariate correlations</head><p>Means, standard deviations, and bivariate correlations between all variables are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Most eco-emotions were significantly positively correlated with environmental concern, apart from indifferent and bored which were significantly negatively correlated with environmental concern. Optimistic, hopeful, and happy were not significantly correlated with environmental concern. In regard to willingness to sacrifice, most ecoemotions were significantly positively correlated with willingness to sacrifice, apart from bored which was negatively correlated. Indifferent and happy were not significantly correlated with willingness to sacrifice. A classification consisting of three segments fit the data significantly better than a two-segment solution, and a four-segment solution did not fit the data significantly better than a three-segment solution. The three-segment solution had a lower BIC value than the two-segment solution, indicating a better fit of the data. Entropy for the three-segment solution was high (.95), indicating high classification certainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref>. Moreover, the threesegment solution was more interpretable than the other segment solutions. As such, the threesegment solution was retained and analyzed. The three segments were labelled emotionally detached, emotionally ambivalent, and empathic alarmed.  The emotionally-detached segment, which comprised 40% of all respondents, scored well below the mid-point on all eco-emotions assessed in the study. Members of the second largest segment, the emotionally ambivalent (34%), scored below the scale midpoint for all emotions, apart from disgust and worry, which were at the scale midpoint, and sadness and frustration, which were slightly above the scale midpoint. The emotionally ambivalent had significantly higher levels of all negative eco-emotions (i.e., grief, despair, ashamed, hurt, depressed, guilty, angry, disgusted, afraid, confused, anxious, sad, frustrated, doubtful, worried, helpless, powerless) and compassion than the emotionally detached (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</p><p>However, these two segments did not differ significantly in their positive (i.e., optimistic, hopeful, happy) and apathetic (i.e., indifferent, bored) eco-emotions. The third segment, the empathic alarmed, was the smallest segment (26%) and scored above the scale midpoint for most eco-emotions, with sadness, worry, and frustration being the highest rated ecoemotions. The empathic-alarmed segment scored below the scale midpoint for optimism, indifference, hope, happiness, confusion, and boredom. Compared to the emotionally ambivalent and emotionally detached, the empathic alarmed had significantly higher levels of all negative eco-emotions and compassion, but did not differ significantly in their positive and apathetic eco-emotions.  For willingness to sacrifice, members of the empathic-alarmed (M = 3.67, SD = 0.65) and emotionally-ambivalent (M = 3.37, SD = 0.63) segments scored significantly higher (p &lt; .001) than the emotionally-detached segment (M = 2.89, SD = 0.76). Respondents in the empathic-alarmed segment were also significantly more willing to make sacrifices for the environment than the respondents in the emotionally-ambivalent segment (p = .015). Overall, these findings support our hypothesis that, based on participants' emotional responses to environmental problems, several segments exist, and that members of each segment differ significantly in their environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice. Willingness to sacrifice was measured with 24 items, all measured on a 5-point Likert scale</p><p>(1 = strongly disagree to 5 = strongly agree).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>The current study aimed to extend our understanding of which eco-emotions occur together, and how patterns of eco-emotions predict environmental concern and willingness to make sacrifices for the environment. We found that respondents could be segmented into three main profile groups based on their emotional responses to environmental problems.</p><p>Moreover, our results indicated that group membership predicted both, environmental concern and willingness to make sacrifices for the natural environment. Each of these findings is discussed in more detail in the sections that follow, along with a discussion of practical implications and limitations of the research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Eco-emotion profile groups</head><p>Applying latent profile analysis to 23 eco-emotions, we identified three distinct segments which were characterized as being emotionally-detached (40%), emotionallyambivalent (34%), or empathic-alarmed (26%) about environmental problems such as climate change. We found that the segments differed in their levels of negative eco-emotions and compassion, but not in their positive (i.e., optimism, hope, happiness) and apathetic ecoemotions (i.e., indifference, boredom). The largest segment, the emotionally detached, reported lower levels of all negative eco-emotions and compassion than the emotionally ambivalent who in turn reported less intense negative eco-emotions and compassion than the smallest segment, the empathic alarmed. As the three segments only differed in their negative eco-emotions and compassion, but not in their positive and apathetic eco-emotions, hypothesis 1 was only partially supported.</p><p>In terms of their socio-demographic characteristics, the three segments differed in age, but not in gender, education, and living area. The empathic alarmed were younger than the emotionally ambivalent and the emotionally detached. This aligns with previous studies which found that younger generations tend to be more engaged and emotionally involved with environmental problems (50) than older generations (e.g., feeling more anxious, angry, and less annoyed when shown climate change related social media content).</p><p>The identified segments have some similarities with those reported by Wang and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> who surveyed Australian residents, but also some key differences. Wang and colleagues identified four segments, which differed in both their intensities and valence of eco-emotions. Their segments were characterized as either feeling strong negative emotions (e.g., anger and fear), weak negative emotions (e.g., anger and fear experienced with lower intensity), ambivalent emotions (moderate levels of positive and negative emotions), or no emotions (low levels of positive and negative emotions). In contrast to their segmentation, we identified three segments, which differed only in their intensity of experienced eco-emotions.</p><p>Using a different statistical approach may have contributed to these findings. While Wang and colleagues used hierarchical cluster analysis to identify emotion profiles within their sample, we employed latent profile analysis (LPA), which is considered the gold standard for segmenting populations and allowed us to use fit indices to identify a segment solution which best fits the data <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52)</ref>. Moreover, while Wang and colleagues reported differences between the four segments in positive (i.e., hopeful, joyful, excited), apathetic (i.e., bored), and negative eco-emotions (e.g., angry, irritated), the segments in the current study only differed in their negative eco-emotions and compassion. The emotionally-detached segment in the current study was similar to the no emotion segment identified by Wang and colleagues, in that they both experienced low levels of all eco-emotions. However, the noemotion segment (24%) they identified was only around half the size of the emotionallydetached segment found in the current study (40%). This suggests a potential cross-cultural difference, with a higher proportion of New Zealanders compared to Australians being emotionally-detached with environmental problems. One explanation for this could be that Australians are more directly impacted by environmental problems such as climate change than New Zealanders <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(53)</ref>, resulting in Australians having less psychological distance towards environmental issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>, which in turn may have led to a greater emotional response <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Emotion patterns predict environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice</head><p>As hypothesized, segment membership predicted how environmentally concerned and willing to make sacrifices the segments were. All segments experienced different levels of environmental concern, with the empathic alarmed being the most concerned, followed by the emotionally ambivalent and the emotionally detached. In terms of willingness to sacrifice, individuals who were empathic alarmed were more willing to give up unsustainable behaviors than emotionally-ambivalent individuals, who in turn were more willing to make sacrifices for the environment than the emotionally detached. The stronger negative ecoemotions felt by the empathic alarmed and emotionally ambivalent may have made the risks associated with environmental problems be perceived as less abstract and thus riskier <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56)</ref>, resulting in greater environmental concern and willingness to make sacrifices.</p><p>Overall, our findings align broadly with those of previous research, in that emotions are important in shaping pro-environmental attitudes and decision-making processes. Our study supports previous research that suggests eco-emotions may be critical to be concerned about environmental problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>, to be willing to make sacrifices for the natural world <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>, and to perform PEB <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34)</ref>. Experiencing eco-emotions may have helped to concretize abstract environmental problems and in turn increased the motivation to perform PEB <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(55)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(56)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(57)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(58)</ref>.</p><p>A difference to previous findings <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59)</ref> was that three segments identified in this study differed primarily in their experienced magnitude of negative eco-emotions and compassion. This suggests that a combination of these types of eco-emotions sets groups of people apart from each other. The importance of negative eco-emotions aligns with findings of a meta-analysis by van Valkengoed and Steg (60), who found that together with outcome efficacy and descriptive norms, negative affect was a strong predictor for a range of climate change adaptation behaviors such as policy support. The unpleasantness of a negative emotional arousal caused by experiencing a range of negative emotions may have acted as a motivator to increase intentions to act environmentally-friendly <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(61)</ref>.</p><p>In addition to differences in all negative emotions between the three segments, members of the emotionally-detached, emotionally-ambivalent, and empathic-alarmed segments differed in their levels of compassion, a finding that contributes to previous research in this area <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">63)</ref>. In a recent study, Pfattheicher and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(63)</ref> found that participants who were assigned to a high-compassionate condition (i.e., had to imagine how a person feels) had higher pro-environmental intentions than those assigned to a lowcompassionate condition. Similar results were reported by Engel and colleagues (62) who found that entrepreneurs who listened to a guided loving-kindness meditation had higher levels of compassion and made more sustainable decisions than a group which only listened to a talk about meditation (without actually meditating). In their study, the relationship between the loving-kindness meditation and pro-environmental decision making was mediated by compassion. In the current study, compassion, which evokes a feeling for the suffering of others <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(64)</ref>, may have increased the awareness of how one's actions impact others negatively and elicited moral concern <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">63)</ref>. This in turn may have acted as a motivator for alleviating the suffering of others and hence may have contributed to the willingness to practice PEB.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Practical implications</head><p>The results of the current study support the view that emotions may be critical for guiding judgements and decisions related to PEB. The fact that the three segments differed primarily in terms of the relative intensity with which segment members experienced negative eco-emotions and compassion can help in the development of communication interventions, which evoke specific sets of emotions (i.e., by inducing a combination of negative emotions and compassion) to engage with groups of people more effectively.</p><p>Our results contribute to findings from a growing body of research on the effects of emotions on PEB. Invoking specific negative emotions such as guilt <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(65)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(66)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">(67)</ref>, fear <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">68)</ref>, frustration, anger and depression <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>, grief <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67)</ref>, and worry <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> have previously all been found to promote PEB, while experiencing sadness and shame on their own were found to be associated with decreased levels of PEB <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(69)</ref>. Mixed effects of anxiety on PEB were previously reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(70)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(71)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">(72)</ref>. The current study found that all negative emotions (including sadness, shame, and anxiety) were higher in groups that reported greater levels of environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice. Thus, it may be that the interaction of negative eco-emotions and compassion increases concern for the environment and intentions to sacrifice unsustainable behaviors. In order for individuals to shift to a segment that is more emotionally engaged and hence more motivated to make sacrifices to benefit the natural environment, it may be beneficial to induce a combination of negative ecoemotions and compassion.</p><p>To further support the success of interventions eliciting specific patterns of ecoemotions, additional factors may need to be considered, including the level of self-efficacy <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">73)</ref>, ethical considerations <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">70,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b73">74)</ref>, and potential adverse effects of too intensely experienced eco-emotions <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">(75)</ref>. Self-efficacy has previously been suggested to influence the course of action. According to the extended parallel process model <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">(73)</ref>, when facing a threat, experiencing negative emotions such as fear only leads to action when a high level of selfefficacy is present. However, when self-efficacy is low, individuals may deny the threat or actively react against the threat (e.g., "climate change is not real") in order to manage their distressing emotions. Hence, to increase the success of emotion-inducing interventions it may be advisable to integrate a self-efficacy element <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>. One way to achieve this is by providing information on how to decrease unsustainable behaviors. This in turn may increase confidence that one's actions contribute to the planet's health and therefore, lead to PEB. A second point to consider is the intensity of experienced eco-emotions. While the current study did not find a reversal effect of stronger experienced eco-emotions on environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice, Pihkala <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">(75)</ref> suggests that when the intensity of negative ecoemotions (e.g., climate anxiety) is too high, it may paralyze people and thereby lead to inaction. Moreover, when negative eco-emotions are too strong, they were previously found to be associated with detrimental mental health outcomes and increased levels of insomnia <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b73">74)</ref>. Therefore, from an ethical point of view, it is important to develop emotioninducing interventions with a safe level of intensity, which in turn may also contribute to an intervention's success.</p><p>In summary, ensuring self-efficacy when inducing a combination of negative emotions with appropriate levels of intensity and compassion may be one way for individuals to move to segments that are more emotionally engaged (i.e., emotionally ambivalent and empathic alarmed), more environmentally concerned, and more willing to make sacrifices to protect the environment. In fact, that would represent a great opportunity, given the emotionally ambivalent and emotionally detached represented nearly three quarters of all participants surveyed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations and future research</head><p>When interpreting the findings of our study, several limitations have to be considered.</p><p>In this study, we surveyed a broad range of New Zealand residents. In terms of age and ethnicity the current sample was roughly representative of the New Zealand population, but females were over-represented. Moreover, our sample may not be truly representative given that we relied on an online panel, which may have excluded certain groups within the population as the online survey required internet access and skills to navigate an online survey <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">(76)</ref>. To validate our findings, future studies can use an experimental design to test how messages which induce specific sets of eco-emotions impact individuals' environmental concern and pro-environmental intentions. A second limitation was the reliance on self-report measures which are prone to socially desirable answering <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">(77)</ref> and may have affected the validity of this study. To mitigate this risk, participants were recruited through a third-party, the study was conducted online, and information provided was kept anonymous. Thirdly, given measuring PEB in real world settings is often difficult, we used willingness to sacrifice as a proxy measure for PEB. This allowed us to include a wide range of sustainable behaviors and hence have a more holistic picture of participants' pro-environmental intentions. While there may be a gap between self-reported willingness to sacrifice and actual behavior, research suggests that intentions are often the strongest predictor of behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">(78)</ref>. Intentions that involve sacrifice may be particularly predictive given they suggest a willingness to engage in behaviors despite the barriers that may be present. Future research can extend and validate the findings of our study by investigating which factors predict eco-emotions of specific groups and by testing whether messages which induce a combination of negative emotions and compassion simultaneously are more effective than messages that evoke a combination of other sets of eco-emotions. Further research is also required to examine the extent to which willingness to sacrifice measures of intent outperform more traditional intention measures in predicting behavior.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>In the current study we investigated which eco-emotions tend to co-occur and how patterns of these eco-emotions relate to pro-environmental action. Overall, this study supports the perspective that eco-emotions may play an important role in affecting how people experience environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice. We identified three segments with distinct sets of eco-emotions (emotionally detached, emotionally ambivalent, and empathic alarmed), with most participants being emotionally detached. Members of the three segments differed in the degree to which they experienced negative eco-emotions and compassion, but not in their experiences of eco-emotions reflecting positivity and apathy.</p><p>The segments also significantly differed in levels of expressed environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice. Members of the empathic-alarmed segment felt more concerned about the environment and were more willing to make sacrifices for the environment than members of the emotionally-ambivalent group, who in turn expressed more concern about the environment and were more willing to make sacrifices to protect it than members of the emotionally-detached segment. Targeting the two largest segments (emotionally detached and emotionally ambivalent) with appeals that focus on eliciting combinations of negative emotions alongside compassion may prove to be an effective way to increase proenvironmental behavior in these groups. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S2</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig 1 presents the deviation from the scale midpoint for all eco-emotions of the three identified segments.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig 1. Centered eco-emotions scores of the emotionally-detached, emotionally-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice. Results from Gabriel's post hoc tests revealed that members of the empathic-alarmed segment (M = 4.33, SD = 0.62) had significantly higher levels of environmental concern (p &lt; .001) than members of the emotionally-ambivalent (M = 3.83, SD = 0.72) and the emotionally-detached (M = 3.08, SD = 0.96; Fig 2) segments. Moreover, emotionally-ambivalent respondents were significantly more concerned about the environment than emotionally-detached ones (p &lt; .001).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig 2. Mean scores for environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice of the emotionally-detached, emotionally-ambivalent, and empathic-alarmed segments. Notes. N = 286. Emotionally detached, n = 114. Emotionally ambivalent, n = 97. Empathic alarmed, n = 75. Error bars represent 95% confidence interval. Environmental concern was measured with seven items on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = strongly disagree to 5 = strongly agree).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Descriptive statistics and correlation matrix of study variables</head><label>1</label><figDesc>-.10 .01 -.05 -.10 -.04 -.18 ** .26 ** .47 ** -.10 -Compassionate 2.81 1.18 .44 ** .24 ** .35 ** .34 ** .22 ** .37 ** .33 ** .33 ** .37 ** .32 ** .38 ** .39 ** .17 ** -.03 .39 ** .38 ** .23 .28 .74 ** .60 ** .72 ** .72 ** .06 .72 ** .61 ** .63 ** .63 ** .58 ** .69 ** .62 ** .49 ** .12 * .10 .63 ** -.12 * .37 ** .47 ** .06 .47 ** -23 Frustrated 2.77 1.32 .73 ** .59 ** .66 ** .64 ** -.02 .77 ** .60 ** .61 ** .61 ** .51 ** .64 ** .56 ** .50 ** .05 .06 .76 ** -.11 .41 ** .40 ** .03 .45 ** .72 ** -* .41 ** .52 ** .50 ** -.03 .53 ** .45 ** .49 ** .44 ** .35 ** .50 ** .42 ** .25 ** -.20 ** .08 .47 ** -.10 .39 ** .17 ** -.17 ** .22 ** .57 ** .53 ** -25 Willingness to Sacrifice 3.26 .76 .40 ** .29 ** .42 ** .34 ** .12 * .42 ** .34 ** .34 ** .35 ** .29 ** .41 ** .36 ** .16 ** -.09 .20 ** .40 ** .02 .44 ** .20 ** -.12 * .19 ** .39 ** .39 ** .59</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD 1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>25</cell></row><row><cell>Sad</cell><cell cols="2">2.80 1.31 -</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Helpless</cell><cell cols="3">2.65 1.33 .60 ** -</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Anxious</cell><cell cols="4">2.43 1.27 .65 ** .57 ** -</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Afraid</cell><cell cols="2">2.42 1.28 .69</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p>** .59 ** .74 ** -Optimistic 2.20 1.12 .02 -.09 .01 .04 -Angry 2.51 1.34 .77 ** .56 ** .67 ** .71 ** .02 -Guilty 2.31 1.29 .63 ** .56 ** .61 ** .60 ** -.01 .65 ** -Ashamed 2.33 1.30 .69 ** .51 ** .60 ** .62 ** .02 .66 ** .73 ** -Hurt 2.21 1.27 .64 ** .53 ** .60 ** .66 ** .09 .70 ** .57 ** .60 ** -Depressed 2.07 1.20 .60 ** .49 ** .57 ** .50 ** .03 .57 ** .50 ** .53 ** .56 ** -Despair 2.30 1.23 .67 ** .56 ** .65 ** .62 ** .02 .66 ** .61 ** .62 ** .66 ** .59 ** -Grief 2.13 1.15 .61 ** .50 ** .54 ** .61 ** .11 .64 ** .52 ** .58 ** .63 ** .54 ** .62 ** -Powerless 2.90 1.35 .46 ** .74 ** .47 ** .50 ** -.06 .45 ** .47 ** .43 ** .46 ** .42 ** .45 ** .43 ** -Indifferent 1.92 1.06 .06 .14 * .15 ** .16 ** .15 ** .12 * .14 * .09 .24 ** .19 ** .11 .19 ** .24 ** -Hopeful 2.34 1.13 .06 -.09 .09 .05 .60 ** .02 .04 .10 .11 .10 .06 .14 * -.03 .19 ** -Disgusted 2.64 1.38 .70 ** .58 ** .57 ** .60 ** .02 .74 ** .63 ** .63 ** .63 ** .51 ** .64 ** .58 ** .49 ** .11 .06 -Happy 1.75 1.07 -.14 * -.17 ** -.05 -.05 .41 ** -.12 * -.12 * ** -Confused 2.12 1.13 .33 ** .45 ** .48 ** .49 ** .15 * .42 ** .45 ** .42 ** .40 ** .40 ** .47 ** .44 ** .38 ** .29 ** .11 .40 ** .08 .15 * -Bored 1.64 1.00 .05 .12 .13 * .17 ** .17 ** .08 .09 .11 .14 * .24 ** .10 .22 ** .13 * .54 ** .19 ** .13 * .26 ** .02 .27 ** -Doubtful 2.28 1.17 .41 ** .46 ** .45 ** .47 ** .09 .43 ** .42 ** .45 ** .51 ** .39 ** .42 ** .47 ** .47 ** .26 ** .10 .45 ** .09 .22 ** .36 ** .24 ** -*** -N = 286. All items were measured on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = minimum to 5 = maximum). * p &lt; .05. ** p &lt; .01.</p>indicates that a model with k segments fits the data better than a model with k-1 segments.</p>Model fit indices for two-to five-segment solutions are shown in Table</p>2</p>.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . Model fit indices for two to five segment solutions for eco-emotions</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Rubin likelihood ratio test. Lower AIC and BIC values suggest a better model fit.Higher entropy indicates higher classification certainty. A significant LMR test indicates that a model with k segments fits the data significantly better than a model with k-1 segments.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Segment Solution</cell><cell>AIC</cell><cell>BIC</cell><cell>Entropy</cell><cell>LMR</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>18824.74</cell><cell>19080.66</cell><cell>.97</cell><cell>2563.33</cell><cell>&lt; .001</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>18234.13</cell><cell>18577.79</cell><cell>.95</cell><cell>633.94</cell><cell>.001</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>18807.88</cell><cell>18439.29</cell><cell>.93</cell><cell>272.24</cell><cell>.600</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>17909.01</cell><cell>18428.16</cell><cell>.94</cell><cell>145.79</cell><cell>.283</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">AIC = Akaike's information criterion. BIC = Bayesian information criteria. LMR = Lo-</cell></row><row><cell>Mendel-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 . Eco-emotions: mean scores, standard deviations, and mean differences across emotionally-detached, emotionally-ambivalent, and empathic-alarmed segments</head><label>3</label><figDesc>(M age = 43.39, SD = 17.15) segments were significantly older than the empathic alarmed (M age = 34.56, SD = 13.62). Table4contains a demographic breakdown of the three retained segments.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Segment</cell><cell cols="2">Emotionally</cell><cell cols="2">Emotionally</cell><cell cols="2">Empathic</cell><cell>Univariate</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell cols="2">detached</cell><cell cols="2">ambivalent</cell><cell cols="2">alarmed</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(n = 114)</cell><cell cols="2">(n = 97)</cell><cell cols="2">(n = 75)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>η 2</cell></row><row><cell>Grief</cell><cell>1.25 a</cell><cell>0.43</cell><cell>2.28 b</cell><cell>0.90</cell><cell>3.29 c</cell><cell>1.08</cell><cell>157.81***</cell><cell>.51</cell></row><row><cell>Despair</cell><cell>1.25 a</cell><cell>0.49</cell><cell>2.49 b</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>3.63 c</cell><cell>1.01</cell><cell>223.42***</cell><cell>.60</cell></row><row><cell>Ashamed</cell><cell>1.26 a</cell><cell>0.48</cell><cell>2.44 b</cell><cell>0.96</cell><cell>3.80 c</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>240.27***</cell><cell>.61</cell></row><row><cell>Hurt</cell><cell>1.28 a</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>2.15 b</cell><cell>0.99</cell><cell>3.68 c</cell><cell>0.96</cell><cell>198.45***</cell><cell>.57</cell></row><row><cell>Depressed</cell><cell>1.33 a</cell><cell>0.63</cell><cell>1.92 b</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>3.37 c</cell><cell>1.09</cell><cell>109.21***</cell><cell>.47</cell></row><row><cell>Guilty</cell><cell>1.34 a</cell><cell>0.62</cell><cell>2.39 b</cell><cell>0.97</cell><cell>3.69 c</cell><cell>1.12</cell><cell>154.62***</cell><cell>.53</cell></row><row><cell>Angry</cell><cell>1.34 a</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>2.71 b</cell><cell>0.92</cell><cell>4.04 c</cell><cell>0.88</cell><cell>307.01***</cell><cell>.66</cell></row><row><cell>Disgusted</cell><cell>1.41 a</cell><cell>0.66</cell><cell>3.00 b</cell><cell>1.06</cell><cell>4.03 c</cell><cell>0.90</cell><cell>260.22***</cell><cell>.60</cell></row><row><cell>Afraid</cell><cell>1.41 a</cell><cell>0.62</cell><cell>2.40 b</cell><cell>0.92</cell><cell>3.96 c</cell><cell>0.83</cell><cell>261.53***</cell><cell>.63</cell></row><row><cell>Confused</cell><cell>1.50 a</cell><cell>0.77</cell><cell>2.23 b</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>2.93 c</cell><cell>1.19</cell><cell>48.71***</cell><cell>.26</cell></row><row><cell>Anxious</cell><cell>1.50 a</cell><cell>0.73</cell><cell>2.36 b</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>3.93 c</cell><cell>0.94</cell><cell>181.60***</cell><cell>.58</cell></row><row><cell>Sad</cell><cell>1.62 a</cell><cell>0.67</cell><cell>3.03 b</cell><cell>0.88</cell><cell>4.28 c</cell><cell>0.69</cell><cell>349.61***</cell><cell>.67</cell></row><row><cell>Frustrated</cell><cell>1.63 a</cell><cell>0.73</cell><cell>3.04 b</cell><cell>1.04</cell><cell>4.13 c</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell>273.01***</cell><cell>.59</cell></row><row><cell>Doubtful</cell><cell>1.67 a</cell><cell>0.93</cell><cell>2.36 b</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>3.12 c</cell><cell>1.17</cell><cell>42.90***</cell><cell>.25</cell></row><row><cell>Worried</cell><cell>1.72 a</cell><cell>0.77</cell><cell>3.00 b</cell><cell>0.94</cell><cell>4.24 c</cell><cell>0.59</cell><cell>322.16***</cell><cell>.62</cell></row><row><cell>Helpless</cell><cell>1.82 a</cell><cell>1.04</cell><cell>2.59 b</cell><cell>0.94</cell><cell>3.97 c</cell><cell>1.07</cell><cell>93.51***</cell><cell>.42</cell></row><row><cell>Powerless</cell><cell>2.15 a</cell><cell>1.21</cell><cell>2.94 b</cell><cell>1.14</cell><cell>4.00 c</cell><cell>1.04</cell><cell>62.95***</cell><cell>.30</cell></row><row><cell>Compassionate</cell><cell>2.24 a</cell><cell>1.07</cell><cell>2.95 b</cell><cell>1.05</cell><cell>3.51 c</cell><cell>1.06</cell><cell>33.44***</cell><cell>.19</cell></row><row><cell>Bored</cell><cell>1.51 a</cell><cell>0.91</cell><cell>1.60 a</cell><cell>0.94</cell><cell>1.91 a</cell><cell>1.18</cell><cell>3.10</cell><cell>.03</cell></row><row><cell>Indifferent</cell><cell>1.77 a</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>1.94 a</cell><cell>0.97</cell><cell>2.13 a</cell><cell>1.28</cell><cell>2.35</cell><cell>.02</cell></row><row><cell>Happy</cell><cell>1.86 a</cell><cell>1.14</cell><cell>1.65 a</cell><cell>1.04</cell><cell>1.71 a</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>1.03</cell><cell>.01</cell></row><row><cell>Optimistic</cell><cell>2.18 a</cell><cell>1.16</cell><cell>2.12 a</cell><cell>1.05</cell><cell>2.33 a</cell><cell>1.16</cell><cell>0.77</cell><cell>.01</cell></row><row><cell>Hopeful</cell><cell>2.24 a</cell><cell>1.10</cell><cell>2.28 a</cell><cell>1.06</cell><cell>2.59 a</cell><cell>1.23</cell><cell>2.15</cell><cell>.02</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">N = 286. V = 1.10, F(46, 524) = 13.94, p &lt; .001, η 2 = .55. Means with different superscripts (in rows) differ</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">significantly at p &lt; .01 (Gabriel). *** p &lt; .001.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>In terms of demographic characteristics, the three segments differed significantly only in age. Members of the emotionally-detached (M age = 48.54, SD = 18.04) and emotionally-ambivalent</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 . Demographic characteristics of the emotionally-detached, emotionally- ambivalent, and empathic-alarmed segments</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Segment Variables</cell><cell cols="2">Emotionally</cell><cell cols="2">Emotionally</cell><cell cols="2">Empathic</cell><cell cols="2">Univariate</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">detached</cell><cell cols="2">ambivalent</cell><cell cols="2">alarmed</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(n = 114)</cell><cell cols="2">(n = 97)</cell><cell cols="2">(n = 75)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>r</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell cols="2">48.54 a 18.04</cell><cell cols="2">43.39 a 17.15</cell><cell cols="2">34.56 b 13.62</cell><cell>18.89***</cell><cell>-0.31</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>%</cell><cell>ZResid</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>ZResid</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>ZResid</cell><cell>c 2 (df)</cell><cell>V</cell></row><row><cell>Gender:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>8.92(4)</cell><cell>0.12</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>1.07</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>-0.51</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>-0.74</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>-0.66</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>0.44</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>0.31</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Non-binary</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>-0.89</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>-0.82</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2.04</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Education:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>15.73(12)</cell><cell>0.14</cell></row><row><cell>Lower than secondary school</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0.75</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>-0.60</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>-0.23</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Secondary school</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>0.86</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>-0.55</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>-0.43</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Trade / professional / technical qualification</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>-0.84</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>-0.22</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Undergraduate degree</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>-1.14</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>1.56</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>-0.37</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Honours / postgraduate degree</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-0.88</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0.23</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0.83</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Master's degree</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>-0.81</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0.77</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0.13</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PhD</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-0.47</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>-1.16</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1.90</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Living Area:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>10.65(8)</cell><cell>0.14</cell></row><row><cell>Inner City</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>-1.05</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0.31</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>0.94</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Suburban</cell><cell>43</cell><cell>-0.28</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>0.85</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>-0.62</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Residential in rural town</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>1.02</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>-0.43</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>-0.77</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Semi-rural</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>-0.57</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0.61</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>1.07</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>-1.79</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>N = 286. Means with different superscripts (in rows) differ significantly at p &lt; .01 (Gabriel). r = Pearson's correlation coefficient. ZResid = adjusted standardized residual. V = Cramer's V. c 2 analyses conducted with Segment membership,</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>environmental concern, and willingness to sacrifice</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>A MANOVA was used to investigate whether the segments differed significantly in</cell></row><row><cell>their environmental concern and willingness to sacrifice. The MANOVA revealed a</cell></row><row><cell>significant effect (L = 0.69, F(4, 566) = 25.93, p = .001), with segment membership</cell></row><row><cell>explaining 31% of the variance in the combined dependent variables (environmental concern</cell></row><row><cell>and willingness to sacrifice). Two follow-up one-way ANOVAs revealed statistically</cell></row></table><note><p>significant large main effects of group membership on levels of environmental concern, F(2, 186.82) = 59.56, p &lt; .001, η 2 = 29, and willingness to sacrifice, F(2, 180.16) = 29.75, p &lt; .001, η 2 = .18, indicating that the segments differed significantly in their levels of</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Appendix. Questionnaire Start of Survey</head><label></label><figDesc>Before you proceed with the survey, please complete the captcha below Informed Consent &amp; Welcome Welcome to the research study! We are interested in better understanding Kiwis' feelings, beliefs, and behaviours related to environmental problems such as climate change.The questionnaire should take you around 10-15 minutes to complete. Your participation in this research is voluntary. You have the right to withdraw at any point during the study. All your responses will be completely anonymous. The Principal Investigator of this study is Andreas K Jaeger and can be contacted at aja223@uclive.ac.nz. This project has been approved by the Educational Research Human Ethics Committee (human-ethics@canterbury.ac.nz). Although this questionnaire is unlikely to raise any personal or upsetting issues, if it does you may wish to contact Lifeline on 0800 543 354 or your GP. According to scientists, human behaviour is causing environmental problems such as climate change.Please indicate on the scale below how willing you are to make changes to your behaviour to prevent environmental problems from happening.</figDesc><table><row><cell>638 637</cell><cell cols="6">By clicking the button below, you acknowledge: Your participation in this research is voluntary. You are 18 years of age or over. You agree to participate in this study and are aware that you may choose to withdraw at any time for any reason. Sociodemographic These first questions are to learn something about you What is your gender? o Male o Female o Prefer not to say make you feel. Please rate how much you agree with the following statements. we ask you to mark o o o o o convenient sentence, in this line even though they are have read this takeaway coffee cups) o o o o o To show that you products (e.g., straws, For each of the words below, indicate how environmental problems such as climate change instead of dairy milk I avoid single-use o Non-binary / third gender What ethnic group do you belong to? Select all that apply to you. o Indian o Other (please specify) __________________________________________________ Not at All Slightly Moderately Very Extremely Sad o o o o o Helpless o o o o o Anxious o o o o o Afraid o o o o o Optimistic o o o o o Angry o o o o o Guilty o o o o o Strongly disagree Somewhat disagree Neutral Somewhat agree Strongly agree I experience concern each time I see or I am concerned that the Strongly disagree Mildly disagree Neither disagree nor agree Mildly agree I am willing to make I am willing to pay Strongly agree an extra effort to find and buy locally o o o o o higher taxes for o o o o o conservation efforts I am very concerned about environmental problems such as climate change o o o o o I am very read media coverage of the likely impacts and consequences of environmental problems such as o o o o o impacts of produced food in New Zealand I am willing to buy an environmental electric car rather I am willing to pay I generally try to buy problems such as o o o o o than a fossil-fuel car, even if the electric car o o o o o more for food that is environmentally-o o o o new furniture where o the wood is climate is more expensive friendly sustainably sourced, o o o o o change will affect me in the foreseeable To reduce my environmental impact, I often walk, even when those I am willing to products are more compost food scraps o o o o o expensive instead of throwing What is the highest qualification you have received? o Less than secondary school o Secondary school qualification o Trade / technical certificate or professional qualification o Undergraduate qualification (Bachelors degree or Undergraduate Diploma) o Bachelor Honours or Postgraduate Certificate, Diploma or Degree o Masters degree o PhD Which of the following best describes the area where you live? o Inner city o Suburban o Residential in rural town o Semi-rural / Peri-urban (e.g., acreage on the edge of town) o Rural What is your age? o 18 o 19 o 20 Eco-emotions, Environmental Concern &amp; Willingness to Sacrifice milk-alternatives o o o o o expensive I am willing to use they are more footprint packaging, even if o o o o o exaggerated. greenhouse gas products with much (up to 100) Ashamed o o o o concerned climate future. cycle, or use public o o o o o them in the rubbish I am willing to accept o Hurt o o o o o Depressed o o o o o Despair o o o o o Grief o o o o o Powerless o o o o o Indifferent o o o o o Hopeful o o o o o Disgust o o o o o Happy o o o o o Compassionate o o o o o Confusion o o o o o Boredom o o o o o Doubt o o o o o Worry o o o o o Frustration o o o o o about potential impacts of environmental problems o o o o o change. The more I learn about environmental problems transport instead of driving my car to nearby places I try to avoid travelling within NZ less pay to work for a I am willing to buy electric devices that company/organization o o o o o that has strong have a better energy "green" policies and efficiency rating, o o o o o procedures even if they are more such as climate such as climate o o o o by plane, even if o o o o o expensive than less I am willing to take o travelling by plane is energy efficient shorter showers to o o o o o change that change, the most convenient options conserve water may affect me personally. I am very more I am willing to pay I am willing to pay I am willing to spend concerned I become. more for my flights to offset the carbon o o o o o more for electricity that comes renewable o o o o most of my holidays o in New Zealand o o o o o concerned I am not emissions produced sources instead of going about potential impacts of environmental problems such as climate change that may affect society in probably by 50% to reduce my o o o o o I am willing to avoid general. o o o o o overly through my flight overseas by plane In winter, I often put concerned about I am willing to reduce my overseas travel by o o o o o on an extra layer of clothes rather than o o o o I support paying more o money for clothes environmental problems such as climate change as I think the impacts are o o o o o at least 50% I am willing to adopt a meat-free diet o o o o o my meat consumption products I am willing to reduce turning the heater on over brand-new o o o o o materials) second-hand products fibres or recycled I am willing to buy that are sustainable (made of natural o o o o o</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>'Strongly agree' on the answer scale I am planning not to have any children</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>o</cell></row></table><note><p>o New Zealand European / Pākehā o Māori o Samoan o Cook Islands Māori o Tongan o Niuean o Chinese</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We would like to express our gratitude to all participants of this study. Special thanks to <rs type="person">Sarah Chamberlain</rs> for her valuable support and proofreading of this paper.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supporting information</head><note type="other">S1</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>543</head><p>Note. Participants could choose more than one ethnicity. Ethnicity "Others" included 544 Samoan (1%), Cook Island Māori (1%), Tongan (1%), Indian (1%). 545</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A safe operating space for humanity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rockström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Noone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Å</forename><surname>Persson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chapin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lambin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7263</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="472" to="475" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Planetary boundaries: Guiding human development on a changing planet</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rockström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fetzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">347</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6223</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1259855</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Earth beyond six of nine planetary boundaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lucht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bendtsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Donges</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Advances</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2458</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outside the safe operating space of the planetary boundary for novel entities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Persson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Carney</forename><surname>Almroth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>De Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Diamond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental science &amp; technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1510" to="1521" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outcomes of environmental awareness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bouzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Safavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Foroutan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mind the gap: why do people act environmentally and what are the barriers to pro-environmental behavior?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kollmuss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Agyeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental education research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="260" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting residents&apos; pro-environmental behaviors at tourist sites: The role of awareness of disaster&apos;s consequences, values, and place attachment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H-L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk as feelings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Loewenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hsee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Welch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">267</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">How emotion shapes behavior: Feedback, anticipation, and reflection, rather than direct causation. Personality and social psychology review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Baumeister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Vohs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nathan</forename><surname>Dewall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="203" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emotion and decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lerner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Valdesolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kassam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual review of psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="823" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Risk as analysis and risk as feelings: Some thoughts about affect, reason, risk and rationality. The feeling of risk: Routledge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Finucane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Macgregor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="36" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emotion and action</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thagard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Emotions and action. Feelings and emotions: The Amsterdam</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Frijda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a Taxonomy of Climate Emotions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pihkala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Climate</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">199</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate anxiety in children and young people and their beliefs about government responses to climate change: a global survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hickman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pihkala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Clayton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lewandowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mayall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Lancet Planetary Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="863" to="e73" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fourth annual survey of Australian attitudes to climate change: Interim report</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Leviston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mccrea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>CSIRO</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Perth, Australia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Climate change in the American mind</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Leiserowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Maibach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rosenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kotcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bergquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ballew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-04">April 2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Yale University and George Mason University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The theory of planned behavior. Organizational behavior and human decision processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="211" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The affect heuristic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Finucane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Macgregor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European journal of operational research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">177</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1333" to="1352" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Appealing to fear: A meta-analysis of fear appeal effectiveness and theories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hepler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Zimmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Saul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1178</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From anger to action: Differential impacts of eco-anxiety, eco-depression, and eco-anger on climate action and wellbeing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Leviston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Climate Change and Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100003</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate anxiety, wellbeing and pro-environmental action: correlates of negative emotional responses to climate change in 32 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ogunbode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hanss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ojala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Salmela-Aro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Den Broek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101887</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Barriers to environmental concern</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Takács-Sánta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Ecology Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The future is now: Reducing psychological distance to increase public engagement with climate change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Risk Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="341" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk communication, public engagement, and climate change: A role for emotions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roeser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Risk analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1033" to="1040" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of goal framing and emotions on perceived threat and willingness to sacrifice for climate change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bilandzic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kalch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Soentgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="491" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When worry about climate change leads to climate action: How values, worry and personal responsibility relate to various climate actions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bouman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Verschoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Albers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Böhm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Poortinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Environmental Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102061</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pride and guilt predict pro-environmental behavior: A meta-analysis of correlational and experimental evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Shipley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Riper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101753</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Negative emotional appeals: The effectiveness of fear and guilt communicative appeals on individuals pro-environmental behaviour and environmental concern to microplastic pollution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The psychological consequences of the ecological crisis: Three new questionnaires to assess eco-anxiety, eco-guilt, and ecological grief</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ágoston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Urban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Csaba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Kőváry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kovacs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Climate Risk Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100441</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of emotion in global warming policy support and opposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Leiserowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Risk Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="937" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recycling and Ambivalence: Quantitative and Qualitative Analyses of Household Recycling Among Young Adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ojala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environment and Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="777" to="797" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hope and climate change: The importance of hope for environmental engagement among young people</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ojala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Education Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="642" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emotions predict policy support: Why it matters how people feel about climate change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Leviston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hurlstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lawrence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Environmental Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building a model of commitment to the natural environment to predict ecological behavior and willingness to sacrifice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Le</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Coy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of environmental psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">About us</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cint</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.cint.com/about" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cint quality charter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cint</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.cint.com/quality" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>cited 2022</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The International Organization for Standardization. ISO 20252:2019(en) Market, opinion and social research, including insights and data analytics -Vocabulary and service requirements</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/#iso:std:iso:20252:ed-3:v1:en" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>cited 2022</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Stats</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.stats.govt.nz/tools/2018-census-place-summaries/new-zealand" />
		<title level="m">census place summaries: New Zealand</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>cited 2022</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qualtrics. Survey Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<pubPlace>Provo, Utah, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Handbook of psychological testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data_Feeling and sacrifice_How eco emotions inform decisions to live with less to protect the natural environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jaeger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">sav. Mendeley Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">12024</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">IBM SPSS statistics for Macintosh</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ibm Corp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<pubPlace>Armonk, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Handbook of item response theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Muthén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mplus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Chapman and Hall/CRC</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="518" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding latent groups in observed data: A primer on latent profile analysis in Mplus for applied researchers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ferguson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hull</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Behavioral Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="458" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Estimating the dimension of a model. The annals of statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="464" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An empirical pooling approach for estimating marketing mix elasticities with PIMS data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ramaswamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Desarbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reibstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information theory and an extension of the maximum likelihood principle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Akaike</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="213" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Selected papers of Hirotugu Akaike</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Millennials stand out for climate change activism, social media engagement with issue</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tyson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Funk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Gen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Pew Research Center</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite mixture models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Peel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Maclahlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">John &amp; Sons</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Audience segmentation and climate change communication: Conceptual and methodological considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Reser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Morrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cooksey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Climate Change</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="459" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Global climate risk index 2019. Who suffers most from extreme weather events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Eckstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M-L</forename><surname>Hutfils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Winges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychological responses to the proximity of climate change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brügger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dessai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Devine-Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Pidgeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature climate change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1031" to="1037" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The affect heuristic in judgments of risks and benefits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Finucane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alhakami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of behavioral decision making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Communication and mental processes: Experiential and analytic processing of uncertain climate information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Marx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Orlove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Leiserowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Krantz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Roncoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Environmental Change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Normative influences on altruism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="279" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New environmental theories: toward a coherent theory of environmentally significant behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="424" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The social-psychological determinants of climate change risk perceptions: Towards a comprehensive model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Der Linden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analyses of factors motivating climate change adaptation behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Van Valkengoed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Steg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature climate change</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive affect and negative affect as modulators of cognition and motivation: The rediscovery of affect in achievement goal theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bj⊘rnebekk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scandinavian Journal of Educational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Powered by compassion: The effect of lovingkindness meditation on entrepreneurs&apos; sustainable decision-making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Engel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ramesh</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Venturing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105986</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feelings for the suffering of others and the environment: Compassion fosters proenvironmental tendencies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pfattheicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sassenrath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schindler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environment and Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="929" to="945" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compassion: an evolutionary analysis and empirical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Goetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Keltner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Simon-Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">351</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twenty years after Hines, Hungerford, and Tomera: A new meta-analysis of psycho-social determinants of pro-environmental behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bamberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Möser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guilt consistently motivates pro-environmental outcomes while pride depends on context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sintov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101776</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding the prevalence of eco guilt and eco grief among adolescents: A salutogenic approach towards building &apos;pro-environmental behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Nambiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IOP Conference Series: Earth and Environmental Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2023</biblScope>
			<publisher>IOP Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of fear appeals on pro-environmental behavior and crucial determinants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M-F</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Advertising</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of induced emotions on environmental preferences and behavior: An experimental study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ibanez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roussel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plos one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">258045</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate anxiety, pro-environmental action and wellbeing: antecedents and outcomes of negative emotional responses to climate change in 28 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ogunbode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hanss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ojala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Salmela-Aro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Van Den Broek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Eco-anxiety and environmental concern as predictors of ecoactivism. IOP Conference Series: Earth and Environmental Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IOP Publishing</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2022</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How can climate change anxiety induce both pro-environmental behaviours and ecoparalysis? The mediating role of general self-efficacy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Innocenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Santarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lombardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ciabini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zjalic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3085</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fear control and danger control: A test of the extended parallel process model (EPPM). Communications Monographs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Witte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="134" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Negative emotions about climate change are related to insomnia symptoms and mental health: Cross-sectional evidence from 25 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ogunbode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pallesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Böhm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Doran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bhullar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aquino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2021</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Suomen mielenterveysseura</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pihkala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Climate anxiety</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The value of online surveys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mathur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Internet research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methods of coping with social desirability bias: A review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nederhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European journal of social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">No glory without sacrifice-drivers of climate (in) action in the general population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thaller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fleiß</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brudermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Science &amp; Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
