<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Do autistic adults spontaneously reason about belief? A replication study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hannah</forename><surname>Partington</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maryna</forename><surname>Nosyk</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gillian</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ruihan</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ishita</forename><surname>Chowdhury</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Sarah</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
							<email>s.white@ucl.ac.uk</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cognitive Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Cognitive Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Psychology and Language Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>WC1N 3AZ</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Do autistic adults spontaneously reason about belief? A replication study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A44030180874E283C18C3E5B1C516447</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Autism</term>
					<term>spontaneous mentalizing</term>
					<term>theory of mind</term>
					<term>anticipatory-looking</term>
					<term>eye-tracking</term>
					<term>false-belief</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>To overcome the criticisms of earlier work using anticipatory-looking paradigms to investigate implicit mentalizing in autism, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref> recently presented a multi-trial paradigm with matched true-belief and false-belief conditions. This study is a replication of Wu et al.'s work using a novel set of stimuli and a separate group of participants, all of whom were naïve to this paradigm. Fifty-four (26 autistic) participants completed an implicit mentalizing task with both high-and low-demand false-belief conditions with two corresponding true-belief control conditions, alongside an explicit mentalizing task. In accordance with <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>, our findings support the presence of spontaneous mentalizing difficulties in autistic adults, despite strong explicit mentalizing abilities.</p><p>Therefore, we provide further evidence that whilst some autistic adults with high-IQs may have developed compensatory strategies that mask mentalizing difficulties on explicit tasks, implicit tasks reveal differences in the underlying spontaneous mechanism.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Do autistic adults spontaneously reason about belief? A replication study</head><p>As autism is often evaluated by clinicians at the behavioural level, its diagnosis is both subjective and susceptible to compensation. There is therefore a need for objective assessments of autism that are sensitive across a range of ages and abilities by tapping into cognitive processes, and implicit mentalizing tasks are a promising candidate. Indeed, work using <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Southgate et al. (2007)</ref>'s anticipatory-looking paradigm has provided evidence for the presence of implicit mentalizing differences in autism <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Senju et al., 2009)</ref>. However, this paradigm has been criticised and thus, the conclusiveness of these findings challenged.</p><p>Recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref> developed <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Southgate et al. (2007)</ref>'s paradigm to address its criticisms. Firstly, they implemented a multi-trial design, increasing power and improving the signal-to-noise ratio. Whilst <ref type="bibr">Wu et al.</ref> were not the first to extend Southgate et al.'s singletrial paradigm to a multi-trial one, they argue that methodological limitations, such as lengthy task durations and deviations to the story and set-up of the false-belief (FB) videos, hinder the extent of the conclusions that can be drawn from these studies (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Schneider et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Schuwerk et al., 2015)</ref>. Secondly, <ref type="bibr">Wu et al. extended Southgate et al.'</ref>s paradigm by introducing a well matched true-belief (TB) control condition to verify that autistic people struggle specifically with spontaneous mentalizing. Again, whilst others have endeavoured to improve upon Southgate et al.'s paradigm by including a control condition (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Gliga et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Schneider et al., 2013)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Wu et al.</ref> argue that these modifications were not sufficiently comparable to the FB condition to make such verifications. Finally, Wu et al. chose to include both high-and low-demand FB conditions. Prior work in non-autistic participants has suggested that the greater cognitive resource required for high-demand FB conditions compromises anticipatory-looking <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Wang &amp; Leslie, 2016</ref>); yet several of the earlier studies which extended Southgate et al.'s paradigm by including multiple trials and a control condition also only included high-demand FB conditions (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Schneider et al., 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Schneider et al., , 2013))</ref>.</p><p>Using this updated paradigm, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref> found that, unlike non-autistic people, autistic people's gaze behaviour was not biased by the protagonist's beliefs, suggesting that autistic people do not spontaneously attribute mental states. Critically, an analysis of gaze patterns over time enabled <ref type="bibr">Wu et al.</ref> to dismiss other non-mentalizing explanations for this result, such as differences in attention or difficulties predicting actions. Furthermore, Wu et al.'s results suggest that their anticipatory-looking paradigm is sufficiently sensitive to overcome compensation strategies, as the autistic group performed comparably to the nonautistic group on a test of explicit mentalistic reasoning.</p><p>To further validate <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>'s paradigm, we conducted a replication of their work using a novel set of FB and TB videos with different participants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p>Fifty-four adults (26 autistic) gave informed consent to take part in this study, which had been approved by the local research ethics committee. The two groups were recruited through a local participant database and were matched on gender, age and IQ (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). All autistic participants had a prior diagnosis of either Autism Spectrum Disorder (5) or Asperger syndrome (21), and 20 met the ADOS criteria for autism/autism spectrum. The remaining six participants were not excluded because they provided a written clinical diagnosis and the ADOS is less sensitive in people with higher IQs <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Kamp-Becker et al., 2013)</ref>. Participants completed the Autism-Spectrum Quotient (AQ) and the autistic group reported significantly higher autistic traits (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Explicit Mentalizing</head><p>Participants completed the Mental State set from Happé's Strange Stories Task (SST).</p><p>See <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">White et al., 2009</ref> for test materials, administration and scoring criteria.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implicit Mentalizing -An Anticipatory-Looking Paradigm</head><p>Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>, the task had two types of trials: familiarisation and experimental. Both started with a protagonist stood behind a screen with two windows in it.</p><p>Below each window was a box with the lid open and one contained a pop-up toy (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). During the familiarisation trials, a puppet appeared on screen and closed the lids of both boxes (empty box first). Once the puppet left the scene, the windows illuminated for 1000ms and a chime sounded simultaneously. Afterwards, the protagonist reached through the window and opened the lid of the box containing the toy. These trials aimed to habituate participants to the sequence of events, and to the contingency between the chime/flash and the protagonist's subsequent reach through the window to retrieve the toy. The location of the toy and handedness of the puppeteer were counterbalanced, resulting in four familiarisation trials, all 15s long. This task had two pairs of matched experimental trial conditions: TB short turn (TBST) and FB high-demand (FBHD), and TB long turn (TBLT) and FB low-demand (FBLD). Up until the point the puppet left the scene, the experimental trials were identical to the familiarisation trials. After this, a telephone rang and the protagonist turned away from the scene. In all except the TBST condition, the puppet re-appeared at this point. In the TBLT condition, the puppet opened and closed the lid of the box containing the toy. In the FBHD condition, the puppet swapped the boxes around and in the FBLD condition, the puppet replaced the box containing the toy with an empty box. Afterwards, the puppet left the scene, a telephone engaged tone was heard, and the protagonist turned back to the scene. The windows then illuminated and a chime sounded for 1s whilst the scene froze for 6s to the end of video. The TBST condition was exactly the same as the FBHD condition except the protagonist turned back to the scene before the puppet re-appeared so that she witnessed the puppet swap the boxes. The direction the protagonist turned, the position of the toy and the handedness of the puppeteer were counterbalanced, resulting in eight trials for each condition, all 30s long.</p><p>As described, the puppet in our videos swaps the boxes containing the toy, instead of opening the boxes and transferring the toy as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al.'s (2024)</ref> videos. However, this is the only fundamental difference between our and Wu et al.'s stimuli. A Tobii X3-120 eyetracker with a sampling rate of 120 Hz was used to record gaze data. Participants sat circa 70cm away from the eye-tracker and a nine-point calibration was conducted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedure</head><p>The SST task was completed first followed by the implicit mentalizing task, which consisted of one familiarisation and four experimental blocks, with a short break between blocks. Contrary to <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>, the blocks were not split into sections with a longer break in-between as this did not seem to help maintain attention. The familiarisation block was presented first and consisted of all four familiarisation trials in a randomised order. Each experimental block began with one familiarisation trial followed by two experimental trials from each condition presented in a randomised order. The familiarisation trial and experimental trials in each block were randomly selected but each was only presented once across the four experimental blocks. Participants were instructed to watch the videos carefully as questions would be asked about them at the end of the task. Questions were included to encourage participants to pay attention and queried basic features of the videos.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Analysis</head><p>Two areas of interest (AOIs) were identified: the window and box area that was consistent (belief-congruent AOI) and inconsistent (belief-incongruent AOI) with the protagonist's belief about the toy's location. The total fixation duration to each AOI from the onset of the windows illuminating to the end of the video (approximately 6s) was extracted through Tobii Pro Studio. From this data, differential looking scores (DLSs; <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Senju &amp; Csibra, 2008)</ref> were calculated as a measure of looking preference, with values ranging from 1 to -1.</p><p>A DLS close to 1 indicates a strong preference for the belief-congruent AOI, while a DLS close to -1 indicates a strong preference for the belief-incongruent AOI.</p><p>Thirteen of the participants (9 autistic) were not above chance in the experimental block familiarisation trials despite the protagonist revealing the toy. As excluding these participants did not alter statistical outcomes, all 54 participants were included in all analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Explicit Mentalizing Task</head><p>There was no significant difference between the autistic (M=11.96, SD=2.66) and non-autistic (M=12.54, SD=2.01) participants' performance on the SST (t(52)=-0.90, p=0.37, d=0.24) and thus, their ability to explicitly infer mental states.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implicit Mentalizing Task</head><p>One sample t-tests (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>) indicated that the non-autistic group showed a significant looking preference towards the belief-congruent AOI in the TBLT and FBLD condition whereas the autistic group did not perform above chance in either condition.</p><p>Neither group performed above chance in the FBHD or its control condition (TBST), indicating that these conditions may not have successfully detected belief monitoring.</p><p>Therefore, subsequent analyses focus only on FBLD and TBLT conditions, which corresponds with the analyses performed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>.</p><p>As expected from <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>, a 2(belief: TB vs FB) x 2(group: autistic vs nonautistic) ANOVA showed a significant main effect of group (F(1, 52)=3.54, p(onetailed)=.03, d=0.04) and no significant interaction between belief and group (F(1, 52)=1. <ref type="bibr">21, p=.28, d=0.01)</ref>. This indicates that the autistic group showed less preference for the beliefcongruent AOI than the non-autistic group, and that the effect of belief on looking preference was comparable across the autistic and non-autistic groups (see Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>). Unlike <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>, we found no significant effect of belief (F(1, 52)=0.02, p(one-tailed)=.44, d&lt;0.01), indicating that participants showed a similar looking bias towards the belief-congruent AOI in the TB and FB conditions (see Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>This study investigated implicit mentalizing in autistic adults. Specifically, a replication of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref> was performed: anticipatory-looking was investigated using a multi-trial paradigm with well-matched TB and FB conditions. Of note, a novel stimuli set was used and all participants were naïve to the paradigm. Our results closely matched those of Wu et al., as we also found evidence for the presence of spontaneous mentalizing difficulties in autistic adults. Despite the autistic group displaying good explicit mentalizing abilities, our findings showed that only the non-autistic group showed a clear looking preference towards the belief-congruent AOI during the FBLD condition. Thus, the autistic participants did not seem to spontaneously anticipate the protagonist's actions based on her false-belief.</p><p>We also replicated results from <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>, who found no interaction between group and belief. Alongside the main effect of group, this indicates that autistic adults spent considerably less time looking at the belief congruent AOI than the non-autistic adults across both TB and FB conditions. Whilst an initially unexpected result, Wu et al. concluded that it may be a result of the TB trials requiring visual perspective taking, itself a mentalizingdependent process <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Hamilton et al., 2009)</ref>. Thus, the TB trials may not act as the mentalizingfree control as intended. Our replication of this finding further highlights the need for the development of a new TB condition without a visual perspective change. This would verify that autistic people's performance is limited solely by a difference in spontaneous mentalizing.</p><p>Whilst our results largely replicated those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>, we did not find an effect of belief on DLSs, meaning that participants showed a similar looking bias towards the belief-congruent AOI across the TB and FB conditions. We also found overall smaller effect sizes. These findings may be a consequence of the higher working memory load of our stimuli set <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Wang &amp; Leslie, 2016)</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref> and in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Southgate et al. (2007)</ref>'s original work, the toy was shown to the participants as it was moved from one box to the other. However, in this study, the participants only saw the toy in its original location, requiring them to remember which box it was in, as the boxes were moved. Therefore, working memory load may have compromised our anticipatory looking paradigm, contributing to the lack of an effect of belief. This divergence from <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>'s findings, and the higher number of our participants performing at chance in the familiarisation trials, suggest that Wu et al.'s stimuli design is more suitable for future work.</p><p>In conclusion, we have demonstrated that the core finding from <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wu et al. (2024)</ref>, the lack of a belief-congruent looking bias in a group of autistic adults, is maintained across participant samples and stimuli. More generally, these findings provide further evidence for the presence of mentalizing differences in autism and highlight the need for tests of mentalizing that tap into the underlying spontaneous cognitive mechanism. Furthermore, non-verbal implicit tasks, such as this anticipatory-looking paradigm, hold promise for facilitating the inclusion of people who are often under-represented in autism research.   Sequence of events in familiarization and experimental trials in implicit mentalizing task Note. Images A to D depict the sequence of events that occur in the familiarization trials: image A shows the initial set-up, image B shows the puppet closing the lids of the boxes, image C shows both windows illuminated (at this point a chime sounded) and image D shows the protagonist reaching through the window above the box with the toy in it and opening its lid. Images E and F depict events from the experimental trials: image E shows the puppet moving the boxes while the actor looks away and Image F shows the puppet moving the boxes while the actor watches. As seen in these images, the protagonist's head followed the movement of the puppet to indicate that she was paying attention to the scene. A C B Mean DLS for TBLT and FBLD conditions for autistic and non-autistic groups Note. A main effect of group but not belief was found and there was no belief*group interaction.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1</figDesc><graphic coords="14,73.06,143.68,108.51,99.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="15,72.00,154.49,335.55,227.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Group descriptive statistics, mean (standard deviation), and comparisons</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Autistic</cell><cell>Non-Autistic</cell><cell>Comparisons</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n = 26)</cell><cell>(n = 28)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gender (Female: Male)</cell><cell>5: 21</cell><cell>7: 21</cell><cell>X 2 (1)=0.26, p=.61</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell>34.88 (7.71)</cell><cell>32.21 (10.70)</cell><cell>t(52)=1.05, p=.30</cell></row><row><cell>Performance IQ a</cell><cell>110.54 (14.43)</cell><cell>114.64 (13.33)</cell><cell>t(52)=-1.09, p=.28</cell></row><row><cell>Verbal IQ a</cell><cell>115.85 (10.13)</cell><cell>117.75 (10.53)</cell><cell>t(52)=-0.68, p=.50</cell></row><row><cell>Full-scale IQ a</cell><cell>114.69 (11.59)</cell><cell>117.64 (11.54)</cell><cell>t(52)=-0.94, p=.35</cell></row><row><cell>AQ b</cell><cell>33.16 (8.74)</cell><cell>13.75 (5.67)</cell><cell>t(51)=9.69, p&lt;.001</cell></row></table><note><p>a Measured using the Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence-II or Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale -III b One autistic participant did not complete</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>One sample t-tests against chance level performance (0)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Condition</cell><cell></cell><cell>Autistic</cell><cell cols="2">Non-Autistic</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>M(SD)</cell><cell>t-test</cell><cell>M(SD)</cell><cell>t-test</cell></row><row><cell>TBLT</cell><cell>0.02(0.37)</cell><cell>t(25)=0.27, p=.79,</cell><cell>0.21(0.42)</cell><cell>t(27)=2.70, p=.01*,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>d=0.05</cell><cell></cell><cell>d=0.51</cell></row><row><cell>FBLD</cell><cell>0.08(0.23)</cell><cell>t(25)=1.77, p=.09,</cell><cell>0.13(0.29)</cell><cell>t(27)=2.43, p=.02*,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>d=0.35</cell><cell></cell><cell>d=0.46</cell></row><row><cell>TBST</cell><cell>0.06(0.24)</cell><cell>t(25)=1.34, p=.19,</cell><cell>0.11(0.33)</cell><cell>t(27)=1.80, p=.08,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>d=0.26</cell><cell></cell><cell>d=0.34</cell></row><row><cell>FBHD</cell><cell>-0.03(0.33)</cell><cell>t(25)=-0.51 , p=.62,</cell><cell>-0.02(0.36)</cell><cell>t(27)=-0.23 , p=.83</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>d=0.10</cell><cell></cell><cell>d=0.04</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spontaneous Belief Attribution in Younger Siblings of Children on the Autism Spectrum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gliga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Senju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pettinato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Charman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>The</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Team</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0034146</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0034146" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Developmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="903" to="913" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual perspective taking impairment in children with autistic spectrum disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brindley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Frith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cognition.2009.07.007</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cognition.2009.07.007" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of the revised algorithm of Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule (ADOS) in the diagnostic investigation of high-functioning children and adolescents with autism spectrum disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kamp-Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ghahreman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heinzel-Gutenbrunner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Remschmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1362361311408932</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361311408932" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Autism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Eye movements reveal sustained implicit processing of others&apos; mental states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bayliss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0025458</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0025458" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Psychology: General</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A temporally sustained implicit theory of mind deficit in autism spectrum disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Slaughter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bayliss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cognition.2013.08.004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cognition.2013.08.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="410" to="417" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implicit and explicit Theory of Mind reasoning in autism spectrum disorders: The impact of experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schuwerk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vuori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sodian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1362361314526004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361314526004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Autism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gaze Following in Human Infants Depends on Communicative Signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Senju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Csibra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cub.2008.03.059</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2008.03.059SPONTANEOUSFALSE-BELIEFREASONING11" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="668" to="671" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mindblind Eyes: An Absence of Spontaneous Theory of Mind in Asperger Syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Senju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Southgate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Frith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="883" to="885" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 5942</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Action Anticipation through Attribution of False Belief by 2-Year-Olds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Southgate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Senju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Csibra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="592" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is Implicit Theory of Mind the &apos;Real Deal&apos;? The Own-Belief/True-Belief Default in Adults and Young Preschoolers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leslie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/mila.12099</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/mila.12099" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mind &amp; Language</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting the Strange Stories: Revealing Mentalizing Impairments in Autism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Happé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Frith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Child Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1097" to="1117" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do autistic adults spontaneously reason about belief? A detailed exploration of alternative explanations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Acem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Chowdhury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Royal Society Open Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">231889</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
