<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Value of Hydropower as a Grid-Scale Storage Resource: A Commodity Market Approach</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Brittany</forename><surname>Tarufelli</surname></persName>
							<email>brittany.tarufelli@pnnl.gov.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barrows</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>AND</roleName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Somani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Boff</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Value of Hydropower as a Grid-Scale Storage Resource: A Commodity Market Approach</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">438B2E86DCC6DB5174332E6BA3FA3027</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T14:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Grid-scale energy storage enhances power system performance by shifting loads and supporting capacity, reliability, and transmission. However, as storage penetration increases, arbitrage opportunities-and associated profits-decline <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Sioshansi et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Li et al., 2024)</ref>. In ERCOT, for example, 2024 saw reduced arbitrage due to moderate weather and expanded storage. This trend contrasts with findings that long-duration storage is essential for reliability and affordability (Blair et al., 2022), suggesting the need for new business models to capture storage's full value. Despite growing deployment in energy storage, empirical research on storage's value remains limited.</p><p>To address this gap, we develop a commodity-market-based framework and apply it to hydropower as a grid-scale storage resource. Using exogenous variation in reservoir storage volume as a proxy for energy storage, we estimate its causal effect on risk premiums-measured by the day-ahead to real-time price spread-in the Northwestern United States between May 2022 and November 2024. Employing fixed effects and lagged dependent variable models, we control for time-invariant heterogeneity across balancing authorities and account for dynamic price behavior.</p><p>We find that a 10% increase in reservoir storage volume reduces risk premiums by 5%, indicating that hydropower reservoir storage mitigates short-term supply-demand imbalances. Our results are robust to dynamic pricing effects and suggest that storage is especially valuable during grid stress events, with pronounced impacts at the upper end of the price distribution. This result indicates that reservoir storage may be more valuable during grid stress events. As most markets lack compensation mechanisms for stored energy, our findings offer empirical support for designing future models that better reflect the risk-reducing benefits of grid-scale storage.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>In this research, we empirically examine the contributions of hydropower reservoir storage volume as energy storage through the lens of commodity markets to better understand the value proposition of energy storage. Our empirical approach considers the Northwestern region of the United States due to its high percentage of storable hydroelectric power in the form of reservoirs.</p><p>We examine the potential benefits (or value) of energy storage for electricity markets in the context of two theories which explain the relationship between spot and future prices in commodity markets: the theory of storage and the risk premium theory.</p><p>In the theory of storage, the relationship between the current spot price and futures price of a commodity is based on the costs and convenience of holding physical inventories in that commodity. The value of storage in this theory is based on the benefits, or convenience yield, derived from holding a physical stock of inventory over time-for example, owning inventory can allow a producer to meet sudden changes in demand or address seasonality. Historically, in electricity markets, this relationship collapses as sufficient megawatt hours of electricity cannot be "carried" from the futures to spot market to address supply and demand imbalances. Futures contracts are instead priced based on an expectation of a spot price and a risk premium, which is an additional compensation for bearing risk. These theories are not mutually exclusive, as changes in the risk premium or expected changes in the spot price can be driven by changes in the interest rate, marginal storage cost, or marginal convenience yield.</p><p>An extensive literature on the theory of storage, as summarized briefly in the next section, finds that futures prices tend to be less than spot prices (backwardation) although futures prices can exceed spot prices (contango) when storage is ample. The underlying intuition is that convenience yield is inversely related to storage levels. The risk premium literature, also discussed in the next section, finds that the risk premium represents the additional compensation to market participants for bearing supply or demand risk. In electricity markets, hedging demand-side risk (due to high demand or high price volatility) can result in excess demand for futures contracts, with futures price being greater than the expected spot price, or a negative risk premium. Hedging supply-side risk (due low demand or low price volatility) typically results in the futures price being less than the expected spot price (positive risk premium) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bessembinder and Lemmon, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al., 2010)</ref>. From these theories, we hypothesize that energy storage should have an inverse relationship with convenience yield or the risk premium, that is, we hypothesize that demand for futures contracts is likely to be higher when hydropower reservoir levels are low, due to increased hedging pressure from demand-side risk.</p><p>Our research design exploits exogenous variation in hydropower reservoir levels and inflow to those reservoirs in the Northwestern region of the United States to determine the value of energy storage. We use robust econometric methods, including fixed effects models and lagged dependent variable models to evaluate the impact of increasing levels of hydropower reservoir storage on day ahead risk premiums in the Columbia River Basin. By using fixed effects models with panel data, we can observe how controlling for time-invariant observed and unobserved heterogeneity from Northwestern balancing authorities-such as regional climate or infrastructure differences-can impact risk premiums. However, fixed effects models also have the underlying assumption that important omitted variables are time invariant. Lagged dependent variable models are instead used to account for the time-dependent nature of electricity prices on risk premiums, where previous spot price realizations can influence both risk perceptions and price expectations <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Botterud et al., 2010)</ref>. By including a lagged risk premium variable, we can account for this dynamic behavior and address this important potential omitted variable bias. However, including a lagged risk premium variable can cause coefficients for other explanatory variables (i.e., hydropower reservoir storage) to be biased downward in the presence of autocorrelation in the errors <ref type="bibr">(Anderson and</ref><ref type="bibr">Hsiao, 1981, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Angrist and Pischke, 2009)</ref>. Our framework, which incorporates both fixed effects and lagged dependent variable models allows us to control for time-invariant heterogeneity across balancing authorities and account for dynamic behavior.</p><p>We acknowledge that including both a lagged risk premium variable and balancing authoritylevel fixed effects in some specifications of the model can induce dynamic panel bias if the lagged dependent variable is correlated with the regression error-a problem that arises when datasets are large N and small T <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Nickell, 1981)</ref>. However, because our dataset is small N and large T (N = 11, T = 552) in the daily average data, and an even larger time dimension in the hourly data this bias from using fixed effects with a lagged dependent variable will be small. We also report different specifications of the model (fixed effects only, lagged dependent variable only) to demonstrate the upper and lower bounds of the potential impact of hydropower reservoir storage on risk premiums.</p><p>We find that increasing levels of hydropower reservoir storage have an inverse relationship with risk premium. That is, an increase in hydropower reservoir storage volume of 10% leads to a decrease in risk premium by approximately 5%. This is in line with both the theory of storage and risk premium theory, as we would expect that increases in storage would have an inverse relationship with the convenience yield or risk premium. Further, when we examine variation in risk premiums across space (i.e., across balancing authorities), we find that an increase in hydropower reservoir storage levels of 10% decreases risk premiums by 5% to 9%.</p><p>Our research is most closely related to the work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al. (2010)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Weron and Zator (2014)</ref> who examine the impact of hydropower reservoir storage on convenience yield and risk premiums in the NordPool, the Norwegian electricity market, which also has high penetration of hydropower reservoir storage. Using a linear regression approach, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al. (2010)</ref> found that an increase in reservoir levels negatively impacted both convenience yield and risk premiums for futures contracts that ranged from a one-to six-weeks in duration. Examining the same set of data but correcting for some noted econometric issues observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al. (2010)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Weron and</ref> Zator came to the opposite conclusion, that an increase in reservoir levels positively impacted risk premiums.</p><p>We build on the model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al. (2010)</ref>, but address the econometric issues noted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Weron and Zator (2014)</ref> and add factors specific to the Northwestern market (natural gas storage, wind and solar production) which provide unique insights into the value of reservoir energy storage. An important contribution of our work is that we also propose a methodology which bounds the impact of including or excluding a lagged-risk premium variable to capture the impact of past market outcomes which can influence current trading decisions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al. (2010)</ref> argue for the inclusion of the spot price variable as an important determinant of the risk premium, but Weron and Zator argue for excluding the spot price as it can induce simultaneity biases that also influence the futures price. We acknowledge that both futures and spot prices are important influences for trading decisions and instead include a lagged risk premium variable, which diminishes the role of bias resulting from the relationship between spot and current prices. In our econometric framework, we acknowledge that including a lagged risk premium variable can induce bias,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> but argue that bias is small, and provides a lower bound for the effect of energy storage, in the form of hydropower reservoir storage, on risk premiums in a market with a high penetration of existing hydropower storage resources.</p><p>Our research reflects the reality of a hydro-rich market in the United States, which can serve as a test-case for the value of energy storage. An important limitation of our work is that energy storage in the form of hydropower reservoir storage is considered long-duration energy storage, and our findings may not apply to emerging short-duration energy storage resources. Another important limitation of our work is that there is limited publicly available data for longer-duration futures contracts in this region, so our findings are limited to the impact of energy storage on shortterm risk premiums.</p><p>Last, as an extension of our work, we consider the impact that increasing hydropower reservoir storage volumes has on other aspects of price formation, including the impact of hydropower reservoir storage on real-time prices and the distribution of real time prices. We find that increases in hydropower reservoir storage volumes are more impactful at the upper end of the real-time price distribution, indicating that hydropower reservoir storage may be even more beneficial during grid stress events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluation of Storage: Two Theories</head><p>Two main theories explain price dynamics and the value of storage in commodity markets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Theory of Storage.</head><p>First introduced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Working (1933)</ref>, this theory links spot and futures prices to the costs and benefits of holding inventories (storage). The price difference between delivery dates is the carrying charge, which reflects storage and financing costs (storage charge), offset by the convenience yield-the benefit of holding physical stocks <ref type="bibr">(Kaldor, 1939;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Working, 1948;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Working 1949)</ref>. When convenience yield exceeds storage costs, futures prices may fall below spot prices (backwardation); when storage costs dominate, futures prices exceed spot prices (contango). Convenience yield decreases as inventories rise, and is highest when stocks are scarce, helping explain observed market behaviors <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Brennan, 1958;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Pindyck, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Pindyck 2001</ref>). Storage also shapes volatility as low inventories and high storage costs tend to increase volatility <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Fama and French, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pindyck 2004a;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pindyck 2004b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Geman and Ohana, 2009)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Risk Premium Theory.</head><p>This framework defines futures prices as the expected future spot price plus a risk premium reflecting participants' risk aversion. If more risk-averse consumers hedge, excess demand pushes futures above expected spot prices (negative risk premium); when producers hedge, excess supply pushes futures below expected spot prices (positive risk premium) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Botterud et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bessembinder and Lemmon, 2002)</ref>. Risk premia rise with volatility and capture the increased compensation needed for bearing supply or demand risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Considine and Larson, 2001)</ref>.</p><p>Unlike the storage theory, this framework applies to both storable and non-storable commodities.</p><p>The two theories are not mutually exclusive: changes in interest rates, storage costs, or convenience yields affect both the expected spot price and risk premium <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Fama and French, 1987)</ref>. Together, they explain how inventories, costs, and risk preferences shape spot-futures price dynamics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hydropower Reservoir Storage as Energy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Storage in the Pacific Northwest</head><p>Our empirical approach examines the value of hydropower reservoir storage as energy storage in the Northwestern region of the United States. This region was selected due to its high percentage of storable hydroelectric power. The Northwest is a region of vertically integrated utilities with robust bilateral trading. In this region, the mid-Columbia trading hub serves as a futures market, while the Western Energy Reach and Wells dams <ref type="bibr">(S&amp;P Global, 2024)</ref>. It serves as a futures market for the Northwestern region, where participants can exchange day-ahead contracts for electricity.</p><p>The Western Energy Imbalance Market (WEIM) is a real-time wholesale power trading market operated by the California Independent System Operator (CAISO) in the western region of the United States. Although the WEIM is operated in a region of primarily bilateral power trading, it provides a centralized market for balancing real-time generation and demand. This enables more efficient allocation of power in the region, which has resulted in substantial cost savings by balancing authorities <ref type="bibr">(CAISO, 2024)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hydropower Dams</head><p>This analysis considers dams which market hydropower at the mid-Columbia trading hub <ref type="bibr">(S&amp;P Global, 2024)</ref>. From furthest upstream to furthest downstream on the Columbia River, these include Wells, Rocky Reach, Rock Island, Wanapum and Priest Rapids dams, as shown in  and further upstream, the Grand Coulee Dam, owned by the United States Bureau of Reclamation <ref type="bibr">(EIA, 2025)</ref>. The Grand Coulee Dam is the largest power plant in the United States with a generating capacity of 6,809 MW and power distributed to eleven states. Downstream from the Priest Rapids Dam are four dams whose power is marketed by BPA.</p><p>To account for the centralized dam structure, we construct a system-level variable which represents the hydropower reservoir storage available in the Wells, Rocky Reach, Rock Island, Wanapum and Priest Rapids dams. To account for the potential impact of the upstream Grand Coulee Dam, we perform robustness tests which examine inflow impacts of this Dam on the risk premium.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Futures price data</head><p>Our region of interest, the Pacific Northwest, is composed of vertically integrated utilities with a robust (but opaque) bilateral trading market. As these utilities are not part of an organized market (ISO or RTO), day-ahead price data is limited. To overcome this limitation, we utilized day-ahead price data for the mid-Columbia trading hub which is made available to the U.S. Energy Information Administration (EIA) from the Intercontinental Exchange (ICE). The ICE day-ahead data are only published when the trade date is a business day, constraining our analysis to these trade dates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spot price data</head><p>Robust participation in the WEIM in this region allows us to obtain 5-minute real-time price data from the California ISO's OASIS system (CAISO OASIS) which publishes locational marginal price (LMP) data for price nodes and aggregated price nodes in the WEIM. 1 Real-time price data were available at aggregate price nodes for the following balancing authorities in the Northwest which also participate in the WEIM: Bonneville Power (BPAT), Avista (AVA), 1 Data for aggregate price nodes represents the weighted average LMP for multiple price nodes, with weights being distribution factors.</p><p>Pacificorp West (PACW), Pacificorp East (PACE), Idaho Power (IPCO), Puget Sound Energy (PSEI), Portland General Electric (PGE), Tacoma Power (TPWR), Seattle City Light (SCL), Nevada Power (NEVP) 1 and Northwestern Energy (NWMT).</p><p>Five-minute price (LMP) data were collected for each balancing authority and converted to hourly averages. As balancing authorities joined the WEIM over time, with the last balancing authority (BPA) joining on May 3, 2022, we limited our study period from May 2022 to November 2024.</p><p>To align with the daily availability of our day-ahead price data, we then aggregated our hourly average real-time pricing data to daily averages by using a load-weighted average of hourly prices for each balancing authority. We obtained load data from the EIA, which publishes hourly load data for each balancing authority.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk premium</head><p>Risk premium is defined as ln(ğ¸ ! ğ‘† !"# ğ¹ !,# ) â„ , consistent with <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Weron &amp; Zator (2014)</ref>, where ğ¹ !,#</p><p>is futures price at time t for a delivery time ğ‘¡ + ğ‘‡ and ğ¸ ! ğ‘† !"# is expected time ğ‘¡ + ğ‘‡ spot price from time ğ‘¡. In this paper, ex-post risk premium is used. As a result, realized spot price at time ğ‘¡ + ğ‘‡ is used for the term ğ¸ ! ğ‘† !"# as a proxy for expected spot price from time ğ‘¡.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> provides summary statistics for the risk premium from May 2022 to November 2024.</p><p>The risk premium is, on average, negative, but there are a limited number of days with a positive risk premium (shown as the percent positive, which is the percentage of days with a positive risk premium in each balancing authority  As an example of the observed trend in the risk premium variable, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> shows the risk premium in Bonneville Power Authority compared to its 20-day moving average. The risk premium in Bonneville Power is on average negative and displays negative skewness.   To generate the variable used for hydropower reservoir storage, hydropower reservoir storage is first averaged across hours to create a daily hydropower reservoir storage value for each reservoir.</p><p>Daily values are then summed across reservoirs to obtain a total hydropower reservoir storage volume for the system on a particular day. This quantity is divided by the sum of maximum hydropower reservoir storage volumes at each dam as defined by the Chelan Public Utility District (Chelan PUD). This results in a variable specification as reservoir storage volume as a percent of maximum reservoir storage capacity. Reservoirs also exhibit seasonality, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>, where values shown for each day are the average for each occurrence of that day in the three years between November 9, 2021, and November 8, 2024 compared to a 20-day moving average. Generally, reservoir storage capacity as a percent of maximum storage capacity is higher in summer and winter, but lower in spring and fall. Inflow is published as the inflow to a particular reservoir at daily granularity, measured in thousands of cubic feet per second. A single inflow variable was specified by first summing inflow across all dams. This variable was specified as a deviation from historical inflows to address for seasonality. Average total inflow to all dams for each calendar date in the year was calculated over  The ratio of mean inflow to usable storage indicates that reservoirs can typically be filled from minimum to maximum storable volume within a day, except under conditions of particularly low inflow. This gives reservoirs operational flexibility across a variety of inflow conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data for other explanatory variables</head><p>This analysis uses historical Henry Hub natural gas prices published by the EIA, which are published at daily granularity. Henry Hub is a natural gas transaction hub located in Louisiana, which serves as a price benchmark for natural gas in the U.S. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Li et al, 2017)</ref>. Natural gas inventory data is obtained from EIA's weekly natural gas storage report, which provides data at weekly granularity. The sum of natural gas inventory across the West and Mountain regions is used to 1 We opted to provide summary data for just one year (2023) of the overall period of analysis (May 2022 to November 2024) in order to give an annual summary of data without bias toward the months with more data. Full summary statistics can be provided by the authors upon request.</p><p>create a natural gas inventory variable, as balancing authorities considered in this analysis span the West and Mountain natural gas storage regions as defined by the EIA.</p><p>Demand data is obtained from the EIA, which publishes hourly demand for balancing authorities 1 . For each balancing authority, hourly demand is summed to daily granularity for consistency with the granularity of other variables. Similarly, wind generation and solar generation data is obtained from the EIA, which publishes hourly generation data by fuel source for each balancing authority. Hourly figures are summed to daily granularity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data for extension to real-time price analysis</head><p>Real-time WEIM price data from CAISO OASIS enables an analysis of the impacts of reservoir level on real-time prices. Excluding day-ahead price data, the dataset used for the analysis of reservoir storage's impact on real-time prices uses the same data sources and variables as the analysis of reservoir storage's impact on risk premium, except variables are aggregated to hourly instead of daily granularity in most cases. Specifically, 5-minute real-time prices were averaged for an hourly average real-time price. Hourly reservoir storage levels and demand levels were included in the real-time price analysis. Solar and wind generation, which are available at hourly totals, were summed to daily totals to address heteroskedasticity in the data. 2 All other variables are maintained at the same level of granularity as in the risk-premium analysis (daily inflow, daily natural gas prices, and weekly natural gas volumes).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Empirical Approach</head><p>Our empirical framework exploits exogenous variation in hydropower reservoir levels and inflow to those reservoirs to determine the value of hydropower reservoir storage, as such, the hydropower reservoir storage for the dam system (as a proportion of max storage capacity) for the dam system is the independent variable of interest.</p><p>1 For demand data from the EIA, several dates 11/04/2024 appeared to have missing data as 0 was reported as load for this date. This date was dropped from the analysis. 2 Other data transformations for wind and solar generation, such as square root transformations, resulted in similar results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk Premium Analysis</head><p>To estimate the short-term impacts of hydropower reservoir storage on risk premiums in the Northwestern U.S. bilateral electricity system, our approach incorporates several variables that control for factors other than hydropower reservoir storage that can impact risk premiums. These explanatory variables are plausibly exogenous, to allow us to establish causality of reservoir storage impacts. We include electricity demand as it has been shown to have a negative and statistically significant impact on risk premium in power markets <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Jacobs et al, 2022)</ref>. Electricity demand is largely insensitive to wholesale prices, making it plausibly exogenous. We include natural gas volume in the West and Mountain regions as natural gas volume has been shown to have a negative impact on forward premium in the PJM interconnection <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Douglas &amp; Popova, 2008)</ref>. Natural gas volume is plausibly exogenous as supply and demand decisions for natural gas storage are determined through other markets. Inflow deviation is included as a control, as increases in reservoir inflow could theoretically increase power supply and reduce power prices <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Botterud et al., 2010)</ref>. This could result in reduced demand for futures contracts and impact risk premiums. As discussed in the preceding section, reservoir inflow is a deviation from historical average inflow, allowing us to identify off of within daily variation in reservoir inflow. To account for increasing uncertainty from renewable resource production and its impact on day-ahead and real-time price spreads, solar and wind generation are also included as controls. Solar and wind generation are dependent on the sun shining or wind blowing and are plausibly exogenous. To control for differences in prices and risk premiums that may vary due to demand variation by weekday we include day-of-week fixed effects. Long-run trends, such as changes in the generation resource portfolio or seasonality are controlled for with month-by-year fixed effects. Because of the time-dependent nature of electricity prices where past realizations of prices can influence futures and expected spot prices (and thus, the risk premium), we also included a lagged risk premium variable in some specifications of our model.</p><p>The time-dependent nature of electricity market variables also raises the potential for nonstationarity in our variables. Non-stationarity can cause spurious regression results if, for example, there is an underlying trend in an exogenous variable that drives results. To address this concern, we use an Augmented Dickey-Fuller (ADF) test to check the stationarity of each independent variable. In instances where the ADF failed to reject the presence of a unit root in any balancing authority, we transformed the data to ensure stationarity.</p><p>Solar generation and demand were found to be non-stationary across most balancing authorities.</p><p>We first-differenced these variables to achieve stationarity. Natural gas price and natural gas volume were also found to be non-stationary. Given the seasonal patterns of these variables, we deseasonalized the data by removing the seasonal component<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">1</ref> , including only the stochastic portion which can't be explained by seasonality as our identifying variation. All other independent variables were found to be stationary.</p><p>For our first model, we propose a fixed effects model to determine the short-term impact of reservoir energy storage on risk premiums. This model establishes the upper bound for the impact of reservoir level on risk premium as it assumes any important omitted variables are time invariant:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ğ‘…ğ‘ƒ !,#,$ = ğ›¼ &amp; + ğ›¼ ' ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! + ğ›¼ ( ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! + ğ›¼ ) ğ· !,$ + ğ›¼ * ğºğ‘‰ ! + ğ›¼ + ğºğ‘ƒ ! + ğ›¼ , ğ‘† !,$ + ğ›¼ -ğ‘Š !,$ +ğ›¼ . ğ‘‹ ! + ğ›¼ / ğµğ´ $ + ğœ– (1)</formula><p>Where ğ‘…ğ‘ƒ !,#,% is the risk premium between time ğ‘¡ and ğ‘¡ + ğ‘‡ in balancing authority ğ‘–. ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! is the reservoir storage volume as a proportion of maximum reservoir storage capacity on day ğ‘¡ in Wells, Rocky Reach, Rock Island, Wanapum, and Priest Rapids dams, expressed as a percent of total capacity. ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! is the deviation from the daily historical average inflow, ğ· !,% is the firstdifferenced electricity demand for each balancing authority, ğºğ‘‰ ! is the deseasonlized weekly gas volume, ğºğ‘ƒ ! is the deseasonalized daily Henry Hub natural gas price, ğ‘† !,% is first-differenced solar generation for each balancing authority, ğ‘Š !,% is wind generation for each balancing authority, and ğ‘‹ ! is a set of time fixed effects which include day-of-week fixed effects and month-by-year fixed effects. In our first model, we also include a balancing-authority fixed effect, ğµğ´ % , to account for observed and unobserved differences in balancing authorities such as differences in infrastructure that may influence supply and demand. We estimate our model with Driscoll-Kraay standard errors to account for both heteroskedasticity and AR1 autocorrelation in the errors.</p><p>As past hourly prices have been shown to be an important explanatory variable for current prices 1 , and could influence futures and expected spot prices, in some specifications of the regression, we include a lagged risk premium variable (RP), as shown in model 2:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ğ‘…ğ‘ƒ !,#,$ = ğ›¼ &amp; + ğ›¼ ' ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! + ğ›½ ' ğ‘…ğ‘ƒ !0' + ğ›¼ ( ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! + ğ›¼ ) ğ· !,$ + ğ›¼ * ğºğ‘‰ ! + ğ›¼ + ğºğ‘ƒ ! + ğ›¼ , ğ‘† !,$ +ğ›¼ -ğ‘Š !,$ + ğ›¼ . ğ‘‹ ! + ğ›¼ / ğµğ´ $ + ğœ– (2)</formula><p>We acknowledge that including a lagged risk premium variable with our balancing-authority level fixed effects can induce dynamic panel bias but demonstrate the potential impact of that bias by providing the upper and lower bounds of reservoir storage impacts on risk premiums in models 1 and 3, respectively. The lower bound is provided by including the lagged risk premium variable but excluding the balancing authority level fixed effects as shown in model 3:</p><p>As reservoir levels may have differential price impacts on balancing authorities, we then assess the short-term impact of reservoir storage on risk premiums over space by using a Prais-Winsten regression in each balancing authority. 2 For this analysis, we assess the models in equation 1 and equation 3 separately for each balancing authority. In this specification of the model, we exclude balancing authority level fixed effects from these equations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Real-time price analysis</head><p>As an extension of our work, we examine how increasing hydropower reservoir storage affects price formation, including impacts on real-time prices and their distribution. To estimate the shortterm impacts of hydropower reservoir storage on real-time prices in the WEIM, our approach leverages our econometric framework formulated for the risk premium analysis but adds an important control needed for the more granular hourly data: hour fixed effects to control for hourly price variation within a day. Because of the time-dependent nature of electricity prices where past 1 See <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Nicholson et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Woo et al., 2016</ref>; and a survey of the literature in Tarufelli et al., 2022 for reference.</p><p>2 We use Prais-Winsten regressions to account for AR1 autocorrelation in the errors <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Prais and Winsten, 1954)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">ğ‘…ğ‘ƒ !,#,$ = ğ›¼ &amp; + ğ›¼ ' ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! + ğ›½ ' ğ‘…ğ‘ƒ !0' + ğ›¼ ( ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! + ğ›¼ ) ğ· !,$ + ğ›¼ * ğºğ‘‰ ! + ğ›¼ + ğºğ‘ƒ ! + ğ›¼ , ğ‘† !,$ +ğ›¼ -ğ‘Š !,$ + ğ›¼ . ğ‘‹ ! + ğœ– (3)</formula><p>realizations of prices can influence future prices, we also included a lagged real-time price variable in some specifications of our model.</p><p>The time-dependent nature of electricity market variables also raises the potential for nonstationarity in our real-time price analysis. We found that only natural gas volume was nonstationary, and deseasonalized that variable by removing the seasonal component 1 , including only the stochastic portion which can't be explained by seasonality as our identifying variation.</p><p>To account for the large number of hours with zero variable renewable generation, we used daily sums of sun and wind generation. We also made several adjustments to address outliers in the data.</p><p>Due to some high, outlying values during a January 2024 polar vortex in the Pacific Northwest, we log transformed gas prices. We also log transformed demand due to a few extreme outlier values. The dependent variable of real-time prices is also log transformed to enable consistency in interpretation with the risk premium analysis.</p><p>For our first real-time price model, we propose a fixed effects model to determine an upper bound of the short-term impact of reservoir energy storage on real-time price:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ğ¿ğ‘€ğ‘ƒ !,$ = ğ›¼ &amp; + ğ›¼ ' ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! + ğ›¼ ( ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! + ğ›¼ ) ğ· !,$ + ğ›¼ * ğºğ‘‰ ! + ğ›¼ + ğºğ‘ƒ ! + ğ›¼ , ğ‘† !,$ + ğ›¼ -ğ‘Š !,$ + ğ›¼ . ğ‘‹ ! + ğ›¼ / ğµğ´ $ + ğœ–<label>(4)</label></formula><p>ğ¿ğ‘€ğ‘ƒ !,% is the logged locational marginal price at time ğ‘¡ in balancing authority ğ‘–. ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! is the reservoir storage volume as a proportion of maximum reservoir storage capacity at time ğ‘¡ in Wells, Rocky Reach, Rock Island, Wanapum, and Priest Rapids dams, expressed as a percent of total capacity. ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! is the deviation from the daily historical average inflow, ğ· !,% is the logged electricity demand for each balancing authority, ğºğ‘‰ ! is the deseasonalized weekly gas volume, ğºğ‘ƒ ! is the logged daily Henry Hub natural gas price, ğ‘† !,% is daily solar generation for each balancing authority, ğ‘Š !,% is daily wind generation for each balancing authority, and ğ‘‹ ! is a set of time fixed effects which include hour fixed effects, day-of-week fixed effects and month-by-year fixed effects. In our first model, we also include a balancing-authority fixed effect, ğµğ´ % , to account for observed and unobserved differences in balancing authorities such as differences in infrastructure that may influence supply and demand. We estimate our model with Driscoll-Kraay standard errors to account for both heteroskedasticity and AR1 autocorrelation in the errors.</p><p>As past hourly prices have been shown to be an important explanatory variable for current prices<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">1</ref> , and could influence futures and expected spot prices, in some specifications of the regression, we include a lagged real-time locational marginal price variable (LMP) with the same log transformation as the dependent variable, as shown in real-time price model 2:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">ğ¿ğ‘€ğ‘ƒ !,$ = ğ›¼ &amp; + ğ›¼ ' ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! + ğ›½ ' ğ¿ğ‘€ğ‘ƒ !0' + ğ›¼ ( ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! + ğ›¼ ) ğ· !,$ + ğ›¼ * ğºğ‘‰ ! + ğ›¼ + ğºğ‘ƒ ! +ğ›¼ , ğ‘† !,$ + ğ›¼ -ğ‘Š !,$ + ğ›¼ . ğ‘‹ ! + ğ›¼ / ğµğ´ $ + ğœ– (5)</formula><p>We acknowledge that including a lagged real-time price variable with our balancing-authority level fixed effects can induce dynamic panel bias but mitigate the potential impact of that bias by providing the upper and lower bounds of reservoir storage impacts on real-time price in model 1 and model 3, respectively. The lower bound is provided by including the lagged real-time price variable but excluding the balancing authority level fixed effects as shown in real-time price model 3:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">ğ¿ğ‘€ğ‘ƒ !,$ = ğ›¼ &amp; + ğ›¼ ' ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! + ğ›½ ' ğ¿ğ‘€ğ‘ƒ !0' + ğ›¼ ( ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! + ğ›¼ ) ğ· !,$ + ğ›¼ * ğºğ‘‰ ! + ğ›¼ + ğºğ‘ƒ ! +ğ›¼ , ğ‘† !,$ + ğ›¼ -ğ‘Š !,$ + ğ›¼ . ğ‘‹ ! + ğœ– (6)</formula><p>Last, as we are also interested in the distributional impact of hydropower reservoir storage volume on real-time prices, we use a quantile regression framework to examine the impact of hydropower on the 50th (ğ‘„ &amp;'( !,% (0.5|ğœ” !,% ) and 95th (ğ‘„ &amp;'( !,% (0.95|ğœ” !,% ) percentiles of the realtime price distribution. This approach allows us to move beyond the mean effects captured by our previous regression analyses to assess how reservoir storage volume influences median and upper quantiles of the real-time price distribution.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">ğ‘„ 123 !,$ (ğœ|ğœ” !,$ ) = ğ›¼ &amp; (ğœ) + ğ›¼ ' (ğœ)ğ‘…ğ¸ğ‘†ğ¹ ! + ğ›½ ' (ğœ)ğ¿ğ‘€ğ‘ƒ !0' +ğ›¼ ( (ğœ)ğ¼ğ‘ğ¹ğ· ! + ğ›¼ ) (ğœ)ğ· !,$ + ğ›¼ * (ğœ)ğºğ‘‰ ! + ğ›¼ + (ğœ)ğºğ‘ƒ ! + ğ›¼ , (ğœ)ğ‘† !,$ + ğ›¼ -(ğœ)ğ‘Š !,$ + ğ›¼ . (ğœ)ğ‘‹ ! + ğ›¼ / (ğœ)ğµğ´ $ + ğœ– (7)</formula><p>To account for the non-standard distribution of the quantile regression estimator, we compute standard errors using bootstrapping, which provides consistent inference under heteroskedasticity and serial correlation within panels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Average Hydropower Reservoir Storage Impacts on Risk Premium</head><p>In our first analysis, we estimate how hydropower reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) impacts the daily average risk premium across all Northwestern balancing authorities in a pooled regression.</p><p>For model ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) we exclude our lagged risk premium variable but include the balancing authority level fixed effect. This establishes the upper bound of the hydropower reservoir storage impact on risk premiums as this model can tend to estimate coefficients that are too large <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Nickell, 1981)</ref>.</p><p>For model ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) we include both balancing authority-level fixed effects, time-fixed effects, and the lagged risk premium variable. With this model, we address time-variant and time-invariant observed and unobserved heterogeneity at the balancing authority-level by including both a lagged dependent variable and fixed effects. We acknowledge that this regression can be slightly biased but note that any bias should be small due to the large time dimension of our data <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Nickell, 1981)</ref>.</p><p>For model ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>) we include the lagged risk premium variable but exclude the balancing authoritylevel fixed effects (and include time fixed effects). With this model we establish the lower bound of the hydropower reservoir storage impact on risk premiums, as this model produces coefficient estimates that will tend to be the most conservative <ref type="bibr">(Anderson and</ref><ref type="bibr">Hsiao, 1981, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Keele &amp; Kelly, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Angrist and Pischke, 2009)</ref>.</p><p>We find that an increase in hydropower reservoir storage volume significantly reduces risk premiums across all balancing authorities. As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">4</ref>, Model 1, which includes balancing authority level fixed effects but does not include the lagged risk premium variable results in an upper-bound estimate for the impact of hydropower reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) on risk premium. The impact is significant and negative, with a coefficient of -0.66, meaning that increasing hydropower reservoir storage volume by 10% of its total storable value results in an estimated decrease in risk premium by approximately 7%. Model 2, which includes both a balancing authority level fixed effect and a lagged risk premium variable results in a negative and statistically significant coefficient of -0.462, indicating a 5% decrease in risk premium for a 10% increase in hydropower reservoir storage. Model 3, which excludes the balancing authority level fixed effect but includes a lagged risk premium variable establish the lower bound estimate of on coefficient at -0.459, meaning that an increase in reservoir storage volume of 10% decreases risk premiums by about 5%. Deviation from average inflow is positively correlated with risk premium, consistent with the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al (2010)</ref>. Wind generation has a small but significantly negative impact on risk premium. Other control variables have positive but statistically insignificant impacts on risk premium. impacts of hydropower reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage volume) across all Balancing Authorities. Model (1) includes the full set of time fixed effects (day of week, month by year), and BA-level fixed effects. Model (2) includes a lagged risk premium variable, the full set of time fixed effects and BA-level fixed effects. Model (3) includes the lagged risk premium variable and the full set of time fixed effects. Standard errors reported in columns (1) -( <ref type="formula">3</ref>) have been transformed to remove AR(1) serial correlation and heteroskedasticity. Standard errors are in parentheses. * p &lt; 0.10, ** p &lt; 0.05, *** p &lt; 0.01.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Balancing authority-level impacts of energy storage on risk premiums</head><p>We then consider the effect of hydropower reservoir storage over space, by examining the impact of reservoir storage volume on each individual Balancing Authority's risk premium. For most balancing authorities, reservoir storage volume had a negative and statistically significant impact on day-ahead risk premium. This is consistent with the findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al. (2010)</ref>, who found a negative impact of reservoir storage volume on risk premium in the NordPool market. The impact was statistically significant at the 10% level in 8 out of 11 balancing authorities. The smallest impact of reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) on risk premium was seen in Nevada Power, which participates in the Northwest through the Pacific Northwest -Southwest Intertie but is geographically remote from the dam system. The coefficient of -0.24 indicates that a increase in reservoir storage volume results in approximately a 2% decrease in risk premium. The greatest impact of reservoir storage volume on risk premium was seen in Portland General Electric. The coefficient of -0.84 indicates that a 10% increase in reservoir storage volume results in approximately an 8% decrease in risk premium. Notes: This table reports impacts of reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) for each Balancing Authority. Model (1) includes the full set of time fixed effects (day of week, month by year). Model (2) includes a lagged risk premium variable and the full set of time fixed effects. Standard errors reported in columns (1) -( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) have been transformed to remove AR(1) serial correlation and heteroskedasticity. Standard errors are in parentheses. * p &lt; 0.10, ** p &lt; 0.05, *** p &lt; 0.01.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Robustness of risk premium results</head><p>Although our pooled and individual balancing authority level results indicate that increases in hydropower reservoir storage volumes decrease risk premiums, a key endogeneity concern arises due to the geographic location of the dams. The Grand Coulee Dam is located upstream from the mid-Columbia dams. Its power is marketed by Bonneville Power Administration, which is a participant in the WEIM considered for this analysis. If the Grand Coulee Dam operators are changing hydropower reservoir storage volumes in response to market conditions, their actions may impact downstream reservoir levels through changing their inflow, resulting in potential endogeneity between risk premium and mid-Columbia inflow variable. To account for this potential endogeneity, we respecified our econometric models (1 through 3) to include a variable representing deviation from average inflow into Grand Coulee, instead of deviation from average inflow into the mid-Columbia reservoirs characterized in the previous section. Inflow to Grand Coulee is plausibly exogenous, as inflow is primarily determined by upstream hydrological conditions (such as snowpack, precipitation, runoff) and upstream dams (in both Canada and the U.S.) have regulated releases under pre-established operational rules (such as the Columbia River Treaty), indicating that upstream water release decisions are not in response to short-term electricity market prices in the WEIM. Like the variable for inflow deviation into mid-Columbia reservoirs, this variable was specified as the deviation from mean inflow between November 2003 and November 2024 for any given date. Data were also obtained from the Columbia Basin Water Management Division of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers.</p><p>With the Grand Coulee inflow variable, we find similar results, although coefficients are smaller in magnitude and estimates have more noise. In Model 1, the estimated coefficient for hydropower reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum capacity) remains negative with a 10% increase in reservoir storage volume reducing risk premium between 4-5%. Models 2 and 3 have a negative, though statistically insignificant coefficient. Overall, the similarity of results to our main specification provides assurance that upstream Grand Coulee dam operations are not significantly affecting downstream reservoir storage volume impacts on risk premiums. We also respecify the regressions for each individual Balancing Authority as Prais-Winsten regressions to analyze the impact of hydropower reservoir storage volume on risk premium with the average inflow into Grand Coulee variable, instead of deviation from average inflow into the mid-Columbia reservoirs. Results of these regressions are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">7</ref>. Similar to the pooled regressions, we find that regression results are slightly smaller in magnitude with more noise but support the conclusion that the impact of reservoir storage volume on risk premium is robust to this particular endogeneity concern of upstream dam operator actions influencing downstream inflow (and reservoir) levels. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Average Hydropower Reservoir Storage Impacts on Real-Time Prices</head><p>We then estimate how hydropower reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) impacts the real-time price across all Northwestern balancing authorities in a pooled regression.</p><p>For real-time price model (1) (Eq. 4) we exclude our lagged real-time price variable but include the balancing authority level fixed effect, this establishes the upper bound of the hydropower reservoir storage impact on real-time prices as this model can tend to estimate coefficients that are too large. For real-time price model (2) (Eq. 5) we include both balancing authority-level fixed effects, time-fixed effects, and the lagged real-time price variable. With this model, we address time-variant and time-invariant observed and unobserved heterogeneity at the balancing authoritylevel by including both a lagged dependent variable and fixed effects. We acknowledge that this regression can be slightly biased but note that any bias should be small due to the large time dimension of our data. For real-time price model (3) (Eq. 6) we include the lagged real-time price variable but exclude the balancing authority-level fixed effects (and include time fixed effects).</p><p>With this model we establish the lower bound of the hydropower reservoir storage impact on realtime price, as this model produces coefficient estimates that will tend to be the most conservative.</p><p>We find that an increase in hydropower reservoir storage volume also significantly reduces real-  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Average Hydropower Reservoir Storage Impacts on Distribution of Real-Time Prices</head><p>With our previous real-time price regressions, we examined the average effect of reservoir storage volume on real-time prices. As the impact of reservoir storage volume may impact price differently across the distribution of prices, our next analysis utilizes a quantile regression approach to assess the impact of reservoir storage volumes on median (50th) percentile of the realtime price distribution and the 95th percentile of the real-time price distribution.</p><p>As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">9</ref>, a 10% increase in reservoir storage volume decreases risk premiums by approximately 5% at the median of the distribution. This result is in line with our previous realtime price regression results which estimate the conditional mean, indicating that our previous regression results are not being driven by skewness or outliers. However, we do find that a 10% increase in reservoir storage volume at the 95 th percentile is more impactful, decreasing risk premiums by approximately 6%. This result indicates that reservoir storage may be more valuable during grid stress events. Also worth noting is that increases in gas prices are more impactful at the upper end of the real-time price distribution and lagged real-time prices (previous realizations of real time prices) are less impactful. All other signs on coefficients are in line with expectations from the literature. Notes: This table reports impacts of reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) using a quantile regression approach Model (1) estimates the 50th percentile of the real-time price distribution and Model (2) estimates the 95th percentile of the real-time price distribution. To account for the non-standard distribution of the quantile regression estimator, standard errors are computed using bootstrapping to provide consistent inference under heteroskedasticity and serial correlation within panels. Standard errors are in parentheses. * p &lt; 0.10, ** p &lt; 0.05, *** p &lt; 0.01.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>We find that, on average, a 10% increase in hydropower reservoir storage volumes reduces risk premiums by 5%. Our regressions are robust to inclusion of a lagged risk premium variable to account for the potential that previous market outcomes can influence both risk perceptions and price expectations, as well as robust to specifications controlling for inflow to Grand Coulee. Our results are consistent with <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Botterud et al (2010)</ref>, who examined the relationship between reservoir level and risk premium in Nord Pool between 1996 and 2006. Intuitively, our findings indicate that higher reservoir storage volumes lower the compensation required by power purchasers for holding electricity futures contracts. In short, storage reduces market participants' risk. We posit that reservoir storage serves as a mechanism for managing short-term imbalances of supply and demand in electricity markets, leading to that reduced risk. As an extension, we then consider the impact of reservoir storage on real-time prices and the distribution of real time prices. We find similar results, a 10% increase in reservoir storage reduces real-time price by 5% on average. At the upper-end of the real-time price distribution-reflecting grid stress events-a 10% increase in reservoir storage is even more impactful, reducing real-time prices by 6%. In future work, we will continue to examine the value of hydropower reservoir storage through assessing the impact of reservoir storage during meteorologically driven grid stress events as well as examine the impact of reservoir storage on other price dynamics such as price spikes and volatility.</p><p>Our current findings provide evidence that hydropower reservoir storage has an important risk reducing effect on electricity markets, pointing to the value of stored energy. While most electricity markets do not currently provide a compensation mechanism for stored energy, new compensation models are emerging, such as the winter reserve mechanism in Switzerland, which contracts and pays hydro operators in Switzerland to hold back water in reservoirs-rather than generating electricity in early winter-so that withheld energy can be dispatched during supply shortages.</p><p>The need for new business and compensation models, as well as what those models may value remains an important area of research for hydropower and other energy storage resources.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIGURE 1: WESTERN ENERGY IMBALANCE MARKET. SOURCE: CALIFORNIA ISO</figDesc><graphic coords="6,53.40,360.03,219.30,313.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. This sequence of dams, which begins at Wells dam, is uninterrupted by other dams. These dams are owned and operated by local public utility districts (Douglas PUD, Chelan County PUD, and Grand County PUD).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIGURE 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIGURE 2: COLUMBIA RIVER BASIN DAMS SOURCE: U.S. ARMY CORPS OF ENGINEERS</figDesc><graphic coords="7,321.90,425.98,247.35,270.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURE 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>FIGURE 3: RISK PREMIUM -BONNEVILLE POWER AUTHORITY</figDesc><graphic coords="10,90.35,464.19,431.27,213.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1,2 Figure 4 depicts the reservoir level as a percent of maximum capacity over the period of study. The graph shows substantial short-term variation in hydropower reservoir levels. Reservoir storage volume as a proportion of maximum reservoir storage capacity typically fluctuates between 0.6 and 0.8, with occasional outlying values above 0.8 or below 0.6.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>FIGURE 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>FIGURE 5: SEASONAL PATTERN OF RESERVOIR STORAGE VOLUME AS A PROPORTION OF MAXIMUM RESERVOIR STORAGE CAPACITY (RESERVOIR FRACTION) FOR THE MID-COLUMBIA DAM SYSTEM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>FIGURE 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>FIGURE 4: RESERVOIR STORAGE VOLUME AS A PROPORTION OF MAXIMUM RESERVOIR STORAGE CAPACITY (RESERVOIR FRACTION) FOR THE MID-COLUMBIA DAM SYSTEM</figDesc><graphic coords="13,102.05,355.30,417.50,219.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>SUMMARY STATISTICS: RISK PREMIUMS BY BALANCINGAUTHORITY (5/2022 TO 11/2024)    </figDesc><table><row><cell>Balancing</cell><cell>Sample</cell><cell>Percent</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>Standard</cell><cell>Skewness</cell><cell>Median</cell><cell cols="2">Maximum Minimum</cell></row><row><cell>Authority</cell><cell>Size</cell><cell>Positive</cell><cell></cell><cell>Deviation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>BPAT</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>6.70</cell><cell>-0.39</cell><cell>0.36</cell><cell>-1.31</cell><cell>-0.33</cell><cell>0.54</cell><cell>-2.10</cell></row><row><cell>AVA</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>8.15</cell><cell>-0.41</cell><cell>0.40</cell><cell>-1.85</cell><cell>-0.36</cell><cell>0.85</cell><cell>-3.40</cell></row><row><cell>IPCO</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>7.61</cell><cell>-0.40</cell><cell>0.37</cell><cell>-1.24</cell><cell>-0.35</cell><cell>0.94</cell><cell>-2.55</cell></row><row><cell>NEVP</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>11.23</cell><cell>-0.43</cell><cell>0.49</cell><cell>-2.16</cell><cell>-0.40</cell><cell>1.20</cell><cell>-4.76</cell></row><row><cell>NWMT</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>6.88</cell><cell>-0.41</cell><cell>0.36</cell><cell>-1.18</cell><cell>-0.37</cell><cell>0.80</cell><cell>-2.51</cell></row><row><cell>PACE</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>6.16</cell><cell>-0.47</cell><cell>0.41</cell><cell>-1.32</cell><cell>-0.44</cell><cell>0.76</cell><cell>-2.78</cell></row><row><cell>PACW</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>5.98</cell><cell>-0.43</cell><cell>0.39</cell><cell>-1.70</cell><cell>-0.36</cell><cell>0.54</cell><cell>-2.46</cell></row><row><cell>PGE</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>6.70</cell><cell>-0.41</cell><cell>0.38</cell><cell>-1.34</cell><cell>-0.35</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>-2.47</cell></row><row><cell>PSEI</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>7.97</cell><cell>-0.40</cell><cell>0.38</cell><cell>-0.90</cell><cell>-0.34</cell><cell>1.06</cell><cell>-2.33</cell></row><row><cell>SCL</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>6.52</cell><cell>-0.42</cell><cell>0.38</cell><cell>-1.43</cell><cell>-0.36</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>-2.49</cell></row><row><cell>TPWR</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>6.16</cell><cell>-0.42</cell><cell>0.37</cell><cell>-1.32</cell><cell>-0.36</cell><cell>0.58</cell><cell>-2.47</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p>shows usable storage volumes for mid-Columbia dams, as reported by Chelan PUD, and total storage volumes as reported by various state and local agencies.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>USABLE STORAGE VOLUMES FOR MID-COLUMBIA DAMS</figDesc><table><row><cell>Dam</cell><cell>Usable storage</cell><cell>Total storage (thousands of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(thousands of acre feet)</cell><cell>acre feet)</cell></row><row><cell>Wells</cell><cell>98</cell><cell>331 (Douglas PUD, 2006)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="7">shows statistics on inflow to mid-Columbia dams with values reported in thousands of</cell></row><row><cell>acre feet. 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">TABLE 3: SUMMARY STATISTICS ON INFLOW TO MID-COLUMBIA DAMS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Dam</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell cols="2">Skewness Standard</cell><cell>Median</cell><cell cols="2">Maximum Minimum</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Deviation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Priest</cell><cell>92.35</cell><cell>2.08</cell><cell>40.25</cell><cell>85.30</cell><cell>263.10</cell><cell>32.60</cell></row><row><cell>Rapids</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rock</cell><cell>88.49</cell><cell>1.82</cell><cell>37.39</cell><cell>83.79</cell><cell>242.21</cell><cell>35.38</cell></row><row><cell>Island</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rocky</cell><cell>86.05</cell><cell>1.67</cell><cell>35.01</cell><cell>82.71</cell><cell>231.63</cell><cell>34.20</cell></row><row><cell>Reach</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Wanapum</cell><cell>93.55</cell><cell>1.66</cell><cell>39.74</cell><cell>88.30</cell><cell>254.30</cell><cell>-16.00</cell></row><row><cell>Wells</cell><cell>87.47</cell><cell>1.67</cell><cell>35.31</cell><cell>82.50</cell><cell>223.70</cell><cell>37.00</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>TABLE 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>POOLED IMPACT OF HYDROPOWER RESERVOIR STORAGE VOLUME ON RISK PREMIUM ACROSS BALANCING AUTHORITIES</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Model (1)</cell><cell>Model (2)</cell><cell>Model (3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BA-level Fixed</cell><cell>Fixed Effects &amp;</cell><cell>Lagged Risk Premium</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Effects</cell><cell>Lagged Risk Premium</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hydropower Reservoir</cell><cell>-0.6608 (0.2679) **</cell><cell>-0.4622 (0.2313) **</cell><cell>-0.4589 (0.2217) **</cell></row><row><cell>Storage Volume (as a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>proportion of maximum</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>capacity)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Inflow Deviation (cubic</cell><cell>0.0005 (0.0002) **</cell><cell>0.0003 (0.0002) **</cell><cell>0.0003 (0.0002) **</cell></row><row><cell>feet per second * 1000)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Demand (MWh)</cell><cell>0.0004 (0.0020)</cell><cell>0.0004 (0.0018)</cell><cell>0.0004 (0.0020)</cell></row><row><cell>Gas Volume (billions of</cell><cell>0.0008 (0.0009)</cell><cell>0.0003 (0.0007)</cell><cell>0.0003 (0.0007)</cell></row><row><cell>cubic feet)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gas Price ($ / million</cell><cell>0.0041 (0.0169)</cell><cell>0.0036 (0.0133)</cell><cell>0.0040 (0.0132)</cell></row><row><cell>btu)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Daily Solar Generation</cell><cell>0.0013 (0.0045)</cell><cell>0.0033 (0.0048)</cell><cell>0.0034 (0.0048)</cell></row><row><cell>(MWh)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Daily Wind Generation</cell><cell>-0.0030 (0.0008) ***</cell><cell>-0.0023 (0.0008) ***</cell><cell>-0.0014 (0.0004) ***</cell></row><row><cell>(MWh)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lagged Risk Premium</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.2751 (0.0423) ***</cell><cell>0.2781 (0.0419) ***</cell></row><row><cell>Balancing Authority</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>N</cell></row><row><cell>Fixed Effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Time Fixed Effects</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Constant</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.2580 (0.2217)</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>552</cell><cell>6072</cell></row><row><cell>R-squared</cell><cell>0.266</cell><cell>0.320</cell><cell>0.321</cell></row><row><cell>Notes: This table reports</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>TABLE 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>IMPACT OF RESERVOIR STORAGE VOLUME ON RISK PREMIUM BY BALANCING AUTHORITY</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Model 2: Prais-Winsten with Lagged</cell></row><row><cell>Balancing Authority</cell><cell>Model 1: Prais-Winsten</cell><cell>Risk Premium</cell></row><row><cell>AVA</cell><cell>-0.76 (0.288) ***</cell><cell>-0.69 (0.265) ***</cell></row><row><cell>BPAT</cell><cell>-0.62 (0.250) **</cell><cell>-0.61 (0.245) **</cell></row><row><cell>IPCO</cell><cell>-0.44 (0.302)</cell><cell>-0.43 (0.281)</cell></row><row><cell>NEVP</cell><cell>-0.24 (0.410)</cell><cell>-0.27 (0.372)</cell></row><row><cell>NWMT</cell><cell>-0.55 (0.267) **</cell><cell>-0.55 (0.245) **</cell></row><row><cell>PACE</cell><cell>-0.33 (0.318)</cell><cell>-0.34 (0.285)</cell></row><row><cell>PACW</cell><cell>-0.74 (0.293) **</cell><cell>-0.71 (0.276) **</cell></row><row><cell>PGE</cell><cell>-0.84 (0.292) ***</cell><cell>-0.77 (0.271) ***</cell></row><row><cell>PSEI</cell><cell>-0.48 (0.283) *</cell><cell>-0.49 (0.277) *</cell></row><row><cell>SCL</cell><cell>-0.57 (0.272) **</cell><cell>-0.54 (0.258) **</cell></row><row><cell>TPWR</cell><cell>-0.65 (0.265) **</cell><cell>-0.62 (0.250) **</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>TABLE 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>POOLED IMPACT OF RESERVOIR STORAGE VOLUME ON RISK PREMIUM ACROSS BALANCING AUTHORITIES WITH GRAND COULEE INFLOW</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Model (2)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model (1)</cell><cell>Fixed Effects &amp; Lagged</cell><cell>Model (3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BA-level Fixed Effects</cell><cell>Risk Premium</cell><cell>Lagged Risk Premium</cell></row><row><cell>Hydropower Reservoir</cell><cell>-0.5175 (0.2619) **</cell><cell>-0.3626 (0.2222)</cell><cell>-0.3580 (0.2224)</cell></row><row><cell>Storage Volume (as a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>proportion of Maximum</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Storage Capacity)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>TABLE 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>IMPACT OF RESERVOIR STORAGE VOLUME ON RISK PREMIUM FOR INDIVIDUAL BALANCING AUTHORITIES WITH GRAND COULEE INFLOW This table reports impacts of reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) for each individual Balancing Authority. Model (1) includes the full set of time fixed effects (day of week, month by year). Model (2) includes a lagged risk premium variable and the full set of time fixed effects. Standard errors reported in columns (1) -(2) have been transformed to remove AR(1) serial correlation and heteroskedasticity. Standard errors are in parentheses.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Model 2: Prais-Winsten with</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model 1: Prais-Winsten,</cell><cell>Lagged Risk Premium, Grand</cell></row><row><cell>Balancing Authority</cell><cell>Grand Coulee Inflow</cell><cell>Coulee Inflow</cell></row><row><cell>AVA</cell><cell>-0.61 (0.273) **</cell><cell>-0.59 (0.248) **</cell></row><row><cell>BPAT</cell><cell>-0.54 (0.237) **</cell><cell>-0.53 (0.228) **</cell></row><row><cell>IPCO</cell><cell>-0.25 (0.292)</cell><cell>0.25 (0.267)</cell></row><row><cell>NEVP</cell><cell>-0.18 (0.422)</cell><cell>-0.20 (0.386)</cell></row><row><cell>NWMT</cell><cell>-0.39 (0.254)</cell><cell>-0.39 (0.228) *</cell></row><row><cell>PACE</cell><cell>-0.22 (0.323)</cell><cell>-0.22 (0.282)</cell></row><row><cell>PACW</cell><cell>-0.63 (0.278) **</cell><cell>-0.62 (0.264) **</cell></row><row><cell>PGE</cell><cell>-0.67 (0.281) ***</cell><cell>-0.61 (0.257) **</cell></row><row><cell>PSEI</cell><cell>-0.40 (0.272)</cell><cell>-0.41 (0.264)</cell></row><row><cell>SCL</cell><cell>-0.46 (0.266) *</cell><cell>-0.44 (0.248) *</cell></row><row><cell>TPWR</cell><cell>-0.53 (0.259) **</cell><cell>-0.50 (0.242) **</cell></row><row><cell>Notes:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>* p &lt; 0.10, ** p &lt; 0.05, *** p &lt; 0.01.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>time prices. Real-time price model 1, which includes balancing authority level fixed effects but does not include the lagged real-time price variable, results in an upper-bound estimate for the impact of hydropower reservoir storage volume on real-time prices. The impact is significant and negative, with a coefficient of -1.5265, meaning that increasing hydropower reservoir storage volume by 10% of its total storable value results in an estimated decrease in real-time price by approximately 15%). Real-time price model 2, which includes both a balancing authority level fixed effect and a lagged real-time price variable results in a negative and statistically significant coefficient of -0.515, indicating a 10% increase in hydropower reservoir storage decreases realtime price by approximately 5.2%. Real-time price model 3, which excludes the balancing</figDesc><table /><note><p>authority level fixed effect but includes a lagged real-time price variable establish the lower bound estimate of on coefficient at -0.503, meaning that an increase in reservoir storage volume of 10% decreases real-time prices by about 5%. Results for other controls are consistent with their theoretical impacts. Increased wind and solar generation reduce real-time price. Increases in demand increase real-time price. Increases in natural gas volume reduce real-time price, and increases in natural gas prices increase real-time electricity prices. Inflow deviation has a positive correlation with real-time price in real-time price models 2 and 3, and an insignificant result in real-time price model 1.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>TABLE 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>POOLED IMPACT OF HYDROPOWER RESERVOIR STORAGE VOLUME ON REAL-TIME PRICES ACROSS BALANCING AUTHORITIES</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Model (2)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Fixed Effects &amp;</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Model (1)</cell><cell>Lagged Real-time</cell><cell>Model (3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BA-level Fixed Effects</cell><cell>Price</cell><cell>Lagged Real-time Price</cell></row><row><cell>Hydropower Reservoir</cell><cell cols="2">-1.5265 (0.1456) *** -0.5148 (0.0523) ***</cell><cell>-0.5033 (0.0523) ***</cell></row><row><cell>Storage Volume (as a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>proportion of Maximum</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Storage Capacity)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Inflow Deviation (cubic</cell><cell>0.00001 (0.0002)</cell><cell>0.00004 (0.00004)</cell><cell>0.00008 (0.00005) *</cell></row><row><cell>feet per second * 1000)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Log Demand (MWh)</cell><cell cols="2">1.2251 (0.0470) *** -0.2740 (0.0218) ***</cell><cell>0.0094 (0.0014) ***</cell></row><row><cell>Gas Volume (billions of</cell><cell>-0.0016 (-0.0006) ***</cell><cell>-0.0004 (0.0002) **</cell><cell>0.0005 (0.0002) ***</cell></row><row><cell>cubic feet)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>Notes: This table reports impacts of reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) across all Balancing Authorities. Model (1) includes the full set of time fixed effects (day of week, month by year), and BA-level fixed effects. Model (2) includes a lagged real-time price variable, the full set of time fixed effects and BA-level fixed effects. Model (3) includes the lagged real-time price variable and the full set of time fixed effects. Standard errors reported in columns (1) -(</p>3</p>) have been transformed to remove AR(1) serial correlation and heteroskedasticity. Standard errors are in parentheses. * p &lt; 0.10, ** p &lt; 0.05, *** p &lt; 0.01.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>TABLE 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>QUANTILE REGRESSION OF THE REAL-TIME PRICE DISTRIBUTION</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>50th Percentile</cell><cell>95th Percentile</cell></row><row><cell>Hydropower Reservoir</cell><cell>-0.5176 (0.0074)***</cell><cell>-0.6174 (0.0392)***</cell></row><row><cell>Storage Volume (as a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>proportion of Maximum</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Storage Capacity)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Inflow Deviation (cubic</cell><cell>0.00005 (0.00002) ***</cell><cell>0.0005 (0.00005)***</cell></row><row><cell>feet per second * 1000)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Log Demand (MWh)</cell><cell>0.2864 (.0096) ***</cell><cell>0.6837 (0.0219)***</cell></row><row><cell>Gas Volume (billions of</cell><cell>-0.0005 (.00007)***</cell><cell>-0.0021 (0.0002)***</cell></row><row><cell>cubic feet)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Log Gas Price ($ / million</cell><cell>0.3224 (.0098)***</cell><cell>0.9617 (0.0247)***</cell></row><row><cell>btu)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Daily Solar Generation</cell><cell cols="2">-0.00000196 (0.0000002)*** -0.00000308</cell></row><row><cell>(MWh)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.0000004)***</cell></row><row><cell>Daily Wind Generation</cell><cell>-0.00000152</cell><cell>-0.00000147</cell></row><row><cell>(MWh)</cell><cell>(0.00000004)***</cell><cell>(0.00000008)***</cell></row><row><cell>Log Lagged Real-time</cell><cell>0.6812 (0.0074)***</cell><cell>0.0577 (0.0193)***</cell></row><row><cell>Price</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Balancing Authority</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Fixed Effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Time Fixed Effects</cell><cell>Y</cell><cell>Y</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>226,796</cell><cell>226,796</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>With a lagged dependent variable, the coefficients for other explanatory variables may be biased downward due to residual autocorrelation as well as absorbing the explanatory power of other variables.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_1"><p>For Wells Dam volume, several dates (09/20/2022, 12/20/2022, 02/21/2023 and 02/28/2024) appeared to have missing data as a negative volume of -7093.2 was reported for these dates. These dates were dropped from the analysis.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Reservoir storage volume (as a proportion of maximum storage capacity) is derived from a reservoir storage variable available from the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers as usable storable volume, rather than a representation of total reservoir volume.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_3"><p>To deseasonalize the natural gas price and natural gas volume variables, we regressed gas price and gas volume on month and year controls and retained the residuals as the transformed values.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_4"><p>See Nicholson et al.,  </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_5"><p>2010;<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Woo et al., 2016</ref>; and a survey of the literature inTarufelli et al., 2022 for reference.   </p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of Dynamic Models with Error Components</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Theodore</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cheng</forename><surname>Hsiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">375</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="598" to="606" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Formulation and Estimation of Dynamic Models Using Panel Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Theodore</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cheng</forename><surname>Hsiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Equilibrium pricing and optimal hedging in electricity forward markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hendrik</forename><surname>Bessembinder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lemmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1347" to="1382" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Storage futures study: Key learnings for the coming decades</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nate</forename><surname>Blair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chad</forename><surname>Augustine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wesley</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Denholm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Will</forename><surname>Frazier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Madeline</forename><surname>Geocaris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jennie</forename><surname>Jorgenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>No. NREL/TP-7A40-81779</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">National Renewable Energy Lab.(NREL)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">2022</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Golden, CO (United States</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between spot and futures prices in the Nord Pool electricity market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Audun</forename><surname>Botterud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tarjei</forename><surname>Kristiansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marija</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ilic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="967" to="978" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The supply of storage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A guide to Chelan PUD&apos;s program for managing the lands and shorelines within the Rock Island Hydroelectric Project Boundary</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">California Independent System Operator.</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.chelanpud.org/docs/default-source/licensing-and-complience/51200-rocky-reach-reservoir-flow-and-storage-characteristics.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Chelan Public Utility District. Mid-Columbia system projects</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Chelan Public Utility District &amp; Kleinschmidt Associates</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2024. 2024, October 18. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Western Energy Imbalance Market surpasses the $6 billion benefit milestone</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk premiums on inventory assets: the case of crude oil and natural gas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Considine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Donald</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Futures Markets: Futures, Options, and Other Derivative Products</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://relicensing.douglaspud.org/documents/pud_relicensing_documents/downloads/PAD/PADVolume1.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Douglas County PUD. Wells Hydroelectric Project: FERC Project No. 2149 Pre-Application Document</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Douglas County PUD</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2024, November 26. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Home -Douglas County PUD</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Storage and the electricity forward premium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Popova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.eneco.2007.12.013</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eneco.2007.12.013" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1712" to="1727" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Commodity Futures Prices: Some Evidence on Forecast Power Premiums and the Theory of Storage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eugene</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Fama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kenneth</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>French</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Forward curves, scarcity and price volatility in oil and natural gas markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">HÃ©lyette</forename><surname>Geman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Steve</forename><surname>Ohana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="576" to="585" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grant PUD: Generation</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.grantpud.org/generation" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Grant PUD</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interest rates and the volatility and correlation of commodity prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gruber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vigfusson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Macroeconomic Dynamics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="600" to="619" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.chelanpud.org/home" />
		<title level="m">Chelan PUD</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Options futures and other derivatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hull</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Pearson Education India</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supply, demand, and risk premiums in electricity markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pirrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbankfin.2021.106390Kaldor</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbankfin.2021.106390Kaldor" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="1939">2022. 106390. 1939</date>
			<pubPlace>Nicholas</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Banking &amp; Finance</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic Models for Dynamic Theories: The Ins and Outs of Lagged Dependent Variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luke</forename><surname>Keele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nathan</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/pan/mpj006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/pan/mpj006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.co.kittitas.wa.us/uploads/documents/cds/smp/reports/Chapter%206.%20Columbia%20River.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Kittitas County. Kittitas County Shoreline Inventory and Characterization Report</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of factors influencing the Henry Hub natural gas price based on factor analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-T</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cursio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12182-017-0192-z</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2018.10.124" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Petroleum Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="494" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Applied Energy</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Value of Energy Storage in a High Storage Future: A Simulation Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tarufelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ramachandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Somani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Boff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Richland, WA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>United States), forthcoming</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between wind generation and balancing energy market prices in ERCOT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nicholson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>No. NREL/SR-5500-49415</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">National Renewable Energy Lab (NREL)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007-2009. 2010</date>
			<pubPlace>Golden, CO (United States</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biases in dynamic models with fixed effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><surname>Nickell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica: Journal of the econometric society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1417" to="1426" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.nwd.usace.army.mil/crwm/cr-dams/" />
		<title level="m">Grand Coulee Dam</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Columbia River Basin Dams</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Army Corps of Engineers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023-08-07">2023. August 7</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inventories and the Short-Run Dynamics of Commodity Prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pindyck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RAND Journal of Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dynamics of commodity spot and futures markets: a primer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pindyck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Energy Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volatility and commodity price dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pindyck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Futures Markets: Futures, Options, and Other Derivative Products</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1029" to="1047" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volatility in natural gas and oil markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pindyck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Energy &amp; Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cowles Commission Discussion Paper: Statistics No</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Prais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Winsten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.nws.usace.army.mil/Missions/Civil-Works/Locks-and-Dams/Chief-Joseph-Dam/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">S&amp;P Global. Methodology and Specifications Guide: US and Canada M2M Power Quantitatively Modeled Forward Curves</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Army Corps of Engineers. Chief Joseph Dam</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1954">1954. 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Trend Estimators and Serial Correlation. pdf Seattle District</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the value of electricity storage in PJM: Arbitrage and some welfare effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ramteen</forename><surname>Sioshansi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Denholm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Jenkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jurgen</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Energy storage enhancements discussion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Caiso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.caiso.com/documents/energystorageenhancements-presentation-sep26_2022.pdf#page=2.00" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-09-26">September 26, 2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2025" to="2029" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Price Formation and Grid Operation Impacts from Variable Renewable Energy Resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tarufelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ganguli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Boff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Somani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2172/1993624</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2172/1993624" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-04">April. 2022. 1993624. 1993624</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">33470</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">No. PNNL--33470</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Columbia River Basin Water Management</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.nwd.usace.army.mil/crwm/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<publisher>U.S. Army Corps of Engineers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Electricity explained: Factors affecting electricity prices</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.eia.gov/energyexplained/electricity/prices-and-factors-affecting-prices.php" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<publisher>U.S. Department of Energy</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Henry Hub Natural Gas Spot Price</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.eia.gov/dnav/ng/hist/rngwhhdm.htm" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<publisher>U.S. Department of Energy</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Natural Gas Weekly Update</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.eia.gov/naturalgas/weekly/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<publisher>U.S. Department of Energy</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.eia.gov/opendata/" />
		<title level="m">Open Data. U.S. Department of Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Energy Information Administration</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<idno>#94-016</idno>
		<ptr target="https://apps.ecology.wa.gov/publications/documents/94016.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Washington State Department of Ecology. Inventory of dams report for selected Washington counties and selected dam hazard categories</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Energy Information Administration</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024. 2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Wholesale Electricity and Natural Gas Market Data. U.S. Department of Energy. Revised Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting the relationship between spot and futures prices in the Nord Pool electricity market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">RafaÅ‚</forename><surname>Weron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">MichaÅ‚</forename><surname>Zator</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Merit-order effects of renewable energy and price divergence in California&apos;s day-ahead and real-time electricity markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Alagappan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chawla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Toyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zarnikau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.enpol.2016.02.023</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enpol.2016.02.023" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Price relations between July and September wheat futures at Chicago since 1885</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Holbrook</forename><surname>Working</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wheat Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="1933">1933</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory of the inverse carrying charge in futures markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Holbrook</forename><surname>Working</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Farm Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1948">1948</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The theory of price of storage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Working</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1254" to="1262" />
			<date type="published" when="1949">1949</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implications of Electricity and Gas Price Coupling in US New England Region</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">iScience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
