<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Bitcoin Adoption Strategy as a Company Asset in Indonesia</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Asian Institute of Research</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Asian Institute of Research</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-09-30">2024-09-30</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Iman</forename><forename type="middle">Patria</forename><surname>Yudha</surname></persName>
							<email>iman_yudha@sbm.itb.ac.id</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">School of Business and Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institut Teknologi Bandung</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Raden</forename><forename type="middle">Aswin</forename><surname>Rahadi</surname></persName>
							<email>aswin.rahadi@sbm-itb.ac.id</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">School of Business and Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institut Teknologi Bandung</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ana</forename><surname>Noveria</surname></persName>
							<email>ana.noveria@sbm-itb.ac.id</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">School of Business and Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institut Teknologi Bandung</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Bitcoin Adoption Strategy as a Company Asset in Indonesia</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Journal of Economics and Business</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">jeb</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">2775-9237</idno>
						<idno type="eISSN">2615-3726</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Asian Institute of Research</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
							<date type="published" when="2024-09-30" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FC2F7CD29E9BBDFD7C60575C246544DB</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.31014/aior.1992.07.03.592</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Bitcoin</term>
					<term>Corporate Asset</term>
					<term>Inflation Hedge</term>
					<term>Shareholder Value</term>
					<term>Risk Mitigation</term>
					<term>Stakeholder Acceptance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This research investigates the strategic adoption of Bitcoin as a corporate asset in Indonesia, focusing on its potential as an inflation hedge and its impact on enhancing shareholder value. Employing a mixed-method approach combining qualitative interviews and the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP), the study explores the challenges, risks, and opportunities associated with integrating Bitcoin into corporate financial strategies. The findings reveal that risk mitigation emerges as the primary priority for companies considering Bitcoin adoption, underscoring the need for robust strategies such as investment diversification, hedging, and scenario analysis. Stakeholder acceptance, encompassing investors, regulators, and market sentiment, is identified as the second most crucial factor, highlighting the importance of a supportive regulatory environment and investor confidence. The research also highlights the significance of analyzing price trends and optimizing asset allocation strategies. The AHP analysis identifies the Strategic Diversification approach as the most preferred alternative, aligning with Modern Portfolio Theory principles. Additionally, the study addresses accounting and financial reporting challenges associated with Bitcoin adoption, emphasizing the need for clear guidance and standards. The implementation plan outlines key aspects such as infrastructure development, education initiatives, risk management frameworks, and regulatory collaboration to facilitate the responsible integration of Bitcoin into Indonesian corporate finance strategies.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Globally, inflation poses a serious threat to businesses as it reduces money's purchasing power and raises the cost of capital due to increased interest rates, which affects both debt and equity <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Cochrane, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Eren &amp; Malamud, 2022)</ref>. Businesses like MicroStrategy, who have to manage these economic conditions to sustain growth and profitability, are especially affected by this difficulty. Due to its decentralized structure and limited quantity, Bitcoin has recently gained attention from businesses looking to diversify their investment portfolios and protect money <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Nakamoto, 2009)</ref>. Furthermore, as demonstrated by the addition of Bitcoin to the treasury reserves of Tesla and MicroStrategy, the acceptance of Bitcoin has an impact on corporate financial strategy. The long-term value of Bitcoin influences this strategic choice, which may have an impact on financial risk management, shareholder value, and the cost of capital <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dahlquist &amp; Pénasse, 2022)</ref>. The laws governing Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies are changing in Indonesia. Bappebti Regulation 13/2022, which describes the rules for cryptocurrency trading and related activities, governs Bitcoin, which is acknowledged as a commodity but not as legal tender <ref type="bibr">(Bappebti, 2022)</ref>. Businesses that want to trade cryptocurrencies have to get certain licenses and adhere to strict AML regulations <ref type="bibr">(BAPPEBTI, 2019)</ref>. With a strong increase in its cryptocurrency market, Indonesia has adopted digital payment trends to the extent that it ranks 20th internationally in the Cryptocurrency Adoption Index for 2022. The establishment of a cryptocurrency exchange with state backing intends to improve investor protection and transparency, demonstrating the government's commitment to regulating this rapidly expanding industry. The nation's cryptocurrency market experienced a significant rise in transaction value and is predicted to gain over $1 billion by 2023, proving its durability even during a down market. For companies in Indonesia, integrating cryptocurrency has several advantages, such as lower operating costs, more access to new markets, and more financial inclusion. Platforms like CEX.IO, which offer a safe entry point for purchasing, selling, and trading cryptocurrencies, encourage this adoption and help Indonesia's cryptocurrency ecosystem flourish. By entering new markets and enhancing payment systems, firms can utilize bitcoin strategically to cut out middlemen, decrease corruption through increased transparency, and promote economic progress. With the establishment of a national cryptocurrency asset exchange and other proactive regulatory measures, the government has established Indonesia as a major player in the global cryptocurrency market, spurring innovation and providing lucrative investment opportunities.</p><p>Cloud-based services, mobile software, and business analytics are the areas of expertise for MicroStrategy (MSTR), a Tysons Corner, Virginia-based global leader in corporate software solutions. The business was founded in 1989 and provides the MicroStrategy Analytics platform, which is well-known for its scalability, flexibility, and capacity to manage massive data volumes. Its clientele includes a wide range of sectors, such as retail, banking, healthcare, and telecommunications. MicroStrategy made the strategic decision to embrace Bitcoin as its principal treasury reserve asset in August 2020. CEO Michael Saylor highlighted the cryptocurrency's potential as a hedge against inflation and a store of value because of its limited quantity. This choice not only set MicroStrategy apart from its competitors but also demonstrated its innovative position at the nexus of technology and finance, allowing it to successfully navigate the rapidly changing domains of blockchain technology and digital assets. The company has demonstrated its innovative approach to capital management by strategically using convertible note issuances to fund its initiatives, including Bitcoin acquisitions. This aligns with the company's long-term vision and positions it as a leader in the incorporation of digital assets into corporate finance strategies.</p><p>In the turbulent world of blockchain and cryptocurrencies, convertible bonds are a valuable financial tool that allow businesses to acquire capital with minimal stock dilution and appeal to a wide range of investors thanks to bond coupons and conversion opportunities. These bonds are especially helpful in sectors like blockchain, where businesses need a lot of capital to grow and innovate. In Indonesia, for example, legal frameworks from organizations like Bappebti, which has set up a national cryptocurrency exchange and futures clearing house, support the integration of cryptocurrencies as acceptable corporate assets. The incorporation of digital assets into corporate plans has been accelerated by the government's encouragement and regulatory support of 229 cryptocurrencies. One example of this is the partnership between Binance and Telkom Indonesia's venture capital arm to launch a new digital asset exchange.</p><p>In this encouraging environment, the research goals center on investigating how Indonesian business executives view and feel about integrating Bitcoin into their corporate strategies, outlining risk management techniques for doing so safely, and evaluating how the price volatility of Bitcoin affects the financial stability and market perception of businesses that are thinking about adopting cryptocurrencies. The purpose of these studies is to determine how prepared Indonesian executives and financial specialists are for the use of cryptocurrencies in corporate operations, as well as what worries them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Literature Review</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Cryptocurrency</head><p>The cryptocurrency market runs on a decentralized network based on blockchain technology, providing strong security and resistance to counterfeiting. Bitcoin leads the way, with assistance from other cryptocurrencies like <ref type="bibr">Ethereum, Ripple, and Litecoin (Manjula et al., 2022)</ref>. With its peer-to-peer, safe, and transparent transactions that are independent of central financial authorities, Bitcoin-which was first introduced in 2008 under the pseudonym Satoshi Nakamoto-has played a significant role in upending established financial institutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Lee et al., 2018)</ref>. Referred to as "digital gold" because of its limited supply of 21 million coins, Bitcoin is a desirable long-term investment that provides stability and an inflation hedge, much like precious metals <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Rauchs, 2018)</ref> The global regulatory discrepancy is reflected in the fact that some nations have banned cryptocurrencies, while others have welcomed them as valid means of exchange <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Rajesh et al., 2022)</ref>. The cryptocurrency market is growing despite obstacles like security, privacy, and regulatory uncertainty. This growth is being driven by the technology's ability to lower transaction costs and speed up transactions, making it a competitive alternative to traditional fiat currency systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Li &amp; Whinston, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Because they provide a more solid option to more established cryptocurrencies, stablecoins-digital currencies linked to reliable assets like fiat currencies-play a crucial role in the cryptocurrency market. According to a study conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Ante et al., (2021)</ref> that examined 1,587 stablecoin transfers between April 2019 and March 2020, these transfers had a significant impact on Bitcoin's trading volumes and returns. The effects of the transfers varied depending on the sender-recipient dynamics, suggesting that different transfer motives and information asymmetries were perceived by the market. Moreover, a study conducted on 565 stablecoin issuance events during the same time frame revealed that although market downturns usually precede issuances, there are notable positive abnormal returns shortly after, which promote price discovery and improve market efficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Ante et al., 2021)</ref>. Four primary stabilization techniques are used to classify stablecoins, which can be issued by central banks or private organizations. This highlights the crucial role stablecoins play in promoting a reliable and effective trading environment amongst the volatility of the cryptocurrency market <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fantacci &amp; Gobbi, 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Modern Portfolio Theory (MPT)</head><p>Harry Markowitz developed Modern Portfolio Theory (MPT) in the 1950s and suggests diversifying investment portfolios to maximize the ratio of risk to return. By using Mean-Variance (MV) research, MPT highlights market interactions and holistic assessment by encouraging investors to see assets as a component of an overall portfolio. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Messica, (2018)</ref>, investor behavior should transition towards a more complete approach to asset management by giving priority to risk concerns above prospective returns when making investment decisions. MPT is particularly relevant in the developing world of cryptocurrencies, offering methods for incorporating virtual assets such as Bitcoin into portfolios to minimize risk and optimize returns. This approach, which emphasizes the crucial role that risk management and diversification play in maintaining long-term investment goals, is still essential for investors navigating the intricate and dynamic world of digital finance <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chen, 2024)</ref>. The potential importance of Bitcoin in augmenting diversification and maximizing risk-adjusted returns on corporate balance sheets is underscored by its relevance in the context of MPT. Portfolio diversification techniques can be greatly impacted by the features of Bitcoin, such as its low correlation with traditional asset classes and its potential as an inflation hedge. Because of its extreme volatility and unpredictability in the regulatory landscape, integrating Bitcoin into investing strategies based on MPT principles might be challenging, but it also presents a special chance to improve portfolio efficiency. Because of its low correlation with traditional financial assets, empirical research suggests that adding Bitcoin to diverse portfolios could enhance expected returns and efficiently manage risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Kajtazi &amp; Moro, 2019)</ref>. But as <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Guesmi et al., (2019)</ref> point out, adding such erratic assets necessitates thorough risk assessment and a calculated approach to preserve portfolio balance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Convertible Bonds</head><p>For businesses like MicroStrategy, convertible bonds are a strategic financial tool that combine elements of debt and equity to improve capital structure and lower capital expenses. Due to the attractive conversion feature, issuers are able to offer lower interest rates than those on standard bonds. These bonds have the dual benefits of fixedincome earnings and the potential for equity gains if the stock value <ref type="bibr">rises Finnerty, (2015)</ref>. Hedge funds, which are adept at managing the risks associated with the dual nature of convertible bonds in the face of credit, interest rate, and stock market fluctuations, are drawn to the bonds' intricate terms, such as conversion ratios and maturity dates <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Batten et al., 2018)</ref>. Convertible bonds also match bondholders' interests with equity investors', which makes them a desirable choice for businesses going through major capital expenditures or strategic transitions like mergers and acquisitions <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Dutordoir et al., 2014)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Cost of Capital</head><p>In corporate finance, the Weighted Average Cost of Capital (WACC) is a critical metric that combines the costs of debt and equity financing to calculate an organization's total financing costs. WACC represents the required return rate from all capital sources and is used as a standard for assessing investment prospects. This helps to inform decisions about new initiatives <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Cacciafesta, 2015)</ref>. WACC is a discount rate that is used in capital budgeting to determine the present value of future cash flows <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Johnston et al., 2018)</ref>. Its application in multivariate regressions to assess potential returns highlights its analytical power in market dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Sultana et al., 2019)</ref>. Conversely, the cost of debt has a direct impact on borrowing costs, which in turn affects a company's capital structure and the proportion of debt to equity <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Choi &amp; Lee, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Lemmon &amp; Zender, 2019)</ref>. Due to its comparatively lower cost, companies may favor debt; nonetheless, a significant dependence might raise the risk of financial distress. Determining loan costs and maximizing capital structure are crucial processes that depend on variables such as interest rates and creditworthiness. The perceived risk of purchasing a company's stock, which is impacted by a number of variables like market volatility and company-specific hazards, is what drives investors' expectations of return, which is reflected in the cost of equity <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Cao et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Mokhova et al., 2018)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Company Valuation</head><p>In the field of corporate finance, sound company valuation techniques are essential for figuring out a company's intrinsic value, which guides important investment choices and long-term financial planning. Financial experts employ a multidimensional strategy that combines methods like Discounted Cash Flow (DCF) Analysis, which takes growth projections and the time value of money into account while discounting expected future cash flows to present value. Furthermore, Market Multiples Valuation evaluates a company's worth by contrasting it with other companies in the same industry using important financial criteria such as the price-to-earnings (P/E) ratio. The industry, development stage, data accessibility, and valuation goal are some of the variables that influence the choice of valuation techniques. In addition to these techniques, financial ratio analysis provides information about the performance and health of a business, including ratios related to profitability, liquidity, solvency, and efficiency.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Bitcoin Market Analysis and Valuation Techniques</head><p>Because of its finite quantity and decentralized character, Bitcoin poses special valuation issues that call for different analytical frameworks. PlanB's Stock-to-Flow (S2F) Model, which forecasts price increases as supply tightens, highlights Bitcoin's scarcity as a value driver. However, it has drawn criticism for oversimplifying market dynamics. Although it lacks forecasting precision, the Power Law Model is able to discern patterns in the very erratic price movements of Bitcoin, pointing to a distribution with frequent small fluctuations and few large changes. The Bitcoin Cycle Index predicts market movements using cyclical patterns, but its accuracy depends on past trends continuing. Because the market is unpredictable, statistical techniques like the Bitcoin Log Regression, which integrate several data sets to model long-term price movements, are not infallible. The Bitcoin Energy Gravity Model (BEGM) bases price on the assumption that the network's security cost equals its market worth. However, this assumption may be called into question by emerging, less energy-intensive solutions. The Pi Cycle Top Indicator also makes use of the mathematical constant Pi to forecast market peaks, yet its usefulness is questioned because of the scarcity of historical data and other market factors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.">Framework Development</head><p>The strategic integration of Bitcoin into MicroStrategy's financial strategy is assessed using the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP), which offers a structured framework for decision-making with an emphasis on market perception, risk management, and capital structure optimization (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). This method evaluates possible effects on the cost of capital by statistically assessing Bitcoin's function as an inflation hedge and its compliance with Modern Portfolio Theory concepts <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chen, 2024)</ref>. Drawing on research on cryptocurrency risk management, it also examines methods for addressing the volatility and market risks related to Bitcoin <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Batten et al., 2018)</ref> Furthermore, the methodology uses insights from cryptocurrency market behavior and valuation tools to investigate how the adoption of Bitcoin impacts MicroStrategy's financial stability and investor perception <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Guesmi et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kajtazi &amp; Moro, 2019)</ref>. AHP facilitates the identification of the most prudent strategic courses of action by means of a weighted analysis, guaranteeing a comprehensive assessment that integrates theoretical understandings and real-world consequences of implementing Bitcoin in corporate finance. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Research Methodology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Research Design</head><p>The Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP) and a qualitative case study approach are used in this study to investigate how Bitcoin might be incorporated into corporate finance strategy as an inflation hedge in the Indonesian context. The qualitative method captures the challenges of integrating this financial technology by offering a thorough analysis of business executives' perspectives and tactics regarding Bitcoin's place in corporate capital structures. Concurrently, AHP is utilized as a numerical instrument to measure and rank the many hazards and advantages linked with Bitcoin, enabling strategic decision-making by ascertaining the relative significance of every criterion via professional evaluations and data gathering.</p><p>By contrasting AHP results with important stakeholder interviews, including those with executives and financial analysts at MicroStrategy in Indonesia, this mixed-method approach is further confirmed. This validation guarantees that the results accurately capture the variables influencing the decisions made about the adoption of Bitcoin, giving a strong basis for assessing financial policies in the face of economic uncertainty and useful information for maximizing shareholder value with Bitcoin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Data Collection</head><p>Purposive sampling is used in the research on the strategic adoption of Bitcoin in Indonesian corporate finance to concentrate on MicroStrategy (MSTR) as a case study. The persons chosen for this study have particular knowledge of how Bitcoin is incorporated into corporate structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Leavy, 2020)</ref>. Semi-structured interviews with seven business owners from various industries, including digital software and FMCG, as well as corporate finance specialists were used as data collection techniques. The target companies were those with market capitalizations between USD 1 million and USD 10 million. The purpose of these interviews is to collect a range of viewpoints regarding the justification, advantages, dangers, and effects of Bitcoin on capital structure and shareholder value. The study also examines past stock market and Bitcoin prices in addition to MicroStrategy's financial reports. This adds a quantitative element by highlighting trends and correlations related to the strategy's ability to reduce inflation risks and increase shareholder value. With a comprehensive framework that guarantees findings are grounded in stakeholder perspectives and empirically validated, this combination of qualitative and quantitative data collection methods offers practitioners and researchers studying corporate finance and cryptocurrency adoption practical insights.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Data Analysis</head><p>Primary data is carefully tabulated and coded in the research on the strategic adoption of Bitcoin inside corporate finance in order to make the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP) via the Expert Choice Decision Analyst software easier to use. This method organizes the investigation to pinpoint and balance important variables impacting business financial plans about the use of Bitcoin. First, important variables are extracted from the data and arranged in a hierarchical structure that is unique to the incorporation of Bitcoin into corporate finance. After determining the geometric mean of these components, the study ranks the factor weights using the Eigen Vector approach within the AHP, guaranteeing consistency with a Consistency Ratio (CR) less than 0.01. In addition, the study makes use of econometric modeling to investigate how macroeconomic policies, including government expenditure, affect economic indicators over time, such as inflation rates, and how they correlate with business cash flows <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Agarwal &amp; Kimball, 2015)</ref>. In the context of Bitcoin adoption, this quantitative analysis looks for causal correlations between business financial success and economic policy. The study combines results from econometric and AHP analysis to examine how Bitcoin might be used in practice to reduce costs associated with inflation on business balance sheets. In order to thoroughly assess how factors like government expenditure and the adoption of Bitcoin affect business financial strategies against inflation, the final phase synthesizes insights from both models. Its goal is to make clear these relationships and the effects they have on corporate financial resilience.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results And Discussion</head><p>The research employs purposive sampling to investigate the strategic adoption of Bitcoin within corporate finance in Indonesia. Purposive sampling is particularly useful in cases where a specific population segment can provide the most pertinent information regarding the research topic. According to <ref type="bibr">Leavy (2017)</ref>, purposive sampling allows researchers to selectively choose individuals who possess specific experiences or insights relevant to the issue being investigated. The author employed a purposive sampling method to select the respondents for this study. Purposive sampling is a non-probability sampling technique in which the researcher relies on their judgment when choosing members of the population to participate in the study <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Etikan, 2016)</ref>. This sampling method is often used when the research requires a specific set of expertise or knowledge from the respondents <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Palinkas et al., 2015)</ref>. The author purposefully selected respondents based on their expertise, experience, and involvement in the fields of blockchain technology, cryptocurrency, and digital finance. The selection process was not random but rather targeted individuals who could provide valuable insights and contribute to a comprehensive understanding of the research topic.</p><p>Educational background was one factor, with respondents having academic expertise in relevant fields, such as those from the Bandung Institute of Technology and the University of Indonesia, chosen to provide theoretical and research-based insights <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Campbell et al., 2020)</ref>. Professional experience was another factor, with respondents having practical experience in the cryptocurrency and digital finance industry, such as co-founders, CEOs, and leaders of startups and established companies, selected to offer hands-on knowledge and understanding of the challenges and opportunities within the field <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Margareth, 2017)</ref>. The author also aimed to include respondents from various institutions, including universities, research centers, startups, and corporations, to ensure a diversity of perspectives and experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Robinson, 2014)</ref>. The inclusion of a researcher from Monash University, Australia, suggests that the author sought to incorporate international perspectives and access to global research in the field <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Maxwell &amp; Aggleton, 2016)</ref>. By purposefully selecting respondents based on these criteria, the author aimed to gather a rich and diverse set of data that would contribute to a thorough understanding of the research topic, ultimately strengthening the validity and reliability of the study's findings. The thematic analysis results, derived from interviews with several stakeholders, reveal diverse insights into the strategic use of Bitcoin. A variety of perspectives on how to incorporate Bitcoin into business financial strategies are revealed by the thematic analysis of interviews centered on the strategic usage of the cryptocurrency by businesses, most notably MicroStrategy. Important discoveries show that businesses like MicroStrategy have modified their capital structures to use Bitcoin as a hedge against inflation by employing special debt-financing techniques like "comfortable bonds," which are better understood by professionals in the field. Convertible bonds are used in these tactics as adaptable financial tools that fit a company's debt capacity, which is essential for maintaining creditworthiness and overseeing Bitcoin investments. Because of MicroStrategy's large investment in Bitcoin, changes in the price of the cryptocurrency have a direct impact on the performance of its stock. The possibility of implementing comparable Bitcoin investment tactics in Indonesia is examined, with an emphasis on risk mitigation and optimal Bitcoin allocation to account for local market quirks. Furthermore, the governance structure of a company-which includes voting privileges and stock classification-influences financial strategy and investment decision-making in a big way. The analysis highlights the challenges of incorporating such cuttingedge financial strategies within well-established corporate frameworks by indicating that using a company's balance sheet to manage a Bitcoin investment portfolio could have a significant impact on the portfolio's performance, leverage, and overall valuation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>No</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>b. Root Cause Analysis</head><p>One of the main obstacles to Bitcoin's limited acceptance in Indonesia, according to the root cause analysis (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>), is regulatory ambiguity. According to interviews, corporations are hesitant to use cryptocurrencies because they are unsure of the compliance requirements and possible liabilities resulting from the lack of a complete regulatory framework. The absence of cooperation between different regulatory organizations, such as the financial, tax, and technological authorities, exacerbates this uncertainty by leading to a fragmented regulatory strategy. Further impeding Bitcoin's integration into the Indonesian market are issues including misinformationfueled unfavorable public opinion, inadequate financial and technological infrastructure, and the perception of Bitcoin's technological limits in comparison to other cryptocurrencies. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Quantitative Analysis</head><p>Applying the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP) provides a methodical way to analyze the complex problem of Bitcoin acceptance in Indonesia. AHP allows for weighted comparisons to determine the relative relevance of various variables by organizing them into categories such as risk management, stakeholder views, technology readiness, legal and budgetary considerations, and regulatory environment. This approach, which takes into account the opinions of regulators, business leaders, and decision-makers, makes it easier to comprehend the factors that encourage and hinder the adoption of Bitcoin. By means of comprehensive interviews and AHP analysis, well-informed suggestions for improving the assimilation of cryptocurrencies into Indonesia's financial environment can be developed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>a. AHP Analysis</head><p>A structured framework with four main criteria-Stakeholder Acceptance, Optimal Allocation, Risk Mitigation, and Price Trends-has been developed on insights from interviews to evaluate the adoption of Bitcoin in Indonesian businesses (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>). Stakeholder Acceptance sub-criteria include remarks made by decision-makers, investment backing, market reaction, and regulatory framework. Market volatility, diversity, liquidity, risk-reward ratio, and credit rating impact are all examined by optimal allocation. The main components of risk mitigation criteria include diversification, insurance, scenario analysis, and hedging techniques. Price Trends measures how well Bitcoin performs in comparison to market sentiment, price trends, and indexes. The extensive framework-which was developed through interviews-defines requirements, sub-requirements, and substitute tactics for the adoption of Bitcoin in Indonesian businesses. With thorough explanations and comments from participants, it offers a reliable foundation for assessing the variables influencing Bitcoin integration. While alterantive strategies (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>)-from Conservative Allocation to Aggressive Expansion-cater to varying risk appetites and outlooks, criteria such as Stakeholder Acceptance, Optimal Allocation, Risk Mitigation, and Price Trends offer a nuanced approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 4: Establishment Alternative</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Alternative Strategy Definition</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conservative Allocation</head><p>Maintain a cautious approach by allocating a smaller portion of the company's assets to Bitcoin (e.g., 10-20% of cash reserves). This strategy minimizes exposure to Bitcoin's volatility while still positioning the company to benefit from potential upside.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strategic Diversification</head><p>Allocate a moderate portion of assets to Bitcoin (e.g., 20-40% of cash reserves) while also investing in other cryptocurrencies and blockchain technologies to diversify risk. This strategy balances between leveraging Bitcoin's potential and mitigating risk through diversification.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Aggressive Expansion</head><p>Significantly increase Bitcoin holdings (e.g., 50% or more of cash reserves), positioning the company as a leader in cryptocurrency adoption among publicly traded companies. This strategy bets on Bitcoin's long-term value proposition and potential for substantial returns.</p><p>Based on the provided information, a strategic evaluation of the Bitcoin investment decision has been conducted using the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP) method. The criteria considered include Stakeholder Acceptance (23.1%), Optimal Allocation (19.2%), Risk Mitigation (38.1%), and Price Trends (19.5%). The AHP analysis results show that the highest priority is given to Risk Mitigation, followed by Stakeholder Acceptance, Price Trends, and Optimal Allocation. With a Consistency Ratio (CR) of 1.6%, it indicates a reasonably consistent assessment. Overall, the Bitcoin investment decision is considered to have a low level of importance (AHP group consensus: 52.0% low), with the primary focus on mitigating the risks inherent in this investment.</p><p>According to the AHP analysis, the most important factor for Bitcoin investments in Indonesian enterprises is risk mitigation (38.1%), which is followed by stakeholder acceptance (23.1%), price trends (19.5%), and optimal allocation (19.2%  <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Alternative Result</head><p>With 51.2% of the total preference, Strategic Diversification is the preferred option in the decision-making framework. This suggests a significant preference for dispersing opportunities and risk through a variety of avenues. Aggressive Expansion, on the other hand, only receives 19.3%, indicating a cautious attitude toward high-risk, high-reward projects. At 29.5%, Conservative Allocation falls in the middle and represents a substantial but cautious approach to resource allocation and capital investment. Overall, this distribution shows that diversity is clearly preferred over aggressive expansion and conservative preservation measures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conservative Allocation</head><p>The data provided appears to be a set of weighted values assigned to various factors under a "Conservative Allocation" strategy at Level 2, which suggests a hierarchy or a multi-tiered decision-making process. Each factor, ranging from Public Statements to Long-term and Short-term Trends, has been assigned a numerical value, presumably representing its relative importance or weight in the context of a conservative strategic approach. For instance, factors such as the Impact on Credit Rating (0.413194444) and Regulatory and Legal Environment (0.40625) have been assigned higher weights, indicating they are of substantial importance in the conservative allocation framework, likely due to their significant implications for stability and compliance. In contrast, Asset Diversification (0.175694444) and Long-term and Short-term Trends (0.186805556) hold lower weights, suggesting they are considered less critical within this conservative paradigm. Digital Asset Insurance and Hedging also receive a high emphasis, marked at 0.4 and 0.390972222 respectively, pointing towards a risk-averse attitude that prioritizes safeguards against potential financial uncertainties Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>: Decision Hierarchy</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strategic Diversification</head><p>The values outlined under "Level 2 Strategic Diversification" suggest a tiered approach where varying degrees of importance are assigned to each financial and market consideration within the context of a strategic diversification framework. Notably, Asset Diversification is emphasized the most with a weight of 0.432638889, aligning with the core tenet of strategic diversification which aims to spread exposure across various assets to mitigate risk. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Aggregate Expansion</head><p>The "Level 2 Aggressive Expansion" data presents a framework for allocating importance to various market and investment factors within an aggressive growth strategy. Categories like Risk/Reward Ratio (0.133333333) and Market Sentiment Analysis (0.11875) are given relatively higher emphasis, suggesting a key interest in the potential high returns associated with higher risks and a keen sense of how the market's mood may present opportunities for rapid growth. Conversely, elements such as Public Statements and Investor Support are assigned the lowest weights (0.072916667 and 0.070138889, respectively), indicating that while these factors are still considerations, they may take a backseat to more direct growth indicators in the aggressive expansion model. Hedging, although typically a defensive strategy, has been given a moderate weight (0.125694444), which could reflect a necessity to manage the increased risks inherent in aggressive expansion pursuits</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Discussion and Implementation Plan</head><p>The regulation of Bitcoin in Indonesia has evolved through various laws and regulations. For instance, BAPPEBTI Regulation No. 5 of 2019 states that although Bitcoin is not recognized as a legal means of payment, it is recognized as a crypto asset that can be traded on the Physical Market for Crypto Assets. Additionally, BAPPEBTI Regulation No. 11 of 2022 mandates that crypto assets like Bitcoin must be supervised and guarded by BAPPEBTI through special inspections at least once a year. These regulations reflect the Indonesian government's efforts to regulate the trading and management of Bitcoin, despite the limitations in its use as an official means of payment. Despite the evolving regulations, the adoption of Bitcoin as a corporate asset in Indonesia is still in its early stages, with many companies just becoming aware of the opportunities and challenges associated with managing digital assets <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Suraya et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Susanto et al., 2021)</ref>. Factors such as the lack of clear regulations, the perceived complexity of managing digital assets, and limited understanding of the technology among decision-makers have contributed to the slow adoption rate. However, as awareness of Bitcoin's potential benefits increases and the regulatory environment becomes clearer, it is expected that more Indonesian companies will start to consider integrating Bitcoin into their corporate asset portfolios <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Wicaksono, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>The quantitative AHP method reveals that risk mitigation emerges as the primary priority (38.1%) for companies considering Bitcoin adoption in Indonesia (Analytical Hierarchy Process Analysis). Companies in Indonesia need to implement robust risk mitigation strategies, such as investment diversification, hedging, and scenario analysis, to minimize the risks inherent in holding Bitcoin. The AHP analysis underscores the importance of strategies like diversification (35.3%), hedging (27.7%), digital asset insurance (19.9%), and scenario analysis (17.2%) in mitigating risk (Analytical Hierarchy Process Analysis). However, the literature suggests that the effectiveness of these strategies may depend on factors such as the company's risk tolerance, investment horizon, and the overall regulatory environment in Indonesia <ref type="bibr">(Symitsi &amp; Chalvatzis, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Suraya et al., 2022)</ref>. This finding aligns with the literature that highlights the price volatility of Bitcoin and the challenges associated with managing digital assets <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Karabulut &amp; Sari, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Susanto et al., 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Stakeholder acceptance, encompassing investors, regulators, and market sentiment, is identified as the second most crucial factor (23.1%) in Bitcoin adoption in Indonesia (Analytical Hierarchy Process Analysis). This resonates with the literature emphasizing the need for investor support <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Wicaksono, 2023)</ref> and a supportive regulatory environment in Indonesia <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Suraya et al., 2022)</ref>. The AHP analysis highlights the importance of factors such as regulatory and legal environment (27.8%), market reaction (22.8%), public statements (17.9%), and investor support (31.5%) within the stakeholder acceptance criteria in Indonesia (Analytical Hierarchy Process Analysis).</p><p>Companies in Indonesia must convince stakeholders of Bitcoin's potential and address concerns related to legal and accounting complexities, which are particularly relevant in the Indonesian context due to the lack of clear guidance from accounting standards like PSAK <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Anthony et al., 2022)</ref>.</p><p>Bitcoin price trends (19.5%) and optimal asset allocation (19.2%) are also significant considerations in the adoption decision for Indonesian companies, as identified by the AHP analysis (Analytical Hierarchy Process Analysis). The literature acknowledges Bitcoin's potential for long-term growth <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Ramadhani, 2022)</ref>, which could be attractive for Indonesian companies looking to increase their overall return on investment. The importance of analyzing price trends and market sentiment is also highlighted (as cited by Dimaz in the data), which is particularly relevant in the Indonesian context, where Bitcoin adoption is still in its early stages <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Suraya et al., 2022)</ref>. The AHP analysis further emphasizes the relevance of factors like market sentiment analysis (40.7%), comparison with market indexes (33.9%), and long-term and short-term trends (25.4%) in assessing price trends for Indonesian companies (Analytical Hierarchy Process Analysis). Indonesian companies need to closely monitor price trends and optimize asset allocation by considering factors such as diversification, liquidity, and risk/reward ratios.</p><p>The AHP analysis identifies the Strategic Diversification strategy as the most preferred alternative (51.2%) for Bitcoin adoption among Indonesian companies (Analytical Hierarchy Process Analysis). This finding aligns with the diversification principles of Modern Portfolio Theory (MPT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Kajtazi &amp; Moro, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Messica, 2018)</ref> and the literature advocating asset diversification to manage risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Guesmi et al., 2019)</ref>, which could be particularly relevant for Indonesian companies navigating the volatile cryptocurrency market. The AHP analysis further emphasizes the importance of factors such as asset diversification (43.3%), investment diversification (36.6%), and long-term and short-term trends (39.7%) within the strategic diversification approach for Indonesian companies (Analytical Hierarchy Process Analysis). Indonesian companies can consider allocating a portion of their assets to Bitcoin while investing in other cryptocurrencies to spread risk.</p><p>Although not explicitly discussed in the AHP results, the literature highlights the accounting and financial reporting challenges associated with Bitcoin as a significant hurdle for Indonesian companies <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Anthony et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Ramadhani, 2022)</ref>. The lack of clear accounting guidance from PSAK (Indonesian Financial Accounting Standards) can cause Indonesian companies to hesitate in integrating Bitcoin into their financial statements, fearing its impact on reported financial performance. As suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Karabulut &amp; Sari, 2022)</ref>, the absence of clear accounting standards can reduce comparability between companies and potentially mislead investors, underscoring the need for a comprehensive framework to address this issue in the Indonesian context. The development of consistent accounting standards and regulatory guidance is crucial to ensure transparent financial reporting for Indonesian companies adopting Bitcoin.</p><p>The implementation strategy addresses important aspects like infrastructure, education, risk management, legislation, and real-world testing with the goal of promoting the use of Bitcoin among Indonesian firms.</p><p>Cooperation with financial regulators such as OJK and Bank Indonesia is essential in order to determine Bitcoin's legal status and create tax regulations. Partnerships with industry groups and accounting bodies ensure sectoral alignment. Knowledge transfer initiatives and international custody alliances are necessary to provide secure infrastructure. Education initiatives clear up misconceptions, and accredited training courses and forums facilitate stakeholder awareness. Companies may overcome risks and acquire useful insights by utilizing real-world pilot projects and robust risk management systems. Continual enhancement, overseen by a specialized task force, guarantees flexibility in response to worldwide developments.</p><p>While the adoption of Bitcoin as a corporate asset is still in its early stages in Indonesia, other countries have shown a more progressive approach. For instance, in the United States, companies like MicroStrategy and Tesla have made significant investments in Bitcoin, with MicroStrategy holding over 130,000 BTC as part of its corporate treasury strategy <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Saundal, 2021)</ref>. Similarly, several publicly listed companies in Canada, such as Galaxy Digital Holdings and Hut 8 Mining Corp, have also embraced Bitcoin as a strategic asset <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Férdeline, 2022)</ref>. These examples showcase a more advanced level of Bitcoin adoption and provide a benchmark for Indonesian companies to consider as the regulatory and market conditions evolve.</p><p>Furthermore, countries like Singapore and Switzerland have established themselves as crypto-friendly jurisdictions, with clear regulatory frameworks and supportive policies for businesses dealing with digital assets. In Singapore, the Payment Services Act provides a licensing regime for crypto businesses, enabling greater transparency and investor protection <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Alekseenko, 2022)</ref>. Switzerland has also taken steps to incorporate blockchain and cryptocurrencies into its legal and regulatory framework, positioning itself as a hub for crypto and fintech innovation <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Pavlidis, 2021)</ref>. These examples demonstrate how a supportive regulatory environment can foster the adoption of cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin within the corporate sector.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>The world has taken notice of MicroStrategy's courageous decision, spearheaded by CEO Michael Saylor, to use Bitcoin as its main treasury reserve asset. The corporation uses debt instruments such as convertible bonds to allocate cash reserves to Bitcoin in a deliberate manner, citing its superior store of value. MicroStrategy's strategy has drawn mixed reviews, but it may establish a precedent for corporate Bitcoin adoption, which might have an effect on stock price and performance. This plan provides Indonesian businesses with a template for capital restructuring as a means of battling inflation. Improving shareholder value and protecting against inflation are two advantages of customizing it for the local market. In order to successfully implement and establish Indonesian firms as leaders in the invention of digital assets, collaboration among stakeholders is essential.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1: Framework Development</figDesc><graphic coords="6,78.90,131.77,438.35,164.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Root Cause Analysis</figDesc><table><row><cell>Theme</cell><cell>Symptom</cell><cell>Potential Root Cause</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-Unclear regulatory</cell><cell>-Absence of comprehensive cryptocurrency</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>framework for</cell><cell>regulations and guidelines</cell></row><row><cell>Regulatory Uncertainty</cell><cell>cryptocurrencies in Indonesia requirements for companies -Lack of clear compliance</cell><cell>-Lack of coordination among regulatory bodies (e.g., financial, tax, and technology authorities)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-Underdeveloped</cell><cell>-Limited investment and development in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>infrastructure and support</cell><cell>cryptocurrency-related financial and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>systems for integrating</cell><cell>technological infrastructure</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cryptocurrencies into the</cell><cell>-Absence of specialized service providers</cell></row><row><cell>Readiness Infrastructure</cell><cell>-Lack of custody, custody, ecosystem Indonesian financial</cell><cell>catering to the needs of Indonesian companies</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and security solutions tailored</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>to the Indonesian market</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-Negative public sentiment</cell><cell>-Prevalence of negative media coverage and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and lack of</cell><cell>misinformation about cryptocurrencies</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>awareness/understanding</cell><cell>-Lack of comprehensive educational initiatives</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>about the benefits and risks of</cell><cell>to inform the public and business community</cell></row><row><cell>Perceptions Stakeholder</cell><cell>Indonesian companies to -Reluctance among Bitcoin</cell><cell>about Bitcoin and its applications</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>adopt Bitcoin due to potential</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>stakeholder backlash</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-Perception of Bitcoin's</cell><cell>-Insufficient innovation and development</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>technological stagnation</cell><cell>within the Bitcoin ecosystem</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>compared to other</cell><cell>-Limited understanding of Bitcoin's technical</cell></row><row><cell>Technological</cell><cell>cryptocurrencies</cell><cell>capabilities and potential use cases</cell></row><row><cell>Limitations</cell><cell>-Lack of confidence in</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Bitcoin's long-term viability</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and use cases</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-Ambiguity in the legal and</cell><cell>-Lack of clear guidelines and alignment on the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>tax treatment of Bitcoin and</cell><cell>legal and tax classification of cryptocurrencies</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>other cryptocurrencies in</cell><cell>-Insufficient guidance on accounting, reporting,</cell></row><row><cell>Legal and Fiscal Complexities</cell><cell>Indonesia compliance and potential -Uncertainty around</cell><cell>and tax implications for corporate Bitcoin holdings</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>liabilities for companies</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>adopting Bitcoin</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Businesses are discouraged from embracing Bitcoin due to legal and fiscal complications, including unclear tax</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">and legal treatment. A more favorable environment for Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies in Indonesia could be</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">created by addressing these underlying causes through the creation of clear regulations, better infrastructure, public</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">education, and improved technological offerings from Bitcoin. This would mirror strategic adoptions like</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">MicroStrategy's use of Bitcoin as a corporate asset.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Establishment Criteria and Sub Criteria For corporations, it involves many people, both inside the corporation itself and from the outside. Inside the corporation, of course, includes employees, shareholders, and so on." -Chris Investor Support "Given that in Indonesia itself, the adoption of Bitcoin on the retail side is still questioned. So if it's done from a corporate side, in my opinion, it shouldn't be suitable yet." -Chris ...if possible, split into 10 wallets, some on exchanges, some in cold wallets, some in resorts, and others, to be safe..." -Jeff Scenario Analysis "MicroStrategy being the first company that issues a bond for their company and buying Bitcoin with those new cash inflow has a risk of leveraging too much...what MicroStrategy is doing has not really a high risk." -Marius ...next month is the Bitcoin halving, usually the following year is still busy and then it will drop and the year after that it will rise again." -Jeff</figDesc><table><row><cell>Theme</cell><cell>Sub-Criteria</cell><cell>Relevant Quotes</cell></row><row><cell>Stakeholder Acceptance</cell><cell cols="2">Public Statements "Market "MicroStrategy's situation is like an 'infinity money glitch.' They can Reaction create debt. And when the price of Bitcoin goes up again, then they can</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>raise new funds." -Chris</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Regulatory and Legal Environment</cell><cell>"The legal and tax complexities related to crypto assets are major considerations for companies in Indonesia before adopting an investment strategy similar to MicroStrategy's." -Overview</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Market</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Volatility</cell><cell>"Speaking from a financial statement perspective, it's actually unhealthy</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>for the company, because the calculation mode is quite biased. When</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>high, it can significantly increase, thus raising its valuation, but when it</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>drops, like what happened to Tesla, it drops a lot." -Jupaka</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Asset</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Diversificatio</cell><cell>"Investing in Bitcoin and other crypto assets like Ethereum and NFTs can</cell></row><row><cell>Optimal</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>be part of a diversification strategy to reduce risk." -Dimaz</cell></row><row><cell>Allocation</cell><cell>Liquidity</cell><cell>"Bitcoin is, in my opinion, the most liquid asset. So, I can sell it to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>everyone in the whole world..." -Marius</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Risk/Reward</cell><cell>"Initially, I was into NFTs, then started taking Bitcoin seriously, because</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ratio</cell><cell>it's one of the investment instruments. Now, I consider Bitcoin as one of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>the digital investment instruments." -Jupaka</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Impact on</cell><cell>"MicroStrategy's situation is like an 'infinity money glitch.' They can</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Credit Rating</cell><cell>create debt. And when the price of Bitcoin goes up again, then they can</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>raise new funds." -Chris</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Hedging</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Risk Mitigation</cell><cell></cell><cell>"To reduce risk, companies can use contracts or staking, by setting upper and lower limits for when to sell their crypto assets." -Dimaz</cell></row></table><note><p>""</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). The overall perceived relevance of Bitcoin investment is low (AHP group consensus: 52.0% low), with a heavy emphasis on managing associated risks, despite the Consistency Ratio (CR) of 1.6% indicating decent consistency. Meanwhile, Regulatory and Legal Environment (27.8%), Market Reaction (22.8%), Public Statements (17.9%), and Investor Support (31.5%) rank top among Stakeholder Acceptance's sub-criteria, with a CR of 0.2%. Securing investor backing is a top priority, along with addressing regulatory concerns and comprehending market reactions, despite its low importance (AHP group consensus: 52.5% low).Risk/Reward Ratio (26.7%) is the most important aspect when evaluating investment considerations. Other important factors include Asset Diversification (24.5%), Liquidity (22.7%), Market Volatility (17.5%), and Impact on Credit Rating (8.5%). The importance of prudent risk management and asset allocation is emphasized by this prioritization. Investment diversification (35.3%) is the most prioritized strategy for mitigating risk, followed by hedging (27.7%), digital asset insurance (19.9%), and scenario analysis (17.2%). The AHP group consensus indicates moderate to low agreement on these risk mitigation techniques, even though the CR is still low at 1.8%. The most important factors in price trend analysis are Market Sentiment Analysis (40.7%), Comparison with Market Indexes (33.9%), and Long-term and Short-term Trends (25.4%). Participants' preferences exhibit a large variation (AHP group consensus: 57.7% extremely low) despite a steady CR of 2.3%. This disparity reflects varying reliance on different techniques for interpreting price changes (Figure</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Investment Diversification and Long-term and Short-term Trends also receive considerable weightings, at 0.365972222 and 0.396527778 respectively, indicating a focus on a broad investment spectrum and an emphasis on understanding market dynamics over time. Conversely, elements such as Hedging, Digital Asset Insurance, and the Risk/Reward Ratio are assigned relatively lower values, suggesting a lesser focus on these areas within the diversification strategy at this level. The moderate weights given to Public Statements, Liquidity, and Scenario Analysis reflect a balanced consideration of market perceptions, financial flexibility, and predictive planning.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Decision Hierarchy</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Level 0</cell><cell>Level 1</cell><cell>Level 2</cell><cell>Glb</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Prio.</cell></row><row><cell>Strategic</cell><cell>Stakeholder Acceptance</cell><cell cols="2">Public Statements 0.179 4.1%</cell></row><row><cell>Evaluation of</cell><cell>0.231</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Bitcoin Decision</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Investor Support 0.315 7.3%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Market Reaction 0.228 5.3%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Regulatory and Legal</cell><cell>6.4%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Environment 0.278</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Optimal Allocation</cell><cell cols="2">Market Volatility 0.175 3.4%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.192</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Asset Diversification 0.245 4.7%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Liquidity 0.227 4.4%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Risk/ Reward Ratio 0.267 5.1%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Impact on Credit Rating 0.085 1.6%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Risk Mitigation 0.381</cell><cell cols="2">Hedging 0.277 10.5%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Digital Asset Insurance 0.199 7.6%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Investment Diversification</cell><cell>13.4%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.353</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Scenario Analysis 0.172 6.5%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Price Trends 0.195</cell><cell>Comparison with Market</cell><cell>6.6%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Indexes 0.339</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Author Contributions: All authors contributed to this research.</p><p>Funding: Not applicable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest:</head><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p><p>Informed Consent Statement/Ethics Approval: Not applicable.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kimball</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5089/9781513567327.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5089/9781513567327.001" />
		<title level="m">Breaking Through the Zero Lower Bound. IMF Working Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Legal regulation of the use of distributed ledger technologies in financial sector of Singapore</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Alekseenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.33975/riuq.vol34ns2.957</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.33975/riuq.vol34ns2.957" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Revista de Investigaciones Universidad Del Quindío</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">S2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fiedler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Strehle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.frl.2020.101867</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.frl.2020.101867" />
		<title level="m">The influence of stablecoin issuances on cryptocurrency markets. Finance Research Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing an anti-counterfeit system using blockchain technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lee</forename><surname>Anthony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Edbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Suhartono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.procs.2022.12.114</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procs.2022.12.114" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Procedia Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">216</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pricing convertible bonds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Batten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L H</forename><surname>Khaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbankfin.2018.05.006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbankfin.2018.05.006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Banking and Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">92</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using the WACC to Rate a New Project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cacciafesta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.2593040</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2593040" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Electronic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Purposive sampling: complex or simple? Research case examples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Greenwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Prior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shearer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Walkem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bywaters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1744987120927206</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1744987120927206" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Research in Nursing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Company reputation and the cost of equity capital</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Omer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11142-014-9292-9</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11142-014-9292-9" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Accounting Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Index Model with Modern Portfolio Theory and its Application to Find Optimal Portfolio in the American Stock Market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.54097/m98skn80</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.54097/m98skn80" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Highlights in Business, Economics and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of IFRS non-audit consulting services on cost of debt: Evidence from Korea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.19030/jabr.v31i5.9401</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.19030/jabr.v31i5.9401" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Business Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fiscal Histories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cochrane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/jep.36.4.125</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1257/jep.36.4.125" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The missing risk premium in exchange rates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dahlquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pénasse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jfineco.2021.07.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfineco.2021.07.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What we do and do not know about convertible bond financing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dutordoir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Seward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Veld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcorpfin.2013.10.009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcorpfin.2013.10.009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Corporate Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dominant currency debt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Eren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malamud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jfineco.2021.06.023</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfineco.2021.06.023" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of Convenience Sampling and Purposive Sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Etikan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.11648/j.ajtas.20160501.11</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.11648/j.ajtas.20160501.11" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Theoretical and Applied Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fantacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gobbi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1515/ael-2020-0053</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1515/ael-2020-0053" />
		<title level="m">Stablecoins, Central Bank Digital Currencies and US Dollar Hegemony: The Geopolitical Stake of Innovations in Money and Payments. Accounting, Economics and Law: A Convivium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cryptopians: idealism, greed, lies, and the making of the first big cryptocurrency craze</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Férdeline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23738871.2022.2071748</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/23738871.2022.2071748" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cyber Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Valuing convertible bonds and the option to exchange bonds for stock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Finnerty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcorpfin.2014.12.012</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcorpfin.2014.12.012" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Corporate Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Portfolio diversification with virtual currency: Evidence from bitcoin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Guesmi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Abid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ftiti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.irfa.2018.03.004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.irfa.2018.03.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Review of Financial Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Vanderstoep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Creswell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Källander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tibenderana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Akpogheneta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Strachan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H A T</forename><surname>Asbroek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Conteh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kirkwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Meek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miyazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nozaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Seitio-Kgokgwe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mashalla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Seloilwe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Odiwuor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sommerville</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cloud-Based Software Engineering. Computers and Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of bitcoin in well diversified portfolios: A comparative global study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kajtazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.irfa.2018.10.003</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.irfa.2018.10.003" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Review of Financial Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The attitude of academic staff towards Bitcoin. Ekonomski Vjesnik</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Karabulut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.51680/ev.35.1.5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.51680/ev.35.1.5" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to the oxford handbook of qualitative research, second edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Leavy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordhb/9780190847388.013.9</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780190847388.013.9" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Oxford Handbook of Qualitative Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cryptocurrency: A new investment opportunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3905/jai.2018.20.3.016</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3905/jai.2018.20.3.016" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Alternative Investments</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymmetric Information, Debt Capacity, and Capital Structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lemmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Zender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/S0022109018000443</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022109018000443" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial and Quantitative Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing Cryptocurrencies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Whinston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10796-019-09966-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10796-019-09966-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Systems Frontiers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Second Edition Qualitative Inquiry &amp; Research Design Choosing Among Five Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Margareth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Экономика Региона</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">INTRODUCTION: Elite education -international perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Maxwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Aggleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9781315755984-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315755984-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Elite Education: International Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Loopholes in Modern Portfolio Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Messica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.3190173</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3190173" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Electronic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Internal factors influencing the cost of equity capital</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mokhova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zinecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Meluzín</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.9770/jesi.2018.5.4(9)</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.9770/jesi.2018.5.4(9)" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Entrepreneurship and Sustainability Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nakamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Bitcoin open source implementation of P2P currency. P2P Foundation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Purposeful Sampling for Qualitative Data Collection and Analysis in Mixed Method Implementation Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Palinkas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Horwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wisdom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hoagwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10488-013-0528-y</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10488-013-0528-y" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pavlidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/17579961.2021.1977222</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/17579961.2021.1977222" />
		<title level="m">Europe in the digital age: regulating digital finance without suffocating innovation. Law, Innovation and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Overview of Blockchain Technology for Identity and Access Management in the IoT Ecosystem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rajesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pattar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Prabha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Manjula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/COMSNETS53615.2022.9668412</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1109/COMSNETS53615.2022.9668412" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">14th International Conference on COMmunication Systems and NETworkS, COMSNETS 2022</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022. 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Impact of Bitcoin Halving Day on Stock Market in Indonesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H Z K</forename><surname>Ramadhani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.32535/jicp.v5i3.1800</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.32535/jicp.v5i3.1800" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Conference Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cryptocurrencies Meeting Business Ecosystems: The Case of Bitcoin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rauchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mname</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.3095875</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3095875" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Electronic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sampling in Interview-Based Qualitative Research: A Theoretical and Practical Guide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14780887.2013.801543</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14780887.2013.801543" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qualitative Research in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cryptocurrencies: Analysis of the Technology and Need for Its Regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saundal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.3903787</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3903787" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Electronic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of WACC in Elucidation of Cross Sectional Stock Returns by Stylized Portfolios: Pragmatic Evidence from Pakistan Stock Exchange</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sultana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Imran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Saleem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31703/gmsr.2019(iv-i).04</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.31703/gmsr.2019(iv-i).04" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Management Sciences Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<pubPlace>IV(I)</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suraya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ramadhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lutfiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Khoirunisa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Rahardja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/CITSM56380.2022.9935848</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1109/CITSM56380.2022.9935848" />
		<title level="m">Blockchain, Information and Speculation Calculations in Indonesia: Recent Work. 2022 10th International Conference on Cyber and IT Service Management, CITSM 2022</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Susanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ibrahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rodiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rosiyadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Setiana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K S</forename><surname>Susanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kusuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Setiawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4018/978-1-7998-8447-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-7998-8447-7" />
		<title level="m">Securing Financial Inclusiveness Adoption of Blockchain FinTech Compliance</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ch010</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kejatuhan FTX Dan Pelajaran Penting Bagi Solusi Crypto Custody: Analisis Risiko Sistemik Dan Perlindungan Aset [The FTX Crash And Important Lessons For Crypto Custody Solutions: Systemic Risk Analysis And Asset Protection]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wicaksono</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bridging Journal of Islamic Digital Economics and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
