<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Short Research Guide for Designing Representative, Proportional, and Random Samples of Papers to Gather Scientometric Data of Research Fields 1</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Manuel</forename><surname>Goyanes</surname></persName>
							<email>mgoyanes@hum.uc3m.es</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Communication</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carlos III University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olga</forename><surname>Blasco-Blasco</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Valencia</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Short Research Guide for Designing Representative, Proportional, and Random Samples of Papers to Gather Scientometric Data of Research Fields 1</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">AC4F674C6E21CD6B8F6B8CBE8AAF27EA</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-23T06:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>representative sample</term>
					<term>proportional sample</term>
					<term>random sample</term>
					<term>scientometric</term>
					<term>sample size</term>
					<term>research patterns</term>
					<term>research fields</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Gathering representative scientometric data from papers (such as the gender of the first author, funding, number of co-authors per paper, authors' affiliation, etc.) is fundamental to examining the state and evolution of research fields. However, despite the need to design representative, proportional, and random samples of research publications to provide generalizable scientific findings of research fields, a simple step-by-step methodological protocol is surprisingly missing. This article addresses this gap and provides a guide for meta-research scholars on how to gather and process data from the Journal Citation Report (JCR) to design random samples proportional to the journals' number of publications and representative of the fields under examination. The study contributes to advancing the scientific study of research patterns in science by presenting a research guide that covers all the methodological steps to provide reliable scientific findings based on the design of representative, proportional and random sample sizes.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A Short Research Guide for Designing Representative, Proportional, and Random Samples of Papers to Gather Scientometric Data of Research Fields</p><p>Despite the many values associated to "good" or "sound" science, many scientists would agree that providing reliable evidence that informs society to solve the most pressing problems is the intended meaning of most scientific endeavors <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Chalmers, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Goyanes, 2020)</ref>. To do that, the sciences typically rely on robust methodologies and technical procedures aimed at reporting the most accurate findings to tackle empirical, social, and theoretical quandaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Bourdieu, et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Goyanes, 2017)</ref>. In this regard, one of the most relevant technical procedures, among many others, is the design of representative samples to infer reliable conclusions of the population under examination <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Grafström &amp; Schelin, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Omair, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>It is widely known by laypeople and largely addressed by statisticians <ref type="bibr">(Serdar et al., 2021)</ref> that representative samples enable the generalization of findings, warranting the inference of results to the target population, saving costs yet losing certain levels of accuracy due to measurement errors <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Jenkins &amp; Quintana-Ascencio, 2020)</ref>. Despite the paramount importance of sample sizes in warranting reliable results, several challenges may impede their proper execution, such as unknown populations, budget allocations, or sampling errors <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Lakens, 2022)</ref>. In social sciences, the design of representative samples is significantly relevant to examining and understanding public attitudes, perceptions, and behaviors of a given target population, particularly in survey research <ref type="bibr">(Taherdoost, 2017)</ref>. In other fields of study, such as biology, economics, or genetics, the appropriate design of samples is also crucial to infer reliable causal findings <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Hart et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gauderman, 2002)</ref>.</p><p>Likewise, scientometric research is also in need of sample designs that accurately represent their target population <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Goyanes et al., 2023)</ref>, for instance, when measuring different research patterns and evolution of scientometric variables of academic fields (), and therefore provide reliable results that can be generalizable.</p><p>Some typical examples may be easily presented. For instance, prior research on scientometrics has largely focused on the examination of gender representation of the first author of papers published in different research fields <ref type="bibr">(Anderse et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Pinho-Gomes et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Denby et al., 2020)</ref>. This analysis, however, can focus on particular cases (such as the five most important journals in a given field), or the field as a whole (all journals in a given field).</p><p>Likewise, research has also examined the number of authors per paper in specific journals and fields <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Sacco &amp; Milana, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Plummer et al., 2023)</ref>. In the former case, a sampling strategy would focus on gathering first the population of papers of the journals under study to then compute the sample size, while in the last, the sampling strategy would consider gathering the population of the papers published in the field (i.e., all journals) to then compute the sample size. In this paper, we focus on the design of sample sizes that are representative of the field, although the same strategy may be followed to analyze other target populations. In what follows, a simple step-by-step guide is presented to manage, process, and compute a representative, proportional and random sample to infer reliable findings of scientometric data, such as the above-mentioned, coming from journals and papers of different research fields and ranked in the JCR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Designing a Representative, Proportional and Random</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample: Example for the Field of Communication</head><p>This guide focuses on the design of representative, proportional and random samples based on data coming from the Journal Citation Report of the field of Communication in 2022, but a similar approach may be followed to examine other fields and years. As data for the population is coming directly from the JCR ranking, the sample is only representative of journals indexed by this ranking and included in this field (N journals = 96).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 1: Selecting the Field(s) of Research and Year(s)</head><p>The first step is selecting in the JCR ranking (or other) the field of study and year to proceed to compute the representative sample.</p><p>Depending on the number of fields and the number of years the researcher is interested in examining, the sample size may accordingly vary. For practical reasons, the study will only focus on one field (Communication), and one year (the most recent available data, 2022), but the same procedure could be implemented to examine multiple fields and years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 2: Generating the Population of Articles for Each Journal in the JCR</head><p>To design a sample size representative of the target population, the target population needs to be known first. In this case, the target population is the sum of all articles published in all journals indexed in JCR in 2022. Accordingly, N is the population size, in this case, the total number of articles. N i is the size of each stratum, i.e., the number of articles for each journal:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">, (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">)</formula><p>where K is the number of journals indexed in JCR in 2022.</p><p>Although not perfectly accurate 1 , the population could be computed by extracting this information directly from the JCR, by examining each journal in the field of communication and checking the "content metrics" section, the source data, and the "total citable items". Specifically, this information is revealed as "number in JCR Year 2022 (A)", by considering either articles, reviews, or both combined.</p><p>In this guide, only articles will be computed. Alternatively, this information can be also gathered directly by signing into the JCR 1 There may be a time gap or discrepancy between articles published each year and their inclusion in an issue, which may be later. The JCR lists the articles published in a giver year, no matter the issue of inclusion.</p><p>platform, and customizing the information displayed. Specifically, "total Articles" in the checklist of customized features needs to be checked. Since the sample needs to be representative of the field and proportional to the journals' research output, the output for each journal needs to be computed. Accordingly, the population or articles is the sum of the research output (i.e., total publications) of all journals (see Table <ref type="table">1</ref> as example, first column), Expression (1). In this example, the population of articles from all journals ranked in the JCR list in communication in 2022 is N articles = 5,045.</p><p>&lt;Insert Table <ref type="table">1&gt;</ref> Step 3: Computing the Representative Sample Size Since the population in this example is finite (N journals = 96, N articles = 5,045), the sample size can be easily computed by many online sample size calculators, including the following parameters: population (N articles = 5,045), confidence level (typically 95%), and margin of error (typically 5%). The mathematical expression for computing the sample size in finite and large populations, (n) that allows to warrant a 95% confidence (1-) and a maximum margin of error (e) of 5%, computed with the population proportion in which p = q = 50, will be:</p><p>(2) Where:</p><p>N is the population size. z is the value of the normal distribution (0,1) or standardized normal distribution. As the confidence level is set at 95%, the value of z = 1,96. e is the sampling error. p is the percentage of success. q is the complementary percentage.</p><p>In the example of the field of communication, the calculations yielded a sample size of 358 articles with the above-mentioned parameters. This sample size is the base for the scientometric analysis of the field. Consequently, any findings related to the research questions of the study (such as the gender representation of first authors in the field, the number of authors in the field, the funded/not funded articles in the field, etc.) to be considered representative should keep this sample size.</p><p>Step 4: Computing the Representative and Proportional</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample Size</head><p>If the analysis wants to adjust the sample size to the proportions of the research output of each journal (since journals, as represented in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, have different levels of publications), a proportional sample size must be designed. If not, a random sample (explained in the next step) of 358 articles can be randomly selected directly from the population of articles from all journals. In this example, a representative and proportional random sample is computed. For the sake of simplicity, the guide addresses first the representative and As the accurate result of this computation is 0.78, and the unit of analysis is the paper, no less than 1 paper can be examined. Accordingly, the results should be rounded up in cases when decimals are above 0.5 and should be rounded down when decimals are below 0.5. As seen in Table <ref type="table">1</ref> the discrepancy between the representative sample and the adjusted representative and proportional sample as a result of rounding up or down according to the decimals, is only 3 papers in favor of the adjusted representative and proportional sample (361-358).</p><p>Step 5: Computing the Representative, Proportional, and</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Random Sample Size</head><p>Once the dataset is representative to the field of research and proportional to the journals' research output, the next step is to randomly select the papers that will ultimately be the basis of the scientometric analysis. This random selection means that all articles from the journals under examination have the same chance of being selected for the study.</p><p>To satisfactorily compute a random sample of papers coming from the representative and proportional sample, two elements are needed: the list of articles for each journal, and a random number generator, which is easy to find online.</p><p>To have the list of articles for each journal in a given year, each journal should be examined extracting this information, once again, from the "content metrics" section, "source data", and the "total citable items" of the JCR platform. Specifically, in the total citable items, the column "Combined (C)", offers the possibility to directly export this data to a manageable software, such as .XLS or .CSV. In this selection, "articles" must be checked while "reviews" must be unchecked, if the analyses only focus on article types. Once the dataset is downloaded, every entry (i.e., paper of the journal), should be assigned with a numerical identification as reflected in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> for Communication Methods and Measures.</p><p>&lt;Insert Table <ref type="table">2&gt;</ref> The reason why every entry (i.e., paper) should have a numerical identification is because it will be the basis for the random selection of papers. For the case of Communication Methods and Measures, the minimum numeral identification is 1, while the maximum is 11, corresponding to the number of articles published by the journal.</p><p>Accordingly, in the (online) random number generator, the minimum number will be assigned a value of 1 and the maximum will be 11.</p><p>According to this calculation (reported in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>), Communication Methods and Measures only have one paper in the representative and proportional sample. Therefore, only one random number should be generated in the random number generator. In the case of this example, the random number generated was 6, meaning that entry number six in the dataset (i.e., "Inter-annotator Agreement Using the Conversation Analysis Modelling Schema, for Dialogue") should be included in the final representative, proportional and random sample for the field of communication. The same procedure should be implemented for the rest of the journals to compute the final representative, proportional and random sample of 361 articles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>This research guide represents a step forward to design representative and proportional random samples of research fields to gather scientometric data. The step-by-step protocol is intended to guide scholars in the design of scientometric projects aiming at producing reliable results that can be generalizable to the target population (i.e., the research field). Tested in the field of communication and based on the JCR list and the journals' research output of this ranking, the guide can also be implemented to examine multiple fields across several years. Likewise, other rankings or journal lists (such as Scopus) could be considered by applying a similar procedure.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>proportional sample size (which is optional) and follows-up with the random selection of articles. Again, for computing the representative and proportional random sample of the field of communication, some information needs to be known. These elements are the population of articles in the field (N articles = 5,045), the representative sample size of articles in the field (N sample_size = 358), and the total number of papers published by a given journal (i.e., N Communication_Methods_and_Measures = 11). It is considered that the sample size of each proportional stratum is directly proportional to the size of each stratum, that is, (3) Considering, for example, the sample size for Communication Methods and Measures, Knowing this information, computing the representative and proportional sample for Communication Methods and Measures will be (N = 1), resulted from multiplying the total number of papers published by the journal (N Communication_Methods_and_Measures = 11) by the representative sample (N sample_size = 358), and dividing it by the population (N articles = 5,045).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Serdar, C. C., Cihan, M., <ref type="bibr">Yücel, D., &amp; Serdar, M. A. (2021)</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">COVID-19 medical papers have fewer women first authors than expected</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Simone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lewiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jagsi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">elife</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">58807</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The craft of sociology: Epistemological preliminaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bourdieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chamboredon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Passeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Walter de Gruyter</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">What is this thing called science?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Chalmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Hackett Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation of women in cardiovascular clinical trial leadership</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Denby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Szpakowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA Internal Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1382" to="1383" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sample size requirements for association studies of gene-gene interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gauderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goyanes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Desafío a la investigación estándar en comunicación: Crítica y alternativas</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Barcelona</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Editorial UOC</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Against dullness: on what it means to be interesting in communication research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goyanes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information, communication &amp; society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research patterns in communication (2009-2019): testing female representation and productivity differences, within the most cited authors and the field</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goyanes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Demeter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grané</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tóth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>De Zúñiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to select representative samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grafström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scandinavian Journal of Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calculating sample size estimates for RNA sequencing data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Therneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Poland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kocher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of computational biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="970" to="978" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A solution to minimum sample size for regressions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jenkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Quintana-Ascencio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">229345</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sample size justification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lakens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Collabra: Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33267</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Where are the women? Gender inequalities in COVID-19 research authorship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pinho-Gomes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hockham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ripullone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Carcel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ global health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2922</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends in the Number of Authors and Institutions in Papers Published in AJPE 2015-2019</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Plummer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sparks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Broedel-Zaugg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brazeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Krebs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brazeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Pharmaceutical Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sample size estimation and sampling techniques for selecting a representative sample</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Omair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health specialties</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">142</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increase in number of authors per article in ten APA journals: 1960-1980</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Sacco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Milana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognitive Therapy and Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
