<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Pedagogy-First Compass Ecosystem: A Framework for Ethical and Adaptive Innovation in Teaching, Learning, and Educator Development A pedagogy-first model integrating ethics, course design, and faculty learning to guide responsible innovation in teaching and professional development</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-10">October 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marcus</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Instructional Designer</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Digital Learning Innovations (DLI)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kennesaw State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Pedagogy-First Compass Ecosystem: A Framework for Ethical and Adaptive Innovation in Teaching, Learning, and Educator Development A pedagogy-first model integrating ethics, course design, and faculty learning to guide responsible innovation in teaching and professional development</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-10">October 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FDA8242199319BA96609254B510EA7BD</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:55+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Pedagogy-First Compass Ecosystem provides a practical framework for designing, implementing, and evaluating innovation in teaching, learning, and faculty development. It is grounded in instructional design theory and ethical practice, placing pedagogy ahead of technology to promote sustainable and equitable change.</p><p>The Ecosystem includes three parts:</p><p>1. The Course Compass, a seven-phase process for strategic alignment, design, delivery, and evaluation. 2. The Compass for Learning (3 levels), guides educator development from awareness to integration and mentorship. 3. The Ethics Framework, a cross-cutting lens promotes transparency, accessibility, fairness, and human oversight in each design stage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">The GenAI Use &amp; Ethics Framework (5 Levels)</head><p>-a classroom-level model that applies these ethical and pedagogical principles to daily instruction, reflection, and assessment. *Originally introduced as the AI Course Compass (Green, 2025), this framework now extends beyond generative AI to include professional-development design, data-informed teaching, and inclusive course redesign across K-12 and higher education contexts. This preprint outlines conceptual foundations, ethical anchors, and research directions for applying the Ecosystem across educational contexts.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Full Description (Project Overview)</head><p>The Pedagogy-First Compass Ecosystem, developed by Marcus Green (Kennesaw State University), expands the author's published AI Course Compass (OLC Insights, 2025) into a broader pedagogy-driven framework for innovation in higher education.</p><p>It connects course design, faculty professional learning, and ethical reflection through three interrelated elements:</p><p>• Course Compass (7 Phases): A structured process aligning outcomes, ethics, and design across strategy, delivery, and evaluation.</p><p>• Compass for Learning (3 Levels): A faculty-readiness model guiding growth from awareness to innovation and mentorship.</p><p>• Ethics Framework: A cross-cutting lens promoting transparency, accessibility, fairness, and human oversight in every design stage.</p><p>This version refines and extends the seven phases published in the AI Course Compass, and three new features: Guardrails (Phase 2), Accessibility &amp; Quality Assurance (Phase 4), and Delivery &amp; Coaching (Phase 5), which move ethical reflection and quality review earlier in the process. The Ecosystem provides a flexible structure for instructional designers, teaching centers, and academic leaders to plan innovation grounded in pedagogy and equity. This preprint establishes authorship continuity and theoretical legitimacy while setting the foundation for future empirical studies and doctoral research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sub frameworks and Applied Models</head><p>The Pedagogy-First Compass Ecosystem also integrates the GenAI Use &amp; Ethics Framework, which serves as the classroom-level application of the Ecosystem's ethical and pedagogical foundations.</p><p>Developed originally as a companion to the AI Course Compass (Green, 2025), the GenAI Use &amp; Ethics Framework provides a five-level progression for integrating generative AI responsibly in teaching and learning.</p><p>Each level represents a deliberate step in ethical classroom innovation, moving from foundational skill demonstration to co-creative inquiry.</p><p>1. Independent Demonstration</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">AI-Enhanced Research &amp; Planning</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">AI-Assisted Refinement</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Collaborative AI</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">AI as Creative Partner</head><p>Where the Course Compass defines institutional and design-level processes, and the Compass for Learning supports educator readiness and professional growth, the GenAI Use &amp; Ethics Framework translates those same principles into daily instructional practice.</p><p>It applies the five ethical dimensions of the Ethics Framework-transparency, accountability, equity, privacy, and human oversight-within real teaching contexts through prompt logs, reflection journals, ethics memos, and accessibility safeguards.</p><p>This ensures that every classroom activity, whether human-or AI-assisted, remains pedagogy-first, ethically transparent, and inclusive by design.</p><p>Functioning as the applied practice model of the Ecosystem, the GenAI Use &amp; Ethics Framework bridges design-level intent with classroom execution.</p><p>It provides instructors with a scaffold for embedding ethical reflection directly into learning activities, while offering institutions a replicable structure for aligning technology adoption with academic integrity and human-centered learning outcomes.</p><p>Across modalities K-12, higher education, and hybrid environments, the Framework applies the Ecosystem's guiding principle: Pedagogy before technology, ethics across all contexts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Applied Use Case: Faculty Professional Development and Course Design</head><p>A district learning team or university's Center for Teaching and Learning (CTL) can apply the Pedagogy-First Compass Ecosystem to strengthen professional development and course design. Using the Course Compass, facilitators move through all seven phases-from Strategic Alignment (Phase 0) to Evaluation &amp; Innovation (Phase 6). Faculty progress through the Compass for Learning levels:</p><p>• Level 1 -Awareness: exploring inclusive pedagogy, AI literacy, and data-informed practices.</p><p>• Level 2 -Application: co-designing course activities using pedagogy-first templates.</p><p>• Level 3 -Integration: mentoring colleagues and leading institutional showcases.</p><p>The Ethics Framework supports each phase, promoting openness in tool use, accessibility in materials, and fairness in assessment. The result is a professional learning cycle that connects ethics, design quality, and faculty growth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Agenda</head><p>Future studies will apply design-based and mixed-methods approaches to explore how the Ecosystem supports:</p><p>• Faculty progression through the Compass for Learning levels.</p><p>• The impact of embedded ethics checkpoints on course quality and equity.</p><p>• Long-term institutional change toward pedagogy-first innovation.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>This framework extends the author's prior publication: Green, M. ( 2025). AI Course Compass: A <rs type="institution">Seven-Phase Framework for Ethical, Equitable, and Adaptive Course Design. Online Learning Consortium Insights</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author's AI Assistance Disclosure</head><p>Portions of this manuscript, including editorial structuring, formatting, and clarity refinement, were developed with the assistance of OpenAI's ChatGPT (GPT-5) under the direction and authorship of Marcus Green.</p><p>All conceptual models, frameworks, and original ideas-including the Pedagogy-First Compass Ecosystem, Course Compass, Compass for Learning, and Ethics Frameworkare the sole intellectual property of the author.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Validation and Authorship Statement</head><p>The Pedagogy-First Compass Ecosystem builds directly on the AI Course Compass (Green, 2025) and verifies conceptual continuity while expanding its scope to faculty development, data-informed teaching, and inclusive course redesign. It introduces early ethical guardrails, explicit accessibility, and quality measures, and ongoing coaches. This preprint establishes intellectual ownership, scholarly credibility, and framework validity for future peer-reviewed research. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>License</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Footer Statement</head><p>This preprint forms part of an ongoing research agenda exploring pedagogy-first innovation and ethical technology adoption in higher education. Future publications will report empirical validation of the Ecosystem in faculty-development and course-design contexts.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
