<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Running head: ELITE DOMINANCE IN ORGANIZATIONAL RESEARCH</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Mehmet</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Orhan</surname></persName>
							<email>m.orhan@nyenrode.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Nyenrode Business University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="NL">the Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yvonne</forename><forename type="middle">G T</forename><surname>Van Rossenberg</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Radboud University Nijmegen</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="NL">the Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Matthijs Bal</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Lincoln</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Running head: ELITE DOMINANCE IN ORGANIZATIONAL RESEARCH</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2F3BB2736CB0E33021A327C427CCB002</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>hegemony</term>
					<term>hyperproduction</term>
					<term>overrepresentation</term>
					<term>prolific scholars</term>
					<term>scientific elites</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Ideally, the academic publication process should be meritocratic, fair, and open to diverse groups of researchers. Yet, many scholarly disciplines are far from this ideal. To investigate the extent and nature of overrepresentation in management and organizational research, we examined 60-year publication trends in three closely related subfields: Management (MNGT), Human Resource Management (HRM), and Industrial-Organizational Psychology (IOP).</p><p>Analyzing over 60,000 publications from 42 top-tier journals, our study reveals an increasing trend in authorship inequalities and a growing dominance of the scientific elite. Individual-level analyses, along with journal and field-level comparisons, show that a select group of researchers has become more influential over time, leading to rising disparities in authorship. Field-level comparisons also show that the most productive IOP researchers publish significantly more articles than those in other fields. Besides rising numbers of publications, the super-elite of IOP are found to dominate more journals, as evidenced by a higher frequency of the same authors appearing on the top-10 most productive list in IOP than in the other two fields. Through network analyses, we revealed that IOP consistently shows a large giant component, indicating that a large portion of IOP authors is part of the "same connected network," reflecting a highly collaborative field where even smaller groups are connected to the broader network. We recommend future advancements in theory, practice, and policy to address these inequalities and promote a more inclusive and equitable research environment.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>divergence from reality, as access alone does not necessarily result in equitable outcomes. To explain this paradoxical condition, <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Lewis (2022)</ref> observes the following: "Issues of representation are inseparable from the science and from the stories we tell about our science and scientific institutions. What counts as 'good science' tends to be research approaches that prioritize the experiences of dominant groups, and not approaches developed to prioritize people placed on the margins of society. The topics that count are ones that fit with the 'master narratives' in the field, and not the 'counter narratives' that sometimes emerge from marginalized groups." (para. 6). Thus, underrepresentation should not be viewed as an isolated issue that can be resolved without addressing the underlying dynamics of dominance and overrepresentation. Current discussions on DEI in research often emphasize separation and variety while neglecting the disparities shaped by prestige, status, and hierarchy <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Harrison &amp; Klein, 2007)</ref>. Consequently, DEI initiatives frequently aim to enhance variety with tokenism and statistical adjustments. However, underrepresentation is not a standalone problem; they are symptoms of the broader issue of dominance by a select group of elite scholars <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Bal et al., 2024)</ref>. To understand the root causes of inequality in research, it is crucial to examine the impact of hierarchical disparities on scientific outputs.</p><p>The current study offers insights into the issue of overrepresentation, taking authorship inequality to the core, and underscores the need for a critical examination of existing institutional practices and publishing policies that impede fair representation and hinder progress in scientific research. Through empirical exploration and comparative analyses, we provide an examination of authorship dominance in management and organization research. By unpacking the paradigm of overrepresentation in scholarly publications, our study contributes to a deeper understanding of this phenomenon.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head><p>To investigate the phenomenon of authorship inequality, our study employs a quantitative discovery approach. This approach, which is often used to detect anomalies and unresolved organizational problems, involves a process of abductive reasoning, and offers a middle ground between inductive interpretive approaches and the hypothetical-deductive model <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Bamberger &amp; Ang, 2016)</ref>. We aim to reveal, describe, and diagnose disparities in production by analyzing 42 prominent journals in closely related MOR fields by examining authors' publication records from 1960 to 2019.</p><p>The quantitative discovery approach allows us to derive insights from our findings, identify plausible relationships, and offer the best available explanation based on established community standards of rigor. Our analysis of the data leads to the development of a series of propositions. In the discussion section, we integrate these propositions with relevant theories, highlighting their connections to prior theoretical developments and emphasizing the insights they provide into the phenomenon under study <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Bamberger &amp; Ang, 2016)</ref>. In the conclusion section, we discuss the implications of our theoretical contributions and offer policy recommendations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Selection and Extraction</head><p>We selected journals from the 2021 Academic Journal Guide from the Chartered Association of Business Schools (ABS List). Our inclusion criteria targeted journals rated 4*, 4, and 3 in the fields of General Management, Ethics, Gender, and Social Responsibility (ETHICS-CSR-MAN), Human Resource Management and Employment Studies (HRM &amp; EMP), Organisation Studies (ORG STUD), and Psychology-Organizational (PSYCH-WOP-OB). We excluded journals outside our research scope, those with inconsistent ratings below 3 in the last three rankings, and those not classified by the Journal Citation Report (JCR) of Clarivate Analytics. To cross-validate the journal classifications, we re-coded them based on JCR categories and created the list for each of the three fields of examination: HRM, IOP, and MNGT.</p><p>Our analysis focused on 42 top-tier journals: 13 from HRM, 15 from MNGT, and 14 from IOP. Data were collected from two primary sources. First, we used the Scopus database for its accurate records of author names and publications <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Kawashima &amp; Tomizawa, 2015)</ref>. We extracted data on researchers who published "articles" and "reviews" in the selected journals between January 1960 and December 2019, excluding editorials, notes, conference papers, letters, and errata. The dataset included 60,034 documents. We analyzed researchers who published at least five papers in one of the three fields, resulting in a sample of 4,825 unique researchers. These researchers were ranked by productivity, labeled anonymously for this study, and the complete dataset is available on the Open Science Framework website <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> .</p><p>In addition to Scopus, we used the Web of Science (WoS) to compute historical evolution in inequalities in each field, as <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Wang and Waltman (2016)</ref> reported better journal and document classification accuracy. We identified all authors (N = 51,610) who published "articles" or "reviews" in the selected journals between 1960 and 2019, excluding other document types. Data were also segmented into three time frames: <ref type="bibr">1960-1979, 1980-1999, and 2000-2019</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gini Coefficient Calculations</head><p>The Gini coefficient, ranging from 0 to 1, is calculated to interpret disparities in resource allocations and informs about the concentration of distribution. A Gini coefficient of 0 indicates perfect equality in distribution, 0.5 signals very high inequality, and 1 demonstrates perfect inequality. In light of this information, we used both Scopus and WoS datasets to understand the extent of dominance and how diverse the most productive researchers are in each field. The Scopus dataset was used to compare individual author productivity in each field, and the WoS dataset was used to compare total productivity and historical patterns.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS AND FINDINGS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>How Much Space is Allocated by the Top Contributors of Each Field?</head><p>Table <ref type="table">1</ref> summarizes the scope of our analyses and presents journal coverage information such as the count of articles, reviews, total count of documents analyzed, starting year of publications included, coverage period, and mean publications per year and per field. Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> presents the publication trends per field. They indicate a rising number of articles published in each field from 1960 to 2019. In 2019, 655 articles were published by 14 IOP journals, 13 HRM journals published 501 articles, and the other 15 MNGT journals covered 823 articles. The current annual journal publications per field averages for HRM, <ref type="bibr">IOP,</ref><ref type="bibr">and MNGT are 38.54,</ref><ref type="bibr">46.79,</ref><ref type="bibr">and 54.87,</ref><ref type="bibr">respectively.</ref> - <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref>-</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Table 1 about here ---------------------------------------- ---------------------------------------- Figure 1 about here ----------------------------------------</formula><p>Furthermore, we also compared the productivity of the most productive scholar in each journal separately. Table <ref type="table">2</ref> shows the mean number of publications of each journal's top-10 most productive researchers. JAP takes the lead on this with an average of 38.6 published papers by the top-10. JVB holds the second position with a mean of 29.5 papers, followed by LQ with 24.2 papers. Among MNGT journals, OrgStud is in the leading position, with an average of 16.4 papers. In HRM, IJHRM is at the front with an average of 20.6 papers. We conducted a Kruskal-Wallis nonparametric ANOVA test to evaluate whether the productivity of the most productive researchers differs by field. Results indicated that the mean publication of top-10 varies significantly based on the discipline. As demonstrated in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the mean publication count is found to be significantly higher in IOP journals than in both fields of HRM (H = 2.81, p = .015) and MNGT (H = 3.22, p = .004), with the test statistic of H = 12.31, p = .002. Results reveal that the most productive IOP researchers are significantly more productive than their counterparts publishing in the other two fields. Conversely, it can also be interpreted that top IOP journals allocate significantly more space to elite scholars than leading HRM and MNGT journals.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">---------------------------------------- Table 2 about here ---------------------------------------- ---------------------------------------- Figure 2 about here ----------------------------------------</formula><p>Another primary purpose of this study is to understand the productivity of the most productive and to examine the differences within and between closely related fields. Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> presents the ranking of the most productive researchers with a publication record of over 50 papers in top-tier journals analyzed.</p><p>----------------------------------------Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> about here ----------------------------------------Out of the 4,825 most productive researchers, only 77 of them (1.60%) are found to publish over 50 articles in our analyses. The data show strong evidence that the researchers, who ranked at the top publish predominantly in IOP outlets. Out of these 77 researchers, 58 of them (75.32%) had more than 50% of publications records in IOP journals. Only six researchers in the most productive list (7.79%) did not possess a IOP publication. Researchers who authored over 70 articles (n = 28) recorded in total of 2,501 publication, of which 2,067 (82.65%) appeared in IOP outlets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Who Are the Top Contributors of Each Field?</head><p>We also provide the list of highly productive researchers publishing the most studies in each field (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>). The mean publication count of the top-10 most productive publishing in IOP journals is 95.2. This statistic is found as 51.3 for MNGT and 41.2 for HRM. The top IOP scholar is Researcher1 with 135 unique IOP journal publications. At the bottom of the list, Researcher13 acquired 79 publications. Researcher29 takes first place in the MNGT field with 70 publications, which is less than the record of the 10 th most productive researcher of IOP. In HRM, Researcher54 tops the list with 57 publications, which shows a noteworthy disparity.</p><p>-</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">--------------------------------------- Table 3 about here ----------------------------------------</formula><p>To further compare publication records, we also analyzed the frequency distribution of publication data (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>). Among three fields, IOP is the only field that hosts the most productive researchers with a publication record of over 80 papers in their journals. According to this, five researchers accomplished a history of between 81 and 100 papers, and two others published numerous papers between 101 and 120. Finally, the most productive researcher, Researcher1, published 135 papers in IOP journals. Twenty-two researchers published more than 60 articles in IOP journals, whereas this record is shared only by one scholar publishing in MNGT journals.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">- Table 4 about here ----------------------------------------</formula><p>To better present the magnitude of inequality among the most prolific researchers in each field, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4</ref> illustrates the Lorenz curves to provide evidence that the concentrated productivity of the most prolific in organizational research. We also calculated Gini coefficients based on the top productive researchers data. Accordingly, IOP is found to be the most unequal among all domains, with Gini = .507. The Gini of MGNT is .459, and that of HRM is .407, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4</ref>.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref>- - <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref>-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Journal Level Comparisons</head><p>Moreover, we present evidence on the extent of the dominance by the most prolific in each journal. Figures <ref type="figure">5</ref><ref type="figure">6</ref><ref type="figure">7</ref>provide information about the publication count of the most prolific in each of the 42 journals analyzed. We color-coded researchers based on the frequency of their appearances as the most productive contributors in their field journals.</p><p>As comparative analyses can verify, IOP appears to be dominated by a handful of most productive researchers. The most accomplished researchers of IOP not only published higher numbers of articles, but were also ranked in the list of top researchers in more journals compared to their counterparts in the other two fields. Both Researcher1 and Researcher6 are listed among the top-10 contributors in six field journals in IOP. Other two authors (Researchers7 and 10) are listed in four journals in IOP. In MNGT, five authors <ref type="bibr">(Researchers 29,</ref><ref type="bibr">56,</ref><ref type="bibr">61,</ref><ref type="bibr">214,</ref><ref type="bibr">and 240)</ref> are listed among the top contributors of three MNGT journals. In HRM, only two authors (Researcher210 and 244) has appeared in the most productive ten researchers of three separate journals.</p><p>---------------------------------------- - <ref type="figure">---------------------------------------</ref>Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> summarizes the information presented in the preceding figures for field analyses and presents the authorship concentration. We demonstrate the elite scholars' broader influence spilling over to adjacent fields. Accordingly, Researcher1 is ranked as the top-10 contributor of seven different journals, one MNGT journal (HumRel) and six IOP (JMP, EJWOP, JVB, JOB, JOHP, and JOOP), followed by Researcher4, who was found the be dominating in six IOP journals. Again, the majority of journals at the top belong to the IOP field, and the top-10 contributors dominate IOP journals, and HumRel, which has a tradition of publishing quantitative, IOP research.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref>- - <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref>-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Historical Trends of Inequalities</head><p>The last analysis investigates inequality trends over the past 60 years. Additionally, we shed light on the changes in researchers' productivity concentration, which can inform about the overall status of the fields concerned. We calculated Gini coefficients by taking a 20-year range for each domain to provide a comparative perspective, and we presented inequalities in three fields on three different time windows; <ref type="bibr">1960-1979, 1980-1999, and 2000-2019.</ref> Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref> shows the changes in the Gini coefficients in each field in the last 60 years for all three areas. In the last two decades, inequalities have gotten larger in all fields. Between 1960 and 1979, IOP hit a Gini coefficient of .333, which signals relatively adequate equality, but it is still with the highest disparity among all fields; MNGT (GiniMNGT = .146) and HRM (GiniHRM =.109). Authorship inequalities in each domain reached their highest levels between 2000-2019. The Gini coefficients in 2000-2019 for each field are as follows: GiniMNGT = .428, GiniHRM = .391, and GiniIOP = .495. Looking at the indices of all time, the current picture of IOP designates that the field is experiencing severe inequality (GiniIOP = .502) against the other two fields, (GiniHRM = .391) and (GiniMNGT = .453). These figures signal that the top researchers of each field are becoming more influential and dominate the publication sphere. Their research productivity represents more and more portions of entire literature.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref>-  <ref type="figure">---------------------------------------</ref>To better present the growing dominance of the most productive, we computed what percentage of all studies published in each domain were authored by the most productive 1%, 5%, 10%, and 20% of researchers. Table <ref type="table">5</ref> shows that the top 1% most productive authored 12.6% of all studies published in IOP between 2000-2019, indicating a steady increase from the previous periods. <ref type="bibr">Between 1980</ref><ref type="bibr">Between and 1999</ref><ref type="bibr">Between , this figure was 9.8% and 7.4% in 1960</ref><ref type="bibr">Between -1979</ref>. The top 1% of HRM authored 11.2% of research in 2000-2019, a steep increase from the previous period, as this figure was only 6.9% of all HRM publications in 1980-1999. On the other hand, in MNGT, the top 1%'s share has risen from 7.6% to 8.8% of all publications from 1980-1999 to 2000-2019. The rising inequalities were evident in all segments of top researchers. For instance, each field's top 10% of researchers authored 45.5% of all research in IOP, 39.3% of HRM, and 38.3% of MNGT publications. All these figures confirm that the share of publications by the bottom researchers declined in all fields. Due to the rising competition and immense influence of the most productive researchers, authorship equalities have deteriorated in all fields in the last 20 years. Figure <ref type="figure">10</ref> zooms into the historical trends of publication share taken by the top 1%, 5%, 10%, and 20%. Across all fields, top publication shares have risen since the 1960s. Among these three fields, the share was the largest in IOP for all top segments.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref>-</p><p>Table 5 about here <ref type="figure">-------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>  <ref type="figure">---------------------------------------</ref>Finally, Table <ref type="table">5</ref> also compares the total number of studies published, the number of researchers, and the average output per researcher in each time window for each field.</p><p>Accordingly, between 2000 and 2019, the number of researchers publishing in IOP reached 14,782, with 36,071 total publications. The mean number of publications per researcher is 2.44 (SD = 4.10) During the same period, 23,085 papers from 11,730 researchers were published in HRM (M = 1.97, SD = 2.86), and 27,092 papers of 12,722 researchers in MNGT journals (M = 2.13, SD = 2.57). We conducted an ANOVA test to test whether the average number of publications per researcher is statistically different in each field. Results confirmed that the mean publication per researcher in IOP is statistically higher than those published in both fields, F(2, 25832.11) = 60.88, p = .000). Even though more research is published in IOP by more researchers, it is noteworthy to highlight that the publication concentration is getting in fewer hands.</p><p>Ultimately, historical patterns and presented statistics establish that authorship inequalities have become more concerning for all fields. Among the three fields, IOP offers the most worrisome picture with historically high and growing inequalities, increasing dominance of the most productive researchers, and ever-increasing publication counts that are unevenly distributed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Network Analyses</head><p>Lastly, to better understand the productivity differentials, it is also useful to analyze the network analyses of each field. The top most connected 50 authors are analyzed in this context.</p><p>The networks are depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">11</ref>. IOP tends to show higher network density compared to HRM and MNGT, particularly in the early periods <ref type="bibr">(1960)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1961)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1962)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1963)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1964)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1965)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1966)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1967)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1968)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1969)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1970)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1971)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1972)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1973)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1974)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1975)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1976)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1977)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1978)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1979)</ref>. This suggests that in IOP, a higher proportion of potential co-authorship connections were realized earlier on, indicating that IOP authors were more collaborative as a community, even in the early stages. In HRM and MNGT, density decreases over time as the field grows larger, which is a natural trend as more authors enter the network. However, in IOP, the density is relatively stable, which suggests a continued strong culture of collaboration across authors. IOP has a consistently high average degree, particularly from 1980 onwards, indicating that authors in IOP tend to work with a larger number of co-authors on average compared to HRM and MNGT. The clustering in IOP is significantly higher than in HRM and MNGT, particularly from 2000 onwards. A higher clustering means that co-authors of an author are more likely to collaborate with each other, forming tight-knit research groups. This trend suggests that IOP authors tend to collaborate within smaller, more interconnected groups, which could be a reflection of the specialized nature of psychological research, where niche areas may involve smaller, highly collaborative teams.</p><p>Finally, IOP consistently shows a large giant component, particularly from 1980 onwards. This indicates that a large portion of IOP authors are part of the "same connected network," reflecting a highly collaborative field where even smaller groups are connected to the broader network.</p><p>The comparison of network centrality measures across IOP, HRM, and MNGT reveals evolving roles of these fields over time (see Figure <ref type="figure">12</ref>). IOP shows a consistent increase in both degree and closeness centrality, indicating its growing connectivity and accessibility within the network, while maintaining a stable level of influence through eigenvector centrality. HRM, starting from a lower base, experiences significant growth in both degree and closeness centrality, catching up with IOP by 2000-2019, signaling its increasing prominence. However, both fields exhibit a decline in betweenness centrality after a peak in the 1980-1999 period, suggesting a diminished role in bridging network gaps. MNGT, despite starting with high levels across all centrality measures, shows less change over time, suggesting sustained influence but limited growth in connectivity compared to IOP and HRM. Overall, IOP and HRM have become more central to their networks over time, while MNGT has maintained a steady but prominent position.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">--------------------------------------</ref>  <ref type="figure">-------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>Figure <ref type="figure">12 about here   ---------------------------------------</ref>-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSIONS</head><p>It is important to acknowledge that variations in research productivity among researchers are to be expected to some extent. Theoretical and empirical evidence suggests that individual performance follows a power-law distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(O'Boyle &amp; Aguinis, 2012)</ref>, offering that it is natural for a small proportion of researchers to contribute the majority of research output. Recent observations also indicate a trend of accelerating publication records and accumulating citations at disproportionate rates <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Larivière &amp; Costas, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Nielsen &amp; Andersen, 2021)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bal (2021)</ref> argued that highly productive researchers in the field of organizational research publish an average of more than 25 papers per year, equivalent to one paper every two weeks. However, the emphasis on quantity by elite researchers raises concerns about the sustainability of the academic publication system. Given that many senior academics already hold secure, tenured positions and are less dependent on journal publications for career advancement, the current publication system may no longer operate on a level playing field. This creates unfair competition, as established scholars tend to outperform ECRs who face the precarious nature of contemporary academia and strive to secure permanent positions. Furthermore, elite academics often occupy significant journal space, reducing the opportunities for ECRs and potentially making them reliant on collaborations through co-authorship <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Cohen &amp; Baruch, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Kwok, 2005)</ref>. These observations underscore the need to address the imbalances within the academic publishing landscape. In the absence of evaluation of the unequal distribution of power and resources, efforts to increase variety alone will remain insufficient to create truly equitable and inclusive environments.</p><p>In this paper, we illustrate authorship inequality and the extent of elite dominance in organizational research, focusing on the three categorically distinct but closely related fields.</p><p>Based on comparative analyses of authorship trends in 42 leading journals of IOP, MNGT, and HRM, we uncovered compelling evidence that (1) authorship inequality has been rising in the last six decades across all fields, and it is reaching alarming levels that threaten the sustainability of academic careers in organizational research. Especially, IOP has been grappling with issues of inequality since its inception and continues to do so. To illustrate the gravity of the situation, it is worth noting that the present authorship disparity in IOP resembles the income inequality distribution in Angola, a nation plagued by poverty and corruption for many years. Moreover, our findings also indicate that (2) IOP journals allocate significantly more space to the most productive authors than two other fields' journals, (3) the super-elite scholars of IOP do not only publish more articles on average than their counterparts in neighboring fields, but they also dominate journals to a greater extent, as we observe a higher frequency of the same authors on the top-10 most productive list in IOP than in the other two fields, and (4) the most productive IOP scholars are more conservative in their publication venue choices. These findings have significant implications for practice, theory, and policy design.</p><p>Despite the growth in the number of scholars engaged in organizational research over the past few decades, the landscape has witnessed a concerning trend: the concentration of journal publications among a select few. This phenomenon is occurring alongside the escalation of global competition, as evidenced by the skyrocketing rejection rates experienced by researchers. This concentration of journal publications in the hands of a limited number of individuals raises important questions about the fairness and inclusivity of the academic publishing system. In addition, although not directly presented in this study, we observed that the most productive scholars share a common set of demographic characteristics such as age (mostly senior), gender (almost always male), and race (almost always white, Western), which rule journal space disproportionately. These findings complement the previous findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bajwa and König (2019)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Lin and Li (2023)</ref>. In summary, our results indicate organizational research journals, especially top IOP journals, are under the control of a smaller number of scholars who publish significantly more articles than their counterparts active in the fields of HRM and MNGT. Furthermore, our analysis reveals a noteworthy trend of hyperspecialization among dominant authors in the field of IOP. These authors exhibit a distinct pattern of maintaining high levels of productivity by exclusively publishing their work in IOP outlets. This finding aligns with the research of <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Ryan and Ford (2010)</ref>, who also highlight the highly specialized nature of IOP scholars. These researchers demonstrate a strong preference for focusing on topics within the realm of IOP and display resistance to publishing in areas outside their specific field. The strategic decision of IOP scholars to concentrate their efforts within their chosen domain is a career-oriented approach that has been shown to yield higher levels of productivity, as supported by the findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Leahey et al. (2017)</ref>. Their findings suggest that individuals who primarily publish within a single field tend to be more productive than those who diversify their publication domains. Consequently, the concentration of certain topics and methodologies among dominant IOP authors may be a deliberate choice driven by a focus on quantity and productivity. Researchers within the IOP field may exhibit reluctance to explore topics that carry uncertain outcomes. This can be attributed to the perception that flagship journals, which are very influential in the field, tend to favor more conservative choices regarding topics and methodologies. As a result, researchers may opt for safer and more predictable research areas to increase their chances of publication in these prestigious outlets. These observations shed light on the strategic behaviors adopted by dominant authors in the field of IOP and provide insights into the potential reasons behind their hyperspecialization and publication choices. It is essential to further explore the implications of these patterns on the diversity and breadth of research within the field, as well as their impact on the overall advancement of knowledge in organizational research.</p><p>In the context of network analyses, the increasing centrality of IOP across various network measures reflects its growing influence and prominence, closely linked to the phenomenon of academic overproduction. The steady rise in degree and closeness centrality indicates that IOP has expanded its connections and become more central within the academic network, likely driven by the pressure to produce more research outputs. Overproduction pushes scholars to collaborate more, publish frequently, and engage with emerging trends, leading to IOP's enhanced accessibility and presence in academic discussions. However, as the field grows and becomes more interconnected, the saturation of publications can dilute the novelty and impact of individual research contributions. IOP's stable Eigenvector centrality suggests its influence within key academic circles, but the decline in betweenness centrality points to a more crowded and less distinct role as an intermediary, a potential side effect of overproduction. With many researchers now working on similar topics, IOP's ability to bridge disconnected areas has diminished. Institutional pressures to publish and the increasing relevance of IOP in addressing organizational challenges have likely fueled this rise, positioning IOP as a central field in academia, but also exposing it to the risks and challenges associated with the overproduction of research. Some of our results are inconclusive as more complex dynamics play a role in growing inequalities, and there might be legitimate reasons why some scholars might be more productive in some fields than others. Yet, our comparative analyses elucidate some crucial findings on the structural problems accumulating over decades. Reducing inequalities is one of the primary goals for scientific and societal development. The debates around academic inequalities related to race, gender, sexual orientation, religion, and social class are lively. Yet, when the intellectual space evolves to be more hegemonic over time, reducing systemic inequalities requires more succinct structural and institutional actions. By taking up a significant proportion of journal space, the most productive, elite academics keep outcompeting ECRs (and researchers in less privileged positions), who unfairly compete for the same outlets with limited resources. There are some vital takeaways for established scholars and editors to ensure equality and eliminate unfair competition at systemic and institutional levels.</p><p>The pressure to publish is an undeniable reality in academia, but the prevailing discourse on "publishing like a machine" has reached a point of absurdity in contemporary academic culture. As pointed out by <ref type="bibr">Harley (2019, p.293)</ref>, the glorification of the "heroic workaholic publishing machine" as a role model sets unrealistic expectations for academic careers and provides flawed examples for early career researchers (ECRs). While dedicated and highly productive scholars can make significant contributions to their respective fields, the current organization of science incentivizes researchers to prioritize productivity above all else.</p><p>However, this emphasis on hyperproduction becomes problematic when considering the limited space available in top-tier journals. It is important to note that our research focused exclusively on these high-ranking journals, and if we were to include other field-specific journals, the volume of publications by hyperproductive authors would multiply significantly.</p><p>The sustainability of this system is a growing concern among many scholars, leading to a recognition of the need for change in recent years. Researchers have begun questioning the true meaning and value of publications <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Berg &amp; Seeber, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Tourish, 2020)</ref>, with some expressing regret over their own history of overproduction and acknowledging its detrimental effects on scientific progress and academic careers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Frith, 2020)</ref>. To ensure the longevity of academic careers, it is crucial to engage in discussions about the genuine value of "high-impact" journals and the true significance of publications. An increasing number of ECRs now perceive the prestige and metrics of journals as more important than the actual content and contribution of their research <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Niles et al., 2020)</ref>. Consequently, the academic publishing system itself becomes progressively dysfunctional, eroding trust in the process as resources are disproportionately allocated to a small, privileged group of individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bal, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>At the same time, the assessment processes of research quality require considerable revision. Faculty hiring, promotion, and tenure committees, university leadership and management teams, external research/grant evaluators, and policymakers should recognize that the congested traffic in journal space is not only caused by rising competition. Elite scholars' snowballing dominance and their hyperproductive publication patterns lead authorship inequalities to perpetuate faster. In the current context, top-tier journals reportedly reject up to 95% of the submissions. It is quintessential to start questioning whether this small percentage of accepted studies should equate to high-quality research. Editors often signal selectivity by reporting rejection rates. Still, our analyses imply that it would not be fair to argue that only 5% is good enough and that 95% of the research submitted is below-standard, especially when only certain names keep showing up in the same scholarly domains. Acknowledging the complex nature of publishing in top journals, academic decision-makers should not treat journal names as a proxy for research quality.</p><p>Editorial teams have a substantial role in handling submissions more fairly and responsibly. Overall, our journal-level analyses present a depressing picture. Not only did elite scholars' paper production grow over time, but proportionally, the space allocated to them has inflated significantly. Not all these figures imply causality on biases, yet, more transparency about processes will help organizational research improve even further. As researchers are expected to share their data and processes for the sake of openness and transparency, the same should apply to journal editors. Ultimately, we believe there are no visible benefits of keeping submissions non-blind because prestige, hierarchy, and power could alter judgments and evaluations. Our policy recommendation that proposes triple-blind editorial review processes can be a starting point to breaking the hurdle of access and systemic discrimination. Unless editorial teams, reviewers, and authors remain blind throughout the submission process, objectivity can be compromised. Accordingly, we invite editorial teams to open up their operations and publication data, integrate transparency in their decisions, and explicitly commit to concrete action plans outlining how they address growing inequalities.</p><p>With this paper, we underline the structural problems that have been growing over decades. At the same time, we problematized the growing authorship inequalities from the overrepresentation angle. Inequality in an academic field, instilled in barriers and systemic practices, contradicts the fundamental scientific ethos and impedes scientific progress. Moreover, toxic overproduction may discourage aspiring individuals from entering academic research because ECRs would subsequently fail to follow the latest scientific findings, which grow exponentially. At the same time, with the dysfunctional publication systems, wrong incentive schemes, and growing inequalities, making scientific contributions will become unattainable for them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sources of overrepresentation and overproduction in research</head><p>To establish a theoretical foundation for understanding the problematic nature of scientific inequalities, Mertonian norms provide the necessary grounds for discussion. In his book The Sociology of Science, <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Merton (1973)</ref> identified four core imperatives within the scientific ethos that are relevant to the problem we investigated in this paper: universalism, communality, disinterestedness, and organized skepticism. Universalism pertains to the evaluation of claims based solely on their validity, regardless of their source. Personal and social characteristics should be disregarded when assessing the merit of scientific arguments. Similarly, the communality principle argues for the freedom of science and scientific institutions from ownership and dominance. Mechanisms that exclude individuals based on their social or membership status, hindering fair access, should be discarded as they undermine scientific progress. The principle of disinterestedness emphasizes that scholars should primarily engage in scholarly activities driven by intellectual curiosity and a pursuit of knowledge that benefits science as a whole, rather than being motivated solely by personal gain and self-interest.</p><p>However, many activities within the current scientific landscape often contradict these norms, as the competitive nature of academia pushes individuals to conduct research for self-interest.</p><p>Network connections, group affiliations, and prestige can significantly impact resource access, making objective evaluations practically unachievable (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Huber et al., 2022)</ref>. As a result, growing inequalities are a direct outcome of a system that has long neglected the fundamental principles of scientific norms. Lastly, the concept that no practice should be taken for granted forms the basis of organized skepticism. Within academia, there is a strong emphasis on individual achievements and rewards, often overemphasizing productivity. Young scholars and early-career researchers often believe that success in academia is solely determined by meritocracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Knights &amp; Richards, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Śliwa &amp; Johansson, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zivony, 2019)</ref>.</p><p>Consequently, disparities in productivity are regarded as natural, while discussions on the true implications of overproduction and the consequences of intellectual hegemony are rarely held. In the current neoliberal academic system, most of these norms are violated, causing a toxic competition that prioritizes quantity over quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Orhan et al., 2024)</ref>.</p><p>Elite scholars' dominance leads to overrepresentation in scholarship in many ways. They are often old, white, male researchers from the Western world, enjoying a privileged position and fame gained primarily through their past research productivity in scholarly journals from the Western world. These researchers frequently occupy gatekeeper roles in academic publishing, imposing control over ontological, methodological, and epistemological approaches in research <ref type="bibr">(Bal &amp; Dóci, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dóci &amp; Bal, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Lewis, 2022)</ref>. The hypercompetitive environment of academia exacerbates this issue, as top journals seek submissions from elite scholars and wellrecognized institutions, further entrenching their dominance <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Nielsen &amp; Andersen, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Along the same line, the hypercompetitive environment fueled by existing forces (i.e., institutions, publishers, rankings, etc.) sets norms and expectations for continuous production.</p><p>Overproduction is rewarded in the current system, and many ECRs wish to collaborate with elite to overcome the publish-or-perish barrier. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Brogaard et al. (2020)</ref> found that articles co-authored with well-known, established researchers receive significantly more citations regardless of the quality of the articles. In parallel, it is highly desirable for ECRs to publish in high-impact journals, since they attract more citations <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(Traag, 2021)</ref>. Another reason why one should publish in top journals at early stages is that the number of publications in high-impact journals is the strongest predictor of landing an academic job <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">(Vuletich et al., 2019)</ref>. Therefore, many ECRs are often dependent on established scholars. This gerontocratic privilege further allows elite scholars to keep occupying a disproportionate space, while at the same time controlling access through network power and/or editorial roles. The issue of diversity in academic research can be viewed as a complex matter because those who are new to the field (or work with relatively less known scholars) struggle and fight to get their work seen, accepted, read, and cited, while elite scholars (or the ones connected to them) often have an easier time getting their work published <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bal, 2021)</ref>. In light of Mertonian norms and how they violated in the current publishing system, we theorize that three major pillars lead to toxic overproduction: (1) collaboration, network effect, and power structures, ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) editorial conservatism and favoritism, (3) gamification of publications and career obsession.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Collaboration, network effect, &amp; power structures</head><p>The proportion of single-authored papers has been declining remarkably, as most publications have come from teams of researchers in the last decades <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abramo et al., 2019)</ref>.</p><p>Technological advancements have facilitated larger networks of researchers, resulting in an increase in the average number of authors per article and a growing list of publications on researchers' resumés.</p><p>Established scholars often have strong connections to influential researchers in their field, which can provide long-term advantages for career advancement. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Colussi (2018)</ref> found that senior researchers who become editors of leading journals tend to have productive social connections, including their doctoral students and colleagues, who often publish a greater number of articles. While it can be argued that these increased levels of productivity are not necessarily biased, it's important to acknowledge that power dynamics and political considerations can influence editorial decisions. Some editors may adjust their evaluation standards based on power imbalances, as rejecting a more powerful and well-connected senior scholar could have different consequences than rejecting an unfamiliar early-career researcher.</p><p>Nevertheless, editors in influential positions often possess a deeper understanding of current trends and research directions in their field, allowing them to provide valuable guidance to their collaborators.</p><p>The dynamics of power and relational networks significantly impact researchers' success. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Heffernan (2021)</ref> emphasized the advantages gained by elite researchers through access to resources and opportunities that are not publicly advertised. These individuals hold considerable power in academia, with their students, early-career researchers, and collaborators reinforcing their position. Collaborations can be mutually beneficial, but established researchers may use their position to form alliances that strengthen their ideas and bolster their influence. However, the potential for established scholars to exert coercive power over early-career researchers and doctoral students raises concerns about power abuse and exploitative practices. Such practices can perpetuate the dominance of established researchers and leave less influential collaborators dependent on them <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Cohen &amp; Baruch, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Täuber &amp; Mahmoudi, 2022)</ref>. Additionally, some researchers engage in gift authorship and publication parasitism, where they receive credit for research contributions without making substantial contributions themselves <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Greenland &amp; Fontanarosa, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Ioannidis, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Kwok, 2005)</ref>. These practices contribute to undeserved overproduction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Editorial favoritism and risk aversion in scholarly publishing</head><p>The editorial processes of academic journals play a pivotal role in shaping the diversity of published research, often influencing whose work is accepted and what ideas gain prominence.</p><p>While peer-review is designed to minimize bias, editors remain the primary gatekeepers, controlling which submissions advance to review and ultimately get published. In competitive journal markets, editors may favor submissions from well-known authors or prestigious institutions to maintain the perceived quality and reputation of their journals. This tendency can lead to editorial conservatism, favoritism, and even implicit cronyism, as previous research has shown <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Colussi, 2018)</ref>. Such preferences contribute to an imbalance, where elite scholars are granted disproportionate space in publications, while emerging voices are marginalized.</p><p>Editors also play a crucial role in amplifying the visibility of established researchers, often granting them easier and faster review processes. This not only consolidates the power of elite scholars but can also transform legitimate journals into platforms serving self-promotion <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Scanff et al., 2021)</ref>. The preferential treatment of prominent researchers reinforces the hyperproduction of their work, while newer or controversial research struggles to break through editorial gatekeeping.</p><p>Moreover, most journals are operated by commercial enterprises that prioritize exclusivity and impose arbitrary limits on the publication space. To remain competitive in terms of citations, readership, and subscriptions, editors may favor well-known authors, whose work is likely to garner citations irrespective of the research's quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Brogaard et al., 2014)</ref>. As a result, despite the steady increase in article submissions, rejection rates continue to rise, exacerbating the bias against lesser-known or innovative scholars.</p><p>The prestige of many top-tier journals is often tied to their long-established reputations.</p><p>However, as these journals age, editors tend to become more risk-averse, particularly when handling emerging or unconventional research problems. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Petersen (2017)</ref> found that this risk aversion leads editors to favor work that aligns with the status quo, systematically excluding new, innovative, or controversial perspectives. This behavior entrenches established ideas and topics, while stifling the exploration of fresh, potentially groundbreaking approaches.</p><p>Consequently, the editorial processes of leading journals can inadvertently perpetuate intellectual conservatism and hinder the advancement of new ideas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gamification of publications and career obsession</head><p>The intense competition for academic publications has led to a proliferation of research, raising concerns about the quality and value of this output <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Edwards &amp; Roy, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Kepes et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Orhan, 2020)</ref>. The current system often prioritizes the quantity of publications over their quality, as exemplified by the rise of hyperproductive researchers <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Ioannidis et al., 2018)</ref>. Even though Ioannidis and colleagues did not specifically cover social sciences in their analysis, this issue is pertinent to many domains as the global competition intensifies.</p><p>Under intense pressure, researchers may adopt strategies to maximize their publication success, such as specializing in narrow research areas that offer incremental findings. This trend leads to redundant publications, self-plagiarism, and the crowding out of diverse perspectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Horbach &amp; Halffman, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Orhan, 2021)</ref>. The dominance of elite scholars in prestigious journals exacerbates this issue, limiting innovation and diminishing the impact of new theories despite rising publication rates <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Park et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Publication pressure often leads to negative experiences such as constant rejection and burnout affecting the well-being and mental health of academics, making academic careers increasingly precarious <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Jaremka et al., 2020)</ref>. Fierce competition has led to a rise in deviant behaviors, including questionable research practices, gaming metrics, obsession with quantity, and opportunistic publishing <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Ioannidis et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Kepes et al., 2022)</ref>. These factors diminish trust in academic institutions, especially among early career researchers (ECRs) who face tougher competition. A study by van Dalen (2021) revealed that ECRs view publication pressure as detrimental to both their careers and scientific progress, a sentiment not necessarily shared by more senior scholars. This discrepancy highlights how the elite, as survivors of the system, support its competitive nature. Just as poverty traps the majority in unequal societies, precarious conditions trap ECRs and many others in academia, while the elite enjoy their privileged positions. As <ref type="bibr">Merton (1968, p.57)</ref> argued: "Eminent scientists get disproportionately great credit for their contributions to science while relatively unknown scientists tend to get disproportionately little credit for comparable contributions." Consequently, established researchers often achieve greater long-term productivity, leading to more citations and resources that further accelerate their productivity <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Bosquet &amp; Combes, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Nielsen &amp; Andersen, 2021)</ref>. This unequal representation in academia affects individuals, teams, institutions, and the advancement of science, benefiting only a small fraction of well-connected, privileged academics under the current publication system <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Krauss et al., 2023)</ref>. Our study aims to shed light on publication inequality and the dominance of elite scholars in management and organizational research, comparing historical trends of overrepresentation and theorizing the sources of this imbalance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations</head><p>Our study faced several limitations, notably the incomplete coverage of databases we relied on. Specifically, several prominent journals, such as the British Journal of Industrial Relations and the Academy of Management Journal, had missing years in the Scopus database, which may have influenced the comprehensiveness of our results. Therefore, actual productivity of elite researchers could be also understated. However, this does not change the overall conclusion of our findings. The full list of missing years in coverages are provided in the Appendix. Additionally, while the study analyzed publications from 1960 to 2019, the coverage of some journals was partial, and the starting dates varied. This underrepresentation of certain years may have affected the accuracy of long-term trends in our analysis. Another limitation of our study is the potential conflation of productivity and tenure. Since we count cumulative publications, older researchers will naturally appear more productive due to their longer careers, regardless of the fairness of the publication process. While younger researchers may eventually surpass current elites, our focus remains on the dominance of established scholars and their disproportionate influence in the academic space. Moreover, our method for analyzing growing inequalities was based on full counting of each researcher's output, where we considered each publication equally without adjusting for co-authorship or collaborative works. This approach did not account for fractional counting, which could provide a more precise analysis of how much academic space is occupied by top researchers. Given that leading researchers often collaborate extensively, future studies should explore fractional counting to better understand the distribution of authorship and the extent of influence exerted by top researchers in the field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concluding remarks</head><p>In closing, efforts to promote DEI are futile unless the essence of the underrepresentation problem is well-understood. Instead of offering an oversimplified solutions that tackle statistical adjustments to underrepresentation, we aim to draw the attention to the ever-increasing dominance of the scholarly elite as a substantial barrier in the intellectual space. While the efforts for decolonization of business school education and curricula are also gaining momentum, it is essential to examine the ways how scientific communications evolve and how research is evaluated may require a fundamental transformation for such efforts being undertaken.</p><p>We acknowledge that this study might trigger a certain level of tension, especially among elite scholars and researchers holding key positions such as editorial roles. Nonetheless, we intend to underline the systemic problems, offer recommendations, and discuss the potential solutions to improve scientific practices. Systemic exclusion of certain groups of researchers not only makes access to science more restrictive but also hinders the future of scientific progress and societal development, which, in turn, further perpetuates inequalities in academia <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Tilghman et al., 2021)</ref>. We hope that some concrete actions to be taken by key stakeholders to reevaluate the existing scholarly mechanisms to rectify policies and procedures that act as barriers. With this paper, we also invite researchers from other fields to examine the degree of inequality in their constituencies to initiate fruitful debates with relevant bodies and respective institutions.</p><p>Table 1. List of Journals Analyzed Title Acronym ABS Rating (2021) Count of Articles Count of Reviews Total Docs Scopus Data from Average Output per Year Human Resource Management Journal HRMJ 4* 713 35 748 1990 * 24.93 British Journal of Industrial Relations BJIR 4 1,239 98 1,337 1963 ‡ 23.46 Human Resource Management HRM 4 1,643 82 1,725 1961 * 29.24 Industrial Relations: A Journal of Economy and Society IR 4 1,588 10 1,598 1961 * 27.08 Work, Employment and Society WES 4 1,182 236 1,418 1987 * 42.97 Economic and Industrial Democracy EID 3 967 315 1,282 1980 * 32.05 European Journal of Industrial Relations EJIR 3 422 67 489 1995 * 19.56 Human Resource Management Review HRMR 3 722 11 733 1991 * 25.28 Industrial and Labor Relations Review ILRR 3 664 144 808 1978 ‡ 19.24 Industrial Law Journal ILJ 3 1,009 28 1,037 1972 * 21.60 International Journal of Human Resource Management IJHRM 3 2,872 66 2,938 1990 * 97.93 New Technology, Work and Employment NTWE 3 495 11 506 1986 * 14.88 Work and Occupations W&amp;O 3 729 66 795 1974 * 17.28 HRM TOTAL (n = 13) 14,245 1,169 15,414</p><p>Table 3. Top-10 Most Productive Researchers in Each Field and Publication Counts Note: The total number of publications in all three fields is stated in parentheses.</p><p>Table 4. Frequency Distributions of Researchers' Publication Count Article Count 1-4 5-20 21-40 41-60 61-80 81-100 101-120 over 120 HRM 14,323 1,034 54 5 0 0 0 0 MNGT 16,927 1,793 98 10 1 0 0 0 IOP 22,115 2,235 243 34 14 5 2 1 IOP MNGT HRM Rank Top Publisher in the Field Publication Count in IOP Journals Top Publisher in the Field Publication Count in MNGT Journals Top Publisher in the Field Publication Count in HRM Journals 1 Researcher1 (156) 135 Researcher29 (70) 70 Researcher53 (57) 54 2 Researcher3 (130) 108 Researcher36 (63) 57 Researcher30 (68) 47 3 Researcher4 (112) 103 Researcher56 (56) 54 Researcher50 (57) 46 4 Researcher8 (94) 92 Researcher67 (52) 52 Researcher51 (57) 46 5 Researcher7 (95) 89 Researcher85 (49) 49 Researcher104 (46) 41 6 Researcher2 (138) 85 Researcher70 (52) 48 Researcher158 (39) 38 7 Researcher9 (90) 83 Researcher86 (49) 48 Researcher64 (53) 37 8 Researcher10 (87) 83 Researcher61 (54) 47 Researcher188 (37) 35 9 Researcher12 (84) 80 Researcher109 (45) 45 Researcher210 (35) 35 10 Researcher16 (79) 74 Researcher76 (51) 43 Researcher244 (33) 33 Mean (SD) 93.2 (17.95) 51.3 (7.78) 41.2 (6.80)</p><p>Table 5. Historical Trends of Publications Shares IOP HRM MNGT <ref type="bibr">2000-2019 1980-1999 1960-1979 2000-2019 1980-1999 1960-1979 2000-2019 1980-1999 1960-1979</ref> Top 1%</p><p>12.6% 9.8% 7.4% 11.2% 6.9% 3.4% 8.8% 7.6% 3.9% Top 5% 32.7% 27.4% 22.8% 27.8% 20.4% 11.0% 25.8% 23.0% 13.5% Top 10% 45.5% 39.2% 33.7% 39.3% 30.8% 20.2% 38.3% 35.1% 21.9% Top 20% 60.2% 52.9% 47.3% 53.3% 44.1% 29.4% 54.2% 50.0% 33.0% Total Records 36,071 13,336 3,734 23,085 5,234 327 27,092 8,932 643 # of Researchers 14,782 7,048 2,269 11,730 3,470 288 12,722 4,888 539 Avg Paper per Researcher 2.44 1.89 1.65 1.97 1.51 1.14 2.13 1.83 1.19 SD 4.10 2.46 1.64 2.86 1.34 0.44 2.57 1.93 0.58 1 Researcher320 13 Researcher1296 13 Researcher570 19 Researcher779 17 Researcher520 11 Researcher22 17 Researcher188 10 2 Researcher75 11 Researcher244 13 Researcher1401 13 Researcher244 13 Researcher461 11 Researcher218 16 Researcher554 8 3 Researcher434 10 Researcher467 13 Researcher47 12 Researcher502 12 Researcher443 10 Researcher128 9 Researcher311 8 4 Researcher284 10 Researcher289 12 Researcher104 12 Researcher210 11 Researcher272 10 Researcher3130 8 Researcher1102 7 5 Researcher30 10 Researcher833 12 Researcher6 10 Researcher1243 11 Researcher51 9 Researcher765 8 Researcher3260 6 6 Researcher864 9 Researcher335 11 Researcher112 10 Researcher585 10 Researcher1514 9 Researcher3343 7 Researcher662 6 7 Researcher175 9 Researcher262 10 Researcher2189 9 Researcher1873 10 Researcher141 9 Researcher2817 7 Researcher1852 5 8 Researcher282 9 Researcher1953 10 Researcher2682 9 Researcher610 10 Researcher2672 9 Researcher3630 7 Researcher1875 5 9 Researcher1026 8 Researcher51 10 Researcher468 8 Researcher322 10 Researcher281 8 Researcher3846 7 Researcher3855 5 10 Researcher281 7 Researcher188 10 Researcher146 8 Researcher1242 9 Researcher335 8 Researcher632 7 Researcher1747 5 1 Researcher2 18 Researcher585 11 Researcher158 36 Researcher53 32 Researcher443 9 Researcher309 12 2 Researcher6 12 Researcher665 9 Researcher740 18 Researcher50 27 Researcher496 6 Researcher599 11 3 Researcher84 11 Researcher210 7 Researcher850 17 Researcher147 23 Researcher1093 6 Researcher1216 11 4 Researcher351 9 Researcher750 7 Researcher972 17 Researcher104 21 Researcher50 6 Researcher529 9 5 Researcher179 8 Researcher244 6 Researcher967 17 Researcher145 20 Researcher2043 6 Researcher3234 7 6 Researcher74 8 Researcher952 6 Researcher947 17 Researcher369 19 Researcher4623 6 Researcher3376 6 7 Researcher634 7 Researcher962 6 Researcher1445 14 Researcher30 19 Researcher632 5 Researcher3194 6 8 Researcher768 7 Researcher578 6 Researcher1344 14 Researcher223 16 Researcher5532 5 Researcher4761 6 9 Researcher674 7 Researcher322 6 Researcher1485 13 Researcher588 15 Researcher4615 5 Researcher3817 6 10 Researcher210 6 Researcher276 6 Researcher1332 13 Researcher468 14 Researcher631 5 Researcher4756 6 11 Researcher147 6 3 journals 2 journals Researcher210 Researcher6 Researcher281 Researcher244 Researcher30 Researcher322 Researcher50 Researcher335 Researcher51 Researcher443 Researcher104 Researcher468 Researcher147 Researcher585 Researcher188 Researcher632 EJIR ILRR HRMR HRMJ BJIR ILJ HRM IR IJHRM NTWE WES W&amp;O EID Figure 6. The Most Productive of MNGT Journals 1 Researcher154 24 Researcher137 8 Researcher183 19 Researcher36 19 Researcher1245 12 Researcher94 17 Researcher61 20 2 Researcher59 19 Researcher319 8 Researcher1752 9 Researcher2 18 Researcher1141 11 Researcher86 16 Researcher114 14 3 Researcher183 16 Researcher125 8 Researcher125 8 Researcher49 17 Researcher997 10 Researcher5 15 Researcher545 14 4 Researcher82 16 Researcher178 7 Researcher424 7 Researcher41 15 Researcher1362 9 Researcher679 15 Researcher109 11 5 Researcher36 15 Researcher37 7 Researcher622 7 Researcher186 14 Researcher240 9 Researcher70 14 Researcher1204 11 6 Researcher240 14 Researcher1466 6 Researcher1791 7 Researcher321 14 Researcher875 9 Researcher29 13 Researcher56 11 7 Researcher726 13 Researcher1187 6 Researcher1047 6 Researcher287 11 Researcher919 9 Researcher1 11 Researcher297 11 8 Researcher23 13 Researcher445 6 Researcher3221 6 Researcher243 11 Researcher214 9 Researcher1942 11 Researcher214 10 9 Researcher162 13 Researcher3610 6 Researcher240 6 Researcher315 10 Researcher459 9 Researcher80 11 Researcher70 10 10 Researcher287 11 Researcher48 6 Researcher859 5 Researcher47 10 Researcher1040 9 Researcher43 11 Researcher695 9 1 Researcher29 26 Researcher2347 10 Researcher706 9 Researcher670 17 Researcher2936 5 Researcher30 6 Researcher29 12 2 Researcher476 17 Researcher61 8 Researcher1046 8 Researcher1531 13 Researcher1507 4 Researcher2382 6 Researcher1036 11 3 Researcher540 17 Researcher2569 7 Researcher886 8 Researcher1567 13 Researcher4865 3 Researcher6042 4 Researcher176 9 4 Researcher86 17 Researcher4164 6 Researcher333 8 Researcher1430 13 Researcher1328 3 Researcher2468 4 Researcher807 8 5 Researcher85 16 Researcher948 6 Researcher1149 8 Researcher67 11 Researcher1596 3 Researcher3177 4 Researcher117 7 6 Researcher196 16 Researcher537 6 Researcher368 7 Researcher2143 9 Researcher214 3 Researcher324 4 Researcher185 7 7 Researcher340 14 Researcher1587 6 Researcher61 7 Researcher618 9 Researcher377 3 Researcher4008 6 8 Researcher448 14 Researcher4017 5 Researcher415 7 Researcher1749 9 Researcher8810 3 Researcher350 6 9 Researcher378 14 Researcher109 4 Researcher1092 7 Researcher502 8 Researcher64 3 Researcher458 6 10 Researcher56 13 Researcher683 4 Researcher215 7 Researcher2689 8 Researcher1092 3 Researcher2691 6 *Only more than 3 publications were taken into account Researcher377 12 Researcher56 11 3 journals 2 journals Researcher454 10 Researcher499 9 Researcher29 Researcher36 Researcher183 Researcher771 9 Researcher56 Researcher70 Researcher287 Researcher1081 9 Researcher61 Researcher86 Researcher377 Researcher273 8 Researcher214 Researcher109 Researcher378 Researcher378 8 Researcher240 Researcher125 Researcher1092 Researcher1109 8 Researcher330 8 JMS JMI Org AMJ OrgStud AMR AMP BJM ASQ JOM CMR EMR* HumRel IJMR OrgSci Figure 7. The Most Productive of IOP Journals 1 Researcher8 55 Researcher26 27 Researcher1 18 Researcher1 23 Researcher117 23 Researcher143 40 Researcher16 54 2 Researcher3 53 Researcher8 26 Researcher10 13 Researcher98 18 Researcher27 21 Researcher201 36 Researcher34 40 3 Researcher12 47 Researcher12 25 Researcher124 11 Researcher216 14 Researcher19 20 Researcher18 32 Researcher24 25 4 Researcher9 36 Researcher9 21 Researcher89 11 Researcher375 13 Researcher4 20 Researcher58 32 Researcher102 20 5 Researcher13 35 Researcher96 18 Researcher307 11 Researcher10 13 Researcher57 14 Researcher1 28 Researcher38 19 6 Researcher55 34 Researcher11 18 Researcher816 11 Researcher21 13 Researcher87 13 Researcher384 28 Researcher239 19 7 Researcher14 34 Researcher648 16 Researcher13 11 Researcher197 12 Researcher66 12 Researcher412 27 Researcher212 17 8 Researcher81 33 Researcher55 16 Researcher672 11 Researcher7 11 Researcher10 12 Researcher93 24 Researcher208 17 9 Researcher83 31 Researcher20 15 Researcher498 10 Researcher19 10 Researcher1 11 Researcher411 24 Researcher825 16 10 Researcher23 28 Researcher680 15 Researcher4 10 Researcher4 10 Researcher6 11 Researcher521 24 Researcher568 15 1 Researcher151 26 Researcher1160 15 Researcher1 21 Researcher221 34 Researcher9 10 Researcher5 19 Researcher249 24 2 Researcher122 24 Researcher11 12 Researcher21 16 Researcher497 24 Researcher489 10 Researcher494 17 Researcher7 22 3 Researcher291 20 Researcher4 11 Researcher22 15 Researcher637 21 Researcher8 9 Researcher1 14 Researcher245 20 4 Researcher199 20 Researcher52 10 Researcher10 12 Researcher700 15 Researcher161 9 Researcher94 13 Researcher119 19 5 Researcher794 19 Researcher7 9 Researcher7 9 Researcher258 11 Researcher4 8 Researcher1835 11 Researcher45 17 6 Researcher449 19 Researcher5 9 Researcher383 9 Researcher2111 10 Researcher310 8 Researcher351 9 Researcher22 16 7 Researcher723 17 Researcher2560 9 Researcher90 9 Researcher43 10 Researcher232 8 Researcher2472 8 Researcher4 15 8 Researcher417 16 Researcher3291 8 Researcher219 9 Researcher2 10 Researcher507 7 Researcher1481 8 Researcher5 13 9 Researcher414 16 Researcher2131 7 Researcher250 9 Researcher1391 9 Researcher482 7 Researcher1573 8 Researcher485 12 10 Researcher550 15 Researcher2510 7 Researcher45 8 Researcher1285 9 Researcher531 7 Researcher360 8 Researcher219 10 6 journals 5 Journals 4 Journals 3 journals 2 journals Researcher1 Researcher7 Researcher5 Researcher11 Researcher22 Researcher4 Researcher10 Researcher8 Researcher12 Researcher45 Researcher9 Researcher13 Researcher55 Researcher19 Researcher219 Researcher21 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix. Journal List with Missing Years in Scopus Coverage</head><p>Summary of the Scopus coverage for the journals you mentioned, highlighting the missing years:</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>-Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4 about here</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figures</head><figDesc>Figures 5,<ref type="bibr" target="#b79">6,</ref> 7 about here    </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>Figure 8 about here</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>Figure 9 about here</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc>Figure 10 about here</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc>Figure 11 about here</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 2 .Figure 5 .</head><label>25</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Violin Plot -Comparisons of Average Publication Count of the Top-10 Most</figDesc><graphic coords="47,150.63,139.20,310.35,206.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><figDesc>Figure 9. Historical Trends of Gini Coefficients</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="48,315.00,123.00,226.75,482.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="48,72.00,99.75,226.70,504.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="54,213.75,99.60,375.58,226.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="55,143.32,127.20,516.43,127.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://www.apa.org/pubs/authors/equity-diversity-inclusion</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>https://osf.io/rpbvt/?view_only=017c7afd486d49ce856d455579236517</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Zivony, A. (2019). Academia is not a meritocracy. Nature HumanBehaviour, 3(10), 1037.   </p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The collaboration behavior of top scientists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Abramo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>D'angelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Di Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://aom.org/about-aom/aom-news/blog-detail_news/releases/2021/07/28/aomlaunches-82nd-annual-meeting" />
		<title level="m">AOM announces 82nd annual meeting</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academy of Management</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021-07-28">2021, Jul 28</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An A is an A&quot;: The new bottom line for valuing academic research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Aguinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cummings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ramani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cummings</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.psychologicalscience.org/diversity-equity-inclusion" />
		<title level="m">APS commitment to diversity, equity, &amp; inclusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Psychological Science</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geographic diversity in economic publishing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Angus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Atalay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Newton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ubilava</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">190</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Leadership Quarterly: State of the journal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Antonakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bastardoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Day</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Eagly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">…</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Leadership Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differences in female representation in leading management and organization journals: Establishing a benchmark</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Auschra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bartosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lohmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104410</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How much is research in the top journals of industrial/organizational psychology dominated by authors from the U</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">U H</forename><surname>Bajwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>König</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">S.? Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1147" to="1161" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Should eminent academics stop publishing? ResearchGate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.13140/RG.2.2.33412.55689</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.33412.55689" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neoliberal ideology in work and organizational psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dóci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Work and Organizational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="536" to="548" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manifestation of academic rackets in management research through early career sessions at academic conferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Van Rossenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Orhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/13505076241234153</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/13505076241234153" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The quantitative discovery: What is it and how to get it published</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bamberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Discoveries</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Seeber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The slow professor: Challenging the culture of speed in the academy</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Toronto Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are academics who publish more also more cited? Individual determinants of publication and citation records</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bosquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-P</forename><surname>Combes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="831" to="857" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the causal effect of fame on citations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brogaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Engelberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Eswar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Van Wesep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.3565487</idno>
		<idno>SSRN 3565487</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3565487" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Networks and productivity: Causal evidence from editor rotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brogaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Engelberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Parsons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abuse and exploitation of doctoral students: A conceptual model for traversing a long and winding road to academia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Baruch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Ethics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="522" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social ties in academia: A friend is a treasure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Colussi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving equity, diversity, and inclusion in academia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Dewidar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Elmestekawy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Welch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Integrity and Peer Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideology in work and organizational psychology: the responsibility of the researcher</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dóci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Work and Organizational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="558" to="560" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reflections on the Journal of Applied Psychology in times of change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Eby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Academic research in the 21st century: Maintaining scientific integrity in a climate of perverse incentives and hypercompetition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environmental Engineering Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Editorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fleishman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast lane to slow science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Frith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends in Cognitive Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Society for Industrial and Organizational Psychology&apos;s guidelines for education and training: An executive summary of the 2016/2017 revision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Payne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Psychologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="678" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ending honorary authorship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Greenland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Fontanarosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">337</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6098</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1019" to="1019" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The one best way?&apos;Scientific&apos;research on HRM and the threat to critical scholarship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Harley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Resource Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confronting the crisis of confidence in management studies: Why senior scholars need to stop setting a bad example</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Harley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Learning &amp; Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What&apos;s the difference? Diversity constructs as separation, variety, or disparity in organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1199" to="1228" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authorship inequality: a bibliometric study of the concentration of authorship among a diminishing number of individuals in high-impact medical journals, 2008-2019</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Perlis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46002</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Academic networks and career trajectory: &apos;There&apos;s no career in academia without networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Heffernan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Higher Education Research &amp; Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="981" to="994" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prestige and relevance of the scholarly journals: Impressions of SIOP members</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Highhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zickar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Melick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial and Organizational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extent and causes of academic text recycling or &apos;self-plagiarism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P J M S</forename><surname>Horbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Halffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="492" to="502" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nobel and novice: Author prominence affects peer review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Inoua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kerschbamer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>König-Kersting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vernon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2205779119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research accomplishments that are too good to be true</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P A</forename><surname>Ioannidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intensive Care Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thousands of scientists publish a paper every five days</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P A</forename><surname>Ioannidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Klavans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Boyack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">561</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7722</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common academic experiences no one talks about: Repeated rejection, impostor syndrome, and burnout</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jaremka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ackerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gawronski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Rule</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sweeny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tropp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">…</forename><surname>Vick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspectives on Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="543" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accuracy evaluation of Scopus Author ID based on the largest funding database in Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kawashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tomizawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1061" to="1071" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Questionable research practices among researchers in the most research-productive management programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kepes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Keener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcdaniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hartman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Organizational Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1190" to="1208" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex discrimination in UK academia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Knights</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gender, Work &amp; Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early-career factors largely determine the future impact of prominent researchers: Evidence across eight scientific fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Danús</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sales-Pardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18794</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The White Bull effect: Abusive coauthorship and publication parasitism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kwok</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Medical Ethics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="554" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How many is too many? On the relationship between research productivity and impact</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Larivière</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Costas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">162709</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prominent but less productive: The impact of interdisciplinarity on scientists&apos; research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Leahey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Beckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stanko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administrative Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What universities say versus do about diversity, equity and inclusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">610</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global diversity of authors, editors, and journal ownership across subdisciplines of psychology: Current state and policy implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspectives on Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="377" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The internationality of published higher education scholarship: How do the &apos;top&apos; journals compare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Merga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>González Canché</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mat Roni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Informetrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101155</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Matthew effect in science: The reward and communication systems of science are considered</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Merton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3810</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Merton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The sociology of science: Theoretical and empirical investigations</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The University of Chicago Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neo-colonialism in the academy? Anglo-American domination in management journals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="915" to="927" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global citation inequality is on the rise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2012208118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender diversity in the management field: Does it matter for research outcomes?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Börjeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1617" to="1632" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why we publish where we do: Faculty publishing values and their relationship to review, promotion and tenure expectations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Niles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schimanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mckiernan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Alperin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">228914</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The best and the rest: Revisiting the norm of normality of individual performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>O'boyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Aguinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personnel Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pardon my French: On superfluous journal rankings, incentives, and impacts on industrial-organizational psychology publication practices in French business schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Orhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial and Organizational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic interactionism between research fraud and research culture: a commentary to Harvey&apos;s analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Orhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quality in Higher Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rise of the most excellent scholar, demise of the field: a fictional story, yet probable destiny</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Orhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Van Rossenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14759551.2024.2383891</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14759551.2024.2383891" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Culture and Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Advance online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Papers and patents are becoming less disruptive over time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Leahey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Funk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">613</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023. 7942</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How innovative are editors?: Evidence across journals and disciplines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Evaluation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Going beyond Western, Educated, Industrialized, Rich, and Democratic (WEIRD) samples and problems in organizational research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pitesa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gelfand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104212</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a psychology of Homo sapiens: Making psychological science more representative of the human population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Martingano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ginges</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11401" to="11405" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial inequality in psychological research: Trends of the past and recommendations for the future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bareket-Shavit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dollins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Goldie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mortenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspectives on Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1295" to="1309" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational psychology and the tipping point of professional identity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial and Organizational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of biomedical journals to detect editorial bias and nepotistic behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Scanff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Naudet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cristea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V M</forename><surname>Bishop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Locher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3001133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.siop.org/Portals/84/docs/SIOP_ET_Guidelines_2017.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Guidelines for education and training in industrial-organizational psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Society for Industrial and Organizational Psychology</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The discourse of meritocracy contested/reproduced: Foreign women academics in UK business schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Śliwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="843" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How bullying becomes a career tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Täuber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mahmoudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41562-022-01311-z</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-022-01311-z" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concrete steps to diversify the scientific workforce</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tilghman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Alberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Colón-Ramos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dzirasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kimble</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Varmus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6538</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The triumph of nonsense in management studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tourish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Learning &amp; Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inferring the causal effect of journals on citations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Traag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quantitative Science Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="496" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How the publish-or-perish principle divides a science: the case of economists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Van Dalen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1675" to="1694" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social and personality psychology PhDs on the academic job market: characteristics and outcomes: A technical report by the SPSP student committee</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vuletich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Guevara Beltran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tissera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://spsp.org/sites/default/files/Social_and_Personality_Psychology_PhDs_on_the_Academic_Job_Market_Characteristics_And_Outcomes_Technical_Report.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale analysis of the accuracy of the journal classification systems of Web of Science and Scopus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Waltman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Missing years: 1964</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Informetrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1967" to="1968" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">2016. 1963. 1965. 1970-2024. 1966. 1969</date>
			<publisher>British Journal of Industrial Relations</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Coverage includes</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978. 1984. 1996-2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1981" to="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Missing years</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979-1980. 1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1985" to="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Academy of Management Journal: Coverage includes 1975-1987</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1989-2024. 1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Missing years</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<monogr>
		<idno>Missing years: 1988</idno>
		<title level="m">Academy of Management Review: Coverage includes 1978-1987</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989-1991. 1996-2024. 1992-1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Coverage includes</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975-1987. 1989-1990. 1993-1994. 1996-2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Missing years</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988. 1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1991" to="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Journal of Management Reviews: Coverage includes 1999-2002</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2004-2024. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Missing years</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Journal of Organizational Behavior: Coverage includes 1981-1982</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1984-2024. 1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Missing years</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
