<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Iconicity in Haitian Creole: A Study on Onomatopoeic Aspect of Bird Names</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Patrice</forename><surname>Kanndèl</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Iconicity in Haitian Creole</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="HT">Haiti</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Rue D. Bolte</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Lilavois 48</addrLine>
									<postCode>HT6311</postCode>
									<settlement>Port-au-Prince</settlement>
									<country key="HT">Haïti</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Iconicity in Haitian Creole: A Study on Onomatopoeic Aspect of Bird Names</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">59810EA6CB61A552BDB47623EE0AC45E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:18+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Haitian Creole</term>
					<term>Iconicity</term>
					<term>Onomatopoeia</term>
					<term>Sound-Symbolic Associations</term>
					<term>Language Evolution</term>
					<term>Lexical Creation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study explores the onomatopoeic aspect of bird names in Haitian Creole, highlighting the significant role of sound-symbolic associations in the evolution and lexical creation within creole languages. It examines a corpus of nineteen Haitian creole ornithonyms formed by onomatopoeia imitating the bird vocalization. The research reveals a high degree of iconicity in Haitian Creole bird names, highlighting the language's capacity to generate ornithonyms through specific sound symbolism relation, morphological flexibility, and reduplication. The study also uncovers the distinctive historical and socio-linguistic background of creole languages that raises an environment conducive to generating a new lexicon deeply rooted in sound symbolism. The findings of this study contribute to our understanding of the relationship between sound and meaning in creole language, enriching our appreciation of the diversity and expressiveness of human languages evolution.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Form and meaning are tightly related, shaping the very essence of linguistic evolution. This relation is often characterized by iconicity -the connection between signs and their referents based on similarities or resemblances <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Peirce 1955)</ref>. Iconicity plays a crucial role in forming ideophones, an open lexical class of marked words that vividly depict sensory imagery representations related to sounds, motions, shapes, colors, and even inner states <ref type="bibr">(Dingemanse 2019</ref><ref type="bibr">(Dingemanse , 2023))</ref>.</p><p>The significance of iconicity varies across different languages, with sound ideophone i.e., onomatopoeia serving as a well-studied manifestation of iconic sound symbolism. Numerous languages utilize onomatopoeia to build portions of their vocabulary, especially in creating bird names <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Cabrera &amp; Carlos 2020)</ref>. For instance, common English examples include Cuckoo (Cuculus canorus), Crow (Corvus cornix), Eagle-Owl (Bubo bubo), and Hoopoe (Upupa epops); comparable onomatopoeic labels are found in several unrelated languages for equivalent bird species ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Marttila 2010)</ref> cited by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Cabrera &amp; Carlos 2020)</ref>), suggesting shared acoustic communication patterns.</p><p>In recent linguistic discussions, iconicity has gained prominence; however, limited empirical studies address its effects on the Haitian Creole (HC) lexicon, particularly about avian appellations. While prior research acknowledges the existence of specific onomatopoeic bird terms in HC e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Edouard 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Govain 2019)</ref>, comprehensive analyses are scarce. Therefore, studying HC's naming practices for birds offers promising prospects for exploring iconicity in action.</p><p>This paper aims to fill this knowledge gap by highlighting underappreciated links between form and meaning within HC's lexicon using cross-linguistic comparisons of onomatopoeic bird names. Consequently, our work advances broader conversations regarding the implications of iconicity on semantic structures, thereby furnishing valuable contributions to disciplines like cognitive science.</p><p>The paper is structured as follows: We begin with a literature review discussing past and present debates around iconicity in bird names, followed by an outline of Haitian Creole, including its ties to ideophones and onomatopoeia. Following sections describe research methods, and data gathering procedures used throughout the investigation. After this, we present significant findings, comparing onomatopoeic bird names from HC against selected equivalents drawn from a sample of 82 Haitian birds. Lastly, we summarize crucial insights, propose potential directions for future exploration.</p><p>By investigating into iconicity and its manifestation in the Haitian Creole lexicon, we hope to shed light on the connections between form and meaning, and how these connections shape our understanding of language and cognition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Litterature review</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1.">Iconicity in the lexicon</head><p>Iconicity, a concept that refers to the relationship between a sign's form and its meaning, is a fascinating aspect of language study. This relationship is characterized by a resemblance between the signifier and the denoted object or concept <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Dingemanse et al. 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Perniss et al. 2010</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Perniss et al. , 2020))</ref>. Iconicity can manifest in several ways, including imagic, diagrammatic, and associative iconicity <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Johansson 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Imagic iconicity refers to the directly perceived similarity between the form and meaning of a sign. An example of this is the crowing of a rooster, which is represented quite similarly in various languages, such as English "cock-a-doodle-doo", Japanese "kokekoko", Hebrew "kukuRiku", Kisi "kukuluukuu" and Haitian creole "koukouyikou".</p><p>Diagrammatic iconicity, on the other hand, resides in the relationship between signs and the relationship between their referents. A classic example of this is the temporal sequence of events depicted in Julius Caesar's famous quote, "veni, vidi, vici" ('I came, I saw, I conquered').</p><p>Another instance is repetition or reduplication very common in Caribbean creoles as in the word kouri for 'run' 'kouri kouri' for 'run more' or 'kouri kouri kouri ' for 'run even more' in Haitian Creole.</p><p>Associative iconicity creates bonds between sets of signs based on shared attributes, leading to semantic kinship amongst words. For instance, the words glitter, glisten, gleam, glare, glimmer, and glow share the onset /gl-/ and meanings related to 'light' and 'vision', including glamor, glitz, and glory and their figurative sense of 'shining'.</p><p>Historically, linguistic theories generally presumed that spoken language vocabularies were fundamentally arbitrary <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Saussure et al. 2005</ref><ref type="bibr">(Saussure et al. [1916]]</ref>). However, recent research supports the claim that iconicity exists extensively in spoken languages, challenging the prevailing opinion of scarce onomatopoeic words in any given language as showed by relatively cross- Moreover, onomatopoeia, a subset of phonological iconicity, seems to constitute a distinct lexical class universal across languages <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Körtvélyessy &amp; Štekauer 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Meinard 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Instances of onomatopoeia are abundant in the description of bird names as body of research has documented the presence of onomatopoeic bird names across various languages and geographies <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abondolo 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Berlin 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Berlin &amp; O'Neill 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ibarra et al. 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Wicaksono et al. 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Yuzieva 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Over a third of the terms in Aguaruna and Huambisa ornithological vocabulary originate from onomatopoeia <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Berlin &amp; O'Neill 1981)</ref>. Comparable figures appear in Tzeltal Maya (49%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Berlin &amp; O'Neill 1981)</ref>. Mapudungun bird names research by <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ibarra et al. (2020)</ref> unearthed 135 etymologies attributed to 72 avian species, half of which featured onomatopoeic origins. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ibarra et al. (2020)</ref>, in a great summary, also reveal that the onomatopoeic origin of bird names was studied among 13 different peoples living in various forested landscapes across the world.</p><p>In total, 2,585 bird names were recorded, out of which 849 had onomatopoeic origins, making up around 33% of all bird names. The highest percentage of onomatopoeic bird names was found among the Mbuti people of the tropical forests in Congo, with 67%, while the lowest was observed among the villagers from Três Ladeiras in the Atlantic Forest of Brazil, at only 15%.</p><p>Other notable percentages include the Delaware people of monsoon forests in Canada with 37%, the Mapuche people of temperate forests in Chile with 47%, and several groups from Papua New Guinea such as the Selepet with 37%, Kaluli with 39%, and Nage with 32%. These findings suggest that onomatopoeia plays a significant role in naming birds for many indigenous cultures worldwide, possibly due to their close relationship with nature and acoustic communication between animals.</p><p>Cross-linguistic and regional parallels surface in bird names. Take, for instance, the word 'crow' for most corvus species in english. It carries uncanny similarities in its composition across various languages, including Albanian korb, Western Armenian akrav, German Krähe, Japanese karasu, and Turkish karga ((Marttila 2010) cited by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Cabrera &amp; Carlos 2020</ref>).</p><p>Marttila's (2010) comprehensive examination of corvid nomenclatures reveals that most languages incorporate an imitation of the typical "kaa/kraa/kar" call in raven and crow labels <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Marttila 2010)</ref>. Similar trends apply to the distinct call of the cuckoo, producing equivalent expressions in diverse languages, such as Ainu kakkok, Basque kuku, Itelmen qekuk, and Kannada kukil. Patterns like these strengthen arguments favoring onomatopoeic forces in bird name creation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Onomatopoeic ornithonym process</head><p>Research suggests that certain aspects of bird vocalizations, such as pitch or amplitude, can predict a bird's size <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Brumm 2009)</ref>. Additionally, previous studies have shown that onomatopoeic words used to describe bird vocalizations can predict the size of birds, with specific phonemes related to specific sizes ('Bodo <ref type="bibr">Winter -YouTube' n.d.;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Winter &amp; Perlman 2021)</ref>. Therefore, it stands to reason that onomatopoeic bird names might also reflect the size of the bird species they represent. This is supported by the fact that bird names have historically served functional purposes, including enhancing communication about animal locations and behaviors during subsistence hunting <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Yuzieva 2012</ref>). These initial names would have evolved over time, maintaining essential acoustic qualities that preserve elements of bird vocalizations <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Ibarra et al. 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Wicaksono et al. 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Yuzieva 2012)</ref>. Given this evidence, it seems plausible that onomatopoeic bird names could offer clues about bird size, making them an interesting area for future investigation.</p><p>Formulating onomatopoeic words involves a series of elaborate transformations, consisting of: 1) sound perception, 2) grasping a bird's image and its accompanying vocals, and</p><p>3) encoding and reconstructing the bird's singular image and voice in memory. Presumably, as noted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kurashkina (2012)</ref> this process took root during the establishment of human language, when hominids possessed well-developed vocal tracts suited for natural sound duplications and heightened auditory sensitivity to capture the salient components of bird voices.</p><p>Overall, every stage involved in the generation of imitations depends on human practical activities, ranging from the earliest reproductive attempts of bird voices to the eventual adaptation of onomatopoeic ornithonyms compliant with specific language guidelines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3.">Other ornithonym process</head><p>Although there is an evident onomatopoeic ornithonym process in a lot of languages, let us not forget that there are other processes such as colors, sizes, shape, habitat, behavior, and philosophy that participate in the naming process as shown by authors e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Wicaksono et al. 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Yuzieva 2012)</ref>. We can classify these processes into three main categories: Visual attributes, Ecological variables, and Behavioural patterns and instincts.</p><p>Visual Attributes: This process involves naming birds based on their physical characteristics such as color, size, and shape. For instance, the Red-winged Blackbird (Agelaius phoeniceus) is named for the patches of red on the wings of the male bird. Similarly, the Longtailed Tit (Aegithalos caudatus) is named for its distinctive long tail, and the Snowy Owl (Bubo scandiacus) is named for its white plumage that resembles snow. In French Rouge-gorge familier 'European Robin' (Erithacus rubecula) is named after its distinctive reddish-orange breast, which is visible when it perches. In Spanish, it is called petirrojo europeo also an homage to its color.</p><p>Ecological Variables: In this process, naming birds are based on their habitat or geographical distribution. For example, Bruant des neiges 'Snow Bunting' (Plectrophenax nivalis) inhabits arctic tundra during breeding season and winters in open fields and meadows.</p><p>Its Spanish name is escribano nival. In those three languages the name reflects its preference for snowy environments. The 'Mountain Bluebird' (Sialia currucoides) is often found in mountainous regions, while the 'Arctic Tern' (Sterna paradisaea) is known for its migration from the Arctic to the Antarctic and back.</p><p>Behavioral Patterns and Instincts: This process involves naming birds based on their behavior or instincts. For instance, the 'Laughing Kookaburra' (Dacelo novaeguineae) is named for its distinctive call that sounds like human laughter. The 'Fishing Eagle' (Pandion haliaetus) is named for its diet and hunting behavior, as it primarily feeds on fish and has a unique method of diving into water to catch its prey.</p><p>To sum up, the study of ornithonym processes, from the genesis of onomatopoeic names to the influence of visual, ecological, and behavioral factors, offers a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between form and meaning in language. This understanding enriches our appreciation of the diversity and expressiveness of human languages. By examining bird names through this framework, we gain valuable insights into how humans categorize and conceptualize the natural world around them. These findings have broader implications for cognitive science, anthropology, and linguistics, shedding light on the evolutionary origins of language and cognition, as well as the social and cultural forces that shape communication systems over time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4.">Onomatopoeia in Haitian Creole lexicon</head><p>Although recognized in various creoles, including Haitian Creole, extensive scholarly examinations focusing on onomatopoeia in these languages are limited. Haitian Creole, also known as Kreyòl Ayisyen, possesses unique characteristics derived from its French lexifier along with distinct African and indigenous American influences <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Lefebvre 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Sylvain 1936)</ref>. With more than 11 million native speakers ('Ethnologue | Languages of the world' n.d.) in some more 4 million in foreign countries, Haitian Creole occupies a crucial position in creole languages do to its official statues and its number or locutors.</p><p>Previous works have acknowledged the presence of onomatopoeia in creoles, albeit sparsely explored e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bartens 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Edouard 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Prou 1999)</ref>. Consequently, there remains a need to investigate deeper into how onomatopoeia materializes and functions within the complex linguistic milieu of Haitian Creole.</p><p>The Haitian Creole possesses a rich repository of onomatopoeic expressions, capturing various natural, artificial sound sources. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Edouard's (2024)</ref> study on ideophones in Haitian Creole (HC) unveils several noteworthy findings across linguistic dimensions that can specifically be applied to sound ideophones i.e. onomatopoeia.</p><p>Starting with phonology, HC's phonological inventory reflects a blend of influences from French, African languages, and more. The language as a distinctive syllabic structure and a set of thirty-three phonemes, comprising vowels, consonants, and glides. Notably, ideophones in HC demonstrate typical sound patterns, often comprising one or two syllables, with indefinite vowel lengthening and occasional consonant-only patterns, although these are infrequent.</p><p>Moving to morphology, HC's word-formation processes, including compounding, reduplication, and affixation, are well-documented. However, onomatopoeias in HC primarily use replication as their morphological strategy, lacking derivational bound morphemes. Six onomatopoeic ideophones are exceptions, forming verbs through the addition of the suffix "-e" to nouns derived from onomatopoeias.</p><p>Syntax analysis reveals the versatility of onomatopoeias in HC sentences, functioning as predicates, complements, modifiers, subjects, and objects. They exhibit a Subject-Verb-Object Semantically, onomatopoeias in HC depict various sound categories, with human-related sounds being the most abundant. Furthermore, synonymous expressions of onomatopoeias across different dialects suggest dynamic socio-linguistic interactions and regional variations.</p><p>Listed below are several examples organized by sound source and accompanied by corresponding sound types and events. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Method and materials</head><p>This study primarily relies on data collected from two authoritative sources: <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fattier 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Séverin 2007)</ref>. Both texts provide valuable information on haitian bird names, descriptions, scientific classifications, and their equivalents in various languages. We utilize the list of 82 To understand the link between onomatopoeia and bird names, we consulted the online bird call database Xeno-canto('xeno-canto :: Sharing wildlife sounds from around the world' n.d.). Xeno-canto, dedicated to sharing wildlife sounds globally, facilitated cross-referencing recorded bird vocalizations with the bird names presented in Severin's and Fattier's works. This enabled us to identify possible correlations between the two datasets.</p><p>Our analytical process involved a comparison of bird vocalizations with their respective vernacular names to detect any apparent resemblances or discrepancies. In our list, we classified the origin of the names based on features such as size, color, shape, habitat, diet, and onomatopoeia. We first classified the birds by the main ornithonym processes. Then, we analyzed the remaining names and compared them to the descriptions provided in Fattier's and Severin's works. Onomatopoeic names typically exhibit reduplication <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Dingemanse 2015)</ref>, so we paid special attention to reduplicated forms. As a native Creole speaker, we were able to place particular emphasis on identifying shared phonemes and syllables that could potentially indicate onomatopoeic influences in the formation of bird names. Additionally, we explored historical developments and regional variations in naming practices to better comprehend the factors shaping these linguistic associations.</p><p>Further analyses involved scrutinizing the phoneme relations between bird calls and their corresponding names, seeking to determine whether specific sound patterns consistently emerged across different taxonomic groups or geographic areas. This examination aimed to illuminate the potential mechanisms driving the transition from bird calls to their names in Haitian Creole, thus contributing to our understanding of sound symbolism and its role in linguistic evolution.</p><p>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Analysis</head><p>Our study led us to a list of nineteen onomatopoeic names, representing a 24% of the corpus. As seen in the table below, these names provide a fascinating insight into the relationship between bird vocalizations and their corresponding names in Haitian Creole. Coccyzus, is a genus of cuckoos' native to the Americas. It encompasses various species.</p><p>These birds exhibit diverse sizes, characterized by slender bodies, long tails, and sturdy legs, often featuring black and white undertail patterns. They inhabit a range of environments, from forests and woodlands to mangroves.</p><p>In Haiti, we identify four species of Coccyzus:</p><p>• Tako fran (Coccyzus longirostris) -'Hispaniolan Lizard Cuckoo'</p><p>• Tako kabrit (Coccyzus rufigularis) -'Bay-breasted Cuckoo'</p><p>• Ti tako (Coccyzus minor) -'Mangrove Cuckoo'</p><p>• Ti tako vant blan (Coccyzus americanus) -'Yellow-billed Cuckoo'</p><p>These birds are known for their vocalizations, emitting persistent and loud calls. Although the calls vary among species, they are generally characterized as repeated cooing. Their calls consist of distinctive series, often described as hollow, wooden-sounding, with harsh and rattling elements, such as "ka-ka" "kow kow," "kwakk kowlp," and "kk-ow" syllables. Another common call is a metallic, rattling sound, often described as "kow-kow-kow," which starts slowly, accelerates, and then decelerates. Those vocalizations are the ones that give him is famous name, onomatopoeic cross linguistically.</p><p>The local name for these birds in Haiti is tako also onomatopoeic although not similar to ethe appellation to the coccycus. The name stems from the characteristic "Tk-rrrr" sound present at the beginning of the call of the one of the endemic Coccyzus species in Haiti, the 'Hispaniolan Lizard Cuckoo' (Coccyzus longirostris). As observe in figure 1 its primary call features a rattling, grating sound that decreases in pitch in the yellow rectangle, accompanied by a harsh "tchk" clicks, and a "cwuh-h-h" observed in the green rectangle <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Payne 2020)</ref>. The 'Bay-breasted Cuckoo' (Coccyzus rufigularis), also known locally as Tako kabrit as kabrit translates to 'goat' inspired by the bird's distinctive vocalizations. Specifically, after the initial rattle, the Bay-breasted Cuckoo produces a peculiar bleating sound that closely resembles a goat's call, hence earning its name.</p><p>Alternative names include "tòkò" in Haiti and "coulicou" in the French Antilles <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fattier 1998)</ref>, cuco in Cuba, or tacó in the Dominican Republic, among others, all of which are onomatopoeic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Koukou (Athene cunicularia),</head><p>In Haitian Creole, the name koukou refers to the 'burrowing owl' (Athene cunicularia).</p><p>This small, long-legged owl is widespread across open landscapes throughout North and South America. Burrowing owls inhabit various environments, including grasslands, rangelands, agricultural areas, deserts, and other open, dry regions with sparse vegetation.</p><p>The name koukou pronounced similarly to cuckoo is onomatopoeic. Burrowing owls can produce a range of sounds such as cooing, warbling, rasping, clucking, screaming, and rattling.</p><p>The most heard vocalization is a two-note cooing reminiscent of a quail, often made by males during mating and territorial defense. Between the different vocalizations made by the (Athene cunicularia), It is the two-note cooing sound that likely inspired its name.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kaw (Corvus genus),</head><p>Corvus species are widely recognized for their onomatopoeic names cross linguistically.</p><p>Among the Caribbean corvids, the Kaw fran, or 'White-necked Crow' (Corvus leucognaphalus), stands as the largest. Endemic to the island of Hispaniola, what sets the whitenecked crow apart from other corvid counterparts is its exceptional and idiosyncratic voice.</p><p>Rather than the typical hoarse croaking associated with crows, the white-necked crow boasts a diverse array of melodious sounds likened to parrot chatter-characterized by sequences of fluid bubbling, sharp squawks, interspersed gentle and rough notes. The source of its onomatopoeic appellation, kaw lies within the unique gliding sound "/w/" featured prominently towards the end of the liquid bubbling noise, enabling distinction from the 'Palm Crow' (Corvus palmarum) as shown in figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>. parlance, the term Gragra is often associated with the bird's flat, harsh guttural "graaah" vocalization see figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>, a stark departure from the varied calls of the White-necked Crow.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kwak (Ardea alba)</head><p>In Haitian Creole, the great egret (Ardea alba) answers to the onomatopoeic name Kwak as well as the common name krabye. Residing primarily in warm temperate and tropical regions worldwide, the great egret constructs tree nests near water in colonies.</p><p>The great egret isn't a vocal bird, giving off a low, gruff croak when disturbed. During the breeding season, colony residents increase their volume, letting loose loud croaking "cuk cuk cuk" sounds and raising the pitch for shriller squawks. This distinctive set of calls gave rise to the bird's secondary name, Kwak in Haitian Creole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pètpèt (Himantopus mexicanus),</head><p>The 'Black-necked Stilt' (Himantopus mexicanus), locally abundant in Haiti, is a shorebird inhabiting American wetlands and coastlines. Black-necked Stilts express sharp, high-pitched calls consisting of "yap" "keek" or similar variations. Under normal circumstances, these calls occur individually, but when alarmed, they become doubled and issued consecutively. Softer versions function as contact calls between adults and offspring.</p><p>Intriguingly, the Haitian name pètpèt originates from the distinctive alarm call, which resembles the sound of "put put" like small bubble of air exploding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kwètkwèt (Turdus genus)</head><p>Two birds share the onomatopoeic name kwètkwèt in Haiti:</p><p>The Kwètkwèt Nwa, 'La Selle Thrush' (Turdus swalesi) -Endemic to Island of Hispaniola -is a secretive bird species occupying broadleaf and pine in the La Selle forests at altitudes around 1300 meters. Primarily active at dusk and dawn, its song features a mix of fleeting upslurred and down-slurred notes combined with sweet whistles of varying lengths, presented gradually and repetitively.</p><p>The Kwètkwèt Fran 'Red-Legged Thrush' (Turdus plumbeus) -Native to the Caribbean, typically performs a composed whistled duet. Its calls comprise an assortment of squeaks, chuckles, and a sharp "tsee-up" sound, with a harsh alarm call like a "wek-wek".</p><p>Although not their most common vocalizations, the onomatopoeic name kwètkwèt perfectly suits these two bird species because their alarm calls contain abrupt, sharp, and highpitched sounds that resemble the name. The reduplication of the syllable kwèt in the name imitates the repetitive nature of the distress signal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grigri (Falco genus)</head><p>The 'American Kestrel' (Falco sparverius) stands out as the smallest and most widespread falcon across North America. Commonly referred to as grigri in Haiti, this diminutive bird of prey sports three main vocalizations -the "klee" or "killy," the "whine,"</p><p>and the "chitter" ('Sounds and Vocal Behavior -American Kestrel -Falco sparverius -Birds of the World' n.d.). When agitated or thrilled, the kestrel issues the memorable "klee" call rapidly, generating a sequence like "klee, klee, klee, klee".</p><p>As for the onomatopoeic quality of the local name "grigri," it bears close resemblance the familiar "klee" sound. While the phonetic linkages between "klee" and grigri aren't immediate, it is worth noting that the "k" and "g" sounds share a place of articulation, i.e., the back part of the tongue touching the soft tissue in the rear region of the roof of the mouth.</p><p>Additionally, the "l" and "r" sounds are liquids, displaying somewhat similar behaviors concerning oral cavity configurations. However, keep in mind that regional variations exist as noted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fattier 1998)</ref>, as evidenced by other designations such as kilikili in certain Haitian communities or "gligli" adopted in Guadeloupe's French-speaking islands.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kit (Coereba flaveola),</head><p>Known as the 'bananaquit' (Coereba flaveola), the kit is a species of passerine bird in the tanager family Thraupidae. This small, active nectarivore is found in warmer parts of the Americas and is generally common.</p><p>Like other 'quits' the bananaquit's sounds are distinctive. Its typical call is a short, highpitched note, given singly but repeated every few seconds. It also has a lower-pitched call note and sometimes gives a continuous high-pitched twittering. The song varies across the range of quit birds but is usually high-pitched and scratchy. Various forms of its call, noted by Fattier (1998), include Kit, ti kit, kitkit, and ti chit; and Sisi or Zizi for the grassquits. All these forms are onomatopoeic, capturing the essence of the bird's vocalization revealing consistent usage of short, high-pitched, and slightly varied combinations of consonantal and vocalic segments:</p><p>1. Kit: This form contains a voiceless velar plosive (k), followed by a high front lax vowel (i), ending abruptly, mirroring the brevity and high pitch observed in the typical call of the bananaquit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>Ti kit: Introducing the diminutive prefix "ti," emphasizing the small size of the bird, precedes the onomatopoeic segment, maintaining consistency with the base form "Kit."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Kit kit: Repeating the onomatopoeic segment reinforces the notion of repeating a high-pitched note, representing the continuous nature of the call.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>Ti chit: Substituting the "k" in "Kit" with a sibilant creates a slightly altered sound, while still retaining the overall impression conveyed by the previous interpretations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p>Sisi and Zizi: Substituting the "k" in "Kit" with an "s" sound (s) creates a slightly altered sound, keeping the essence of the bird's vocalization. The "s" sound adds a different tonal quality to the call, offering an alternative interpretation while still capturing the high-pitched and repetitive nature of the bird's typical call.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kikiliki (Myadestes genibarbis)</head><p>The Rufous-throated Solitaire (Myadestes genibarbis) belongs to the Turdidae family and is a medium-sized, year-round dweller of rich, damp montane woods. The Rufous-throated Solitaire thrives in subtropical or tropical humid lowland forests and subtropical or tropical wet mountainsides.</p><p>Within Haiti, this bird carries three distinct names: Mizisyen, kikiliki, and kikiliflit. Each title pays homage to the iconic vocalizations of the Rufous-throated Solitaire, notably kikiliki, which constitutes a spot-on onomatopoeia. Often detected initially by its sound, the bird's tune unfolds as a string of extended, unmodulated flute-like peeps manifested at fluctuating frequencies. Similarly, its call shares this description but features sharper pitches. Displaying preening habits combined with vocal performances, the compound phrase kikiliflit cleverly integrates onomatopoeic qualities with the instrument-based allusion to flit, literally flute, aptly describing the bird's uniquely identifiable voice.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pipirit (multiple genus)</head><p>Three unrelated birds carry the name "pipirit" in Haiti, reflecting their shared vocal characteristics:</p><p>1.</p><p>Pipirit gri (Tyrannus dominicensis) -'Gray Kingbird'</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>Pipirit rivyè (Ceryle alcyon) -'Belted Kingfisher'</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Pipirit tèt fou (Contopus hispaniolensis) -'Hispaniolan Pewee'</p><p>The Gray Kingbird is a member of the tyrant flycatchers family Tyrannidae. Initially described on the island of Hispaniola, it got its species name "dominicensis" due to its first discovery location. The loud, rolling trill, as seen in figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>, "pipiri, pipiri" inspires many local onomatopoeic names, such as pestigre or pitirre in Spanish-speaking Greater Antilles, or petchary an pipieri in some English-speaking islands. The Belted Kingfisher is a large, conspicuous water kingfisher native to North America. It emits a characteristic rattling call (figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>) while flying about its habitat, and both male and female individuals respond to disturbances with strident, mechanical rattles.</p><p>The Hispaniolan Pewee is a Tyrannidae family species endemic to the island of Hispaniola in the Caribbean. Known for a lack of distinctive field marks, it emits a repeated mellow "pip" contrasting with the more vocal tendencies of other pewees added with repeated weet sound.</p><p>Interestingly, these three unrelated birds share the name pipirit due to perceived song similarities, displaying the complexity of language and bird identification.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.2.Basic Onomatopoeic Elements</head><p>Our study proves that there a are some basic onomatopoeic elements that contribute to bird naming in Haitian Creole. Individual consonants and vowels directly correspond to the articulation of bird vocalization. Here is an analysis with examples, noting the presence or absence of phonemes:</p><p>• Plosive Consonants (Present: K, P, T): Often employed to reproduce hard or sharp sound, those are the most common consonant in our corpus as in Kikiliki, Pipirit, Kaw, Kit, Kwak, Tako.</p><p>• Liquids (Present: Scarce R, L): Used to render soft or rugged, continuous, or a rolling flowing sounds. Grigri, Gragra, Kilikili, Kikiliki.</p><p>• Sibilants (Scarce: S, Ch): Typically linked to gentler hissing. It can convey softness or stealth. e.g., Sisi, Zizi, Ti Chit.</p><p>• Nasals (Absent): Typically linked to gentler vocalizations but absent in our data.</p><p>• Open Vowels (Present: A, È,): Associated with expansive or relaxed oral gestures, often used for amplified sounds. e.g., Pètpèt, Kwak, Kaw, Kwètkwèt.</p><p>• Closed Vowels (Present: I): Symbolizing restricted or constrained oral gestures, usually applied for shorter, clipped and high-pitched sounds. e.g., in Pipirit, Kilikili, Kikiliki.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TIER 2: Syllabic Units and Patterns</head><p>Building on Tier 1, this layer introduces syllabic units and recurrent sequences, intensifying the correspondence between phoneme composition and intended meaning through diagrammatic iconicity. These arrangements can help accentuate pitch contours, stress distribution, and temporal dynamics, thus making the onomatopoeic segments increasingly recognizable.</p><p>• • Example 1: Kwèt kwèt -The reduplication of "kwèt" accentuates the abrupt, sharp, high-pitched alarm calls of these birds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Repetitions and Reduplications</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>Example 2: Pipirit -The repetition of "pi" and "rit" enhances the rolling trills and mechanical rattle of the bird's call.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>Example 3: Kikiliki, The repetition of "ki" and the switch to include "li" indicts the rolling peep sound of the bird's call.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TIER 3: Contextual Integration and Interpretation</head><p>Finally, this topmost stratum integrates the lower-level onomatopoeic units within the wider context of Haitian Creole morpho-syntax and semantics. Doing so allows the named bird to keep a holistic identity tied to its habitat, biology, and cultural significance.</p><p>• Compounding: Creating composite structures that merge independent onomatopoeic fragments to form new meaningful constructs.</p><p>• Example 1: Tako Kabrit -The compound name combines Tako with Kabrit, 'goat', reflecting the bird's call and enhancing its cultural significance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>Example 2: Kaw fran -The compound name combines Kaw with "Fran" 'common' suggesting a cultural or geographical distinction.</p><p>• Derived Forms: Building on set up onomatopoeic bases via affixation or inflection, generating derivative units that signal distinctions in size or location.</p><p>• Example 1: Ti Kaw -The derived form includes the prefix "Ti" ('small') denoting reduced scale, distinguishing it from other crows and reflecting its smaller size or habitat preference.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>Example 2: Pipirit Rivyè -This name features "rivyè" ('river')</p><p>indicating is habitat.</p><p>Overall, this hierarchical model offers a structured perspective on the phoneme-tomeaning mapping in Haitian bird names, isolating critical links between the onomatopoetic portions and their intended referents. By progressively assimilating simpler components into higher-order configurations, the suggested schema underscores the multiplicity of layers operating simultaneously within the sound-based naming tradition, fostering a dynamic, flexible, and culturally informed appreciation of this remarkable linguistic practice.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.3.Other processes</head><p>Haitian </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>This study reveals the significant role of sound-symbolic associations in the evolution and lexical creation within creole languages. While earlier studies have highlighted the importance of ideophonic creation in Haitian Creole, this research extends these findings by focusing on the contribution of sound-symbolic connections in forming words in creole languages.</p><p>Haitian Creole shows a high degree of iconicity in bird names, proving an extraordinary capacity to generate memorable avian terms through morphological flexibility and reduplication. This linguistic creativity is not just a phenomenon, but also a reflection of the deep cultural connections between the people and their natural environment.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>In conclusion, our study of onomatopoeic bird names in Haitian Creole has revealed both the language's uniqueness and its close association with the natural environment. By exploring these associations, we gain a deeper understanding of how language, culture, and ecology intertwine, shaping the way we name and perceive the world around us. It underscores the importance of studying distinct aspects of iconicity in language, offering insights into the interplay between sound, meaning, and culture. Consequently, illuminating the interaction between human cognition, expressiveness, and environmental awareness.</p><p>Additionally, focusing on these onomatopoeic terms reveals the resilience and adaptability of Haitian Creole despite external influences-such as dialectal variants, borrowing, and semantic shifts-that inevitably impact any living language. For instance, even when incorporating foreign words or experiencing modifications in regional dialects, Haitian</p><p>Creole maintains a consistent ability to innovate and produce captivating bird names deeply rooted in local traditions and experiences.</p><p>In turn, this investigation enhances our comprehension on broader questions concerning language evolution, lexicon expansion, and the emergence of novel vocabularies in creoles specifically. Specifically, the sound-symbolism demonstrated by Haitian Creole bird names suggests that sound symbolism serves as a key catalyst for linguistic innovation. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>linguistic works and handbooks(Akita &amp; Pardeshi 2019;<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Hinton et al. 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Perniss et al. 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Voeltz &amp; Kilian-Hatz 2001)</ref>. Iconicity plays a significant role in expanding the expressive capabilities of spoken languages. Such marked words, variously labelled as mimetics, expressives, phonaesthemes, and ideophones, facilitate the communication of sensory imagery(Akita &amp; Pardeshi 2019;<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kwon 2015)</ref>.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>SVO) order, with potential changes influenced by pragmatic factors. Onomatopoeias in HC sentences also serve as adverbs, contributing to the semantic depth of verbal constructions and resembling manner adverbials in other languages. Due to the multifunctionality existent in Haitian Creole lexicon, they also can serve as other open lexical classes as verbs, adjectives, or nouns without any inflections.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>bird names provided by Severin in 2007, recognized as the most comprehensive work on birds in Haiti. Although Avibase, the main global source for bird species, reports 273 species, with 15 being endemic and 27 introduced, Severin's list exclusively encompasses species that inhabit Haiti and are integral to Haitian culture. This distinction is crucial, as it highlights the potential reliance of Haitian Creole on ornithonym processes, favoring familiar or vernacular endemic birds.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 Coccyzus longirostris sonogram. Adapted by the author from Ian Davies, XC97182. Accessible at www.xeno-canto.org/97182</figDesc><graphic coords="14,106.33,266.35,412.20,142.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 2 Corvus leucognaphalus Sound from Ross Gallardy, XC308607. Accessible at www.xenocanto.org/308607</figDesc><graphic coords="16,72.35,72.95,223.80,134.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 4 Tyrannus dominicensis sonogram from Paul Driver, XC357038. Accessible at www.xenocanto.org/357038</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>:</head><label></label><figDesc>Commonly used to strengthen the intensity or duration of represented sounds Repetition in animal communication enhances the signals' effectiveness, ensuring nearby individuals receive warnings quickly.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6 Temnotrogon roseigaster from https://abcbirds.org/bird/hispaniolan-trogon/</figDesc><graphic coords="27,167.83,70.85,288.00,187.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 : Some onomatopoeia in Haitian Creole in their sound source</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Goulougoulou (Turkey gobbling)</cell></row><row><cell>Reptiles and</cell><cell>Kwòòk (Frog croaking), Ssssss (Snake whistling)</cell></row><row><cell>Amphibians</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Insects</cell><cell>Zzzzz (Mosquito buzzing), Vonvon (Beetle moving)</cell></row><row><cell>Fish and</cell><cell>Flap (Fish splashing), Foufou (Blowing air from a pufferfish),</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Badabadaw (Fish flapping outside of water)</cell></row><row><cell>Voice</cell><cell>Chwicwhi (Whispering), Atchoum (Sneezing), Hanm (Yawning or</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>swallowing), Wounouwounou (Mumbling), Yenyen or Nyènyè (Crying)</cell></row><row><cell>Human</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>Category Sound Source Onomatopoeia and Event Natural Sounds Water Tchouboum (Heavy object falling into water), Tchòw (Urinating), chchchchch (Water flowing gently), Glouglou (Liquid trickling from a bottle) Air Vlaw (Wind blowing through clothes), Vou (Violent wind), chwiiiii (Rustling leaves), ffffffffffffff (Gentle breeze) Earth Goudougoudou (Earthquake rumbling), Trililili (Rolling pebbles descending from a mountain), Godow (Thunder) Fire Plapla (Wood crackling), Pètpèt (Charcoal popping) Animals Mammals Myaouw (Cat meowing), Wap wap (Puppy barking), Hihan (Donkey braying), Houhou (Owl hooting) Birds Gragra (Crow croaking), Koukouyikou (Rooster crowing), Body Bip bip (Heart beating), Plop plop (Quick footsteps), Pla pla (Hand clapping), Hanm (Eating), Glòt glòt glòt (Drinking), Brrrr (Vomiting) Art ifa cts Musical Instruments Peng peng (Piano playing), Teng teng (Guitar strumming), Pim pim (Percussion drumming)</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 : Onomatopoeic Haitian bird names Haitian bird names Latin name</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>English</cell><cell>Vocalization sample</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Creole has a rich ornithological vocabulary inherited from French, a legacy of historical slavery and bird imports during the slave trade. Words such as kanna (Anas genus), poul (Fullica and Gallinula genera), ranmye (Columba genus), and toutrèl (Zenaida genus) are examples of this French influence. To differentiate between bird species, additional naming processes are employed. Visual attributes, including color, size, and shape, are fundamental to bird naming in many languages, including Haitian Creole. Color, or chromatic characteristics, are key descriptors in distinguishing and naming birds. In Haitian Creole, color-based ornithonyms may describe the entire bird or specific body parts. For example, Békasin zèl blan (Catoptrophorus semipalmatus) translates to 'white-winged godwit'; Bannann mi fran (Icterus dominicensis) is known as the 'yellow banana' or Hispaniolan Oriole; and Flaman woz (Phoenicopterus ruber) water hen' while terrestrial habitats are represented in names like Chwèt bwa (Asio stygius)-meaning 'forest owl'-and Chwèt savann (Asio flammeus)-'savannah owl'. Dietary preferences are also evident in names such as Krabye ble (Egretta caerulea), literally 'blue crab-eater' symbolizing the Little Blue Heron, a wading bird that primarily consumes fish and crustaceans.Understanding behavioral patterns enables accurate predictions of bird movements, social structures, and seasonality. For example, the term Plonjon fran (Podilymbus podiceps), signifying the 'diving duck' incorporates behavioral patterns. Similarly, some birds are named based on their usage. For example, Wanga nègès refers to the (Anthracothorax Dominicus), also known as the 'Antillean Mango'. Wanga nègès literally translates to 'magical spell on negresse'. This naming is influenced by beliefs and practices where these birds are used in the preparation of a magical mixture believed to attract women.</figDesc><table><row><cell>means 'pink flamingo'.</cell></row><row><cell>Size is another key factor in bird naming. For instance, Ti kaw (Corvus palmarum) is</cell></row><row><cell>referred to as the 'small crow', and Gwo malfini savann (Circus cyaneus) is recognized as the</cell></row><row><cell>'large savannah hawk'. Additionally, the size of individual bird body parts can lead to specific</cell></row><row><cell>names, such as Toutrèl ke fen (Zenaida macroura), or 'Mourning Dove with slim tail'</cell></row><row><cell>highlighting the unique, slender appearance of its tail.</cell></row><row><cell>Distinct physical features also play a crucial role in bird recognition. For example, Bèk</cell></row><row><cell>kwaze (Loxia leucoptera megaplaga) emphasizes the peculiar, crooked mandibles of the</cell></row><row><cell>crossbill; Espatil (meaning spatula) denotes the Roseate Spoonbill's uniquely shaped bill; and</cell></row><row><cell>sizo (Fregata magnificens) literally 'scissor'.</cell></row><row><cell>Ecological variables, such as habitats and diets, are significant in bird naming practices.</cell></row></table><note><p>These factors assist naturalists in identifying specific species. For instance, aquatic ecosystems are reflected in names like Poul dlo tèt wouj (Gallinula chloropus), interpreted as the 'red-headed</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Considering the multiple vocalizations of birds, it's important to understand what motivates the speaker to use a specific onomatopoeia instead of another. The case of Haitian Creole suggests that people might be more alerted by the bird's alarm call, explaining why, for animals with multiple vocalizations, the name mostly comes from the alarm call. However, this does not particularly explain why koukou is related to owl, but not to cuckoo in Haitian Creole, even if the argument of phonological cribble for each language is considered.While this study highlights Haitian Creole's rich linguistic legacy and its deep ties to the natural world, certain challenges arise when trying to precisely measure the extent of iconicity and trace the development of sound-symbolic motifs across time. Potential future research can tackle these issues head-on by employing cross-disciplinary strategies to dissect the multifaceted relationship among language, culture, and ecology in creole societies.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Furthermore, while this study primarily focuses on Haitian Creole bird names, more</cell></row><row><cell>investigations should examine various semantic domains to establish whether comparable</cell></row><row><cell>trends persist throughout different taxonomies. Expanding the scope of inquiry will allow</cell></row><row><cell>researchers to better understand the pervasiveness and impact of sound symbolism on creole</cell></row><row><cell>language systems.</cell></row><row><cell>Expanding on Séverin's observation (2007) regarding the profound relationship between</cell></row><row><cell>Haitian culture and birds, one can find these feathered creatures fulfilling multiple roles, serving</cell></row><row><cell>as sources of nutrition, controlling harmful insect populations in gardens, disposing of deceased</cell></row><row><cell>organisms, facilitating pollination, providing delightful music, acting as indicators of</cell></row><row><cell>approaching inclement weather like rain, adorning nature, and much more. A remarkable</cell></row><row><cell>The distinctive illustration of the language's creativity lies in the national bird of Haiti, the Hispaniolan Trogon</cell></row><row><cell>historical and socio-linguistic background of creole languages-namely, contact, (Priotelus roseigaster) figure 6.</cell></row><row><cell>accommodation, and innovation-fosters an environment conducive to generating a new</cell></row><row><cell>lexicon deeply rooted in sound symbolism.</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>The institution commonly known as the University of Haiti is originally named Université d'État d'Haïti, which translates to 'State University of Haiti'.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>I would like to extend sincere gratitude to two anonymous reviewers for their valuable and insightful feedback during the preparation of this work.</p></div>
<div><head>Competing Interests</head><p>The author declares no competing interests.</p></div>
<div><head>Funding</head><p>No funding was received for the completion of this project.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phonosemantic Subsets in the Lexicon: Hungarian Avian Nomenclature and L&apos;Arbitraire Du Signe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Abondolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1179/174582107x235375</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Central Europe</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideophones, Mimetics and Expressives</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1075/ill.16</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Iconicity in Language and Literature</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Akita</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pardeshi</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideophones and sound symbolism in Atlantic Creoles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bartens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Suomalaisen tiedeakatemian toimituksia. Sarja Humaniora</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">304</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Evidence for pervasive synesthetic sound symbolism in ethnozoological nomenclature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Berlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="93" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sound symbolism</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The pervasiveness of onomatopoeia in Aguaruna and Huambisa bird names</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Berlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Neill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Ethnobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bodo</forename><surname>Winter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="&lt;https://www.youtube.com/" />
		<title level="m">watch?time_continue=1816&amp;v=R1ETw21oCGE&amp;embeds _referring_euri=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com%2Fsearch%3Fq%3Dbodo%2B</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-05-14">May 14, 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>winter%2Band%2Bbird%2Band%2Bonomatopoeia%2Band%2Bsize%26sca_esv%3D 9ed8fe13a8c6ea88%26biw%3D1536%26bih%3D730%26tbm%3Dvid&amp;source_ve_pa th=MzY4NDIsMjg2NjY&amp;feature=emb_logo&gt;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Song amplitude and body size in birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Brumm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00265-009-0743-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1165" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Iconicity in language: an encyclopedic dictionary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cabrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Carlos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge Scholars Publishing</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Newcastle upon Tyne</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideophones and reduplication: Depiction, description, and the interpretation of repeated talk in discourse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dingemanse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1075/sl.39.4.05din</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studies in Language</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="946" to="970" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideophone&apos;as a comparative concept</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ideophones, mimetics, and expressives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>John Benjamins Amsterdam</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideophones</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordhb/9780198852889.013.15</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Oxford Handbook of Word Classes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van Lier</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="476" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>st ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Construals of iconicity: experimental approaches to form-meaning resemblances in language</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dingemanse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Perlman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Perniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/langcog.2019.48</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Language and Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Idéophonie et catégorisation en créole haïtien : une analyse linguistique des idéophones (Bachelor&apos;s degree). Université d&apos;État d&apos;Haïti</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Edouard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Faculté de Linguistique Appliquée</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ethnologue | Languages of the world</title>
		<ptr target="&lt;https://www.ethnologue.com/&gt;" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-05-10">May 10, 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Contribution à l&apos;étude de la genèse d&apos;un créole: l&apos;Atlas linguistique d&apos;Haïti, cartes et commentaires</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fattier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>Presses Universitaires du Septentrion</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Villeneuve d&apos;Ascq</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Convergences lexico-sémantiques entre les créoles haïtien et jamaïcain : rôle de l&apos;analogie</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Govain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="94" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sound symbolism., Digitally printed 1st pbk. version</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nichols</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ohala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>J. J.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge ; New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Winged Voices: Mapuche Ornithology from South American Temperate Forests</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Ibarra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Caviedes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Benavides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2993/0278-0771-40.1.89</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Ethnobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cross-linguistic vocal iconicity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.13140/RG.2.2.20805.63200</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>object Object</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Purpose and Aim of the Series&apos;. Onomatopoeia in the World&apos;s Languages, p. V-VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Körtvélyessy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Štekauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1515/9783111053226-202</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<publisher>De Gruyter</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The formation and motivation of onomatopoeic ornithonyms as a result of ecological and communicative interactions of man and birds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kurashkina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Online Journal of Natural and Social Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The natural motivation of sound symbolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.14264/uql.2015.1013</idno>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://espace.library.uq.edu.au/view/UQ:372363&gt;" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-04-11">2015. April 11, 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD Thesis</note>
	<note>The University of Queensland</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Creoles, their substrates, and language typology. Typological studies in language (TSL)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lefebvre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>John Benjamins Pub</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Amsterdam; Philadelphia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A cross-linguistic study of lexical iconicity and its manifestation in bird names. Helsinki: Helsingin yliopisto</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marttila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nykykielten laitos</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinguishing onomatopoeias from interjections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Meinard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.pragma.2014.11.011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Pragmatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hispaniolan Lizard-Cuckoo (Coccyzus longirostris), version 1.0&apos;, Birds of the World. Cornell Lab of Ornithology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Payne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2173/bow.hislic1.01species_shared.bow.project_name</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<pubPlace>Ithaca, NY, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Philosophical writings of Peirce</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Peirce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>1. Publ.,</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1955">1955</date>
			<publisher>Dover Publ</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>new ed., unabr. and unaltered republ. of the book 1. publ. 1940 under the title: The Philosophy Bof Peirce</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Perniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1075/ill.17</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Operationalizing Iconicity. Iconicity in Language and Literature</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ljungberg</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iconicity as a General Property of Language: Evidence from Spoken and Signed Languages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Perniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vigliocco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpsyg.2010.00227</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haitian Creole Ideophones: An Exploratory Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Prou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Haitian Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Center for Black Studies Research</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cours de linguistique générale. Grande bibliothèque Payot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Saussure</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bally</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>De Mauro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Éd. critique</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Payot</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Nachdr. der Ausg. 1916</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sounds and Vocal Behavior -American Kestrel -Falco sparverius -Birds of the World</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Séverin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;https://birdsoftheworld.org/bow/species/amekes/cur/sounds&gt;" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-05-10">2007. May 10, 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ti zwazo kote w a prale. Societé Audubon Haïti</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Le creole haitien: morphologie et syntaxe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sylvain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1936">1936</date>
			<pubPlace>Suzanne Sylvain; Wetteren</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F K</forename><surname>Voeltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kilian-Hatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Ideophones: papers presented at the 1st International Symposium on Ideophones held Jan. 1999, St. Augustin, Ger. Typological studies in language. Presented at the International Symposium on Ideophones</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Benjamins</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Birds Names: Embodyment of The Relationship Between Human and Environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wicaksono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Macaryus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ermawati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4108/eai.8-9-2020.2301450</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Presented at the Proceedings of the First International Conference on Communication, Language, Literature, and Culture</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Surakarta, Central Java, Indonesia; Surakarta, Central Java, Indonesia, Surakarta, Indonesia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>EAI</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020-09-09">2020. ICCoLLiC 2020, 8-9 September 2020. ICCoLLiC 2020, 8-9 September 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings of the First International Conference on Communication, Language, Literature, and Culture</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Size sound symbolism in the English lexicon&apos;, Glossa: a journal of general linguistics, 6/1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Winter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Perlman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5334/gjgl.1646&apos;xeno-canto</idno>
		<ptr target="&lt;https://xeno-canto.org/&gt;" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sharing wildlife sounds from around the world</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-05-10">2021. May 10, 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The semantics of bird denominations in the Mari language&apos;, Eesti ja soome-ugri keeleteaduse ajakiri</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yuzieva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.12697/jeful.2012.3.1.19</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Estonian and Finno-Ugric Linguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
