<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Towards a Spatial Understanding: Transcriptome Profiling of the Tumor Landscape After Ablative Focused Ultrasound Regimens</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Biorepository and Tissue Research Facility</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Focused Ultrasound Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_46tWmTC">
					<orgName type="full">University of Virginia School of Medicine, Research Resource Identifiers (RRID)</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Spatial Biology Core at the University of Virginia</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_jaqzdsM">
					<orgName type="full">GeoMx</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><surname>Bullock</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Virginia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charlottesville</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Beirne B. Carter Center for Immunology Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Virginia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charlottesville</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Frederic</forename><surname>Padilla</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Focused Ultrasound Foundation</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charlottesville</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Awndre</forename><surname>Gamache</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Virginia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charlottesville</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Beirne B. Carter Center for Immunology Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Virginia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charlottesville</settlement>
									<region>VA</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Towards a Spatial Understanding: Transcriptome Profiling of the Tumor Landscape After Ablative Focused Ultrasound Regimens</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5F91800C3A0D8EC26CCABCCA0BA4848F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Despite recent advances with immunotherapy, metastatic cancer is incurable in most cases. Thus, there is an unmet need to improve both local and systemic therapies for metastatic disease. Focused ultrasound (FUS) therapy stands at the forefront of non-invasive and non-ionizing oncologic treatments, utilizing concentrated ultrasound energy to achieve selective tumor destruction <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Padilla et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>FUS refers to the convergence of ultrasound, and therefore non-ionizing, waves into a focal volume for non-invasive perturbation of tumor tissues, without damage to tissues outside of the targeted area. The mechanisms of action of FUS are highly versatile,and trigger a broad spectrum of bioeffects that can be thermal or mechanical in nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Cranston, Leslie and Ter Haar, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Meng, Hynynen and Lipsman, 2021)</ref>. For ablation of tumor tissues, two main mechanisms of action are thermal ablation and a form of mechanical ablation known as histotripsy <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Xu et al., 2024)</ref>. With thermal ablation, ultrasound energy is delivered at mild intensity, to heat the tissue until temperature of thermal coagulation is reached (typically around 65°C in soft tissues). With histotripsy, extremely high intensities are used, to generate high-amplitude focused ultrasound pulses inducing in mechanical liquefaction of tissues into subcellular debris <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Xu et al., 2024)</ref>.</p><p>Interestingly, separate case studies implementing either the histotripsy or thermal focused ultrasound (T-FUS) therapy modalities have shown shrinkage of nontargeted metastases in patients with extensive metastatic disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Vidal-Jove et al., 2013</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2021)</ref>. This, along with an abundance of preclinical data, suggests that localized immunogenic effects of FUSinduced cell death within the tumor microenvironment have the potential to promote systemic antitumor immunity <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Joiner, Pylayeva-Gupta and Dayton, 2020)</ref>. Additionally, FUS-induced cell death has been shown to improve antigen availability, dendritic cell activation and maturation, and anti-tumor T-cell responses <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Liu et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Pepple et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Thim et al., 2024)</ref>. Notably, most of these studies ascertain the transcriptional state, or characterize single cell suspensions, of bulk tumor homogenate. While these approaches have been useful for gleaning the general effects of FUS therapy, they lack sufficient precision to determine how FUS-related immune-sequalae spatially associate with FUS-induced lesions.</p><p>T-FUS, Laser-induced thermotherapy, microwave ablation therapy and radiofrequency ablation therapy are all methods that have been utilized to thermally ablate cancer. In all cases, evidence of immunomodulation post treatment has been characterized <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Haen et al., 2011)</ref>. Although there is a dearth of comparative studies to determine whether the quality of immunomodulation differs between these modalities, the core mechanism of action between them relies upon the delivery of energy resulting in heating. In contrast, boiling histotripsy (BH) is a high intensity focused ultrasound ablation strategy that induces lesions through predominantly mechanical tissue fractionation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Khokhlova et al., 2015)</ref>. Moreover, BH is thought to drive unique immunostimulatory effects which coincide with anti-tumor immunity <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(van den Bijgaart et al., 2022)</ref>. The specific inflammatory signatures which promote this immunosensitization, and whether the periablative zone of BH lesions host the majority of the immune response to tumors, are poorly understood. Quantification and characterization of intratumoral changes in immune cell clustering and innate-immune pathway induction following FUS treatments is necessary to understand potential differences in immunogenicity. Thus, we have performed an initial study that employs spatial transcriptome profiling to determine what underlies the putative differences between these FUS modalities.</p><p>Tumor fraction ablation with FUS has been shown to influence immunogenic effects, with sparse-scan regimens (spatially sparse distributed ablation zones) suggested to be more immunogenic than dense-scan regimens (condensed ablation zones) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Liu et al., 2010)</ref>. This could be due to a higher density of immune cell clusters that form due to the maintenance of viable tumor parenchyma, which may promote the persistence and recruitment of tumor-associated immune cells. These data suggest that the periablative area around FUS lesions may be a key niche that supports systemic immunity. We investigate the general hypothesis that FUS-induced inflammation primarily modifies immune-sequela within the periablative zone of FUS induced lesions, and that the distal regions of treated tumors will maintain the transcriptional and cellular landscape of sham-treated tumors. Utilizing a digital spatial transcriptome profiling technique, we examine the identities of immune cells and the inflammatory transcriptome in this area, aiming to clarify how FUS therapy's immunosensitizing byproducts are spatially distributed and to assess the potential of enhancing periablative volume for improved adjuvant effects.</p><p>The deployment of spatial transcriptome profiling technologies like GeoMX is revolutionizing our understanding of tumor microenvironments (TME). Traditional RNA-seq does not retain information about the original spatial location of cells within the tissue, losing the context of cellular interactions and microenvironments. By facilitating intricate analysis at the cellular level while maintaining information on tissue structure, GeoMX can offer an unprecedented window into the complex interplay between FUS-induced lesions, cancer cells and their surrounding milieu. This technology is particularly adept at dissecting the spatial and morphological intricacies of tumor tissues, providing insights into how different treatment strategies impact the TME. Here, we utilize GeoMX to perform a comparative analysis of the transcriptional variations induced by either BH or T-FUS therapy in contrast to control conditions and determine whether these phenomena are localized to regions around the lesions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1A</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>In this study we employ the MC38 colorectal adenocarcinoma model. As we are interested in how immune cells are responding to FUS therapy, it is imperative that immune cells are available in the TME to respond. MC38 is the quintessential "hot" tumor murine model and contains diverse and plentiful immune cells available for profiling <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Kienzl et al., 2024)</ref>. Additionally, the fibrous tumor stroma displays limited regions of necrosis, which makes it more amenable to focused ultrasound therapy. MC38 has also been employed in studies which characterize DC activation and tumor control after T-FUS and mechanical-FUS ablative therapy. In this case, mechanical-FUS ablative therapy was observed to have a more potent effect on inducing a stronger anti-tumor response and inhibitory effect on tumor growth after rechallenge <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Hu et al., 2007)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detection of ablation zones and ROI assignment:</head><p>GeoMX enables segmentation of morphological markers to spatially partition and interrogate specific regions of interest in a in a histological context. This enables deep characterization of the transcriptomic signatures that delineate both the discrete cell subsets and inflammatory pathways that describe the TME. Additionally, the acute effects of both T-FUS and BH have been shown to induce potent DAMP induction and immune cell recruitment 24 hours post therapy. Thus, we collected tissues 24 hours post treatment for characterization. To enable the selection of regions of interest (ROI) in tumors were stained for H&amp;E, cleaved CASP-3 or PARP1, and Hsp70 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1B</ref>). Sham, BH, and T-FUS treated tumors display differences in the morphology of their necrotic (PARP1 + ) regions (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1B</ref>). Relative to sham, BH samples contain acellular regions (smooth pink area in H&amp;E) surrounded by areas of fragmented nuclei and reduced cell membrane integrity. The T-FUS treated samples do not contain acellular regions but are predominated by areas of fragmented nuclei and reduced cell membrane integrity. These morphological features correspond with what has been published regarding BH and T-FUS treatment modalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Khokhlova et al., 2011)</ref>. Hsp70 was used to define the area of influence relating to FUS-induced lesions. ROIs selected around Hsp70 + areas were negative for necrotic staining. We refer to these as periablative (peri) versus distal ROIs. The induction of Hsp70 after treatment with both modalities suggests that the lysate produced by BH can induce similar stress response pathways as T-FUS, despite being a predominantly mechanical rather than thermal mode of ablation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparison of peri-ablation and distal ROI after FUS:</head><p>To better understand the impact of FUS treatment on the tumor microenvironment, we performed dimensionality reduction and gene expression analyses on the collected ROIs. Dimensionality reduction of collected ROIs demonstrates that FUStreated samples cluster separately from untreated (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2 A-C</ref>). When assessing bulk ROIs, compared to untreated samples, nearly 1000 genes are differentially regulated 24h after tumors are treated with either BH or T-FUS (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2 D</ref>). Gene Ontology (GO) analysis shows the upregulation of RNA processing, regulation and biogenesis pathways localized to the nucleus and promoting translation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2 E</ref>).</p><p>We hypothesized that the periablative areas would have distinct transcriptional profiles from distal regions. Surprisingly, dimensionality reduction analysis revealed no unique clusters between these regions. Moreover, there were minimal differentially expressed genes between periablative and distal regions of both BH and T-FUS treated tumors (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3 A-D</ref>). This data suggest that the transcriptional milieu is somewhat consistent throughout the tumor after FUS treatment. This may reflect a broad sphere of influence of DAMPs released by the primary lesion, or the activity of FUS away from the biologically discernable ablative/peri-ablative regions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Estimates of acute inflammation:</head><p>A potent inflammatory response has been reported in response to T-FUS in a 4T1 murine breast cancer model in the form of upregulation of innate immune sensor genes and genes encoding for the pro inflammatory cytokines IL-6 and IL-1β , as well as other inflammasome-related genes 24 hours post treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Fite et al., 2021)</ref>. We looked at gene expression of inflammasome-related genes and discovered that most genes, including IL-6 and IL-1β, displayed no difference, or a trending decrease, relative to sham controls, except for txn1 (Sup_inflammasome A and B). These data suggest that sham tumors may already be in a heightened state of inflammasome activity that cannot be further augmented in response to BH or T-FUS therapy.</p><p>Cellular deconvolution analysis suggests alterations in T cell and macrophage populations after FUS: MC38 has also been well characterized in the context of the spatial technologies and analysis pipelines that we have employed <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Chen et al., 2017)</ref>. The publicly available scRNAseq data has been optimized for cell type deconvolution in this context, which enable the estimation of immune cell proportions and abundance within ROIs. Cell deconvolution analysis revealed a significant increase in Th17 T cells in treated tumors (CellDecon A-B). However, no difference was seen between peripheral and distal regions (CellDecon C-D). Interestingly, we also observed a trending increase in the proportion of activated dendritic cells, M0 and M2 macrophages, and CD8 T cells in the peripheral regions of treated tumors (CellDecon C-D). These cells play crucial roles in antigen presentation, tumor killing, and the initiation of adaptive immune responses, hinting at a potentially more conducive environment for immune-mediated tumor suppression in these areas. In contrast, there was a trending reduction in Th2 cells, Mast cells, monocytes, and M1 macrophages, which could reflect a shift away from certain anti-inflammatory responses. This reduction may also contribute to a more balanced immune milieu, possibly curtailing the recruitment of cells that may otherwise support tumor growth or suppress effective antitumor immunity. Overall, these findings highlight the dynamic alterations in the tumor immune environment following treatment, suggesting a reprogramming towards a milieu potentially more favorable for antitumor immunity.</p><p>The molecular mechanisms underlying FUS-induced tissue damage and its effects on the tumor microenvironment are poorly understood. Our studies, and those of others, have shown that T-FUS can induce tumor ablation by causing coagulative necrosis in the treated area. Whereas BH leads to acellular debris and subsequent necrosis of the surrounding region <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Khokhlova et al., 2011)</ref> We anticipated that FUS-induced inflammation would primarily modify immune-sequela within the peri-ablative zone of FUS induced lesions, as defined by HSP70 expression. Moreover, we also hypothesized that the distal regions would phenocopy what is seen in the sham state. Contrary to this hypothesis, we found that even though treated tumors elicited unique transcriptome profiles from shams, there was minimal variance in gene expression between peripheral and distal regions of treated tumors, underscoring a uniform transcriptional response to FUS modalities across the tumor landscape. This suggests a more complex interaction between treatment and tumor biology than originally anticipated. Systemic effects of tissue injury could explain why the effects of localized tissue injury from these treatments radiate across the entire tumor and do not simply result in a return to the baseline state observed in sham tissues. It is known that acute tissue injury can result in the release of various DAMPs that can systemic effects, such as IL1b. Additional research into the dose-response relationship and temporal dynamics of FUS-treated tumors are needed to further clarify the mechanistic basis for this phenomenon.</p><p>Both modalities elicited the induction of similar gene pathways related to RNA processing and ribosome biogenesis. Ribosome biogenesis is a critical, multi-step cellular process responsible for constructing ribosomes, the protein synthesis machinery of the cell <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Wang et al., 2021)</ref>. And this underlies general physiological function of all cell processes. In tumor cells, ribosome biogenesis is dysregulated and contributes to their heterogenous nature, as well as promoting tumor growth and expansion <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Zisi, Bartek and Lindström, 2022)</ref>. The activation of these pathways could signify a transition in the overall state of the tumor towards growth. In contrast, sham tissues displayed gene expression profiles that are associated with regulation of inflammatory responses, production of cytokines, and DAMP pathway activation. It is possible that treatment with BH and T-FUS both resulted in the eradication and subsequent suppression of these active processes. Thus, the changes induced by both modalities may provide a unique opportunity to intervene with drugs that specifically target ribosome biogenesis pathways. TH17 cells lack robust cytotoxic capabilities and are thought to exert their anticancer effects indirectly by aiding the arrival of effector tumor suppressive immune cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kryczek et al., 2009)</ref>. Indeed, IL-17 is linked with an increase in tumorinfiltrating IFNγ+ T cells. Specifically, TH17 derived IL-17 and IFNγ work together to boost the secretion of CXCL9 and CXCL10 chemokines by cancer cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kryczek et al., 2009)</ref>. These chemokines are crucial for attracting immune cells, such as T cells and NK cells, to the tumor site. The distal region of T-FUS treated tumors displayed a significant increase in CXCL9 transcripts relative to peripheral regions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3 D</ref>). Additionally, a trending increase was observed for CXCL10 expression in treated tumors relative to shams(Sup_inflammasome B). The extent to which TH17 cells influence this distinct expression pattern remains an open question, highlighting a potential avenue for further research to fully understand the mechanisms of TH17 cell involvement in tumor immunity.</p><p>Heat shock proteins (Hsps) are a group of chaperone proteins that are synthesized in response to cellular stress, such as heat or radiation. Hsp70 is one of the most studied members of this family and has been shown to play a crucial role in protecting cells from stress-induced damage <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Daugaard, Rohde and Jäättelä, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Radons, 2016)</ref>. Interestingly, we found that FUS-induced lesions exhibit an edge of Hsp70 expression 24 hours after treatment, whereas the necrotic areas of sham tumors do not exhibit this expression profile (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1B</ref>). The upregulation of Hsp70 in the edge of FUS-induced lesions suggests that this region is undergoing cellular stress and attempting to protect itself from further damage. This response may be triggered by the release of intracellular contents from the necrotic cells, which can activate the immune system and lead to the recruitment of inflammatory cells to the site of injury. Additionally, Hsp70 expression may contribute to the clearance of damaged proteins and organelles from the damaged cells, thus promoting tissue repair and regeneration. Surprisingly, although Hsp family members were detected in greater abundance in BH and FUS treated tissues relative to shams, there was no detected restriction of expression between peripheral and distal localizations (Sup_HSPA). This is despite the clear margins of Hsp70 expression around the tumor. This data suggests that Hsp70 may be post transcriptionally regulated in a way that prevent epitope accessibility in the distal regions of the tumor. Nonetheless, the observation of Hsp70 expression at the edge of FUS-induced lesions provides important insights into the molecular mechanisms underlying FUS-induced tissue damage and the potential role of Hsp family members in tissue repair and regeneration. Further investigation is needed to elucidate the precise mechanisms by which FUS induces cellular stress and Hsp70 expression, as well as to explore the therapeutic implications of these findings.</p><p>Nonthermal histotripsy tumor ablation has been shown to promote abscopal response and DC activation that enhances cancer immunotherapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Qu et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">van den Bijgaart et al., 2022)</ref>. Additionally, inoculation with cell-free tumor debris created by histotripsy, unlike those made by radiation or freeze/thaw methods, offers some degree of immunity against implanted tumors <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Pepple et al., 2023)</ref>. The data indicate that mechanical histotripsy produces a distinct type of tumor debris, which in turn prompts a different immune response compared to that following T-FUS. Thus, it is surprising that there is a significant overlap between the genes that were upregulated between modalities in this study. Although boiling histotripsy resulted in primarily a mechanical ablation, it is possible that the thermal component of this therapy may be enough to alter the tumor debris in a similar way as T-FUS. Treatment with BH has been shown to create a paste of tumor debris during over treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Khokhlova et al., 2011)</ref>. Here, short pulses (&lt;5ms) were used which theoretically should not induce thermal phenomena <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Wang et al., 2013)</ref>. Further investigation of this this modality is needed to determine if the lesions induced are devoid of thermal phenomena.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations:</head><p>This study comes with several limitations. The instrumentation used differs from that used by other groups, which could lead to different physical phenomena hindering the triangulation of treatment parameters that lead to similar bioeffects. We used a tumor model that is known to be well infiltrated and has a high baseline of immune activity relative to most other models studied. This study focuses on a single timepoint. While we chose a timepoint that has been commonly characterized in the field, there is a lack of temporal nuance to the study that is likely necessary to fully appreciate the bioeffects of FUS therapies. Given these constraints, it's imperative to approach the interpretations and broader applications of our findings with caution, acknowledging that further studies, encompassing diverse instrumentation, tumor models, and multiple timepoints, are essential to comprehensively understand the bioeffects and therapeutic potential of FUS therapies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods:</head><p>Mice and Tumor Model.</p><p>C57BL/6J mice (Jackson Laboratory) were maintained at the University of Virginia under specific pathogen-free conditions. Mouse experiments were performed in accordance with the Animal Welfare Act and approved by the University of Virginia Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. Parental MC38 cells (Kerafast:ENH204-FP) were implanted subcutaneously in PBS.</p><p>Focused Ultrasound Therapy.</p><p>FUS treatments were delivered using an in-house designed system at the University of Virginia <ref type="bibr">(Figure)</ref>. It is composed of 4 single elements focused transducers (Sonic Concept), confocally aligned, each of 33mm diameter and 55mm radius of curvature, for a total equivalent aperture of 105mm. The focal zone at -6dB was measured with a needle hydrophone to be roughly spherical, with a width of 1mm and length of 1.2mm, for a volume less than 1mm^3.</p><p>For targeting, a high-resolution imaging array (MS200, center frequency 30MHz, Visualsonics) is housed at the center of the probe, so that the focal spot is contained within the imaging plane. The therapeutic system is completed with 3D mechanical stages controlled by an Arduino, and driven by a user interface developed in Matlab for treatment planning and for performing the treatment. The animal is positioned above the water bath on a plane holder with a hole in its center where the tumor is positionned.</p><p>For thermal ablation, the four transducers are driven simultaneously by a function generator and a power amplifier (E&amp;I, 200W), delivering a total of 13W (about 10W acoustics) for 7s per treatment point, resulting in a 75C peak temperature as measured by thermocouple.</p><p>For boiling histotripsy treatment, the transducer were connected to a four-channel power amplifier (TPO, Sonic Concept) delivering 115W per channel (460W total), and driven with 5ms pulses at a PRF of 2HZ for 30s (resulting in 60 pulses per treatment point).</p><p>For each of the two FUS modalities, a volume of approximately 40% of the tumor was treated in each case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Digital spatial profiling.</head><p>The GeoMx® DSP platform (NanoString Technologies, Seattle, WA, USA) was employed for spatial transcriptome profiling of murine colon adenocarcinoma <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Merritt et al., 2020)</ref>. GeoMX spatial profiling was performed on 5µm sections cut from FFPE tissues, deparaffinized and rehydrated on glass slides. Tissue sections were then incubated with the murine whole transcriptome analysis(WTA) panel.</p><p>To enable ROI selection, slides were stained with, cleaved CASP-3 or PARP1, and Hsp70. H&amp;E slides were assessed for smooth pink acellular regions surrounded by areas of fragmented nuclei and reduced cell membrane integrity, which is indicative of BH, or fragmented nuclei and reduced cell membrane integrity which is indicative of T-FUS. These morphological features correspond with what has been published regarding BH and T-FUS treatment modalities and were characterized by a pathologist.</p><p>Following slide scanning, flanking H&amp;E, cleaved-PARP1 and Hsp70 stained tissue sections were examined to identify suitable areas for ROI placement. Circular or polygonal ROIs containing approximately 1600 cells were selected in the tumor periphery (distal), directly adjacent to FUS lesions(proximal), or in areas of necrosis. ROIs in each niche, proximal or distal, were placed to sample multiple regions of similar characteristics. Areas of necrosis that were sampled did not yield significant information. After barcode collection, samples underwent NGS sequencing (NovaSeq S4-output of ~2250M reads/lane (Illumina)) at the University of Minnesota.</p><p>Counts were normalized on the GeoMx® instrument to the third quartile for each target. As a higher expression cutoff can lead to less statistical noise, an expression cutoff of 30 counts and LOQ of 2 was employed to enhance statistical acuity <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Rachid Zaim et al., 2020)</ref>. PCA, tSNE, and UMAP dimensionality reduction was run on the GeoMx® DSP platform using the DimReduction.R script V1.2. To assess expression differences across tissue sites, a linear mixed model (LMM) was applied, accounting for the variable number of ROIs per specimen. The Benjamini-Hochberg method corrected p-values to control the false discovery rate, with results presented as a volcano plot. A fold change cutoff of 1.2 was employed to determine differentially expressed genes.</p><p>Cell type deconvolution was performed with the GeoMX DSP software script SpatialDecon_plugin.R V1.3. The deconvolution matrix was derived from a dataset that specialized for both RNA hybridization data and murine immune cells in the context of C57BL/6 mice and MC38 tumors <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Chen et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Pathway enrichment analysis was performed with EnrichR-KG <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Chen et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kuleshov et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Xie et al., 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Availability:</head><p>Text files of raw data and sample information of the NanoString GeoMx DSP have been deposited at the gene expression omnibus: Uploadinprogress Should further details be needed to reinterpret the data presented in this paper, they can be obtained by reaching out to the primary contact upon request.    Cancer cells Collect and section tumors Identify slides Stain and process Start GeoMx run Scan and select ROIs Color key Gene clusters association to tissue domains Spatially-resolved Gene expression 5 Data analysis 6 t-SNE1 t-SNE2 -30 -30 -20 -20 -10 -10 0 0 10 10 20 20 30 30 Label Label Label Label Label Label Label Label 1 10 Nucleotide Tumor implantation 1 2 3 4 A B -10 -5 0 5 -10 -5 0 5 tSNE Dimension 1 tSNE Dimension 2 Region Distal Peri Treat BH T_FUS Sham -2 0 2 4 -5.0 -2.5 0.0 2.5 5.0 UMAP Dimension 1 UMAP Dimension 2 Region Distal Peri Treat BH T_FUS Sham -40 0 40 -50 0 50 100 150 PC1 (Var = 29.1%) PC2 (Var = 12.7%) Region Distal Peri Treat BH T_FUS Sham -30 0 30 60 -50 0 50 100 150 PC1 (Var = 29.1%) PC3 (Var = 6.3%) Region Distal Peri Treat BH T_FUS Sham -30 0 30 60 -40 0 40 PC2 (Var = 12.7%) PC3 (Var = 6.3%) Region Distal Peri Treat BH T_FUS Sham Treated Sham A B C D E -40 0 40 -40 0 40 PC1 (Var = 27.7%) PC2 (Var = 15.8%) Treat T_FUS Region Distal Peri -75 -50 -25 0 25 -40 0 40 PC1 (Var = 27.7%) PC3 (Var = 8.7%) Treat T_FUS Region Distal Peri -75 -50 -25 0 25 -40 0 40 PC2 (Var = 15.8%) PC3 (Var = 8.7%) Treat T_FUS Region Distal Peri -50 0 50 -40 0 40 PC1 (Var = 18.9%) PC2 (Var = 12.8%) Region Peri Distal Treat BH -50 -25 0 25 -40 0 40 PC1 (Var = 18.9%) PC3 (Var = 9.5%) Region Peri Distal Treat BH -50 -25 0 25 -50 0 50 PC2 (Var = 12.8%) PC3 (Var = 9.5%) Region Peri Distal Treat BH -10 0 10 20 -25 0 25 tSNE Dimension 1 tSNE Dimension 2 Treat T_FUS Region Distal Peri -5 0 5 10 -15 -10 -5 0 5 10 tSNE Dimension 1 tSNE Dimension 2 Region Peri Distal Treat BH -1.0 -0.5 0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 -2 -1 0 1 2 UMAP Dimension 1 UMAP Dimension 2 Region Distal Peri Treat BH -5 0 5 -2.5 0.0 2.5 UMAP Dimension 1 UMAP Dimension 2 Treat T_FUS Region Distal Peri A B D C -50 -25 0 25 50 -80 -40 0 40 PC2 (Var = 13.9%) PC3 (Var = 13%) Region Peri Treat BH T_FUS A B C D E -50 -25 0 25 -25 0 25 50 tSNE Dimension 1 tSNE Dimension 2 Region Peri Treat BH T_FUS -2 -1 0 1 2 3 -1.0 -0.5 0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 UMAP Dimension 1 UMAP Dimension 2 Region Peri Treat BH T_FUS -80 -40 0 40 -40 0 40 80 PC1 (Var = 21.5%) PC2 (Var = 13.9%) Region Peri Treat BH T_FUS -50 -25 0 25 50 -40 0 40 80 PC1 (Var = 21.5%) PC3 (Var = 13%) Region Peri Treat BH T_FUS A C D B A B A B</p><note type="other">Figure Legends:</note></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>. The quality of peripheral inflammation produced T-FUS and BH has yet to be characterized. T-FUS and BH samples exhibit evidence of clustering, with the pronounce effects occurring along PC3 in the PCA analysis (Fig 4A). With the described cutoffs, there are around 200 differentially expressed genes between T-FUS and BH (Fig 4D). GO analysis again shows upregulation of mRNA processing pathways in BH compared to T-FUS (Fig. 4 E). Whereas, T-FUS shows upregulation of growth factor signaling pathways Discussion:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Experimental Design and Histological Analysis of Treated Tumors (A) Schematic overview of the study design for spatial transcriptome analysis. (B) Representative histological and immunohistochemical analyses of sham, BH, or T-FUS treated tumors. Images show H&amp;E staining alongside cleaved-CASP3 and Hsp70 immunohistochemistry, highlighting the distinct necrotic and stress response patterns induced by each treatment modality.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Gene Expression Alterations Induced by Therapeutic Ultrasound Modalities (A-C) Dimensional reduction plots (PCA, tSNE, UMAP) comparing gene expression profiles of sham, BH, or T-FUS treated tumor regions 24 hours post-treatment. (D) Volcano plot showcasing genes differentially expressed in treated tumors relative to sham controls, highlighting in red those with an adjusted p-value &lt; 0.05 and a fold change &gt; 1.2. (E) Gene Ontology (GO) analysis of upregulated genes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Transcriptional Profiles of Peripheral and Distal Tumor Regions Following Treatment (A-C) ) Dimensional reduction plots (PCA, tSNE, UMAP) comparing gene expression profiles between peripheral and distal regions within sham, BH, or T-FUS-treated tumors. (D) Volcano plot showcasing genes differentially expressed between peripheral and distal regions, highlighting in red those with an adjusted p-value &lt; 0.05 and a fold change &gt; 1.2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Differential Gene Expression and Pathway Activation in Peripheral Regions of BH vs. T-FUS Treated Tumors (A-C) ) Dimensional reduction plots (PCA, tSNE, UMAP) comparing gene expression profiles between peripheral regions of tumors treated with BH or T-FUS, compared to sham. (D) Volcano plot showcasing genes differentially expressed between BH or T-FUS-treated tumors, highlighting in red those with an adjusted p-value &lt; 0.05 and a fold change &gt; 1.2. (E) GO analysis for differentially expressed genes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="10,101.44,426.63,357.60,250.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="15,93.69,93.93,363.05,166.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="15,96.33,275.37,428.27,179.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="16,73.96,91.32,463.92,159.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments:</head><p>This work was supported by <rs type="funder">Biorepository and Tissue Research Facility</rs> which is supported by the <rs type="funder">University of Virginia School of Medicine, Research Resource Identifiers (RRID)</rs>: <rs type="grantNumber">SCR_022971</rs>. This work was supported by the <rs type="funder">Spatial Biology Core at the University of Virginia</rs>. This work used the <rs type="funder">GeoMx</rs> in the <rs type="institution" subtype="infrastructure">University of Virginia School of Medicine Spatial Biology Core Facility</rs>, RRID:<rs type="grantNumber">SCR_023281</rs></p><p>We thank <rs type="person">Dr. John Hossack</rs> for allowing us to utilize the Vevo 2100 imaging system. This work was supported by the <rs type="funder">Focused Ultrasound Foundation</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_46tWmTC">
					<idno type="grant-number">SCR_022971</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jaqzdsM">
					<idno type="grant-number">SCR_023281</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<listOrg type="infrastructure">
				<org type="infrastructure">					<orgName type="extracted">University of Virginia School of Medicine Spatial Biology Core Facility</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical high-intensity focused ultrasound creates unique tumor debris enhancing dendritic cell-induced T cell activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J E</forename><surname>Van Den Bijgaart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fimmu.2022.1038347</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1038347</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enrichr: interactive and collaborative HTML5 gene list enrichment analysis tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1471-2105-14-128</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">128</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference of immune cell composition on the expression profiles of mouse tissue</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/srep40508</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">40508</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Review of High-Intensity Focused Ultrasound in Urology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cranston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Leslie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ter Haar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/cancers13225696</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The heat shock protein 70 family: Highly homologous proteins with overlapping and distinct functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Daugaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rohde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jäättelä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.febslet.2007.05.039</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">581</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3702" to="3710" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune modulation resulting from MR-guided high intensity focused ultrasound in a model of murine breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Fite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41598-020-80135-1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">927</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">More than just tumor destruction: immunomodulation by thermal ablation of cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Haen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2011/160250</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical &amp; Developmental Immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">160250</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigation of HIFU-induced anti-tumor immunity in a murine tumor model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1479-5876-5-34</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Translational Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Focused ultrasound for immunomodulation of the tumor microenvironment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Joiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Pylayeva-Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dayton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4049/jimmunol.1901430</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">205</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2327" to="2341" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlled tissue emulsification produced by high intensity focused ultrasound shock waves and millisecond boiling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Khokhlova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1121/1.3626152</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3498" to="3510" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Histotripsy methods in mechanical disintegration of tissue: towards clinical applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khokhlova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3109/02656736.2015.1007538</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of hyperthermia : the official journal of European Society for Hyperthermic Oncology, North American Hyperthermia Group</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative study of the immune microenvironment in heterotopic tumor models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kienzl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/cancers16020295</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phenotype, distribution, generation, and functional and clinical relevance of Th17 cells in the human tumor environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kryczek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1182/blood-2009-03-208249</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1141" to="1149" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enrichr: a comprehensive gene set enrichment analysis web server 2016 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kuleshov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nar/gkw377</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">W1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Boosting high-intensity focused ultrasound-induced anti-tumor immunity using a sparse-scan strategy that can more effectively promote dendritic cell maturation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1479-5876-8-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Translational Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applications of focused ultrasound in the brain: from thermoablation to drug delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hynynen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lipsman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41582-020-00418-z</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Reviews. Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiplex digital spatial profiling of proteins and RNA in fixed tissue</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Merritt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41587-020-0472-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Biotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="586" to="599" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidelines for immunological analyses following focused ultrasound treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Padilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/jitc-2023-007455</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal for immunotherapy of cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatiotemporal local and abscopal cell death and immune responses to histotripsy focused ultrasound tumor ablation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pepple</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1012799</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1012799</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-thermal histotripsy tumor ablation promotes abscopal immune responses that enhance cancer immunotherapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/jitc-2019-000200</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal for immunotherapy of cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personalized beyond Precision: Designing Unbiased Gold Standards to Improve Single-Subject Studies of Personal Genome Dynamics from Gene Products</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rachid Zaim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/jpm11010024</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personalized medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human HSP70 family of chaperones: where do we stand?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Radons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12192-016-0676-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Stress &amp; Chaperones</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="404" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Focused ultrasound ablation of melanoma with boiling histotripsy yields abscopal tumor control and antigen-dependent dendritic cell activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Thim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Theranostics</note>
	<note>Preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complete Responses after Hyperthermic Ablation by Ultrasound Guided High Intensity Focused Ultrasound Plus Systemic Chemotherapy for Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vidal-Jove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2013/586769</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Conference Papers in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Liver Histotripsy Mediated Abscopal Effect-Case Report</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vidal-Jove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TUFFC.2021.3100267</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Ultrasonics, Ferroelectrics, and Frequency Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3001" to="3005" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated analysis of the roles of RNA binding proteins and their prognostic value in clear cell renal cell carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2021/5568411</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of healthcare engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">5568411</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Histological and biochemical analysis of mechanical and thermal bioeffects in boiling histotripsy lesions induced by high intensity focused ultrasound</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-N</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2012.10.012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ultrasound in Medicine &amp; Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene Set Knowledge Discovery with Enrichr</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/cpz1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current protocols</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">90</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Histotripsy: A Method for Mechanical Tissue Ablation with Ultrasound</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-bioeng-073123-022334</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Biomedical Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeting ribosome biogenesis in cancer: lessons learned and way forward</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zisi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bartek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lindström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/cancers14092126</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
