<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Climate change risks for the West African Economic and Monetary Union reduction advanced approaches</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Mathieu</forename><surname>Badolo</surname></persName>
							<email>mathieu.badolo@cesmb.org</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Centre Mathieu Badolo de recherche et d&apos;innovation</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ouagadougou</settlement>
									<country key="BF">Burkina Faso</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Climate change risks for the West African Economic and Monetary Union reduction advanced approaches</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">029BDEFD7D27FCFFD6A0AEE13CB907C5</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:33+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>UEMOA</term>
					<term>Climate change</term>
					<term>risks</term>
					<term>reduction</term>
					<term>scientific framework</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In many regions of the world, economic and social development levers include economic, social, institutional and political subregional and regional integration organizations. In climate vulnerability contexts, climate change adverse effects could deteriorate these development levers, reduce their contribution to economic and social development and their impacts. A solution for reducing these risks is to integrate subregional integration organizations into national and regional climate change resilience policies. In this article, the Badolo resilience formalism and the ClimResilience scientific framework are used to develop the Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework. It suggests West African economic and monetary union configurations to be achieved to protect it from climate change direct and indirect adverse effects. They are governed by specific climate change impacts, vulnerability factors, resilience solutions classes. Basically, the Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework proposes a new approach, methodological tools, information bodies and decision making tools to efficiently build the West African Economic and Monetary Union configurations which protect it from regression dynamics linked to the impacts of climate change.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.Introduction</head><p>In many regions of the world, economic and social development levers include economic, social, institutional and political subregional and regional integration organizations. In climate vulnerability contexts, climate change adverse effects could deteriorate these development levers, reduce their contribution to economic and social development and their impacts. A solution for reducing these risks is to integrate subregional integration organizations into national and regional climate change resilience policies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.The West African Economic and Monetary Union (UEMOA) includes eight countries which are Benin, Burkina Faso, Ivory Coast, Guinea Bissau, Mali, Niger, Senegal and Togo. These different countries are characterized by multiple vulnerabilities to climate change, which are risks for the West African Economic and Monetary Union principles and objectives, institutional system, financial regime and actions <ref type="bibr">[6 -7]</ref>. Reducing these risks is a challenge to consider for configurations of economic and monetary union on which climate change has only minor adverse effects. This article proposes the Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework to design, plan and implement subregional resilience dynamics integrating climate change risks linked the West African Economic and Monetary Union. The scientific foundations of this scientific framework are the Badolian resilience formalism which specifies which specifies the climate change resilience configurations to be achieved. The methodological tools of the ClimResilience framework are used to develop resilience trajectories information bodies. The UemoaClimPrsopect resilience scheme suggests resilience trajectories including short-term, medium-term and long-term resilience trajectory segments. <ref type="bibr">[8 -9]</ref>. The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework proposes a new approach, methodological tools, information bodies and decision making tools to efficiently build the West African Economic and Monetary Union configurations which protect it from regression dynamics linked to the impacts of climate change.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methodology</head><p>The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework includes three basic parameters which are the vector y (y1, y2, y3, y4, y5, y6, y7, y8) associated with the eight UEMOA member countries, the climate risks vector r (r1, r2, r2, r3, r4) and the vector u (u1, u2, u3, u4) associated with UEMOA.</p><p>The components of these vectors are: ▪ y1= Benin, y2= Burkina Faso , y3= Côte-d'Ivoire, y4= Guinée Bissau, y5= Mali, y6= Niger, y7= Sénégal, , y8= Togo. ▪ r1= floods, r2=droughts, r3 = heat waves, r4 = sea level rise. ▪ u1= UEMOA principles and objectives , u2= UEMOA institutional system, u3= UEMOA financial regime, u4= UEMOA actions</p><p>The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework scientific foundations are the Badolian climate resilience formalism . It specifies the UEMOA resilience configuration ũ and the UEMOA member countries resilience configuration Ỹ to be achieved <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>:</p><p>▪ r ũ≈ ø ▪ r Ỹ≈ ø</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Information families for national resilience configurations</head><p>The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework information families for national resilience configurations are information matrices and bodies. The elements aij (i = 1, …, 4; j = 1, …, 8) of the UEMOA member countries climate change direct and indirect impacts matrix A (4, 8) are <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9 ]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">• aij = riyjdo, riyjd1, ..., riyjdm</formula><p>The family dyj (j = 1, ..., 8) of climate risks impacts on a country yj is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">▪ dyj = a1j U a2J U a3j Ua4j</formula><p>The climate risks impacts on the UEMOA area family dy is: dy = dy(dy1, dy2, dy3, dy4, dy5, dy6, dy7, dy8)</p><p>The elements bij (i = 1, …, 4; j = 1, …, 8) of the UEMOA member countries climate risks vulnerability factors matrix B (4, 8) are <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9 ]</ref>:</p><p>• bij = riyjvo, riyjv1, ..., riyjvm The vulnerability factors group riyjvk (k = 0, …, m) is the group of vulnerability factors to be reduced to mitigate the climate change impact riyjdk.</p><p>The family vyj (j = 1, ..., 8) of vulnerability factors of a country yj to climate change is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">• vyj = b1j U b2J U b3j U b4j</formula><p>The UEMOA area vulnerability factors to climate change family vy is:</p><p>• vy = vy (vy11, vy2, vy3, vy4, vy5, vy6, vy7, vy8)</p><p>The elements cij (i = 1, …, 4; j = 1, …, p) of the matrix C (4, 8) of the resilience solutions of the UEMOA zone to climate change are:</p><p>• bij = riyjzo, riyjz1, ..., riyjzm The resilience solutions group riyjzk (k = 0, …, m) is the group of resilience solutions to be implemented to mitigate the climate change impact riyjdk.</p><p>The family zyj (j = 1, ..., 8) of the resilience solutions of a country yj to climate change is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">• zyj = c1yj U c2yJ U c3yj U c4yj</formula><p>The UEMOA area resilience solutions to climate change family zy is:</p><p>• zy = zy (zy1, zy2, zy3, zy4, zy5, zy6, zy7, zy8)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Information families for UEMOA resilience configurations</head><p>The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework Climate change risks families for UEMOA principles and objectives, institutional system, financial regime and actions are :</p><p>• du1 = dy(u1) = dy1(u1), dy2(u1), dy3(u1), dy4(u1), dy5(u1), dy6(u1), dy7(u1), dy8(u1)</p><p>• du2 = dy(u2) = dy1(u2), dy2(u2), dy3(u2), dy4(u2), dy5(u2), dy6(u2), dy7(u2), dy8(u2)</p><p>• du3 = dy(u3) = dy1(u3), dy2(u3), dy3(u3), dy4(u3), dy5(u3), dy6(u3), dy7(u3), dy8(u3)</p><p>• du4 = dy(u4) = dy1(u4), dy2(u4), dy3(u4), dy4(u4), dy5(u4), dy6(u4), dy7(u4), dy8(u4)</p><p>The combination (du) of the families du1, du2, du3 and du4 is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">• du = du1 U du2 U du2 U du3 U du4</formula><p>The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework UEMOA vulnerability factors to climate change risks family is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">• vu = vu1 U vu2 U vu2 U vu3 U vu4</formula><p>The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework UEMOA resilience solution to climate change risks family is: Information classes for the short-term resilience segment χ1 UEMOA facilities for the implementation of information classes χ1dy, χ1vy, χ1zy; strategies for integrating information classes χ1du, χ1vu, χ1zu, χ1Ỹ, χ1ũ into the management of UEMOA UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework resilience scheme χ1dy, χ1vy, χ1zy, χ1du, χ1vu, χ1zu, χ1Ỹ, χ1ũ UEMOA facilities for the implementation of information classes χ2dy, χ2vy, χ2zy; strategies for integrating information classes χ2du, χ2vu, χ2zu, χ2Ỹ, χ2ũ into the management of UEMOA Resilience information families, dy, vy, zy, du, vu, zu, χ1, χ2, χ3, ỹ, ũ Information classes for the medium-term resilience segment χ2 χ2dy, χ2vy, χ2zy, χ2du, χ2vu, χ2zu, χ2Ỹ, χ2ũ UEMOA facilities for the implementation of information classes χ3dy, χ3vy, χ3zy; strategies for integrating information classes χ3du, χ3vu, χ3zu, χ3Ỹ, χ3ũ into the management of UEMOA Information classes for the long-term resilience segment χ3 χ3dy, χ3vy, χ3zy, χ3du, χ3vu, χ3zu, χ3Ỹ, χ3ũ Figure (1): UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework elements A resilience trajectory segment χk (k =1, 2, 3) : • mitigates a climate risk impacts class χkdy. It is a portion of the family (dy) ; • reduces a vulnerability factors class χkvy. It is a subset of the family vy; • implements a resilience solutions class χkzy. It is part of the family zy; • reduces a climate change risks class χkdu . It is a subfamily of the family (du); • reduces a vulnerability factors class χkvu. It is a subfamily of the family (vu);</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">• zu = zu1 U zu2 U zu2 U zu3 U zu4</formula><p>• implements a resilience solutions class χkzu, which is a subfamily of the family (zu);</p><p>• achieves a configuration of resilience χkỹ to climate risks;</p><p>• achieves a configuration of resilience χkũ to risks induced by climate change.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>Reducing climate change risks for the West African economic and monetary union is a complex action whose efficiency and impact are determined by the robustness and relevance of the theoretical, methodological and decisionmaking tools implemented. Climate change risks reduction trajectories should be based on approaches, information families and resilience schemes that achieve planned resilience objectives. The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework proposes a new approach, methodological tools, information bodies and decision making tools to efficiently build the West African Economic and Monetary Union configurations which protect it from regression dynamics linked to the impacts of climate change.</p><p>Theoretical and methodological tools for improving the scientific foundations of climate change risks integration into national or regional resilience policies is strongly considered in scientific literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. The Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework is a new scientific contribution. It results from the Badolian resilience formalism and the ClimResilience framework tools. Its Climate change impacts, vulnerability factors and resilience solutions corpuses are multi-risk and concern the UEMOA eight member countries. The resilience scheme implements the ClimResilience resilience approach to build short-term, medium-term and long-term resilience configurations. Political management of climate change resilience could integrate specific UEMOA facilities for each member country, based on the bodies of information proposed. Fundamentally, the Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework integrates the theoretical, methodological and decision making tools of the Badolian resilience formalism and the ClimResilience scientific framework for climate change risks reduction new scientific foundations for the West African Economic and Monetary Union.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>The objective of this article was scientific foundations of climate change risks reduction for the West African economic and monetary union. The main contribution proposed is the Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework. It results from the Badolian resilience formalism and the ClimResilience framework tools. Its Climate change impacts, vulnerability factors and resilience solutions corpuses are multi-risk and concern the UEMOA eight member countries. The resilience scheme implements the ClimResilience resilience approach to build short-term, medium-term and long-term resilience configurations. Political management of climate change resilience could integrate specific UEMOA facilities for each member country, based on the bodies of information proposed. Fundamentally, the Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework integrates the theoretical, methodological and decision making tools of the Badolian resilience formalism and the ClimResilience scientific framework for climate change risks reduction new scientific foundations for the West African Economic and Monetary Union</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure ( 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure (1) describes the elements of the Badolo UemoaClimPrsopect scientific framework</figDesc><graphic coords="3,401.76,467.28,182.76,78.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of interest</head><p>The author declares no financial or non-financial conflicts of interest ORCID ID Mathieu Badolo : <ref type="url" target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0419-3183">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0419-3183</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing regional economic impacts and responses to climate change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Abler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Shortle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adam</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gbadebo</forename><surname>Oladosu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0921-8181(00)00022-9</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0921-8181(00)00022-9" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global and Planetary Change</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0921- 8181</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of climate change on incomes and convergence in Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Florent</forename><surname>Baarsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jessie</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Granadillos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">William</forename><surname>Hare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Knaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mario</forename><surname>Krapp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michiel</forename><surname>Schaeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hermann</forename><surname>Lotze-Campen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.worlddev.2019.104699</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.worlddev.2019.104699" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Development</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0305-750X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104699</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate change and food security causality in ECOWAS region: Do countries interdependence matter?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Messiah</forename><surname>Abaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Walter</forename><surname>Okwudili Ugwuoke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.foohum.2024.100393</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foohum.2024.100393" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Food and Humanity</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2949-8244</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100393</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Innocent Okwanya</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate risk and financial stress in ECOWAS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mamadou</forename><surname>Amadou Nouhou Diallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Seydou</forename><surname>Mouminy Bah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nourou Ndiaye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jclimf.2023.100025</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclimf.2023.100025" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Climate Finance</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2949-7280</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100025</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing two decades of change across the Eco-Regions of West Africa using remote sensing technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Makinde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Marchant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Salami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.sciaf.2023.e02056</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sciaf.2023.e02056" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific African</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2468-2276</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2056</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate change in Africa: Impacts, adaptation, and policy responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lotsmart</forename><surname>Fonjong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Matose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sonnenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2024.102912</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2024.102912" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Environmental Change</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0959-3780</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">102912</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing Climate Change Risks in Africa -A Global Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ademola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Adenle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Keith</forename><surname>Twomlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Alverson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rafaello</forename><surname>Cattaneo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pradeep</forename><surname>Cervigni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Saleemul</forename><surname>Kurukulasuriya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ariella</forename><surname>Huq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jane</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Helfgott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ebinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2017.06.004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolecon.2017.06.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecological Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0921-8009</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Badolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31219/osf.io/fksjp</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.31219/osf.io/fksjp" />
		<title level="m">The Badolian climate change resilience mathematical formalism</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ClimResilience, a global climate resilience framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Badolo</forename><surname>Mathieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21203/rs.3.rs-3942168/v1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-3942168/v1" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A methodology for assessing climate services&apos; needs: West Africa case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Veronica</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Grasso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maxx</forename><surname>Dilley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amir</forename><surname>Delju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nakiete</forename><surname>Msemo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cliser.2021.100252</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cliser.2021.100252" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Climate Services</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2405-8807</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100252</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Re-balancing climate services to inform climate-resilient planning -A conceptual framework and illustrations from sub-Saharan Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Katharine</forename><surname>Vincent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Declan</forename><surname>Conway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dougill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joanna</forename><surname>Pardoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emma</forename><surname>Archer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ajay</forename><surname>Gajanan Bhave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rebecka</forename><surname>Henriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neha</forename><surname>Mittal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Mkwambisi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Estelle</forename><surname>Rouhaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dorothy</forename><surname>Tembo-Nhlema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.crm.2020.100242</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.crm.2020.100242" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Climate Risk Management</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2212-0963</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100242</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monitoring, evaluation and learning requirements for climate-resilient development pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edward</forename><surname>Sparkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Saskia</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Werners</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cosust.2023.101329</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cosust.2023.101329" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Environmental Sustainability</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1877-3435</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of the global climate change impacts, adaptation, and sustainable mitigation measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Abbass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Qasim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11356-022-19718-6</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-022-19718-6" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ Sci Pollut Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42539" to="42559" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An overview of climate change adaptation and mitigation research in Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Baninla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sharifi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Allam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sjp</forename><surname>Tume</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Gangtar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fclim.2022.976427</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Clim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">976427</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Climate change in Africa: Impacts, adaptation, and policy responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lotsmart</forename><surname>Fonjong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Matose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sonnenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2024.102912</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2024.102912" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Environmental Change</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0959-3780</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">102912</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
