<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">How to Develop and Use Open Educational Resources</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Flavio</forename><surname>Azevedo</surname></persName>
							<email>f.a.azevedo@uu.nl</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Emily</forename><surname>Friedel</surname></persName>
							<email>emilyjfriedel@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sarah</forename><surname>Ashcroft-Jones</surname></persName>
							<email>sarah.ashcroft-jones@columbia.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Max</forename><surname>Korbmacher</surname></persName>
							<email>max.korbmacher@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kelly</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
							<email>k.e.lloyd@leeds.ac.uk</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dushime</forename><forename type="middle">Richard</forename><surname>Mudahera</surname></persName>
							<email>mudaherarich@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Antonia</forename><surname>Krasteva</surname></persName>
							<email>antoniakrasteva65@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hakile</forename><surname>Resulbegoviq</surname></persName>
							<email>hakile.resulbegoviq@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giorgia</forename><surname>Andreolli</surname></persName>
							<email>giorgia.andreolli@eurac.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Leticia</forename><surname>Micheli</surname></persName>
							<email>l.rettore.micheli@fsw.leidenuniv.nl</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Interdisciplinary Social Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Utrecht University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Deakin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Mailman School of Public Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Haukeland University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bergen</settlement>
									<country key="NO">Norway</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiography</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Western Norway University of Applied Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bergen</settlement>
									<country key="NO">Norway</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Leeds Institute of Health Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Leeds</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Framework for Open and Reproducible Research Training</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Framework for Open and Reproducible Research Training</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Ljubljana</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute for Applied Linguistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Eurac Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="department">Social, Economic and Organisational Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Leiden University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center for Neuroscience and Cell Biology and Centre for Innovative Biomedicine and Biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Globally Distributed Open Research and Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Priya Silverstein</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Coimbra</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">How to Develop and Use Open Educational Resources</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6ED0C9301911B4569EF27C5B208BC3E0</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.35542/osf.io/sn693</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-19T16:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>FA: Conceptualisation, Project Administration, Supervision, Writing -original draft, Writing -reviewing &amp; editing. EF: Project Administration, Writing -reviewing &amp; editing. SAJ: Visualization, Writing -reviewing &amp; editing. HR: Visualization. MK, KL, DRM, AK, GA, LM, PS: Writing -reviewing &amp; editing Open Educational Resources</term>
					<term>Educational Equity</term>
					<term>Epistemic Justice</term>
					<term>Critical Pedagogy</term>
					<term>Knowledge Co-Creation</term>
					<term>Decolonising Education</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This chapter explores the critical role of Open Educational Resources (OERs) in advancing open science and promoting educational equity. OERs are freely-available teaching and learning materials that can be reused and adapted, making them powerful tools for democratising access to knowledge. Drawing on principles from critical pedagogy, feminist, and decolonial scholarship, we position OERs not only as cost-saving tools but as instruments of epistemic justice and inclusion. This chapter outlines five foundational principles for OER development-accessibility, inclusivity, collaboration, sustainability, and social justice-and offers a step-by-step framework for creating, implementing, and sustaining high-quality OERs. Case studies are presented to demonstrate participatory and community-driven approaches to OER creation. We also examine common challenges such as structural inequality and linguistic barriers, providing actionable strategies for addressing each. By embedding values of openness, fairness, and co-creation, we show how OERs can help reshape curricula and cultivate more inclusive academic ecosystems.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">What are Open Educational Resources?</head><p>Open Educational Resources (OERs) are teaching and learning materials made freely available under licences that permit reuse and adaptation. By removing cost barriers, they expand access and help democratise knowledge. As such, OERs are fundamental to the broader open science movement, which promotes access to data, publications, and educational materials <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Parsons et al., 2022)</ref>. Both OERs and open science emphasise empowerment, discourse, and social equity within research, educational, and pedagogical settings. Defining OERs invites a deeper question: why should educators and institutions invest in creating and using them? The following section explores the motivations behind OER adoption, drawing on empirical evidence and social justice frameworks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Why Create and Use OERs?</head><p>International bodies such as UNESCO, the EU Commission, and NASA have endorsed OERs as a means to expand universal access to high-quality open learning materials and foster more inclusive and equitable knowledge societies <ref type="bibr">(European Commission, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">NASA, 2025;</ref><ref type="bibr">UNESCO, 2021)</ref>. Empirical research supports these claims: students using OERs perform as well as those using commercial textbooks, with marginalised students benefiting substantially from OER adoption <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Nusbaum et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Colvard et al., 2018)</ref>. OERs thus offer a means to advance educational equity while preserving academic quality. By alleviating financial burdens without compromising rigour, OERs can mitigate inequities in educational participation and success.</p><p>Beyond simple cost-saving benefits, OERs carry a deeper promise of democratising knowledge production and decolonising curricula. Critical pedagogy urges educators to move away from a 'banking' model of education where students are passive recipients of knowledge, towards a participatory model that treats learners as co-creators <ref type="bibr">(Freire, 1970)</ref>. OERs operationalise this vision by inviting both instructors and students to actively engage in producing, revising, and improving educational materials. Such collaborative knowledgemaking fosters what Freire called 'critical consciousness', empowering learners to question and shape the knowledge structures that affect their lives <ref type="bibr">(Freire, 1970)</ref>. Similarly, feminist pedagogues like bell hooks emphasise that teaching can be an act of liberation and inclusion-a process of transgression against racial, gender, and class hierarchies in traditional education, especially when teachers and students learn together <ref type="bibr">(hooks, 1994)</ref>. Openly sharing educational resources resonates strongly with these values, offering opportunities for diverse voices to be heard and integrated into learning materials.</p><p>Decolonial scholars further emphasise that the co-creation and free distribution of knowledge challenge the legacy of science for domination and disrupt colonial power imbalances in academia <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Kato et al., 2023)</ref>. By valuing indigenous knowledge systems, local contexts, and multilingualism, OERs resist one-size-fits-all narratives and instead promote epistemic justice <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Fricker, 2007)</ref>. Thus, developing and using OERs is not only a technical and logistical endeavour, but a pedagogical and political project aimed at epistemic emancipation <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Cassiani, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">dos Santos et al., 2024)</ref>. This chapter outlines a detailed framework for creating and utilising OERs within open science education. The following sections provide academics, early-career scholars, and educators with the guiding principles and practical steps to harness OERs to advance open and equitable education. We conclude with OER case studies from the Framework for Open and Reproducible Research Training (FORRT), which illustrates a community-driven model for open education in open science.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">How Can We Create OERs?</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Key Principles for Developing OERs</head><p>When developing OERs, educators should be guided by principles that ensure these resources fulfil their promise of openness and equity. We highlight five of these interrelated principles-accessibility, inclusivity, sustainability, collaboration, and social justice-that are central to OER creation. Accessibility in design is an ethical imperative in OER creation, ensuring that 'open' truly means open for all. Inclusive OERs are intentionally designed to reflect diverse identities, cultures, and epistemologies, rather than centring traditional hegemonic or dominant viewpoints. Sustainability in OERs involves long-term maintenance planning, which includes building an enduring, supportive community. The collaborative principle recognises that open education is a shared endeavour, moving beyond the lone instructor model to collective knowledge-building. Underpinning all of these is a commitment to social justice: OERs should actively promote equitable access and outcomes in education. The FORRT case studies at the end of this chapter provide examples of these five principles in action. Grounded in these foundations, we propose a practical, replicable framework that educators can implement and adapt in OER development.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Practical Steps to Create OERs</head><p>Developing OERs-whether a single lesson or an entire textbook-can be approached systematically. Here, we outline a step-by-step guide to creating OERs, from initial planning through iterative improvement, informed by best practices in instructional design and community.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Six practical steps for OER creation</head><p>Step 1: Identify Needs and Engage Stakeholders. Every OER project should start with a clear understanding of the educational need it intends to fill. Gaining this understanding may include conducting a needs assessment (what problem are you solving?) and articulating the specific project goals. Critically, identify the audience (e.g., first-year undergraduates) and your target learning outcomes.</p><p>In participatory OER design, early stakeholder engagement is key to building buy-in and including diverse voices and perspectives. Stakeholders can include students, other instructors or colleagues, and community representatives. For example, consider holding a focus group with students about what they find challenging in the current materials, or consult academic peers regarding the most helpful content or format. If the OER is intended for a global audience, connect with educators from different regions to ensure maximal adaptability. Open education ethos also encourages reuse and remix, so assess existing resources -you might find an open dataset or graphic you can adapt rather than creating one from scratch.</p><p>Step 2: Planning and Design. With a clear need identified, begin designing the OER by defining the scope and structure of the material, ensuring alignment with learning outcomes, and creating an outline. Applying principles of backward design can be useful <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Wiggins &amp; McTighe, 2005)</ref>. First, start with the learning outcomes or competencies, then plan content and activities that lead to them, and finally consider how learners will demonstrate their learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Stein &amp; Graham, 2020)</ref>. During planning, inclusive design should be integrated from the outset rather than retrofitted later. This includes mindfully incorporating diverse examples, avoiding culturally-specific idioms that might not translate, and including explanatory context for learners less familiar with background knowledge.</p><p>Decide on the level of OER interactivity (e.g., static text vs. multimedia) while keeping accessibility in mind: multimedia should have alternatives, such as transcripts for audio and captions for video. Finally, select an appropriate licence type; most OERs use a Creative Commons CC-BY, CC-BY-SA, or CC-BY-SA-NC licence to maximise reuse. Ensure source materials such as illustrations and datasets are compatible with this selection. Consider design modularity. Structure your content to ensure others can easily reuse individual components, such as by writing the materials using short, self-contained chapters. We recommend using storyboarding or outline templates to help organise your content. Overall, well-planned OERs should have a logical flow that enables the flexibility for future remixing.</p><p>Multiple approaches should be employed to ensure a collaborative OER design. This may include assigning roles based on expertise to draft different sections of the material, determining early how credit will be allocated (e.g., CRediT taxonomy; <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Brand et al., 2015)</ref>, and planning a timeline for engaging various contributors (e.g., stakeholders, reviewers). We recommend utilising shared working platforms (e.g., Google Docs, GitHub, Open Science Framework [OSF]) to allow asynchronous contributions and foster transparency and version control from the beginning. By the end of Step 2, you should have developed a comprehensive outline of the OER, a collaborative team plan for creation, and identified a shared working platform to guide subsequent development.</p><p>Step 3: Content Development and Open Licensing. This step is the core work of writing the textbook or building the course materials. As you develop content, continuously apply open principles: attribute sources and use open content whenever possible. For example, prefer Creative Commons images over copyrighted ones. If you include excerpts of text or data, ensure these are in the public domain, openly licensed, or fall under fair use; otherwise, seek permission or alternatives. Many OER developers maintain a spreadsheet to track permissions and licences of included materials.</p><p>Ensure clarity and accessibility in the original text by writing in clear prose, defining jargon, and avoiding unnecessarily elitist or overly technical language. Incorporate interactive elements and use open rather than proprietary software to enhance learning. For example, embedding quizzes using the open source tool, H5P, or including discussion prompts.</p><p>Periodic peer review is valuable for identifying errors, suggesting additional perspectives, or indicating where clarity is lacking. Checking for inclusivity and bias throughout is also essential: Are various social groups represented appropriately, and is the language inclusive? Engaging co-authors from different academic and sociodemographic backgrounds and consulting external advisors can help here. Throughout development, maintain documentation, such as a changelog, to record sources and rationales for content decisions to facilitate future revisions. Finally, apply the chosen open licence visibly on the work (e.g., a CC-BY licence statement on the front page and in the metadata). This clearly communicates how the material can be used, a hallmark of OERs.</p><p>Step 4: Testing and Piloting. Before full release, conduct a pilot review or, ideally, implement the OER in a live course for one term or module. Observe how students interact with the material: Do they understand it? Are there frequent questions or misconceptions? Gather feedback from learners through surveys or focus groups on usability (e.g., was it easy to navigate?), engagement (e.g., did the activities help learning?), and any content gaps or biases.</p><p>If a live pilot is not feasible, consider a review pilot by sharing the draft OER with a small group of peers or target users outside class. Some OER projects host workshops or hackathons where participants review materials and provide feedback, exemplifying the participatory principle by treating end-users as co-creators. Systematically analyse the feedback to assess for common themes and/or critical issues, and test all technical aspects (e.g., ensure all live links work).</p><p>To ensure inclusivity, accessibility checks are crucial. Use tools such as accessibilitychecker.org for websites, and wherever possible, involve users with disabilities to test accessibility (e.g., ask a screen-reader user to test an e-textbook). For transparency, document the feedback and planned changes openly (e.g., on a project site or appendix). By the end of Step 4, you should have a list of revisions to make, based on end-user input, to enhance the OER's effectiveness. At this stage, prepare the required supplementary material, e.g., generate a table of contents, index, and accessibility transcripts, to help package your final OER.</p><p>Step 5: Refinement and Iterative Revision. Revise the OER according to pilot/review feedback, which may involve minor edits (typos, clarifications) or larger changes (e.g., reordering sections, addressing a noted gap). Carefully address any cultural or bias issues raised. This may include adding content from a crucially missing perspective or rephrasing text that inadvertently marginalises a group. Revisions should also consider alignment: double-check that the revised content aligns with the intended learning outcomes and assessments to ensure resource coherence.</p><p>Given the iterative nature of OERs, a key question is when conclude the revision process. A practical approach is to publish the content with a version 1.0 once all major feedback is incorporated and the content meets the project goals, e.g., 'Open Science Lab Manual, Version 1.0 (2025)'. Using version control is best practice and signals to users that content is maintained and may be updated. Once the OER is ready to be published, the next challenge is ensuring it reaches those who most need it.</p><p>Step 6: Dissemination and Community Building. Share and promote your OER to help it reach relevant learners and educators. Start by choosing appropriate OER repositories or platforms for hosting, such as university OER libraries, OER Commons, MERLOT, the OSF, GitHub, or domain-specific sites (e.g., forrt.org). Include descriptive keywords and an abstract, and ensure metadata (e.g., author, licence, tags) are attached to improve discoverability.</p><p>Next, consider how to advertise the resource through social media, conference presentations, webinars, and/or directly contacting relevant networks (e.g., email Open Education listservs or relevant teaching organisations). Another powerful approach is to encourage early adopters and ask for short testimonials to be shared to enhance credibility. Building a community around the OER can lead to a virtuous cycle of dissemination. Establish forums for users to share experiences, tips, and feedback (e.g., a public GitHub page, an email inbox for feedback, etc.). These support newcomers and inform future userdriven revisions.</p><p>Where possible, track usage, such as through platform download statistics or records of adoption. This is useful for demonstrating impact, e.g., 'X University saved Y dollars by switching to this OER', which may encourage further adoption and can evidence future funding applications. From a social justice perspective, dissemination should target communities that stand to benefit most. This may also include identifying volunteers to translate the materials into relevant languages, and, where possible, acquiring funding for those efforts. While openness means anyone can use a resource, proactive outreach ensures everyone knows they are invited.</p><p>By following these practical steps-engage, plan, develop, pilot, refine, disseminateeducators can systematically create effective OERs that are embraced by the community. These steps are not strictly linear, as continuous improvement is a cornerstone of quality, open educational materials. Overall, these practices embody the earlier principles described at the beginning of the chapter: stakeholder engagement and piloting promote inclusivity and social justice, collaboration is inherent throughout, sustainability is ensured by community building, and accessibility is considered at multiple stages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Challenges and Solutions in OER Implementation</head><p>While OERs promise to democratise knowledge and expand access, they are not immune to the structural inequities and systemic challenges that pervade traditional educational systems. Without conscious intervention, OERs can replicate or even exacerbate existing disparities. Critical, feminist, and decolonial scholars have long cautioned that openness alone does not equate to justice-genuine transformation requires an intersectional awareness of power, representation, and access. The infographic below outlines these core challenges alongside key issues and promising solutions, serving as both a diagnostic tool and a roadmap. Recognising and addressing structural challenges is essential, but so is equipping educators to navigate and use OERs in their classrooms. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">How Educators Can Adopt and Adapt OERs</head><p>Successfully adopting and adapting OERs requires more than simply replacing traditional materials with free alternatives. It is a strategic and pedagogical process involving critical evaluation, thoughtful integration, and intentional customisation to ensure that resources meet the diverse needs of learners while aligning with course objectives. Educators must engage in iterative practices, as each stage of adopting and adapting OER materials-such as discovering existing resources, integrating and customising content, seeking student engagement, establishing accessibility support, and reflection-builds upon the others, reinforcing the openness, equity, and sustainability that undergird the open education movement.</p><p>This participatory and justice-oriented approach echoes critical pedagogical traditions, notably Paulo Freire's (1970) vision of education as a collaborative and emancipatory act. When thoughtfully implemented, OER adoption is more than cost-effective or efficient; it is transformative. It can reshape the educational experience by democratising knowledge production and dissemination. The following figure provides an overview of best practices for educators seeking to adopt and adapt OERs. These practices are adaptable across disciplines and educational levels, offering a flexible yet structured roadmap toward more open, inclusive, and contextually relevant teaching. This case study is a dynamic example of OER creation in action, aligned strongly with participatory and inclusive design.</p><p>The POST-Edu initiative provides an OER example of co-creation and capacity-building that encapsulates many themes of this chapter. The initiative is creating OER modules to help educators teach open science, and it does so through a positive, inclusive, and participatory design process (https://forrt.org/teaching_os).</p><p>Project Overview: POST-Edu (Promoting Open Science Teaching) is funded by a national research council (NWO, Netherlands). The primary output is three self-paced training modules for educators: (1) a positive module focusing on how to frame open science teaching in an encouraging, benefit-driven way; (2) a participatory module focusing on engaging students in the process; and (3) an inclusive module focusing on diversity and inclusion in open science education. These modules will be openly published as an online toolkit, functioning as an OER for educators.</p><p>Participatory Design Events: POST-Edu models participatory co-design (i.e., designed in collaboration with end-users from the beginning). In Phase 1 (mid-2024), the team organised three launch events (virtual workshops), inviting educators from various universities to share their experiences, needs, and wishes regarding teaching open science. Qualitative data were collected through guided discussions and brainstorming with educators to directly inform module content, ensuring it addresses real-world scenarios. Such an approach is reminiscent of Freirean pedagogical circles <ref type="bibr">(Freire, 1970)</ref>, where the teachers collectively reflect and generate knowledge about their practice. These events also help build a community of practice before the modules are released-participants are listed as contributors in the final output and likely feel invested in the outcome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Content Development with Evidence Base:</head><p>In Phase 2 (late 2024-2025), the POST-Edu team is developing the modules in close collaboration with educators who were invited to participate in the project either as members of the Development Teams (i.e., developing content) or Focus Teams (i.e., providing feedback to Development Teams). They are drawing on FORRT's clusters (https://forrt.org/clusters/) and resources, meaning the content will be grounded in a comprehensive literature base. Each module is created with interactive pedagogy in mind-including self-reflection prompts (e.g., 'Is my course syllabus diverse?'), exercises and examples of how the topics could be incorporated into teaching/mentoring. Planned Open Dissemination: Once developed and tested by educators in Phase 3, the modules will be released openly as an online toolkit. Importantly, because these modules themselves are OERs, a teacher in Brazil could take a module, translate it, and adapt examples to local science contexts-enabling localisation. The project's funding and structure ensure that materials will be free and encourage adaptation. By providing structured training for educators, POST-Edu addresses a meta-level of OER usage, since to teach open science, one should use open materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Challenges and Anticipation:</head><p>The POST-Edu team is mindful of challenges such as varying baseline knowledge. Hence, modules may need different entry points or a modular design to cater to different levels. Motivating busy faculty to engage with another training is also challenging. To that end, framing modules as short, benefit-oriented, and directly applicable is key.</p><p>Though still in progress, POST-Edu exemplifies the forward-looking approach to OERs: fostering an open education ecosystem through community-building and focusing on educators as learners and agents of change.</p><p>2nd Case Study: OpenLearn Course on Open Research This case study underscores the viability of an individual scholar leading a high-impact OER in open science, and the importance of institutional support (platforms such as OpenLearn) in amplifying such efforts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background and Development:</head><p>The course was created by Dr Priya Silverstein, an early-career researcher deeply engaged in open science education, after they were approached by the Open University (OU), which hosts the OpenLearn platform. All online courses created through OpenLearn are obligatorily OERs, meaning they can be accessed for free by anyone with an internet connection. They can also be downloaded for offline archiving and dissemination. Initial drafts of the course drew on existing OERs-including some from FORRT-along with Priya's own expertise. Following this, pilot reviews were conducted by OU researchers and a broader group of interdisciplinary staff, followed by iterative revisions, before being published on the OpenLearn platform. Following user feedback, additional updates were iterated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Accessibility and Format:</head><p>The OpenLearn platform supports a variety of media, and the 'Open Research for Researchers' course takes advantage of this by including written text, short videos, and quizzes. All materials are provided in an accessible manner-transcripts for videos, alt-text for images, and mobile-friendly content-to ensure learners with disabilities or low bandwidth are not excluded. An 'interactive decision-making tree' allows learners to explore scenarios about opening their research. The entire course takes around 8 hours of self-paced learning. Learners can enrol for free and earn a certificate of completion, incentivising participation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Community and Reach:</head><p>The course content is openly licensed, allowing for adaptation. Existing on a well-known platform ensures sustainability and visibility-the OU maintains the site, reducing the maintenance burden for Priya (or other researchers), who can be contracted to edit as needed.</p><p>Challenges: As Priya was the sole course author, they felt they could not always capture diverse perspectives. The interdisciplinary feedback stage was useful, with researchers, librarians, and research support staff providing a wide variety of perspectives. However, Priya was responsible for deciding how to integrate any contradictory feedback, and the interdisciplinary group was relatively homogenous.</p><p>Although OpenLearn offers the opportunity to provide feedback, there is no current plan for continuously updating the course. However, due to its CC-BY licence, FORRT can transfer and adapt the course content into different formats. The FORRT Glossary https://forrt.org/glossary/ is a concrete example of a communitydriven OER that addresses a specific need: making the language of open science comprehensible and accessible. The Glossary contains definitions of terms related to open scholarship, from 'confirmatory research' to 'preprint' to 'data warehouse', all written in approachable language and with scholarly references.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Genesis of the Glossary:</head><p>The idea for the Glossary emerged from the realisation that students and faculty new to open research often feel overwhelmed by the jargon and proliferation of initiatives. Two key papers <ref type="bibr">(Crüwell et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kathawalla et al., 2021)</ref> highlighted the need for digestible introductions to open science topics. In response, FORRT set out to compile a glossary. The development was highly collaborative: contributors were invited to draft entries on terms within their expertise, using a shared template to ensure consistency. The Glossary team had an editorial process-drafts were reviewed by others for clarity and accuracy, simultaneously reinforcing community learning.</p><p>Design for Inclusivity and Clarity: Glossary definitions are friendly to novices, avoiding overly technical language. For instance, instead of saying 'HARKing: Hypothesising After Results are Known,' the Glossary entry unpacks why HARKing is problematic and contrasts it with preregistration, in plain terms. Where relevant, the entries note where controversies or multiple definitions exist. Consequently, the Glossary does not claim absolute authority but serves as a guide-aligning with an open pedagogy stance of inviting questioning. The multilingual aspect (with German and Arabic translations available) greatly extends inclusivity and champions linguistic diversity and social justice <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Piller, 2016)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Accessibility and Medium:</head><p>The Glossary is freely available on the FORRT website. It is organised alphabetically and cross-referenced internally to encourage exploration. The entire English Glossary is also downloadable as a PDF and CSV, supporting sustainability and reusability. The content has a CC-BY-SA-NC licence and can be adapted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Utility and Impact:</head><p>The FORRT Glossary has become a widely used reference. Some have integrated it into their learning management systems so that hovering over a term shows the definition. Outside formal education, the Glossary is helpful for anyone navigating open science. By increasing access to discipline-specific language, this OER helps broaden participation. The community aspect also continues: the Glossary is dynamically updated as new terms emerge, as an open, community-maintained resource.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reflections:</head><p>The FORRT Glossary project underscores how an OER can target micro-level needs (definitions) that have macro impacts (building a shared language). It shows that not all OERs have to be large textbooks. In critical pedagogy, the Glossary helps decolonise language by making the scientific elite's often exclusive language accessible to those historically excluded, including students from non-Western backgrounds and/or less privileged institutions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>OERs are more than just cost-free teaching tools-they are powerful instruments for fostering equity, epistemic justice, and participatory knowledge creation in education. Grounded in the principles of accessibility, inclusivity, collaboration, sustainability, and social justice, OERs can transform curricula, decentralise authority in knowledge production, and amplify and elevate voices traditionally excluded. Developing high-quality, inclusive OERs requires intentional planning, iterative refinement, and active community engagement. By embedding critical pedagogical values and prioritising openness -not just in licence, but in process-educators can contribute to a more equitable and just educational landscape. Ultimately, the creation and adoption of OERs is not merely a technical undertaking; it is a political and ethical commitment to reimagining education as a shared, inclusive, and liberatory practice.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. OER implementation: challenges and proposed solutions</figDesc><graphic coords="11,63.00,97.20,460.25,614.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Best practices and strategies for OER adoption and adaptation</figDesc><graphic coords="13,63.00,97.20,433.85,626.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>3rd</head><label></label><figDesc>Case Study: FORRT Glossary Project This case study exemplifies how a focused, collaborative OER can effectively democratise knowledge in the open science education space.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="1,-14.20,750.80,651.29,92.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,-23.20,750.50,651.29,92.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,164.52,97.20,257.25,648.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond authorship: Attribution, contribution, collaboration, and credit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hlava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1162/qss_a_00097</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1162/qss_a_00097" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Learned Publishing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Counter-hegemonic science education: Understanding the effects of coloniality and proposing a decolonial pedagogy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cassiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11422-021-10043-x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11422-021-10043-x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cultural Studies of Science Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1353" to="1360" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Colvard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Impact of OERs on Various Student Success Metrics</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Politicization of Socioscientific Issues as an Inalienable Condition for Scientific Education in the Brazilian Context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dos</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G F</forename><surname>De Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Carnio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-031-63382-9_7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-63382-9_7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A Moral Inquiry into Epistemic Insights in Science Education</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zeidler</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Nature Switzerland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="105" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Commission staff working document: Analysis and mapping of innovative teaching and learning for all through new technologies and Open Educational Resources in Europe (SWD/2013/0341 final</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">European Commission.</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=SWD:SWD_2013_0341" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-08-14">2013. August 14, 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Epistemic injustice: Power and the ethics of knowing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fricker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0244611</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0244611" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Teaching to Transgress: Education as the Practice of Freedom</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decolonial scientific education to combat &apos;science for domination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Galamba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A P</forename><surname>Monteiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11422-023-10165-4</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11422-023-10165-4" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cultural Studies of Science Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The replication crisis has led to positive structural, procedural, and community changes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Korbmacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Azevedo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pennington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pownall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elsherif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Breznau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kalandadze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>O'mahony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Ø</forename><surname>Olsnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-S</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gjoneska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Röer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s44271-023-00003-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s44271-023-00003-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Guidelines for using NASA images and media. NASA</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.nasa.gov/nasa-brand-center/images-and-media/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-04-14">2025. April 14. August 14, 2025</date>
			<publisher>National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OERs as a Tool for Educational Equity: Evidence From an Introductory Psychology Class</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Nusbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cuttler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Swindell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/feduc.2019.00152</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3389/feduc.2019.00152" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">152</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A community-sourced glossary of open scholarship terms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parsons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Azevedo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Elsherif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Shahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Govaart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Aczel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41562-021-01269-4</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-021-01269-4" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="312" to="318" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Linguistic Diversity and Social Justice: An Introduction to Applied Sociolinguistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Piller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Essentials for Blended Learning: A Standards-Based Guide</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000379949.locale=en" />
		<title level="m">UNESCO Recommendation on Open Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>UNESCO</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wiggins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mctighe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Understanding by design</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ASCD</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
