<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Dyadic Person Similarity Predicts Similarity in Face Judgements</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">City, University of London</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_PfXVnyw">
					<orgName type="full">Leverhulme Trust</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rochelle</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>City St</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Lúcia</forename><surname>Garrido</surname></persName>
							<email>lucia.garrido@city.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>City St</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">George&apos;s</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of London</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Northampton Square</addrLine>
									<postCode>EC1V 0HB</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Dyadic Person Similarity Predicts Similarity in Face Judgements</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2F982E33B4382FBBBCEB66D0A5BF062F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T14:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Face percepTon</term>
					<term>Social percepTon</term>
					<term>Intersubject representaTonal similarity analysis</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Perceivers consistently extract informaTon from faces to judge whether others are aWracTve, trustworthy, or dominant. However, there is also substanTal variability among perceivers when making these facejudgements. Here, we invesTgated whether dyadic similariTes in parTcipants' personaliTes are related to similariTes in their face-judgements. 307 parTcipants based in the UK rated 24 faces on six traits. ParTcipants also rated themselves on social-traits and completed a personality quesTonnaire. We computed dissimilariTes between pairs of parTcipants for face-judgements, self-rated-social-traits, and personality-traits, resulTng in three separate dissimilarity matrices. Using representaTonal similarity analysis, we showed that both the selfrated-social-traits and personality-traits matrices were significantly correlated with the face-judgements matrix. Importantly, these associaTons were stable when controlling for age, gender, ethnicity, and locaTon. These findings show that people who are more similar to each other also perceive others in a similar manner, and could form the basis for how we gravitate towards others and build friendships.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Over the past two decades, psychologists have explored the importance of face-trait percepTon and the potenTal roles they play in our social interacTons. People tend to judge very quickly whether someone has the intenTon and the ability to help or harm us, traits that psychologists call trustworthiness and dominance <ref type="bibr">(Oosterhof &amp; Todorov, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sutherland et al., 2013)</ref>. These traits seem to be fundamental social dimensions across the world <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Jones et al., 2021)</ref> as they underlie many other judgements that we make about others, parTcularly on first encounter. Since social interacTons likely involve discerning how approachable and safe a person is, one potenTal characterisTc about these traits is that they may be perceived in relaTon to the observers themselves.</p><p>Since the 1960s, researchers have invesTgated this relaTonship between the way we perceive ourselves and the way we perceive others. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Dornbusch et al. (1965)</ref> found that there is more overlap in a perceiver's use of terms to describe other people than there is when others describe a single target person. This points to the possibility that there is likely a framework that the observer is using consistently to make judgements beyond the informaTon extracted from the face. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Markus, Smith and Moreland (1985)</ref> found that people are more likely to aWribute certain person characterisTcs to others if they aWribute the same traits to themselves. The observed person is also perceived as more similar and more likeable by the observer. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Albright, Kenny, and Malloy (1988)</ref> found significant posiTve correlaTons between people's self-percepTons and their judgements of others based on specific characterisTcs such as aWracTveness, formal dress sense, neatness of dressing appearance and age (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Srivastava, Gugliemo, &amp; Beer, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wood, Harms, &amp; Vazire, 2010</ref>). Thus, it seems likely that there is a common tendency to judge others using mental frameworks based on our own traits and disposiTons. While we extract social informaTon from the face, it is also apparent that our own disposiTons play an important role in our judgements of others.</p><p>Considering this, it is important to explore the extent to which our own disposiTons, relaTve to face characterisTcs, play a role in the way we perceive a face. Many studies have focused on the target-face characterisTcs that influence our social judgements. For instance, smiling faces are consistently perceived as more trustworthy and high facial masculinity is consistently perceived as more dominant (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Oosterhof and Todorov, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sutherland et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Vernon et al., 2014)</ref>. However, past research has also shown that there yet remains substanTal variability among perceivers when making social judgements about the same faces. Specifically, while inter-rater agreement (i.e. correlaTons between pairs of perceivers) of social judgements of faces is typically low to moderate (about 0.3 to 0.4; <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hönekopp, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Oosterhof and Todorov, 2008)</ref>, intrarater agreement (i.e. test-retest reliability of the same perceiver) is considerably higher (about 0.7; <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hönekopp, 2006)</ref>, indicaTng the presence of important and consistent individual differences among perceivers (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Germine et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sutherland et al., 2020)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hönekopp (2006)</ref> showed that both shared taste and private taste contributed about equally to face aWracTveness judgements. More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hehman et al. (2017)</ref> esTmated the effects of perceiver and target variance for a large range of social traits, including intelligence, competence, aWracTveness, friendliness, trustworthiness, dominance, among others. Results from mulTlevel models quanTfied the variance that was aWributable to the perceiver and to the target, and the authors found that the variance in raTngs for all traits was due to both the perceiver and to the target. In other words, raters consistently relied on factors related to themselves and on factors related to the target face characterisTcs, and the extent of the relaTve contribuTons of perceiver and target depended on the trait.</p><p>Given that much variance in face judgements is related to the perceiver, this variance could be related to our individual differences. Face judgements are indeed influenced by the parTcular groups or subgroups to which the perceivers belong, and are thus affected by ethnicity, gender <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Hönekopp, 2006)</ref>, and cultural background <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Sofer et al., 2017)</ref>. Face judgements are also influenced by individual differences in other disposiTons such as anxiety levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Willis et al., 2013)</ref> and personality traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(MaWarozzi et al., 2015)</ref>. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">MaWarozzi et al. (2015)</ref> found that those higher in trait agreeableness perceived faces as more trustworthy.</p><p>A recent study invesTgated the relaTonship between the structure of personality and face percepTon across the world <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Oh, MarTn and Freeman, 2022)</ref>. Specifically, the authors invesTgated whether the personality structure of people living in one region relate to how they perceive social traits in the faces of others. Selfreport personality trait raTngs and face trait judgements were gathered from large exisTng datasets from 42 countries. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Oh et al. (2022)</ref> computed average distances between trait pairs, separately for personality and face judgements. These resulted in representaTonal dissimilarity matrices (RDMs) of the structure of both personality and face judgements for each world region. Results showed that, for most world regions, the two RDMs were significantly associated, indicaTng that the structure of personality was related to the structure of face percepTon. In other words, where there is a co-occurrence of traits in one's personality, this cooccurrence is also reflected in the social judgements made about the face. Furthermore, two countries that were more similar in their personality structure also showed higher similarity of the structure of face judgements.</p><p>It is possible that, even within a single world region, people who are more similar to each other in their own disposiTons and traits also show more similar social trait judgements. Support for this comes from recent neuroimaging studies that have shown that pairs of people with similar personality traits also have similar brain acTvaTon paWerns. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Finn et al. (2020)</ref> invesTgated the relaTonship between pairwise brain similarity and personality similarity, using inter-subject representaTonal similarity analysis (RSA; <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kriegeskorte, Mur &amp; Bandenni, 2008)</ref>. The authors analysed funcTonal magneTc resonance imaging (fMRI) data of parTcipants who viewed naturalisTc video-clips, and personality raTngs from the same parTcipants. Results showed that inter-subject similariTes in personality between parTcipants were associated with inter-subject similariTes in brain acTvity in ventral temporal cortex, frontal cortex, and cerebellum. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Matz et al. (2022)</ref> found comparable results using both fMRI and electroencephalography (EEG). These results suggest that an alignment in brain acTvity can indeed be predicted by an alignment in personality.</p><p>Successful social interacTons between people partly rely on a consistent understanding of our social world, so the alignment between people with similar disposiTons may lead to successful social interacTons, such as the iniTal stages of friendship development, affiliaTon, moTvaTons towards community formaTon, and relevant in-group behaviours <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Robbins &amp; Krueger, 2005)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Selpout et al. (2010)</ref> showed that people choose others as friends who are similar to themselves in levels of agreeableness, extraversion and openness. <ref type="bibr">Parkinson, Kleinbaum and Wheately (2018)</ref> have also demonstrated that friendship and social distance between people can be predicted by similariTes in brain acTvity. In terms of trait percepTon, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bronstad and Russell (2007)</ref> showed that pairs of people in close relaTonships have higher inter-rater agreement when raTng face aWracTveness compared to pairs of strangers. However, it was not possible from this study to disTnguish whether these shared percepTons were a result of spending Tme together and having shared experiences, or instead had the preferences themselves contributed to the forming of the relaTonships. In any case, it seems possible that the moTvaTon to gravitate towards those who are like us and become friends may be related to an alignment in perspecTves.</p><p>Taken together, the studies reviewed here suggest that there is an important link between how similar we are to others and its effect on any shared perspecTves we might have. However, there remains the quesTon as to the specific content of these aligned perspecTves, especially relaTng to social percepTon. Specifically, do we perceive people in a similar way if we have more similar personaliTes? The present study aims to invesTgate whether individuals who are more similar in their personality and self-perceived social trait disposiTons also perceive face traits in a more similar manner. We used inter-subject RSA <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Kriegeskorte et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Finn et al., 2020)</ref> to analyse the associaTon between person similarity and face judgement similarity. We hypothesised that pairs of people who are more similar in their own (self-perceived) personality and social traits also make judgements about faces in a more similar way. More specifically, we predicted that intersubject person similarity (measured as similarity in personality-traits and similarity in self-rated-social-traits) is significantly posiTvely correlated with face-judgement similarity (based on raTngs of faces).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ParTcipants</head><p>We recruited 320 parTcipants in total (Mage = 37.88; SD = 11.54; 182 idenTfied as women, 133 as men, and 4 as other). We pre-registered our study, specifying sample size, inclusion, and exclusion criteria (hWps://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/ZR92G). ParTcipants were recruited through online parTcipant pool Testable Minds (hWps://minds.testable.org) and received compensaTon for their Tme. Our goal was to test 300 parTcipants. We sTpulated that, if auer removing parTcipants because of the exclusion criteria we ended up with fewer than 300 parTcipants, we would test 10 addiTonal parTcipants at a Tme unTl we obtained a final sample of at least 300 parTcipants.</p><p>As inclusion criteria, all parTcipants had to be aged 18 or older, have English as first language, and had to be living in the UK. Given that <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Oh et al. (2022)</ref> found an effect of country on the percepTon of social traits, here we wanted to avoid country as a source of variability and therefore focused on people in the UK only.</p><p>We had three pre-registered exclusion criteria to ensure data quality. First, there were four "catch" trials and parTcipants who failed two or more catch trials were excluded. The catch trials are described in the Procedure. Second, we excluded parTcipants who provided the same raTng in 10 consecuTve trials of the Face Judgements Task. Third, we excluded parTcipants who responded too quickly (responses of 200ms or less) in 10% or more of the trials of the Face Judgements Task. The exclusion criteria were applied before analysis, and 13 parTcipants were excluded. Two parTcipants were excluded because of the first and second criteria and eleven parTcipants were excluded because of the second criterion only. No parTcipants were excluded because of the third criterion.</p><p>The final sample consisted of 307 individuals (Mage = 37.97; SD = 11.55; 171 women, 132 men, 4 other). 268 parTcipants were right-handed, 29 were leu-handed, and 10 were ambidextrous. 238 parTcipants described their ethnicity as White, 12 as Mixed, 27 as Asian, 25 as Black, and 5 as 'Other' (we used these ethnicity terms based on opTons from the 2021 Census; Office for NaTonal StaTsTcs, 2021). All parTcipants lived in the UK and reported their geographical locaTon (see Supplementary InformaTon 1).</p><p>The study was approved by the Psychology Research Ethics CommiWee at City, University of London.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design and variables</head><p>We used a correlaTon design with two main variables: person similarity and face-judgement similarity. We operaTonalised person similarity in two ways (1) Personality-traits similarity: the similarity between parTcipants in terms of their Big Five personality traits, which were measured with the Personality-traits QuesTonnaire described below and (2) Self-rated-social-traits similarity: the similarity between parTcipants in terms of self-perceived social traits, which were measured with the Self-rated-social-traits QuesTonnaire described below. Face-judgements similarity corresponds to the similarity between parTcipants in terms of their judgements of social traits in faces of others, measured with the Face-judgements Task described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials</head><p>Personality-traits Ques7onnaire. We used the InternaTonal Personality Item Pool (IPIP-NEO-60) personality quesTonnaire to measure personality-traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Maples-Keller et al., 2019)</ref>. The IPIP-NEO-60 has shown to have strong internal consistency and validity when compared against quesTonnaires such as the NEO PI-R <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Costa &amp; McCrae, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Maples-Keller et al., 2019)</ref>. It consists of 60 statements, such as "Love to daydream.". ParTcipants rated how well each statement described them using a 5-point scale ranging from 1 (Very inaccurate) to 5 (Very accurate). There are 12 items that correspond to each of the 5 Big Five personality traits (Openness, ConscienTousness, Extraversion, Agreeableness, and NeuroTcism).</p><p>Self-rated-social-traits Ques7onnaire. We created a quesTonnaire to measure self-rated social traits. We used the 13 traits used by <ref type="bibr">Oosterhof and Todorov (2008)</ref>: Trustworthiness, Dominance, AWracTveness, Sociability, EmoTonal Stability, Aggressiveness, Intelligence, Care, Meanness, Confidence, Weirdness, Unhappiness and Responsibility. ParTcipants were asked to 'Please rate how well each word describes YOU'. Each word was presented next to 9-point scale from 1 (Does not describe me) to 9 (Describes me).</p><p>Face-judgements Task. STmuli consisted of 24 neutral face sTmuli from the Chicago Face Database (hWps://<ref type="url" target="https://www.chicagofaces.org/">www.chicagofaces.org</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Ma, Correll, &amp; WiWenbrink, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ma, Kantner, &amp; WiWenbrink, 2020)</ref>. Six faces per ethnicity were selected (three men and three women). Faces from four ethniciTes were selected: White, Black, LaTno and East Asian. Supplementary InformaTon 2 has the list of the names of the pictures selected from the database. The pictures had white backgrounds and were presented in colour with a 600 x 450-pixel size.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedure</head><p>The study was created on Testable (hWps://<ref type="url" target="https://www.testable.org/">www.testable.org</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Rezlescu et al., 2020)</ref>. ParTcipants completed the study online on a desktop or laptop computer. ParTcipants read the informaTon sheet and provided consent to take part in the study. ParTcipants then completed the Face-judgements Task, followed by the Selfrated-social-traits QuesTonnaire and finally the Personality-traits QuesTonnaire.</p><p>In the Face-judgements Task, parTcipants were presented with the face pictures and were asked to judge each face on six social traits. The traits were: Trustworthiness, Dominance, AWracTveness, Sociability, Aggressiveness and Intelligence. These traits are known to be associated with the main dimensions in which we judge the faces of others <ref type="bibr">(Oosterhof &amp; Todorov, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Sutherland et al., 2013)</ref> and were shown to explain a substanTal part of the variance in social judgements raTngs of parTcipants in the UK <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Jones et al., 2021)</ref>. In each trial, parTcipants were presented with one face paired with one trait and were asked to rate the face, e.g., 'How TRUSTWORTHY is this person?' on a 9-point scale from 1 (Not at all) to 9 (Extremely). Each of the 24 faces was paired with each of the traits resulTng in 144 total trials. The order of trials was randomised for each parTcipant.</p><p>A total of 4 aWenTon quality check trials or "catch" trials were included in the study and were related to the Face-judgements Task. For the first aWenTon check, auer reading the instrucTons of the Face-judgements Task but before starTng the task, parTcipants were presented with a statement which read "Please confirm what you will be doing in the present study". ParTcipants selected out of 3 simple opTons: "raTng places", "raTng faces" and "raTng objects". The remaining aWenTon check trials were presented at the end of the Facejudgements Task: these tested whether parTcipants remembered which faces they had seen during the task. We reasoned that if parTcipants had been paying aWenTon, they would be able to disTnguish faces that were presented during the task (each repeated 6 Tmes) from novel faces. There were three trials. In each trial, three faces were presented, where two of the faces had been shown in the Face-judgements Task and one face was novel. ParTcipants had to select the novel face. The three faces within each trial were of the same ethnicity and gender (e.g., 3 white males, 3 black women, 3 LaTno males).</p><p>ParTcipants then completed the Self-rated-social-traits QuesTonnaire and finally they completed the Personality-traits QuesTonnaire. Upon finishing the study, parTcipants were prompted to read the study debrief and click 'FINISH' to save their results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Analysis</head><p>We used inter-subject RSA <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Kriegeskorte et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Finn et al., 2020)</ref> to analyse the associaTon between person similarity and face-judgements similarity. RepresentaTonal dissimilarity matrices (RDMs) were computed where each entry in a matrix represents the pairwise dissimilarity between two parTcipants on each of our measures. Three main RDMs (each with dimensions 307 x 307) were computed: (1) RDM Personality-traits: each parTcipant's scores on the Personality-traits QuesTonnaire were compared with each of the other parTcipants' scores in a pairwise way (i.e., each matrix entry contains the dissimilarity value between pairs of vectors, with each vector containing 60 items), (2) RDM Self-rated-social-traits: each parTcipant's scores on the Self-rated-social-traits QuesTonnaire were compared with each of the other parTcipants' scores in a pairwise way (i.e., each matrix entry contains the dissimilarity value between pairs of vectors, with each vector containing 13 items), and (3) RDM Face-judgements: each parTcipant's raTngs on the Face-judgements Task were compared with each of the other parTcipant's scores in a pairwise way (i.e., each matrix entry contains the dissimilarity value between pairs of vectors, with each vector containing 144 items). We used Euclidean distance as the main measure of dissimilarity in the RDMs. We first z-scored the vectors for each parTcipant before compuTng Euclidean distances.</p><p>For the main analyses, we first correlated RDM Self-rated-social-traits with RDM Face-judgements and second, we correlated RDM Personality-traits with RDM Face-judgements. Before compuTng correlaTons, we vectorised each of the 307-by-307 RDMs by extracTng the lower off-diagonal (i.e. all elements below the main diagonal) of each matrix. This yielded three vectors (one for each RDM) containing 46,971 values each. We used Spearman rank order correlaTons of the resulTng vectors. For readability, we describe below that we correlated RDMs, but in all cases we correlated the vectorised RDMs. Because the entries in each matrix (and values of resulTng vectors) are not independent from each other (i.e., the same parTcipant appears paired with each of the other parTcipants), we cannot use parametric staTsTcs which rely on independence assumpTons <ref type="bibr">(Selpout et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Chen et al., 2016)</ref>. We thus tested whether each of these two correlaTons were significantly higher than zero by using random permutaTon tests. To do this, we conducted 1,000 iteraTons. For each iteraTon, we re-computed the Person Similarity RDM by first randomly permuTng the order of parTcipants and then re-compuTng the RDM. Then, we computed the correlaTon between the permuted person similarity RDM (RDM Self-rated-social-traits or RDM Personality-traits) and the original RDM Face-judgements to obtain a correlaTon for that iteraTon. This allowed us to esTmate the null distribuTon with 1,000 permuted correlaTons. To be considered significant, the 'actual' correlaTon needed to be higher than 95% of the 'permuted' correlaTons (p &lt; .05).</p><p>We also computed confidence intervals of the correlaTons by bootstrapping (random resampling with replacement). For each of 1,000 resamples, we randomly selected 307 parTcipants (resampling with replacement), re-computed all RDMs, and conducted all correlaTon analyses again. We provide the 95% confidence intervals of the correlaTons based on the 2.5 th and 97.5 th percenTles of the bootstrapped correlaTons.</p><p>All analyses (except mixed effects modelling) were conducted in Matlab (version R2021b; Mathworks, <ref type="url" target="www.mathworks.com">www.mathworks.com</ref>). All anonymised data and code for main analyses are openly available: hWps://doi.org/10.25383/city.26519890.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>In this study we aimed to invesTgate whether person similarity is related to face-judgements similarity. In other words, do people who are more similar to each other in terms of their disposiTons also make more similar face judgements? In the Face-judgements Task, parTcipants rated 24 faces, each face on six social traits (trustworthiness, dominance, aWracTveness, sociability, aggressiveness, and intelligence). To measure their own disposiTons and personality traits, parTcipants completed a Self-rated-social-traits QuesTonnaire, and a Personality-traits QuesTonnaire. For each of the three variables, we computed pairwise similarity for all pairs of parTcipants. Briefly, we computed vectors of all z-scored raTngs for each parTcipant. We then computed Euclidean distances between vectors of all pairs of parTcipants (for the same variable) to obtain pairwise distances (dissimilariTes) between parTcipants. This resulted in one intersubject representaTonal dissimilarity matrix (RDM) for each of the three variables: RDM Face-judgements, RDM Self-rated-social-traits, and RDM Personality-traits (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). We then invesTgated whether intersubject person similarity could predict intersubject face-judgements similarity.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> Intersubject RDMs depic7ng the pairwise (dis)similarity between all par7cipants (Self-rated-social-traits similarity, Personality-traits similarity, Face-judgements similarity) and their correla7ons.</p><p>Note. Intersubject RDMs for each variable and Spearman correlaTons between RDMs: RDM Self-rated-socialtraits, RDM Personality-traits, RDM Face-judgements. Colour bars show Euclidean distances with blue indicaTng higher similarity (lower distance) and yellow indicaTng lower similarity (higher distance). RDM Facejudgements is ranked for visualisaTon purposes only, depicTng the most similar pairs of parTcipants from the top leu of the matrix (i.e., darker blue entries) to the least similar pairs of parTcipants at the boWom right of the matrix (i.e., yellower entries). The other RDMs are ranked based on this same RDM. Spearman correlaTons are shown between the vectorised RDMs, with p-values esTmated with random permutaTon tesTng.</p><p>Person similarity is associated with Face -judgements similarity Correla7on between Self-rated-social-traits similarity and Face-judgements similarity. The first analysis looked at whether similar people (in terms of their self-rated social-traits) also make similar judgements of social traits in faces. To do this, RDM Self-rated-social-traits was correlated with RDM Face-judgements using Spearman rank-order correlaTon (auer vectorising the elements below the main diagonal of each matrix), resulTng in a posiTve correlaTon of rs = .125 (95% bootstrapped confidence interval = [.069 .198]) (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). We carried out non-parametric permutaTon tests to esTmate a null distribuTon and test whether this correlaTon was significantly higher than zero. For each of 1,000 iteraTons, the RDM Self-rated-social-traits was re-computed auer randomly shuffling (permuTng) the order of parTcipants, and then we re-computed the correlaTon between the original RDM Face-judgements and the permuted RDM Self-rated-social-traits. To be considered significant, the actual correlaTon had to be higher than 95% of the permuted correlaTons. Results showed that the actual correlaTon was higher than all 1,000 permuted correlaTons, and therefore was significantly higher than zero (p &lt; .001, permutaTon tests). In other words, the more similar pairs of people were in their raTngs of their own social traits, the more similar their raTngs were of the faces of other people, which supports our hypothesis.</p><p>Correla7on between Personality-traits similarity and Face-judgements similarity. The same procedure was carried out: RDM Personality-traits was correlated with RDM Face-judgements (auer vectorising the RDMs). There was a posiTve correlaTon of rs = .194 (95% bootstrapped CI = [.139 .262]), which was significantly higher than zero (p &lt;.001) (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). These results revealed that the more similar people are in their personality structure, the more likely they are to rate faces in a similar way, which supports our hypothesis. For completeness, we also correlated the RDM Self-rated-social-traits with the RDM Personality-traits (see Supplementary InformaTon 3).</p><p>Split-half reliability of Face-judgements similarity. We also computed split-half reliability of the RDM Facejudgements as a way of esTmaTng the highest possible correlaTon we could expect with face-judgements similarity (i.e., as a way of esTmaTng the noise ceiling). To compute split-half reliability, we conducted 1,000 random splits of the Face-judgements Task data, and re-computed the RDM Face-judgements (again, 307 x 307 RDM across parTcipants) for each split, and then correlated the RDMs across splits. More specifically, for each iteraTon, we randomly divided the data on the Face-judgements Task for each parTcipant in two halves (with 72 trials in each half). We then computed an RDM Face-judgements using all data from Split 1 (a 307 x 307 RDM across parTcipants) and an RDM Face-judgements using all data from Split 2 (again, a 307 x 307 RDM across parTcipants). In other words, the RDMs for each split have the same structure as the RDM Facejudgements for the main analysis, but they are based on just half of the raTng data from each parTcipant. For each iteraTon, we correlated the two RDMs (Split 1 vs Split 2; auer vectorising the values under the main diagonal for each RDM) using Spearman correlaTons. The resulTng correlaTons across 1,000 iteraTons varied between .474 and .605, with a mean of rs = .558. This is our esTmaTon of the reliability of RDM Facejudgements, and shows moderate consistency of the between parTcipants' differences when using independent data across splits. We also interpret this reliability as the maximum correlaTon we could expect of any variable or model with the RDM Face-judgements. When considering this noise ceiling, the person similarity variables seem to explain a substanTal proporTon of the variance in face-judgements similarity (22.40% for RDM Self-rated-social-traits and 34.77% for RDM Personality-traits), though there is sTll considerable unexplained variance in face-judgements similarity.</p><p>Person similarity is associated with Face-judgements similarity auer controlling for demographic variables We next invesTgated whether the posiTve correlaTons between person similarity and face-judgements similarity could be accounted by similariTes in demographic variables. In other words, we invesTgated whether the correlaTons between person similarity and face-judgements similarity could be accounted by similariTes in the demographic variables age, gender, ethnicity, and parTcipant geographical locaTon. We thus carried out mulTple regression analyses with RDM Face-judgements as the outcome variable and person similarity as predictor variables, controlling for age, gender, ethnicity, and parTcipant locaTon. We note that we use predictor and outcome variables here solely as staTsTcal terms for the mulTple regression, in that the variance of one variable can predict the variance of another variable. Our study design is correlaTonal and from our data, we cannot establish causality or determine which variables precede others. As before, and because the entries in each RDM are not independent, we conducted permutaTon tests to test whether parameter esTmates from the regression analyses were significantly different from zero. P-values for the beta-values were esTmated using random permutaTons (1,000 iteraTons) to esTmate null distribuTons of the parameter esTmate for each variable.</p><p>RDMs were computed for each demographic variable (RDM Age, RDM Gender, RDM Ethnicity, and RDM Region). Pairwise distances between each pair of parTcipants were computed based on each demographic variable separately, thus producing a dissimilarity matrix for each variable (i.e., for RDM Age, pairwise distances in age were computed between all parTcipants). RDM Age used Euclidean distance as the dissimilarity measure. For RDM Gender and RDM Ethnicity (which were based on categorical variables), we classified each pair of parTcipants as same ('0') or different ('1'). For RDM Region, the actual geographical distances between laTtude and longitude co-ordinates for the centre of each UK region were computed using Haversine distance. Co-ordinates for the midpoint of the 12 UK regions were obtained using GeoMapApp (<ref type="url" target="www.geomapapp.org">www.geomapapp.org</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Ryan et al., 2009)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mul7ple regression predic7ng</head><p>Face-judgements similarity with Self-rated-social-traits similarity and demographic variables as predictors. We first looked at the associaTon between RDM Self-rated-social-traits and RDM Face-judgements (auer vectorising the RDMs by extracTng the values below the diagonal). As expected, simple regression analysis showed that self-rated-social-traits similarity could significantly predict face-judgements similarity (𝛽 = .123, p &lt; .001, permutaTon tests), explaining 1.78% of the variance (R 2 = .0178). When all RDMs for demographic variables were included as predictors along with the RDM Self-ratedsocial-traits (all RDMs vectorized), the total model explained 6.13% of the variance in face judgement similarity (R 2 = .0613). Looking at the parameter esTmates for each predictor variable (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>), similarity in all demographic variables were associated with face-judgements similarity (especially ethnicity), but there is unique substanTal variance explained by person similarity (𝛽 = .138, p &lt; .001).</p><p>Table <ref type="table">1</ref> Regression analyses using Self-rated-social-traits similarity to predict Face-judgements similarity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simple Regression</head><p>𝛽, p</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MulTple Regression 𝛽, p</head><p>Self-rated-social-traits similarity .123, p &lt; .001 .138, p &lt; .001 Age .065, p = .007 Gender .033, p = .013 Ethnicity .184, p = .001 Region .082, p = .036 Note. Simple regression results including only RDM Self-rated-social-traits as predictor. MulTple regression results including RDM Self-rated-social-traits and RDMs for demographic variables as predictors: 𝛽 = parameter esTmates; P-values esTmated by random permutaTons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mul7ple regression predic7ng Face-judgements similarity with Personality-traits similarity and demographic variables as predictors.</head><p>We next looked at the associaTon between RDM Personality-traits and RDM Facejudgements (auer vectorising the RDMs by extracTng the values below the diagonal). Simple regression showed that personality-traits similarity could predict face-judgements similarity (𝛽 = .199, p &lt; .001, R 2 = .0397). When all the RDMs for demographic variables were included as predictors along with the RDM Personality-traits, the model explained 7.8% of the variance in face-judgements similarity (R 2 = .078). Looking at the parameter esTmates for each predictor variable (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>), all RDMs for demographic variables were associated with face-judgements similarity (specially ethnicity), but there is unique substanTal variance explained by personality-traits similarity (𝛽 = .190, p &lt; .001). Linear mixed effects modelling with crossed random effects. To address the non-independence issues of intersubject correlaTon analyses when controlling for covariates, Chen and colleagues (2017) recommended the use of linear mixed effects modelling with crossed random effects to account for repeTTons of parTcipants in mulTple dyads. Therefore, in addiTon to the mulTple regression analyses described above, we also conducted linear missed effects modelling. We used R StaTsTcal Souware (version 4.4.2; R Core Team, 2024). We followed the procedures suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Chen et al. (2017)</ref> (doubling the data, correcTng for degrees of freedom) and fit linear mixed models using lme4 <ref type="bibr">(version 1.1.35.5;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bates et al., 2015)</ref> and lmerTest <ref type="bibr">(version 3.1.3;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Kuznetsova et al., 2017)</ref>. We thus used linear mixed effects models to predict face-judgements similarity with person similarity (separate models for self-rated-social-traits similarity and personality-traits similarity) and demographic variables as fixed effects, and parTcipants in each dyad as random effects. Results showed that self-rated-social-traits similarity was a significant predictor of face-judgements similarity (𝛽 = .076, t = 21.840, p &lt; .001). Personality-traits similarity was also a significant predictor of face-judgements similarity (𝛽 = .072, t = 23.61, p &lt; .001). These results are in line with the mulTple regression results above and again show that person similarity can predict face-judgements similarity, even auer controlling for demographic predictors.</p><p>Results are stable with at least 120 parTcipants and across traits We next conducted exploratory analyses to invesTgate the stability of the above results. We first invesTgated the stability of the main correlaTons between person similarity and face-judgements similarity across mulTple sample sizes, and found that correlaTons between RDMs became stable with around 120 parTcipants (see Supplementary InformaTon 4). This analysis also demonstrated that the results are not just dependent on our large sample size, nor are they dependent on only a few parTcipants.</p><p>We next invesTgated whether the associaTon of person similarity with face-judgements similarity is stronger for some face judgements than others. Results showed that person similarity was significantly associated with face-judgements similarity for all traits separately, though all correlaTons were lower than when considering all traits together (see Supplementary InformaTon 5).</p><p>We also conducted exploratory analyses invesTgaTng the extent to which individual differences in specific social and personality traits contribute to average face judgements (see Supplementary InformaTon 6). These results suggested that our main findings of similarity in face-judgements similarity being predicted by person similarity cannot be fully explained by associaTons of any specific personality traits (or self-rated-social-traits) with means for specific face-judgements, and instead seem to reflect paLerns of responses across traits. Finally, we computed inter-rater agreement of face judgements to invesTgate agreement of face-judgements across parTcipants (see Supplementary InformaTon 7). Results showed low to moderate inter-rater agreement, which is comparable to results from previous studies (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Oosterhof &amp; Todorov, 2008)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>In the present study, we invesTgated whether people who are similar in their personality and social disposiTons also make more similar social judgements about others. We measured pairwise similarity between parTcipants' traits and disposiTons (i.e., person similarity) using their responses from self-report quesTonnaires on social traits (self-rated-social-traits) and the Big 5 personality traits (personality-traits). We separately looked at similarity between parTcipants' face judgements using their raTngs of unfamiliar faces based on six social traits (trustworthiness, dominance, aWracTveness, sociability, aggressiveness, and intelligence). We found that there was a small but reliable correlaTon between pairwise person similarity and pairwise face-judgements similarity. Thus, two people who perceive themselves in a similar way, in terms of their self-rated-social-traits as well as their personality-traits, also make more similar social judgements about others' faces. This effect is present even auer controlling for age, gender, ethnicity, and geographical locaTon (though, these variables, especially ethnicity, also contribute to a significant proporTon of independent variance found in face-judgements similarity). The results suggest that pairs of people who are similar in their own traits and disposiTons perceive others in a similar manner.</p><p>The results from this study provide support for our hypothesis and are consistent with results from previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Oh et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Matz et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Finn et al., 2020)</ref>. In parTcular, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Oh et al. (2022)</ref> demonstrated that the personality structure within a given world region is related to the structure of face percepTon within that same region. In our study, we extended these findings to show that these associaTons are not dependent on world region only, and can be seen within the same country. Thus, within the UK only, pairs of people who have similar personaliTes also perceive others' faces in a more similar way. Therefore, individuals' own personaliTes and disposiTons (within the same culture and speaking the same naTve language) are also related to how they perceive faces. While this study was designed to look within one country in parTcular, it is an obvious limitaTon that the results cannot be generalised to different countries/regions/cultures. It is important for future studies to replicate this effect within different countries, world regions, and cultures. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Finn et al. (2020)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Matz et al. (2022)</ref> demonstrated that those with similar personaliTes also had more similar brain acTvity. Here, we extended these findings to show that similarity in personality and social traits is also related to their social percepTon, specifically in parTcipants' first impressions of faces. It would be interesTng to invesTgate in future studies whether similarity in disposiTons predicts similarity in other behaviours as well, and specifically if the associaTon observed here depends more strictly on using social sTmuli such as faces.</p><p>Despite much focus of social trait percepTon research on the characterisTcs of the target faces that are associated with different types of judgements, there is increasing evidence showing that the perceiver characterisTcs also contribute to the variance in social trait judgements of faces (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Hönekopp, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hehman et al., 2017)</ref>. We believe that our study contributes to the understanding of the sources of this variance due to the perceiver. We suggest that there are systemaTc sources of variance in face trait raTngs related to parTcipants' own traits and disposiTons, and that these can be studied by looking at covariance/similariTes across parTcipants.</p><p>It could be that the similariTes between parTcipants' traits and disposiTons are relevant to how people form friendships and relaTonships. One on hand, <ref type="bibr">Selpout et al. (2010)</ref> showed that friends choose others who are similar to themselves in levels of agreeableness, extraversion and openness. On the other hand, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bronstad and Russell (2007)</ref> showed that pairs of friends (or people in close relaTonships) rate aWracTveness in faces in a similar manner. These similariTes in social percepTon could happen because friends spend Tme together and develop shared views. However, our results showed that even strangers who are similar in terms of their personality and social traits also perceive others in a similar way. We suggest that this could be an important mechanism in the formaTon of friendships: maybe we gravitate towards similar others because we actually perceive the social worlds as they do. If people with similar disposiTons also perceive others in a similar way, it seems possible that they will trust and approach the same people. It would be interesTng to test this directly in small-scale communiTes while they are forming <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Parkinson et al., 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Many studies in the field of person percepTon have reported substanTal perceiver effects when raTng others (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Albright et al., 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Srivastava et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wood et al., 2010)</ref>. These studies have focused on raTngs of others' personality-traits (many Tmes auer meeTng others in-person) and not on raTngs of social traits in faces per se, but have consistently shown that individuals tend to perceive others in a parTcular way that relates to their own personality. In some cases, individuals tend to perceive others with similar traits as they perceive themselves, but this is not always the case <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Wood et al., 2010)</ref>. These past studies, however, have focused on global effects of perceiving others: the same individual tends to perceive others as generally more (or less) agreeable, for example. Our study suggests an addiTonal dimension to these perceiver effects, in that the individual's own personality-traits are associated with which specific faces are perceived to be more or less trustworthy, for example. It is not a global effect of finding all faces more (or less) trustworthy, but instead how perceivers rank specific faces on trustworthiness. In other words, the perceiver's personality traits seem to be associated with parTcular ways in which they map facial characterisTcs to social traits raTngs. It will be very interesTng for future studies to aWempt to bring these fields together to fully understand how perceiver effects contribute to social and person percepTon.</p><p>One important limitaTon to our results is that we only know that person similarity is associated with facejudgements similarity, but cannot know about causality or how this associaTon emerged/developed. It is also possible that a third variable is associated with both person similarity and face-judgements similarity, but that there is no mechanisTc link between the two variables per se. We think future studies replicaTng this associaTon across regions/samples, and also looking at possible third variables will be very valuable. SimilariTes in upbringing, environments, culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Sofer et al., 2017)</ref>, mood, and even cogniTve domains could contribute to the associaTon between person similarity and face-judgements similarity. We think that larger studies looking at a broader range of variables, and even across development, could help shed light on the possible mechanisms linking these variables.</p><p>The effect size of the associaTon between person similarity and face-judgements similarity was small, with correlaTons of .13 and .19. We argue, however, that these effect sizes were stable across different analyses, and when using sub-samples of the data (see Supplementary InformaTon 4). We also note that our esTmated noise ceiling for the RDM Face-judgements was around .56, which we interpret as the maximum correlaTon we could expect with this variable. In this light, the observed correlaTons show that person similarity can explain about 22% to 35% of the RDM Face-judgements. Even though these are not negligible effects, here is sTll considerable unexplained variance in face-judgements similarity.</p><p>One final important limitaTon is that we did not control for the possibility of parTcipants knowing each other. Given that our data was collected online, it was impossible for us to obtain such informaTon. In a country of more than 60 million people, it seems unlikely that many parTcipants knew each other. Future studies could record IP addresses or laTtude/longitude for more accurate determinaTon of locaTon, and even recruit a more equal number of parTcipants from each region. It could also be interesTng for future studies to directly manipulate whether parTcipants know each other or not.</p><p>To conclude, we invesTgated the relaTonship between dyadic person similarity and the similarity in face judgements. We showed that pairs of people who are similar in their disposiTons and personaliTes also make more similar judgements about others' faces. AddiTonally, those who were the same gender and ethnicity, and those who were nearer in terms of age and geographical locaTon also made more similar judgements, but these effects were independent from the one accounted for by person similarity. Future studies could invesTgate whether the associaTon between person similarity and face-judgements similarity is important for how people build friendships.</p><p>ParKcipants' regions of residence in the United Kingdom All parKcipants lived in the UK and reported their geographical locaKon (see Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>; we used UK regions based on Census 2021 data published from the Office of NaKonal StaKsKcs: hVps://explore-local-staKsKcs.beta.ons.gov.uk/areas/K02000001).</p><p>Table S1 Par%cipants' regions of residence in the United Kingdom Region N Par%cipants North East 7 North West 35 Yorkshire and The Humber 23 East Midlands 17 West Midlands 29 East of England 31 London 56 South East 37 South West 22 Wales 13 Scotland 32 Total Northern Ireland 12 5 307 Note. Number of parKcipants living in each of twelve UK regions (taken from the Census 2021; the Office of NaKonal StaKsKcs). Supplementary InformaKon 4 How many parKcipants are needed for stable correlaKons?</p><p>We invesKgated the stability of the RDM correlaKons across mulKple sample sizes. CorrelaKons between RDMs were computed at cumulaKve intervals, where the sample size of parKcipants increased by 10 unKl reaching 300 (i.e., iteraKons from 10-300 in steps of 10). For each step, we carried out 20 iteraKons. In each iteraKon, the required number of parKcipants were randomly sampled from the total number of parKcipants and computed all the same RDMs and correlaKon analyses as in the main manuscript. For example, for 50 parKcipants, we conducted 20 iteraKons; for each iteraKon, we randomly sampled 50 parKcipants from the total number of parKcipants; we then computed three 50-by-50 RDMs, one for each variable: RDM Self-ratedsocial-traits, RDM Personality-traits, and RDM Face-judgements; we vectorised the RDMs and computed correlaKons between RDM Face-judgements and RDM Self-rated-social-traits, and between RDM Facejudgements and RDM Personality-traits; correlaKons were then averaged across the 20 iteraKons for this sample size. We repeated this procedure for each sample size from 10 to 300.</p><p>CorrelaKons between RDM Self-rated-social-traits with RDM Face-judgements and correlaKons between RDM Personality-traits with RDM Face-judgements became stable with around 120 parKcipants (Figure S4-1). From this, it is apparent that a sample size between 120 and 160 parKcipants may be sufficient. It is also clear that the results are not just dependent on our large sample size, nor are they dependent on only a few parKcipants. Note. The plot shows the correlaKon results with different numbers of parKcipants. For each iteraKon, a random sample of parKcipants was selected (N specified in the x-axis), RDMs were computed, and the correlaKon analyses were carried out. This process was carried out cumulaKvely, starKng with a sample size of 10 parKcipants unKl 300 parKcipants. The lines show mean correlaKons for each sample size and the error bars show standard deviaKons across samples for the same N.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary InformaKon 7</head><p>How much do parKcipants agree on the face-judgements? We next computed inter-rater agreement of face-judgements to invesKgate agreement of face raKngs across parKcipants. We computed inter-rater agreement in two ways. First, we computed inter-rater agreement by using a 'pairwise approach', in which we computed the correlaKon of the raKngs of each parKcipant with the raKngs of each of the other parKcipants. Second, we computed inter-rater agreement by using a 'one versus others approach' by compuKng the correlaKon of the raKngs of each parKcipant with the average of all the other parKcipants. We computed these measures for all trials of the Face-judgements Task and also per trait (i.e., separately for Trustworthiness, Dominance, AVracKveness, Sociability, Aggressiveness and Intelligence). Results in Table <ref type="table">S7</ref>-1 show low to moderate inter-rater agreement for all traits and per trait, and these results are comparable to ones from previous studies (e.g. <ref type="bibr">Oosterhof &amp; Todorov, 2008)</ref>, and again demonstrate that there are substanKal individual differences in face-judgements. AVracKveness was the trait with the highest inter-rater agreement.</p><p>Table S7-1 Inter-rater agreement for the Face-judgement Tasks (all traits and per face trait) Mean inter-rater agreement (SD) Face Judgement Task Pairwise One vs others All traits (all trials) Trustworthiness Dominance AVracKveness Sociability Aggressiveness Intelligence .23(.08) .13(.08) .16(.09) .28(.10) .22(.09) .14(.08) .19(.09) .48(.16) .36(.22) .39(.22) .50(.20) .44(.20) .39(.23)</p><p>.42(.21) Note. In the 'pairwise approach', we computed the correlaKon of the raKngs of each parKcipant with the raKngs of each of the other parKcipants. In the 'one versus others approach', we computed the correlaKon of the raKngs of each parKcipant with the average of all the other parKcipants.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure</head><figDesc>Figure S4-1 RDM correla%ons across different sample sizes.</figDesc><graphic coords="22,36.00,358.27,372.78,267.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="8,36.00,123.89,523.00,413.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="24,36.00,431.51,506.47,174.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Regression analyses using Personality-traits similarity to predict Face-judgements similarity.Simple regression results including only RDM Personality-traits as predictor. MulTple regression results including RDM Personality-traits and RDMs for demographic variables as predictors. 𝛽 = Parameter esTmates; P-values esTmated by random permutaTons.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Simple Regression</cell><cell>MulTple Regression</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>𝛽, p</cell><cell>𝛽, p</cell></row><row><cell>Personality-traits similarity</cell><cell>.199, p &lt; .001</cell><cell>.190, p &lt; .001</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell></cell><cell>.059, p = .017</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell>.031, p = .014</cell></row><row><cell>Ethnicity</cell><cell></cell><cell>.170, p &lt; .001</cell></row><row><cell>Region</cell><cell></cell><cell>.085, p = .032</cell></row><row><cell>Note.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work was supported by a PhD studentship from <rs type="funder">City, University of London</rs> to RW and a <rs type="funder">Leverhulme Trust</rs> <rs type="grantName">Research Fellowship</rs> to LG (<rs type="grantNumber">RF-2024-326</rs>).</p></div>
<div><head>Statements and DeclaraTons</head><p>This research received approval from the <rs type="institution">Psychology Research Ethics CommiWee at City, University of London</rs>. All parTcipants provided informed consent to parTcipate electronically. The authors declare no potenTal conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publicaTon of this arTcle. The hypotheses, methods, and plan for main analyses were pre-registered before starTng data collecTon: hWps://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/ZR92G. Primary data and scripts for main analyses are publicly available: hWps://doi.org/10.25383/city.26519890.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PfXVnyw">
					<idno type="grant-number">RF-2024-326</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">Research Fellowship</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION Dyadic Person Similarity Predicts Similarity in Face Judgements</head><p>Rochelle Williams 1 , Lúcia Garrido CorrelaKon between Self-rated-social-traits similarity and Personality-traits similarity For completeness, we correlated the RDM Self-rated-social-traits with the RDM Personality-traits. This would inform us about the consistency in self-report person similarity between parKcipants. Results showed that there was a posiKve and substanKal correlaKon between the two RDMs (rs = .588; 95% bootstrapped CI = [.537 .641]), which was significantly higher than zero (p &lt; .001, permutaKon tests). These results suggest that there is high consistency in the two self-report person similarity measures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary InformaKon 5</head><p>Does person similarity predict face-judgements similarity for specific traits? We invesKgated whether the associaKon of person similarity with face-judgements similarity is stronger for some face-judgements than others, (e.g., the correlaKon between person similarity and face trustworthiness judgements, specifically). It could be the case that consistencies in people's disposiKons are reflected in certain traits more strongly than in others. In other words, can we use person similarity to predict face-judgements similarity for all of the social traits? One problem with doing these correlaKons separately is that there are fewer trials per condiKon, so the sizes of these correlaKons cannot be directly compared to the ones using all traits simultaneously. In the analyses below, the person RDMs (RDM Self-rated-social-traits and RDM Personality-traits) were the same as in the main manuscript. However, we computed mulKple RDM Face-Judgements, one for each of the face-judgements in the Face-judgements Task (Trustworthiness, Dominance, AVracKveness, Sociability, Aggressiveness and Intelligence).</p><p>CorrelaKons between RDM Self-rated-social-traits and RDMs for each of the face-judgements: Results revealed that there were small but significant posiKve correlaKons between RDM Self-rated-social-traits and each of the individual face-trait RDMs, namely for RDM Face-trustworthiness (rs = .038, p &lt; .001, random permutaKons), RDM Face-dominance (rs = .045, p &lt; .001), RDM Face-aVracKveness (rs = .067, p &lt; .001), RDM Face-sociability (rs = .061, p &lt; .001), RDM Face-aggressiveness (rs = .011 , p = .005), and RDM Face-intelligence (rs = .057, p &lt; .001).</p><p>CorrelaKons between RDM Personality-traits and RDMs for each of the face-judgements: For the correlaKons between RDM Personality-traits and the RDMs of each face-traits, results revealed that there were also small but posiKve significant correlaKons with the RDMs for all face traits, namely for RDM Face-trustworthiness (rs = .067, p &lt; .001), RDM Face-dominance (rs = .072, p &lt; .001), RDM Face-aVracKveness (rs = .11, p &lt; .001), RDM Face-sociability (rs = .090, p &lt; .001), RDM Face-aggressiveness (rs = .036, p &lt; .001), and RDM Face-intelligence (rs = .058, p &lt; .001).</p><p>These results showed that self-rated-social-traits similarity and personality-traits similarity could also predict similarity of trait raKngs for each of the traits individually, and were not driven by any specific face-judgements. The highest correlaKons were between personality-traits similarity and face-judgements similarity for aVracKveness and sociability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary InformaKon 6</head><p>How do individual differences in person traits predict mean raKngs of faces? We conducted further analyses invesKgaKng the extent to which individual differences in specific self-ratedsocial-traits and personality-traits contribute to the average face judgements. Specifically, we wanted to understand whether scoring higher or lower on each of the personality-traits and self-rated-social-traits is correlated with mean raKngs of the face judgements for each trait. For example, if someone rates themselves as more trustworthy, are they more likely to rate others as more trustworthy? <ref type="bibr">Matarozzi et al. (2015)</ref> had found that individuals who score higher on Agreeableness tend to rate faces as more trustworthy. Here, we extended these analyses to all traits measured. Specifically, for each parKcipant, we computed: (i) individual scores for each of the 13 self-rated-social-traits (based on the Self-rated-social-traits QuesKonnaire), (ii) individual scores for each of the Big Five personality-traits (based on the Personality-traits QuesKonnaire), and (iii) mean raKngs for each social trait on the Face-judgements Task (by compuKng the mean of all face raKngs for each trait for the same parKcipant). We then correlated measures in (i) and (iii), and (ii) and (iii) (Figure <ref type="figure">S6</ref>- 1). We corrected for mulKple comparisons using False Discovery Rate (FDR) correcKon.</p><p>Regarding correlaKons between individual differences in self-rated-social-traits and mean face-judgements (Figure <ref type="figure">S6</ref>-1a), there was only a significant posiKve correlaKon between self-rated-aggression and faceaggression. With regards to correlaKons between individual differences in personality-traits (Big 5 scores) and mean face-judgements (Figure <ref type="figure">S6</ref>-1b), there were no significant correlaKons aser correcKon for mulKple comparisons. These results demonstrate that our main findings of face-judgements similarity being predicted by person similarity cannot be fully explained by associaKons of any specific person-traits with specific facejudgements, and instead seem to reflect paAerns of responses across traits. We did not replicate the significant posiKve correlaKon between agreeableness and trustworthiness, but our sample was smaller than the one in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">MaVarozzi et al. (2015)</ref> and we controlled for mulKple comparisons of all traits. In any case, our results suggest that individual differences in person traits are not associated only with specific changes in means of face-judgements, but instead with changes in paAerns of judgements across many traits.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus in personality judgements at zero acquaintance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Albright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Malloy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">387</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lonely individuals process the world in idiosyncraTc ways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>López</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="683" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finng Linear Mixed-Effects Models Using lme4</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maechler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bolker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Sta7s7cal SoSware</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beauty is in the &apos;we&apos; of the beholder: Greater agreement on facial aWracTveness among close relaTons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bronstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Percep7on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1674" to="1681" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Untangling the relatedness among correlaTons, part I: Nonparametric approaches to inter-subject correlaTon analysis at the group level</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Glen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Israel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="259" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Untangling the relatedness among correlaTons, part II: Inter-subject correlaTon group analysis through linear mixed-effects modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="825" to="840" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccrae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">NEO Personality Inventory-Revised (NEO-PI-R)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Psychological Assessment Resources</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The perceiver and the perceived: Their relaTve influence on the categories of interpersonal cogniTon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dornbusch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hastorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Muzzy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vreeland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">434</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Idiosynchrony: From shared responses to individual differences during naturalisTc neuroimaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Finn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gleren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Khpjandu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Molfese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Handwerker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bandenni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116828</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Individual AestheTc Preferences for Faces Are Shaped Mostly by Environments, Not Genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Germine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bronstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blokland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Smoller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kwok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Anthony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rhodes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2684" to="2689" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The unique contribuTons of perceiver and target characterisTcs in person percepTon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sutherland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Flake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Slepian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="529" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Once more: Is beauty in the eye of the beholder? RelaTve contribuTons of private and shared taste to judgements of facial aWracTveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hönekopp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Psychology: Human Percep7on and Performance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">To which world regions does the valence-dominance model of social percepTon apply?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matching categorical object representaTons in inferior temporal cortex of man and monkey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kriegeskorte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bodurka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Esteky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bandenni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1126" to="1141" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">lmerTest Package: Tests in Linear Mixed Effects Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kuznetsova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brockhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H B</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Sta7s7cal SoSware</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Chicago Face Database: A Free STmulus Set of Faces and Norming Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Correll</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wiwenbrink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavior Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1122" to="1135" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chicago Face Database: MulTracial Expansion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kantner</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wiwenbrink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavior Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1289" to="1300" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using item response theory to develop a 60-item representaTon of the NEO PI-R using the InternaTonal Personality Item Pool: Development of the IPIP-NEO-60</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Maples-Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sleep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality assessment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of the self-concept in the percepTon of others</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Markus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Moreland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1494</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of gender and personality on first impression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mawarozzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marzocchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vicari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">135529</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personality similarity predicts synchronous neural responses in fMRI and EEG data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Matz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Baek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cerf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scien7fic Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14325</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="beta.ons.gov.uk/areas/E92000001-england" />
		<title level="m">explore-local-staTsTcs</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>England</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Office for NaTonal StaTsTcs</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ethnic group variable: Census 2021</title>
		<ptr target="hWps://www.ons.gov.uk/census/census2021dicTonary/variablesbytopic/ethnicgroupnaTonalidenTtylanguageandreligionvariablescensus2021/ethnicgroup" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Office for NaTonal StaTsTcs</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personality across world regions predicts variability in the structure of face impressions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Martn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1240" to="1256" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The funcTonal basis of face evaluaTon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Oosterhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the Na7onal Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11087" to="11092" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similar neural responses predict friendship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kleinbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wheatley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">332</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Team</forename><surname>Core</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;hWps://www.R-project.org/" />
		<title level="m">R: A Language and Environment for StaTsTcal CompuTng. R FoundaTon for StaTsTcal CompuTng</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">More Tme for science: Using Testable to create and share behavioral experiments faster, recruit beWer parTcipants, and engage students in hands-on research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rezlescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Danaila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Miron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Amariei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Progress in Brain Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">253</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social projecTon to ingroups and outgroups: A review and metaanalysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global MulT-ResoluTon Topography (GMRT) synthesis data set</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B F</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Carbowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Coplan</forename><surname>O'hara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Melkonian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Arko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Weissel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ferrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Goodwillie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nitsche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bonczkowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zemsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1029/2008GC002332</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochemistry. Geophysics. Geosystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3014</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emerging late adolescent friendship networks and Big Five personality traits: A social network approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Selpout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Burk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Branje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Denissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Aken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Meeus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="538" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In the eye of the beholder: Perceived, actual, and peer-rated similarity in personality, communicaTon, and friendship intensity during the acquaintanceship process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Selpout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Denissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Branje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Meeus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1152" to="1165" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">For your local eyes only: Culture-specific face typicality influences percepTons of trustworthiness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dotsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Oikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wigboldus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Percep7on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="914" to="928" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceiving others&apos; personaliTes: Examining the dimensionality, assumed similarity to the self, and stability of perceiver effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gugliemo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Beer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="520" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Individual differences in trust evaluaTons are shaped mostly by environments, not genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A M</forename><surname>Sutherland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Burton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A M</forename><surname>Blokland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Germine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Palermo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Collova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rhodes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the Na7onal Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10218" to="10224" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social inferences from faces: Ambient images generate a three-dimensional model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sutherland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Oldmeadow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Towler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Burt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cogni7on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do facial first impressions reflect a shared social reality? Bri7</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A M</forename><surname>Sutherland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rhodes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Burton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">sh Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling first impressions from highly variable facial images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vernon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sutherland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hartley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the Na7onal Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3353" to="E3361" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relaTonship between anxiety and the social judgements of approachability and trustworthiness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Willis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Dodd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Palermo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">76825</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceiver effects as projecTve tests: What your percepTons of others say about you</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Harms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vazire</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of gender and personality on first impression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mavarozzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marzocchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vicari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">135529</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The funcKonal basis of face evaluaKon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Oosterhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the Na%onal Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11087" to="11092" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
