<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Cosmic Channel Capacity: Extending the Shannon Limit to Universal Scales</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Logan</forename><surname>Nye</surname></persName>
							<email>lnye@andrew.cmu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Cosmic Channel Capacity: Extending the Shannon Limit to Universal Scales</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">359DC19588449DA8AEB508302CE66C03</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>on Cosmic Information Transmission Limits</term>
					<term>10</term>
					<term>2 Comparison of Cosmic and Classical Information Theories</term>
					<term>10</term>
					<term>3 Future Prospects for a Comprehensive Cosmic Information Theory</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Shannon's Channel Capacity, a foundational concept in classical information theory, establishes the fundamental constraints on information transmission through classical channels. This paper extends Shannon's seminal work to cosmic scales, integrating quantum and gravitational effects to formulate a novel framework for "cosmic channel capacity." This framework addresses the unique challenges associated with information processing and transmission across vast cosmic distances and within extreme gravitational environments. Our principal contributions are: (1) a generalized formula for cosmic channel capacity that incorporates quantum entanglement and spacetime curvature; (2) modified limits on information transmission in the presence of black holes and the expanding universe; and (3) identification of potential observational signatures in gravitational waves and anisotropies in the cosmic microwave background. This comprehensive approach enhances our understanding of the fundamental limits of information processing and transmission in the universe, with significant implications for quantum gravity, cosmology, and the intrinsic nature of information.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction 1.Background on Shannon's Information Theory</head><p>In 1948, Claude Shannon revolutionized our understanding of communication with his groundbreaking work on information theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">[85]</ref>. At its core lies the concept of channel capacity, which quantifies the maximum rate of reliable information transmission over a noisy channel. This foundational work has profoundly influenced fields ranging from computer science to biology <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[24]</ref>. Shannon's channel capacity theorem states that for any channel with capacity C, there exist codes allowing information transmission at rates arbitrarily close to C with negligible error probability. Mathematically, channel capacity C is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">C = max p(x) I(X; Y )<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where I(X; Y ) is the mutual information between input X and output Y , maximized over all possible input distributions p(x).</p><p>For a discrete memoryless channel with additive white Gaussian noise, the Shannon-Hartley theorem gives the capacity as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">C = B log 2 1 + S N<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where B is channel bandwidth, S is average signal power, and N is average noise power. This theorem has been crucial in designing modern communication systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">[78]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Motivation for Extending to Cosmic Scales</head><p>While Shannon's theory has been invaluable for terrestrial communication systems, it was developed within the framework of classical physics. As our understanding of the universe has evolved, particularly with quantum mechanics and theories of quantum gravity, we must ask: How do these principles apply at cosmic scales? Several key considerations motivate this extension:</p><p>1. Quantum effects on information: At cosmic scales, quantum phenomena such as entanglement (the non-local correlation between particles) and superposition (the ability of quantum systems to exist in multiple states simultaneously) may fundamentally alter information transmission <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>.</p><p>2. Gravitational influences: Extreme gravitational environments, like those near black holes or in the early universe, could significantly impact information processing and transmission <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>.</p><p>3. Cosmic expansion: The universe's expansion introduces unique challenges to longdistance information transmission, affecting signal propagation in ways not addressed by classical theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[46]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Holographic principle:</head><p>This principle suggests that the information content of a volume of space can be described by a theory on its boundary, hinting at deep connections between information and spacetime structure [92, <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">87,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">22]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Black hole information paradox:</head><p>The ongoing debate about information preservation in black holes underscores the need for a better understanding of information dynamics in extreme gravitational scenarios <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">59]</ref>.</p><p>These considerations not only motivate the extension of Shannon's concept to cosmic scales but also suggest that such an extension could provide insights into fundamental questions in physics, such as the nature of quantum gravity and the origin of spacetime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Overview of Key Concepts</head><p>To extend Shannon's theorem to cosmic scales, we must integrate several key concepts from modern physics:</p><p>1. Quantum Information Theory: Extends classical information theory to quantum systems, introducing concepts like qubits and quantum entanglement <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>.</p><p>2. General Relativity: Einstein's theory of gravity, crucial for understanding how spacetime curvature affects information propagation <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref>.</p><p>3. Quantum Field Theory in Curved Spacetime: Allows the study of quantum effects in gravitational backgrounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[17]</ref>.</p><p>4. Holographic Principle: Suggests a deep connection between the information content of a volume of space and the physics on its boundary <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">[92,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b90">87]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Entanglement Entropy:</head><p>Quantifies the amount of quantum information shared between subsystems <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">[83]</ref>.</p><p>6. Cosmic Horizons: Introduce fundamental limits to information accessibility in an expanding universe <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">[80,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">25]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">Thesis Statement and Paper Objectives</head><p>This paper proposes a novel framework for understanding information processing in the universe by extending Shannon's concept of channel capacity to cosmic scales. Our approach, which we term "cosmic channel capacity," incorporates quantum and gravitational effects to provide a unified perspective on information dynamics in the cosmos. We hypothesize that by developing this comprehensive theory of information processing at cosmic scales, we can gain deeper insights into the nature of information, spacetime, and the fundamental workings of the universe. Our primary objectives are:</p><p>1. To formulate a mathematically rigorous definition of "cosmic channel capacity" that incorporates quantum and gravitational effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>To derive fundamental limits on information transmission and processing at cosmic scales, accounting for quantum effects, gravitational influences, and cosmic expansion.</p><p>3. To apply these cosmic information limits to specific astrophysical scenarios, such as black hole information processing and long-distance communication across expanding space.</p><p>4. To identify potential observational signatures that could test our theory, focusing on gravitational wave observations and cosmic microwave background anisotropies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p>To examine the implications of our framework for fundamental physics, including the black hole information paradox and the emergence of classical spacetime from quantum information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5">Paper Structure</head><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: Section 2 provides the theoretical foundations necessary for our work. Section 3 presents the derivation of our cosmic channel capacity formula. Section 4 applies this framework to specific cosmic-scale scenarios. Section 5 discusses the implications for fundamental physics. Section 6 explores observational and experimental prospects. Section 7 examines cosmic-scale error correction and information preservation. Section 8 considers technological implications. Finally, Section 9 concludes with a discussion of challenges and future directions. Through this exploration, we aim to establish cosmic channel capacity as a powerful new paradigm for understanding the fundamental nature of information processing in the universe, extending Shannon's seminal work to the largest scales imaginable. By bridging the gap between information theory and fundamental physics, we hope to provide new insights into the nature of space, time, and information in the cosmos.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Theoretical Foundations</head><p>This section provides a comprehensive overview of the key concepts and theories that form the foundation of our cosmic channel capacity framework. We begin with classical information theory, progress to quantum information theory, and then extend to gravitational and cosmological concepts. Throughout, we emphasize the connections between these areas and their relevance to our central thesis of cosmic channel capacity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Review of Classical Information Theory</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1">Shannon's Channel Capacity Theorem</head><p>Shannon's channel capacity theorem, introduced in his seminal 1948 paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">[85]</ref>, is the cornerstone of classical information theory. It establishes fundamental limits on the rate at which information can be reliably transmitted over a noisy communication channel, revolutionizing our understanding of communication systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[24]</ref>.</p><p>Theorem 1 (Shannon's Channel Capacity Theorem). For a discrete memoryless channel, the channel capacity C is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">C = max p(x) I(X; Y ) (3)</formula><p>where the maximum is taken over all possible input distributions p(x), and I(X; Y ) is the mutual information between input X and output Y .</p><p>This theorem provides the foundation for our cosmic channel capacity concept, which we will extend to incorporate quantum and gravitational effects.</p><p>The mutual information I(X; Y ), a key concept in information theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[24]</ref>, is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">I(X; Y ) = x∈X y∈Y p(x, y) log 2 p(x, y) p(x)p(y)<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where p(x, y) is the joint probability distribution of X and Y , and p(x) and p(y) are their respective marginal distributions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2">Noise and Error Correction in Classical Channels</head><p>In classical information theory, noise is modeled as a random process that corrupts the transmitted signal. A common model is the additive white Gaussian noise (AWGN) channel <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">[77]</ref>, where the received signal Y is related to the transmitted signal X by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Y = X + N (<label>5</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">)</formula><p>where N is a Gaussian random variable with zero mean and variance σ 2 .</p><p>Error correction codes, pioneered by Hamming <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[33]</ref>, allow for reliable communication over noisy channels by adding redundancy to the transmitted information. The fundamental theorem of error correction ensures that reliable communication is possible even in noisy environments, up to the fundamental limit set by the channel capacity. This concept will be crucial when we consider error correction in cosmic-scale information transmission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Quantum Information Theory</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Quantum States and Qubits</head><p>In quantum information theory, the fundamental unit of information is the qubit, analogous to the classical bit. A qubit can be in a superposition of states, represented as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">|ψ⟩ = α|0⟩ + β|1⟩<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where |α| 2 + |β| 2 = 1. This superposition principle is key to understanding quantum information processing and will play a crucial role in our cosmic channel capacity framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Quantum Entanglement and Information</head><p>Quantum entanglement, a phenomenon with no classical analog, is fundamental to quantum information theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>. For a bipartite quantum system in a pure state |ψ⟩, the entanglement entropy is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">S ent = -Tr(ρ A log 2 ρ A )<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where ρ A = Tr B (|ψ⟩⟨ψ|) is the reduced density matrix of subsystem A. Entanglement entropy will be a crucial quantity in our cosmic channel capacity formula, as it captures the quantum correlations that may enhance information transmission across cosmic scales.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3">Quantum Channels and Capacity</head><p>Quantum channels generalize classical channels to the quantum domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>. A quantum channel E is described by a completely positive, trace-preserving (CPTP) map. The quantum capacity Q(E) of a channel, introduced by Lloyd <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref>, is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Q(E) = lim n→∞ 1 n max ρ I c (ρ, E ⊗n )<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where I c (ρ, E) is the coherent information of the channel E with respect to input state ρ. This capacity represents the maximum rate at which quantum information can be reliably transmitted through the channel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Gravitational Effects on Information Transmission</head><p>General relativity introduces several important effects on information transmission <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref>:</p><p>1. Gravitational time dilation: The proper time experienced by a signal depends on the gravitational potential, affecting the perceived information transmission rate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Gravitational lensing:</head><p>The bending of light by massive objects can affect the path and integrity of information-carrying signals.</p><p>3. Gravitational waves: These ripples in spacetime can potentially carry information and interact with other information-carrying signals.</p><p>The propagation of a quantum field ϕ in curved spacetime is described by the Klein-Gordon equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[17]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">(□ + m 2 )ϕ = 0 (9)</formula><p>where □ is the d'Alembertian operator in curved spacetime. This equation will be crucial in understanding how quantum information propagates on cosmic scales in our framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Cosmological Concepts Relevant to Information Transmission</head><p>Several cosmological concepts are crucial for understanding information transmission on cosmic scales:</p><p>1. Cosmic Expansion: Described by the Friedmann-Lemaître-Robertson-Walker (FLRW) metric:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">ds 2 = -c 2 dt 2 + a 2 (t)[dr 2 + r 2 (dθ 2 + sin 2 θdϕ 2 )] (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">)</formula><p>where a(t) is the scale factor. This expansion affects signal propagation across cosmic distances and will be a key factor in our cosmic channel capacity formula.</p><p>2. Cosmic Horizons: These fundamental limits to information exchange in an expanding universe <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">[80]</ref> will play a crucial role in defining the ultimate bounds of our cosmic channel capacity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Inflationary Expansion:</head><p>This period of rapid expansion in the early universe <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[32]</ref> has significant implications for the causal structure and information content of the observable universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Recent Developments</head><p>Recent work has further illuminated the connections between quantum information, gravity, and cosmology:</p><p>• Quantum error correction and holography: Almheiri et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[5]</ref> have shown how quantum error correction codes naturally emerge in holographic theories, providing new insights into the AdS/CFT correspondence.</p><p>• Entanglement and emergent spacetime: Van Raamsdonk <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">[94]</ref> and others have proposed that spacetime itself may emerge from quantum entanglement, suggesting a deep connection between quantum information and the structure of spacetime.</p><p>• Gravitational decoherence: Researchers are exploring how gravity might affect quantum coherence, with potential implications for large-scale quantum experiments and the quantum-to-classical transition <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[9]</ref>.</p><p>These developments highlight the rich interplay between quantum information, gravity, and cosmology, setting the stage for our exploration of cosmic channel capacity. In the next section, we will build upon these foundations to formulate our cosmic channel capacity framework, extending Shannon's concept to incorporate quantum and gravitational effects at the largest scales.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Formulating a Cosmic Channel Capacity</head><p>In this section, we develop our novel concept of cosmic channel capacity, extending Shannon's classical information theory to incorporate quantum and gravitational effects at cosmic scales. This extension is necessary to account for the unique challenges posed by quantum mechanics and general relativity when considering information transmission across vast cosmic distances and in extreme gravitational environments. Our goal is to provide a unified framework that bridges the gap between classical information theory and the fundamental physics of the cosmos.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Definition of "Cosmic Channel"</head><p>To extend Shannon's concept of channel capacity to cosmic scales, we must first define what we mean by a "cosmic channel." This definition serves as the foundation for our subsequent analysis and calculations, building upon the holographic principle proposed by 't Hooft and Susskind <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">[87,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">22]</ref>.</p><p>Definition 1 (Cosmic Channel). The cosmic channel is a quantum information processing system comprising the geometric structure of spacetime and the quantum fields that permeate it. Mathematically, we express this as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">Cosmic Channel ≡ (M, g µν , {ϕ i }) (<label>11</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">)</formula><p>where M is a 4-dimensional manifold, g µν is the metric tensor defining the geometry of spacetime, and {ϕ i } is the set of quantum fields on M.</p><p>The geometric structure of spacetime, encoded in g µν , provides the backdrop for information propagation, while quantum fields {ϕ i } serve as the carriers of information. The dynamics of this system are governed by the Einstein field equations and the equations of motion for quantum fields in curved spacetime, as described in the framework of quantum field theory in curved spacetime <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[17]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Deriving the Cosmic Channel Capacity Formula</head><p>We now present a step-by-step derivation of our cosmic channel capacity formula, starting from Shannon's classical result and progressively incorporating quantum and gravitational effects. This approach is inspired by the work of Lloyd on quantum channel capacity <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref> and recent developments in quantum information theory in curved spacetime <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">[93]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Starting from Shannon's Classical Formula</head><p>We begin with Shannon's classical formula for channel capacity <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">[85]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">C classical = B log 2 1 + S N (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">)</formula><p>where B is the bandwidth, S is the signal power, and N is the noise power.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Quantum Generalization</head><p>To account for quantum effects, we replace the classical mutual information with its quantum analog and introduce terms for quantum entanglement and complexity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">C quantum = max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent + βC QC ]<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where:</p><p>• I(X : Y ) is the quantum mutual information, generalizing classical mutual information to quantum systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>.</p><p>• S ent is the entanglement entropy, quantifying quantum correlations <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">[83]</ref>.</p><p>• C QC is the quantum complexity, representing the computational difficulty of preparing or manipulating quantum states <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23]</ref>.</p><p>• α and β are dimensionless coupling constants.</p><p>The entanglement entropy S ent is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">S ent = -Tr(ρ A log 2 ρ A ) (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">)</formula><p>where ρ A is the reduced density matrix of subsystem A.</p><p>For the quantum complexity term C QC , we use the "complexity equals action" conjecture:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">C QC ≈ S action πℏ<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where S action is the action of the Wheeler-DeWitt patch of the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3">Accounting for Gravitational Influences</head><p>To incorporate gravitational effects, we introduce the cosmic scale factor a(t) from the FLRW metric and impose the holographic bound:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">C cosmic (t) = 1 a(t) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent + βC QC ]<label>(16)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">C cosmic (t) ≤ 2πk B R(t)E(t) ℏc ln 2<label>(17)</label></formula><p>where R(t) is the cosmic horizon radius and E(t) is the total energy within the horizon at time t.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.4">Final Cosmic Channel Capacity Equation</head><p>Combining these elements, our final mathematical framework for cosmic channel capacity is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">C cosmic (t) = min 1 a(t) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent + βC QC ] , 2πk B R(t)E(t)</formula><p>ℏc ln 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(18)</ref> subject to the cosmological dynamics described by the Friedmann equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b102">[99]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Physical Interpretation and Analysis</head><p>Each component of our cosmic channel capacity formula has a distinct physical interpretation:</p><p>1. Quantum Mutual Information I(X : Y ): Represents the total (classical and quantum) correlations between sender and receiver.</p><p>2. Entanglement Entropy Term αS ent : Captures the potential enhancement of channel capacity due to quantum entanglement across cosmic scales.</p><p>3. Quantum Complexity Term βC QC : Accounts for information encoded in the complexity of cosmic-scale quantum states.</p><p>4. Scale Factor a(t): Represents the dilution of information density due to cosmic expansion.</p><p>5. Holographic Bound: Ensures consistency with the holographic principle, setting an ultimate limit on information content.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Dimensional Analysis</head><p>To verify the consistency of our formula, we perform a dimensional analysis:</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">• [C cosmic ] = [T ime] -1 (bits per second) • [a(t)] = [1] (dimensionless) • [I(X : Y )] = [S ent ] = [C QC ] = [1] (dimensionless, measured in bits) • [α] = [β] = [1] (dimensionless coupling constants) • [k B ] = [Energy][T emperature] -1 • [R(t)] = [Length]</formula><p>• [E(t)] = [Energy]</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">• [ℏ] = [Energy][T ime] • [c] = [Length][T ime] -1</formula><p>This analysis confirms that our formula is dimensionally consistent, with the right-hand side having units of bits per second.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Numerical Estimates and Examples</head><p>To build intuition, let's consider some numerical examples:</p><p>1. Entangled Qubits: For two maximally entangled qubits separated by a cosmic distance, S ent = 1 bit. If α = 0.1, this contributes 0.1 bits to the channel capacity.</p><p>2. Cosmic Complexity: For a system of N = 10 80 qubits (approximately the number of particles in the observable universe), C QC ∼ 2 10 80 . With β = 10 -100 , this contributes about 10 -20 bits to the capacity.</p><p>3. Holographic Bound: For the observable universe (R ∼ 4.4 × 10 26 m, E ∼ 10 70 J), the bound is approximately 10 122 bits/s.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Comparison with Classical Shannon Limit</head><p>In the classical limit (negligible quantum and gravitational effects), our formula reduces to the Shannon limit:</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">lim α,β→0 a(t)→1 C cosmic (t) ≈ max p(x) I(X : Y ) ≈ B log 2 1 + S N<label>(19)</label></formula><p>This demonstrates the consistency of our framework with established theory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7">Limitations and Assumptions</head><p>Our formula makes several key assumptions:</p><p>• The applicability of quantum field theory in curved spacetime.</p><p>• The validity of the holographic principle at all scales.</p><p>• The "complexity equals action" conjecture.</p><p>These assumptions may break down in extreme scenarios, such as near spacetime singularities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8">Alternative Formulations and Historical Context</head><p>Our approach builds on previous attempts to extend information theory to quantum and gravitational regimes, such as Lloyd's work on the computational capacity of the universe <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[53]</ref>. Alternative formulations might include different measures of quantum information or different approaches to incorporating gravitational effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.9">Testable Predictions</head><p>Our formula leads to several testable predictions, which will be explored in detail in Section 6. These include:</p><p>• Modifications to gravitational wave signals due to quantum information effects.</p><p>• Signatures of cosmic-scale quantum correlations in the cosmic microwave background.</p><p>• Limits on information transmission in extreme gravitational environments.</p><p>In the following sections, we will apply this framework to specific astrophysical scenarios (Section 4), discuss its implications for fundamental physics (Section 5), and explore observational prospects (Section 6).</p><p>This comprehensive formulation of cosmic channel capacity provides a unified framework for understanding information transmission at the largest scales, incorporating quantum and gravitational effects. It opens up new avenues for exploring fundamental questions in physics and cosmology, which we will investigate in the remainder of this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Cosmic-Scale Information Transmission Scenarios</head><p>This section applies our cosmic channel capacity framework to several specific scenarios of information transmission at cosmic scales. We will examine black hole information transmission, entanglement-assisted cosmic communication, early universe to CMB information transfer, and intergalactic communication. These examples demonstrate the broad applicability of our framework and its potential to provide new insights into fundamental questions in cosmology and astrophysics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Black Hole Information Transmission</head><p>Black holes present a unique challenge and opportunity for studying information transmission at cosmic scales. We examine how our framework applies to the process of black hole evaporation through Hawking radiation, addressing the long-standing black hole information paradox.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1">Hawking Radiation as an Information Channel</head><p>Hawking radiation, the thermal emission from black holes predicted by quantum field theory in curved spacetime <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[35]</ref>, can be viewed as an information channel from the black hole to the external universe. The temperature of Hawking radiation for a Schwarzschild black hole is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">T H = ℏc 3 8πGM k B (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">)</formula><p>where M is the mass of the black hole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2">Channel Capacity for Black Hole Evaporation</head><p>Applying our cosmic channel capacity formula to the Hawking radiation process yields:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">C BH (t) = min 1 a(t) max p(x)</formula><p>[I(X : Y ) + αS ent (A : R) + βC QC (t)] , A(t) 4Gℏ ln 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(21)</ref> where I(X : Y ) is the quantum mutual information between the black hole state X and the emitted radiation Y , S ent (A : R) is the entanglement entropy between the black hole (A) and the radiation (R), C QC (t) is the quantum complexity of the black hole state, and A(t) is the area of the black hole's event horizon.</p><p>The evolution of the black hole mass due to Hawking radiation is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">dM dt = - ℏc 6 15360πG 2 M 2<label>(22)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.3">Comparative Analysis and Numerical Example</head><p>For a solar mass black hole (M ⊙ ≈ 2 × 10 30 kg), we estimate:</p><p>• Initial Hawking temperature: T H ≈ 6.2 × 10 -8 K</p><p>• Initial channel capacity: C BH (0) ≈ 3.8 × 10 77 bits/s</p><p>• Evaporation time: τ evap ≈ 2.1 × 10 67 years</p><p>The total information transmitted over the black hole's lifetime is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">I total = τevap 0 C BH (t)dt ≈ 2.5 × 10 145 bits<label>(23)</label></formula><p>This result suggests that a solar mass black hole can transmit an amount of information far exceeding its Bekenstein-Hawking entropy (S BH ≈ 10 77 bits) during its lifetime. In contrast, classical models predict no information transmission from black holes, highlighting the novel insights provided by our framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.4">Observational Prospects and Open Questions</head><p>While direct observation of Hawking radiation remains challenging, potential observational tests include:</p><p>• Gravitational wave signatures from black hole mergers, which may contain imprints of quantum information effects.</p><p>• Anomalies in the spectra of primordial black holes, if they exist.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Entanglement-Assisted Cosmic Communication</head><p>We now consider how quantum entanglement could enhance communication over cosmic distances, a scenario with potential implications for both fundamental physics and future technologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">Entanglement-Assisted Channel Capacity</head><p>The channel capacity for entanglement-assisted communication in an expanding universe is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">C EA,cosmic (t) = 1 a(t) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + S ent (A : B)]<label>(24)</label></formula><p>where S ent (A : B) is the entanglement entropy between the two communicating parties A and B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.2">Numerical Example and Comparative Analysis</head><p>Consider two parties separated by a comoving distance of 1 Gpc who share 100 entangled qubits:</p><p>• Current scale factor: a(t 0 ) ≈ 1</p><p>• Entanglement entropy: S ent (A : B) = 100 bits</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">• Classical channel capacity: C classical ≈ 1 bit/s</formula><p>The entanglement-assisted capacity is then:</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">C EA,cosmic (t 0 ) ≈ 101 bits/s<label>(25)</label></formula><p>This 100-fold increase in channel capacity compared to classical communication demonstrates the potential power of quantum entanglement for cosmic-scale communication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.3">Observational Prospects and Theoretical Challenges</head><p>Potential observational tests include:</p><p>• Detection of coordinated variability in distant quasars, which could indicate quantum entanglement on cosmic scales.</p><p>• Anomalous correlations in the cosmic microwave background, potentially arising from primordial entanglement.</p><p>Theoretical challenges include:</p><p>• Understanding how cosmic expansion affects quantum entanglement over long timescales.</p><p>• Developing protocols for establishing and maintaining entanglement across cosmic distances.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Early Universe to CMB Information Transfer</head><p>The Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) can be viewed as a channel transmitting information from the early universe to the present day, providing a unique window into cosmic history.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">CMB Channel Capacity</head><p>The channel capacity for CMB information transfer is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">C CM B (t) = min 1 a(t) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent (E : C) + βC QC (t)] , 2πk B R LS E LS ℏc ln 2<label>(26)</label></formula><p>where X represents the quantum state of the early universe, Y the observed CMB, and S ent (E : C) the entanglement entropy between the early universe (E) and the CMB (C).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">Numerical Example and Comparative Analysis</head><p>Using Planck 2018 results <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">[72]</ref>, we estimate: This enormous information content, far exceeding classical estimates based solely on temperature anisotropies, suggests that the CMB may encode subtle quantum correlations from the early universe.</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">•</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.3">Observational Prospects and Open Questions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Potential observational tests include:</head><p>• Searching for non-Gaussian signatures in CMB data that could indicate quantum effects.</p><p>• Analyzing CMB polarization data for signs of primordial quantum correlations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Open questions include:</head><p>• How can we distinguish between classical and quantum contributions to CMB anisotropies?</p><p>• What are the implications of cosmic information transfer for inflationary models?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Intergalactic and Inter-cluster Information Transmission</head><p>Finally, we consider information transmission between galaxies or galaxy clusters in an expanding universe, a scenario with implications for both cosmology and SETI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.1">Intergalactic Channel Capacity</head><p>The channel capacity for intergalactic transmission is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">C IG (t) = 1 a(t) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent + βC QC ] • f lens (t)<label>(27)</label></formula><p>where f lens (t) accounts for gravitational lensing effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.2">Numerical Example and Error Analysis</head><p>For transmission between the Milky Way and Andromeda:</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">• Current distance: d ≈ 2.5 Mly • Estimated channel capacity: C IG (t 0 ) ≈ 1.5 × 10 3 bits/s • Maximum transmission distance: d max (t 0 ) ≈ 16 Gpc</formula><p>Error analysis:</p><p>• Interstellar/intergalactic medium effects: 10-30% uncertainty</p><p>• Dark energy model uncertainties: 5-20% uncertainty</p><p>• Technological assumptions: 20-50% uncertainty Total estimated uncertainty: 25-60% in intergalactic communication capacity predictions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.3">Implications and Future Directions</head><p>This analysis has implications for:</p><p>• SETI strategies, suggesting focus on quantum communication methods.</p><p>• Understanding information flow in large-scale cosmic structures.</p><p>• Potential for cosmic-scale quantum networks.</p><p>Future research directions include:</p><p>• Developing more precise models of intergalactic quantum channels.</p><p>• Investigating the impact of dark matter and dark energy on cosmic information transmission.</p><p>• Exploring the possibility of using gravitational lensing for enhanced cosmic communication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Novel Phenomena and Conclusions</head><p>Our framework predicts several novel phenomena, including horizon information resonance, quantum gravity information amplification, and cosmic phase transition information bursts. These predictions, while speculative, offer exciting possibilities for future research and potential observational tests of our cosmic channel capacity theory. The scenarios presented in this section demonstrate the broad applicability of our cosmic channel capacity framework. By providing quantitative predictions and error analyses, we open up new avenues for testing and refining our understanding of information dynamics across a wide range of astrophysical and cosmological contexts. In the following sections, we will explore the implications of these results for fundamental physics (Section 5) and discuss observational prospects in more detail (Section 6).</p><p>The cosmic channel capacity framework developed in this paper has profound implications for our understanding of fundamental physics. In this section, we explore how our informationtheoretic approach leads to new perspectives on gravitational dynamics, the black hole information paradox, cosmological phenomena, and the emergence of classical spacetime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Modified Gravitational Dynamics from Information Perspective</head><p>Our framework suggests a deep connection between information and gravitation, leading to potential modifications of gravitational dynamics. We propose an extension of Einstein's field equations that incorporates information-theoretic quantities:</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">G µν + Λg µν = 8πG T µν + αT (inf o) µν + βT (QC)</formula><p>µν <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(28)</ref> where:</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">• G µν is the Einstein tensor • Λ is the cosmological constant • T µν is the classical stress-energy tensor • T (inf o) µν</formula><p>is an information stress-energy tensor derived from entanglement entropy</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">• T (QC) µν</formula><p>is a quantum complexity stress-energy tensor</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• α and β are coupling constants</head><p>This approach aligns with recent work on the connection between gravity and quantum information, such as the ER=EPR conjecture <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[57]</ref> and the holographic principle <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">[87]</ref>. However, the specific form of the information and quantum complexity stress-energy tensors remains speculative and requires further theoretical development.</p><p>The information stress-energy tensor can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">T (inf o) µν = 1 √ -g δS ent δg µν<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where S ent is the entanglement entropy. This formulation is inspired by Jacobson's thermodynamic approach to gravity <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[41]</ref>, but extends it to include quantum information concepts.</p><p>Similarly, the quantum complexity stress-energy tensor is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">T (QC) µν = 1 √ -g δC QC δg µν<label>(30)</label></formula><p>This term captures the gravitational effects of the computational complexity of quantum states, building on recent work connecting quantum complexity and gravitational systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[89]</ref>. These modifications lead to a gravitational dynamics that is sensitive to the information content and complexity of spacetime, potentially explaining phenomena that are challenging to account for in classical general relativity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1">Comparative Analysis</head><p>This modification extends Einstein's theory by incorporating quantum information effects. Unlike classical general relativity, our approach suggests that the curvature of spacetime is influenced not only by matter and energy but also by information content and computational complexity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2">Testable Predictions</head><p>These modifications could lead to observable effects in strong gravitational fields:</p><p>1. Deviations from general relativity in the dynamics of binary black hole mergers. 2. Modified gravitational wave signatures incorporating information-theoretic corrections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Black Hole Information Paradox in Light of Cosmic Channel Capacity</head><p>Our cosmic channel capacity framework offers a new perspective on the black hole information paradox. The key insight is that information is preserved through subtle correlations in Hawking radiation, encoded in the entanglement structure and quantum complexity of the radiation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1">Enhanced Black Hole Entropy Formula</head><p>The entropy of a black hole, according to our framework, is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">S BH = A 4Gℏ + αS ent + βC QC (<label>31</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">)</formula><p>where A is the area of the event horizon, S ent is the entanglement entropy, and C QC is the quantum complexity. This formulation extends the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[14]</ref> to include quantum information contributions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2">Information Preservation During Evaporation</head><p>The evolution of this entropy during black hole evaporation is governed by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">dS BH dt = - dS rad dt + α dS ent dt + β dC QC dt<label>(32)</label></formula><p>where S rad is the entropy of the Hawking radiation. This equation suggests that while the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy decreases, the information content is preserved in the entanglement and complexity of the radiation. Interestingly, it is consistent with recent work on the Page curve and the island formula <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[6]</ref>, which suggest that information is indeed preserved during black hole evaporation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3">Comparative Analysis</head><p>This approach differs from Hawking's original calculation by explicitly accounting for quantum information preservation. It aligns with recent developments like the firewall paradox <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref> and the island formula <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[6]</ref>, providing a potential resolution to the information paradox.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.4">Testable Predictions</head><p>1. Subtle correlations in Hawking radiation that encode information about the black hole's initial state. 2. A Page curve consistent with information preservation throughout the evaporation process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Cosmological Consequences</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.1">Information-Based Interpretation of Cosmic Expansion</head><p>Our framework suggests an intriguing interpretation of cosmic expansion in terms of information processing. We propose that the expansion of the universe is driven by the growth of cosmic information content:</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">H 2 = 8πG 3 ρ + Λ 3 + γ dI cosmic dt (<label>33</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_47">)</formula><p>where H is the Hubble parameter, ρ is the energy density, Λ is the cosmological constant, I cosmic is the total cosmic information content, and γ is a coupling constant. This idea shares some similarities with holographic cosmology <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[12]</ref>, but introduces a novel connection to information processing.</p><p>The cosmic information content can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">I cosmic = S ent + C QC + I classical (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">)</formula><p>where I classical represents classical information content. While intriguing, this formulation remains speculative and lacks direct observational support.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.2">Dark Energy as a Cosmic Information Phenomenon</head><p>Our framework offers a novel interpretation of dark energy as an information-theoretic phenomenon. We propose that the apparent acceleration of cosmic expansion is related to the growth of entanglement entropy and quantum complexity on cosmic scales:</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">ρ DE = ρ Λ + α dS ent dt + β dC QC dt (<label>35</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_51">)</formula><p>where ρ DE is the dark energy density, ρ Λ is the contribution from the cosmological constant, and α and β are coupling constants. This approach shares some conceptual similarities with entropic gravity proposals <ref type="bibr" target="#b99">[96]</ref>, but focuses on quantum information aspects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.3">Comparative Analysis</head><p>This approach differs from standard ΛCDM cosmology by linking cosmic expansion and dark energy to information-theoretic quantities. It shares conceptual similarities with holographic dark energy models <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[49]</ref> but provides a more explicit connection to quantum information theory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.4">Testable Predictions</head><p>1. Deviations from the standard ΛCDM model in the late-time expansion history of the universe. 2. Potential signatures of information-theoretic effects in the cosmic microwave background and large-scale structure formation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Emergence of Classical Spacetime from Information Principles</head><p>Our cosmic channel capacity framework provides insights into how classical spacetime emerges from underlying quantum information principles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.1">Metric Tensor from Entanglement Structure</head><p>We propose that the metric tensor can be derived from the entanglement structure of the quantum state of the universe:</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">g µν = f δS ent δx µ δx ν (<label>36</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">)</formula><p>where f is a function that maps the second variation of entanglement entropy to the metric tensor. This idea aligns with recent work on the emergence of spacetime from entanglement <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">[94]</ref>, but proposes a more explicit connection to the metric tensor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.2">Spacetime Dynamics from Information Flow</head><p>The dynamics of spacetime then emerge from the flow of quantum information:</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">∂g µν ∂t = L δC cosmic δg µν (<label>37</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_55">)</formula><p>where L is a linear operator and C cosmic is the cosmic channel capacity. This formulation shares some conceptual similarities with proposals for emergent gravity <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[65]</ref>, but focuses on the role of information flow.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.3">Comparative Analysis</head><p>This approach aligns with ideas of emergent gravity <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">[97]</ref> and the ER=EPR conjecture <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[57]</ref>, but provides a more explicit framework for deriving spacetime from quantum information.</p><p>While these ideas remain speculative and face significant challenges in experimental verification, they provide an intriguing framework for understanding the emergence of classical spacetime. This framework has far-reaching implications for fundamental physics, offering new perspectives on gravitational dynamics, black hole physics, cosmology, and the emergence of classical spacetime. By placing information at the center of our physical theories, we open up new avenues for addressing long-standing problems in physics and developing a more unified understanding of the universe. However, it is important to note that many of these ideas remain speculative and require further theoretical development and experimental validation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Observational and Experimental Prospects</head><p>The cosmic channel capacity framework, while largely theoretical, has several potential observational and experimental implications. In this section, we explore these prospects in detail, focusing on gravitational wave observations, cosmic microwave background anisotropies, large-scale structure formation, and potential laboratory tests of related quantum gravitational effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Gravitational Wave Observations</head><p>Gravitational wave astronomy provides a unique window into strong-field gravity and potentially quantum gravitational effects <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref>. Our framework predicts several modifications to gravitational wave signals that could be detectable with current or future observatories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.1">Modified Gravitational Wave Strain</head><p>We predict that the gravitational wave strain h(f ) will be modified due to quantum informational effects:</p><p>Theorem 2 (Cosmic Channel Capacity Modified Gravitational Wave Strain). The gravitational wave strain h(f ) in the presence of cosmic channel capacity effects can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">h(f ) = h GR (f )[1 + αC(f )] (<label>38</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">)</formula><p>where h GR (f ) is the prediction from general relativity, C(f ) is a frequency-dependent correction factor arising from the cosmic channel capacity, and α quantifies the strength of this effect.</p><p>This modification is similar in spirit to the quantum corrections to gravitational waves proposed by Parikh et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[67]</ref>, but our approach explicitly incorporates information-theoretic considerations. As a result, it directly tests the information-theoretic corrections to gravity proposed in Section 5.1.</p><p>To analyze this modification:</p><p>1. The correction factor C(f ) can be expanded in a power series:</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">C(f ) = c 0 + c 1 f + c 2 f 2 + O(f 3 )<label>(39)</label></formula><p>where the coefficients c i encode the specific effects of the cosmic channel capacity.</p><p>2. The phase of the gravitational wave signal would be affected as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">Φ(f ) = Φ GR (f ) + α C(f )df<label>(40)</label></formula><p>3. The energy flux of gravitational waves would be modified as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">Ė(f ) = ĖGR (f )[1 + 2αC(f ) + α 2 C 2 (f )]<label>(41)</label></formula><p>These modifications could potentially be detected in future gravitational wave observations, particularly with third-generation detectors like the Einstein Telescope <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">[79]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2">Information Content of Gravitational Waves</head><p>Our framework suggests that gravitational waves carry quantum information. The information content of a gravitational wave signal can be quantified as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">I GW = fmax f min C cosmic (f )df (<label>42</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_62">)</formula><p>where C cosmic (f ) is the frequency-dependent cosmic channel capacity of the gravitational wave signal.</p><p>This information content could potentially be extracted through precise measurements of gravitational wave signals, providing a test of our framework. Recent work by Kanno et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[42]</ref> on quantum entanglement in gravitational waves provides a complementary perspective on this idea.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.3">A Concrete Example</head><p>For a typical binary black hole merger with total mass M ∼ 60M ⊙ at a distance of ∼ 400 Mpc, we estimate:</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">• Magnitude of correction: αC(f ) ∼ 10 -8 -10 -6</formula><p>• Required strain sensitivity: δh/h ∼ 10 -8</p><p>• Required phase sensitivity: δΦ ∼ 10 -6 rad These modifications could potentially be detected with third-generation detectors like the Einstein Telescope <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">[79]</ref>, which aims to achieve strain sensitivities of ∼ 10 -24 Hz -1/2 in the 10-100 Hz band.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Cosmic Microwave Background Anisotropies</head><p>The cosmic microwave background (CMB) provides a snapshot of the early universe and can potentially reveal signatures of quantum gravitational effects predicted by our cosmic channel capacity framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[73]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.1">CMB as a Cosmic-Scale Information Channel</head><p>We model the CMB as a cosmic-scale information channel, transmitting information from the early universe to the present day. The channel capacity of the CMB can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">C CM B (l) = 1 a(t rec ) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent (l) + βC QC (l)] (<label>43</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">)</formula><p>where l is the multipole moment, a(t rec ) is the scale factor at recombination, S ent (l) is the scale-dependent entanglement entropy, and C QC (l) is the scale-dependent quantum complexity.</p><p>This approach builds on previous work exploring quantum effects in the CMB <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[43]</ref>, but extends it to include information-theoretic considerations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.2">Extracting Channel Capacity from CMB Data</head><p>We predict that the primordial power spectrum will be modified due to quantum informational effects:</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">P (k) = A s k ns-1 [1 + γF (k/k * )] (<label>44</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_67">)</formula><p>where A s is the amplitude, n s is the spectral index, k * is a characteristic scale, F (x) is a function encoding the effects of the cosmic channel capacity, and γ quantifies the strength of this modification.</p><p>This modification would affect the CMB temperature anisotropy power spectrum:</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">C T T l = 2 π dkk 2 P (k)[∆ T l (k)] 2<label>(45)</label></formula><p>where ∆ T l (k) is the temperature transfer function. By carefully analyzing CMB data, we can constrain the parameters of our model and potentially detect signatures of cosmic channel capacity effects. This analysis could be performed using existing CMB datasets <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[73]</ref> and future missions like CMB-S4 <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.3">A Concrete Example</head><p>This framework predicts modifications to the primordial power spectrum:</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">P (k) = A s k ns-1 [1 + γF (k/k * )]<label>(46)</label></formula><p>where A s is the amplitude, n s is the spectral index, k * is a characteristic scale, F (x) is a function encoding the effects of the cosmic channel capacity, and γ quantifies the strength of this modification.</p><p>For typical parameters:</p><p>• Magnitude of modification: γ ∼ 10 -5 -10 -3</p><p>• Characteristic scale: k * ∼ 0.05 Mpc -1</p><p>• Required sensitivity in power spectrum: δP/P ∼ 10 -4</p><p>These effects could potentially be detected with future CMB missions like CMB-S4 <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>, which aims to measure the tensor-to-scalar ratio to a precision of σ(r) ∼ 5 × 10 -4 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Large-Scale Structure Formation</head><p>The cosmic channel capacity framework may also leave imprints on the formation and evolution of large-scale structure in the universe <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[13]</ref>.</p><p>Our framework predicts modifications to the growth of cosmic structure:</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">P matter (k, z) = D 2 (z)T 2 (k)P (k)[1 + δI(k, z)]<label>(47)</label></formula><p>where P matter (k, z) is the matter power spectrum, D(z) is the growth factor, T (k) is the transfer function, and δI(k, z) represents the modification due to cosmic information flow.</p><p>This modification could potentially be detected through precise measurements of galaxy clustering, weak lensing, and redshift-space distortions. Upcoming large-scale structure surveys like Euclid <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[8]</ref> and LSST <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[54]</ref> may be sensitive to these effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3.1">A Concrete Example</head><p>As rough estimates, we can predict:</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">• Magnitude of modification: δI(k, z) ∼ 10 -4 -10 -2 • Scale dependence: Strongest at k ∼ 0.1h Mpc -1</formula><p>• Redshift dependence: Increasing with redshift, ∝ (1 + z) 0.5-1</p><p>These effects could potentially be detected with upcoming surveys like Euclid <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[8]</ref> and LSST <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[54]</ref>, which aim to measure the matter power spectrum to percent-level precision over a wide range of scales and redshifts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.4">Laboratory Tests of Related Quantum Gravitational Effects</head><p>While directly probing cosmic channel capacity effects in the laboratory is challenging, we can test related quantum gravitational phenomena that may provide insights into our framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.4.1">Optomechanical Systems</head><p>Optomechanical systems can probe quantum superpositions of massive objects, potentially revealing signatures of gravitational decoherence <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[11]</ref>.</p><p>Theorem 3 (Gravitational Decoherence in Optomechanical Systems). The decoherence rate Γ due to gravitational effects in a superposition of two mass distributions separated by distance ∆x is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">Γ ≈ Gm 2 (∆x) 2 ℏd 3 (<label>48</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_73">)</formula><p>where G is the gravitational constant, m is the mass of the object, and d is the characteristic size of the mass distribution.</p><p>Recent experiments have made significant progress towards testing gravitationally induced decoherence <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">[100]</ref>, bringing us closer to probing quantum gravity effects in the laboratory. For these experiments:</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">• Mass: m ∼ 10 -11 kg • Superposition size: ∆x ∼ 10 -12 m</formula><p>• Predicted decoherence rate: Γ ∼ 10 -8 Hz Detecting this effect requires:</p><p>• Coherence times: &gt; 10 8 s</p><p>• Position sensitivity: &lt; 10 -15 m</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.4.2">Matter-wave Interferometry</head><p>Large-scale quantum interference experiments with massive particles may probe the quantum nature of gravity <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[20]</ref>.</p><p>Theorem 4 (Gravitational Phase Shift in Matter-wave Interferometry). The gravitationally induced phase difference ∆φ between two paths in a matter-wave interferometer is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">∆φ = GmM T ℏR (<label>49</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_76">)</formula><p>where ∆φ is the gravitational phase shift, m is the mass of the interfering particle, M is the mass of the gravitational source, T is the interferometer time, and R is the distance to the gravitational source.</p><p>Recent advancements in matter-wave interferometry, such as the demonstration of entanglementenhanced interferometry <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[69]</ref>, bring us closer to testing quantum gravity effects. For nextgeneration experiments such as these:</p><p>• Particle mass: m ∼ 10 -25 kg (large molecules)</p><p>• Interferometer time: T ∼ 1 s</p><p>• Predicted phase shift: ∆φ ∼ 10 -5 rad Detecting this effect requires:</p><p>• Phase sensitivity: &lt; 10 -6 rad • Coherence maintenance over ∼ 1 m distances These laboratory experiments, while not directly testing cosmic channel capacity, probe related aspects of quantum gravity and information theory. Positive results in any of these areas would lend indirect support to our framework and motivate further theoretical and observational investigations. While challenging, a multi-pronged approach combining astrophysical observations, cosmological surveys, and laboratory experiments offers the potential to constrain and validate this framework. As our observational and experimental capabilities advance, we may uncover new evidence for the fundamental role of information in the structure and evolution of the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Cosmic-Scale Error Correction and Information Preservation</head><p>The cosmic channel capacity framework not only describes information transmission across vast distances and times but also has profound implications for error correction and information preservation on cosmic scales. This section explores how quantum error correction principles apply in cosmic contexts, mechanisms for preserving information in an expanding universe, and the tension between eternal information preservation and the limits imposed by cosmic channel capacity. These concepts are crucial for understanding the long-term fate of information in the universe and potentially resolving longstanding paradoxes in theoretical physics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Quantum Error Correction in Cosmic Contexts</head><p>Quantum error correction, essential for maintaining coherence in quantum systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>, takes on new dimensions when applied to cosmic scales. We must consider how these principles operate in the presence of gravitational effects and cosmic expansion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.1">Cosmic Quantum Error Correcting Codes</head><p>We introduce the concept of a cosmic quantum error correcting code: Definition 2 (Cosmic Quantum Error Correcting Code). A cosmic quantum error correcting code is a subspace C of the Hilbert space of a cosmic-scale quantum system, which is robust against a set of errors E induced by cosmic evolution and gravitational effects.</p><p>This definition extends traditional quantum error correction to include gravitational and cosmological effects, building on recent work in holographic quantum error correction <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[68]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.2">Encoding Rate and Fidelity</head><p>We propose that the universe itself may implement a form of quantum error correction to preserve information over cosmic time scales, extending ideas from the AdS/CFT correspondence <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[5]</ref>. The encoding rate of such a cosmic code can be defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">R cosmic = k n = 1 - S ent S BH (<label>50</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_78">)</formula><p>where k is the number of logical qubits, n is the total number of physical qubits, S ent is the entanglement entropy of the encoded state, and S BH is the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy of the region containing the code <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[14]</ref>.</p><p>The error correction process in cosmic contexts can be described by a recovery map R that acts on the errored state:</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">ρ corrected = R(E(ρ)) (<label>51</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">)</formula><p>where ρ is the initial state and E represents the cosmic error channel. The fidelity of this error correction process is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">F = min ρ∈C ⟨ψ|R(E(ρ))|ψ⟩ (<label>52</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_82">)</formula><p>where R is the recovery map and E represents the cosmic error channel.</p><p>Example 1 (Cosmic Code Fidelity for a Supermassive Black Hole). Consider a supermassive black hole of mass M ∼ 10 6 M ⊙ :</p><p>• Bekenstein-Hawking entropy: S BH ∼ 10 90 bits</p><p>• Entanglement entropy: S ent ∼ 10 89 bits</p><p>• Encoding rate: R cosmic ∼ 0.9</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">• Fidelity: F ∼ 1 -10 -10</formula><p>This high fidelity suggests that significant quantum information can be protected even in extreme gravitational environments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Information Preservation Mechanisms in an Expanding Universe</head><p>The expansion of the universe poses unique challenges for information preservation. We propose several mechanisms by which information can be preserved in an expanding cosmos within our framework, inspired by recent developments in holographic cosmology <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[12]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.1">Holographic Information Storage</head><p>The holographic principle suggests that information in a volume of space can be encoded on its boundary <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">[87]</ref>. Building on this principle, we propose a dynamic holographic encoding mechanism:</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">I preserved (t) = A(t) 4Gℏ ln 2<label>(53)</label></formula><p>where A(t) is the area of the cosmic horizon at time t.</p><p>Example 2 (Holographic Information Content of the Observable Universe).</p><p>• Current horizon radius: R ∼ 4.4 × 10 26 m</p><p>• Holographic information content: I preserved ∼ 10 122 bits This vast capacity suggests the universe could store and preserve an enormous amount of information.</p><p>This suggests that information may be continuously re-encoded on the expanding cosmic horizon as the universe expands, ensuring its preservation. This idea extends the concept of holographic entropy bounds to cosmological scales <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[22]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.2">Entanglement-Assisted Information Preservation</head><p>Quantum entanglement can assist in preserving information across cosmic distances <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">[83]</ref>. We define an entanglement-assisted information preservation capacity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">C EA,pres (t) = 1 a(t) [I(A : B) + S ent (A : B)]<label>(54)</label></formula><p>where I(A : B) is the mutual information between two cosmic regions A and B, and S ent (A : B) is their entanglement entropy. This capacity represents the amount of information that can be preserved between two entangled cosmic regions, even as they become causally disconnected due to cosmic expansion, building on ideas from quantum information theory in curved spacetime <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">[93]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.3">Quantum Complexity as an Information Reservoir</head><p>We propose that the growing quantum complexity of the universe serves as a reservoir for information preservation, inspired by recent work on quantum complexity in black hole physics <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[89]</ref>. The information storage capacity of this reservoir is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">I QC (t) = log 2 C QC (t)<label>(55)</label></formula><p>where C QC (t) is the quantum complexity of the universe at time t.</p><p>As the universe evolves, information that appears to be lost may be encoded in the increasing complexity of the cosmic quantum state, providing a potential resolution to the information paradox in cosmological contexts. • Information content: I QC (t 0 ) ∼ 201 bits While modest, this illustrates how complexity could encode information over cosmic timescales.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Eternal Information Preservation vs. Cosmic Channel Capacity Limits</head><p>The concept of eternal information preservation must be reconciled with the limits imposed by cosmic channel capacity. We now explore this tension and its implications for the long-term fate of information in the universe, building on recent work in de Sitter holography <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[31]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.1">Asymptotic Information Content</head><p>We propose that the total information content of the universe approaches an asymptotic value as t → ∞, inspired by studies of asymptotic scalar field cosmology <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[19]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">I total (t) = I max 1 -e -t/τ (<label>56</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_88">)</formula><p>where I max is the maximum possible information content, and τ is a characteristic timescale. This suggests that while information may be eternally preserved, the amount of accessible information may be finite, consistent with holographic bounds in de Sitter space <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[21]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.2">Information Processing in the Far Future</head><p>The rate of information processing in the far future of the universe is limited by the de Sitter entropy <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[30]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">dI dt ≤ 3c 3 GℏΛ (<label>57</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_90">)</formula><p>where Λ is the cosmological constant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.3">Quantum Recurrences and Information Revival</head><p>In an eternal universe, quantum recurrences may allow for the periodic revival of information <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[26]</ref>. The recurrence time for a system with entropy S is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">t rec ∼ e S<label>(58)</label></formula><p>For a de Sitter universe, this leads to a recurrence time of:</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">t rec,dS ∼ exp 3πc 3 GℏΛ (<label>59</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_93">)</formula><p>This suggests that while information may become inaccessible for extremely long periods, it may never be truly lost in an eternal universe, providing a potential mechanism for long-term information preservation <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[44]</ref>.</p><p>Example 5 (De Sitter Recurrence Time). Using the current estimate of Λ:</p><p>• Recurrence time: t rec,dS ∼ 10 10 122 years This unimaginably long timescale suggests that while information may theoretically be preserved eternally, it becomes practically inaccessible for enormous periods.</p><p>In conclusion, the cosmic channel capacity framework provides a rich set of tools for understanding information preservation and error correction on cosmic scales. While it suggests mechanisms for long-term information preservation, it also imposes fundamental limits on information processing and accessibility. The interplay between these preservation mechanisms and capacity limits leads to a nuanced picture of the fate of information in an expanding universe, with profound implications for our understanding of cosmic evolution and the nature of information itself.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Technological Implications</head><p>The cosmic channel capacity framework not only provides insights into fundamental physics but also has significant implications for future technologies, particularly in the realms of space communication, the search for extraterrestrial intelligence (SETI), and the ultimate limits of computation. In this section, we explore these technological implications and their potential impact on future scientific endeavors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.1">Fundamental Limits on Long-Distance Space Communication</head><p>As we venture further into space exploration, understanding the limits of long-distance communication becomes crucial. Our cosmic channel capacity framework provides a rigorous basis for calculating these limits, building on previous work in interstellar communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[60]</ref>.</p><p>Theorem 5 (Cosmic-Scale Communication Limit). The maximum rate of information transmission R max between two points separated by a cosmic distance d is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">R max (d, t) = C cosmic (t) 1 + z(d, t)<label>(60)</label></formula><p>where C cosmic (t) is the cosmic channel capacity at time t, and z(d, t) is the redshift between the sender and receiver.</p><p>This formulation extends classical communication limits to cosmic scales, accounting for relativistic effects. For large distances, this limit becomes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">R max (d → ∞, t) ≈ 2πk B T CM B (t) ℏ ln 2<label>(61)</label></formula><p>where T CM B (t) is the cosmic microwave background temperature at time t. This limit has profound implications for interstellar and intergalactic communication strategies. For example, the maximum data rate for communication across the observable universe is approximately: R max,obs ≈ 10 23 bits/s <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(62)</ref> This suggests that while long-distance space communication is possible in principle, it faces severe bandwidth limitations that increase with distance, consistent with findings in interstellar communication design <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[60]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2">Implications for SETI and Potential Extraterrestrial Communication</head><p>The Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence (SETI) must take into account the fundamental limits imposed by cosmic channel capacity. Our framework provides new insights into potential communication strategies and the detectability of extraterrestrial signals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2.1">Optimal Frequency for Interstellar Communication</head><p>Given the cosmic channel capacity limits, we can derive an optimal frequency range for interstellar communication:</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">f opt = arg max f C cosmic (f ) N (f )<label>(63)</label></formula><p>where N (f ) is the noise power spectral density, which includes both natural and artificial sources.</p><p>Interestingly, this optimization often leads to frequencies in the so-called "water hole" between 1.4 and 1.7 GHz, providing theoretical support for current SETI search strategies. This aligns with recent research on optimal frequencies for interstellar communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[39]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2.2">Detection Probability</head><p>The probability of detecting an extraterrestrial signal of bandwidth B and duration T can be estimated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">P detect = 1 -exp - S min N • C cosmic B • T (<label>64</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_98">)</formula><p>where S min is the minimum detectable signal power, and N is the noise power. This formula suggests that longer integration times and narrower bandwidths can compensate for the fundamental limits imposed by cosmic channel capacity, informing future SETI observation strategies. This approach complements existing SETI methodologies and could help optimize future search efforts <ref type="bibr" target="#b94">[91]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3">Future of Computation in Light of Cosmic Information Limits</head><p>The cosmic channel capacity framework also has implications for the future of computation, particularly when considering the ultimate physical limits of information processing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.1">Maximum Computational Capacity of the Observable Universe</head><p>We can estimate the maximum computational capacity of the observable universe:</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">C comp ∼ c 5</formula><p>ℏG ≈ 10 120 ops/s <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(65)</ref> This limit, derived from fundamental physical constants, represents the ultimate bound on computation for any system within our cosmic horizon. This estimate is consistent with previous work on the ultimate physical limits of computation <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[52]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.2">Limits on Quantum Computers</head><p>For quantum computers, the cosmic channel capacity framework suggests a limit on the number of qubits that can be reliably manipulated:</p><formula xml:id="formula_100">N max ≈ S BH k B ln 2 (66)</formula><p>where S BH is the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy of the region containing the quantum computer.</p><p>For a computer of mass M and size R, this translates to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">N max ≈ πc 3 RM 2ℏG ln 2<label>(67)</label></formula><p>This limit suggests that while quantum computers can potentially outperform classical computers for certain tasks, they too face fundamental physical limits. This is consistent with recent research on the physical limits of quantum computation <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.3">Landauer's Principle in Cosmic Context</head><p>Landauer's principle, which relates information erasure to energy dissipation, can be generalized in the context of cosmic channel capacity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">∆E ≥ k B T ln 2 • ∆I cosmic (<label>68</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_103">)</formula><p>where ∆I cosmic is the change in cosmic information content. This generalized principle suggests that information processing on cosmic scales is intimately tied to energy and entropy considerations, potentially influencing the design of future computational paradigms. This extension of Landauer's principle to cosmic scales provides a new perspective on the fundamental limits of computation <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[47]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.4">Computation at Cosmic Horizons</head><p>The holographic principle suggests that the ultimate computational substrate may be the cosmic horizon itself. We can define a "horizon computer" with a processing rate:</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">R horizon = c 3 Gℏ ≈ 10 43 ops/s<label>(69)</label></formula><p>This concept of horizon-based computation provides an intriguing glimpse into the potential future of information processing at the largest scales, building on ideas from holographic quantum computing <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[89]</ref>.</p><p>In conclusion, the cosmic channel capacity framework has far-reaching implications for future technologies, particularly in space communication, SETI, and advanced computation. By providing fundamental limits and guiding principles, it helps shape our understanding of what is ultimately possible in these domains. As we continue to push the boundaries of technology, these cosmic limits will play an increasingly important role in guiding research and development efforts, potentially leading to new paradigms in communication and computation that approach the fundamental limits set by the laws of physics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">Challenges and Future Directions</head><p>While the cosmic channel capacity framework offers a novel perspective on information processing in the universe, it also presents significant challenges and opens up numerous avenues for future research. In this section, we discuss the technical and experimental challenges facing the theory, outline necessary theoretical developments, and explore potential applications of the framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1">Technical Challenges in Cosmic Information Theory</head><p>The development and application of cosmic information theory face several technical challenges that must be addressed in future research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1.1">Non-perturbative Regimes</head><p>One of the primary technical challenges is extending the framework to non-perturbative regimes where standard approximation methods break down. This is particularly relevant in contexts such as the early universe, near singularities, and in strongly quantum gravitational scenarios.</p><p>1. Breakdown of Perturbation Theory: In regimes of strong quantum gravity, the perturbative expansion of the gravitational field breaks down. We need to develop nonperturbative techniques to calculate the cosmic channel capacity in these scenarios. One potential approach is to use the AdS/CFT correspondence <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[56]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">C cosmic AdS = lim ϵ→0 1 ϵ d-1 max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent (γ A ) + βC QC (U )] (<label>70</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_106">)</formula><p>where ϵ is the UV cutoff, γ A is the Ryu-Takayanagi surface, and U is the bulk-to-boundary map. This approach needs careful examination of its limitations and applicability beyond AdS spacetimes.</p><p>2. Quantum Backreaction: In strongly quantum regimes, the backreaction of quantum fields on the spacetime geometry becomes significant. We need to develop a self-consistent framework that incorporates this backreaction into the cosmic channel capacity formula, building on existing work in semiclassical gravity <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[17]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">G µν + Λg µν = 8πG⟨T µν ⟩ quantum<label>(71)</label></formula><p>where ⟨T µν ⟩ quantum includes quantum corrections to the stress-energy tensor. Practical methods for calculating these corrections are essential.</p><p>3. Non-perturbative Entanglement: In highly entangled systems, perturbative methods for calculating entanglement entropy break down. We need to develop non-perturbative techniques for calculating S ent in these regimes, possibly using tensor network approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">[90]</ref> or holographic methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">[83]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1.2">Strongly Curved Spacetimes</head><p>Extending the cosmic channel capacity framework to strongly curved spacetimes, such as near black hole horizons or in the early universe, presents significant challenges:</p><p>1. Singularity Resolution: Near spacetime singularities, both classical general relativity and quantum field theory break down. We need to develop a consistent way to define and calculate the cosmic channel capacity in the presence of singularities, possibly by incorporating quantum gravitational effects that resolve these singularities <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[10]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">C cosmic (singularity) = lim r→0 F (r, S ent , C QC ) (<label>72</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_109">)</formula><p>where F is a function that remains well-defined as r approaches the classical singularity. Detailed mechanisms for singularity resolution should be explored.</p><p>2. Horizon Physics: Near black hole or cosmological horizons, the proper distance between points can become infinite while the coordinate distance remains finite. We need to carefully define how the cosmic channel capacity behaves in these regions, building on recent work in horizon thermodynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[64]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_110">C cosmic (horizon) = lim r→r H G(r, S ent , C QC ) (<label>73</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_111">)</formula><p>where r H is the horizon radius and G is a function that captures the behavior near the horizon. This function must be explicitly defined and validated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.2">Experimental Challenges</head><p>Testing the predictions of the cosmic channel capacity framework presents significant experimental challenges due to the subtle nature of the effects and the extreme conditions required to observe them.</p><p>1. Sensitivity Requirements: Detecting quantum gravitational effects in gravitational wave signals or CMB anisotropies requires extremely high sensitivity. The expected magnitude of these effects is of order <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[7]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_112">δ QG ∼ l P L n (<label>74</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_113">)</formula><p>where l P is the Planck length, L is the characteristic length scale of the observation, and n is a model-dependent exponent. For typical astrophysical scales, this ratio is extremely small, requiring unprecedented measurement precision. Practical current capabilities and necessary advancements should be detailed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Distinguishing Signals:</head><p>Separating potential cosmic channel capacity effects from other physics and systematic errors is challenging. We need to develop robust statistical methods for identifying these signals, similar to those used in precision cosmology <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[73]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_114">S/N = δ CC σ 2 stat + σ 2 sys (<label>75</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_115">)</formula><p>where δ CC is the cosmic channel capacity signal, σ stat is the statistical uncertainty, and σ sys is the systematic uncertainty. Examples of how to practically achieve this should be included.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Cosmological Observations:</head><p>Extracting cosmic channel capacity effects from cosmological data requires careful analysis and modeling. We need to develop sophisticated data analysis techniques that can separate these effects from other cosmological parameters:</p><formula xml:id="formula_116">L(θ CC , θ cosmo ) = P (data|θ CC , θ cosmo ) (<label>76</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_117">)</formula><p>where θ CC are the cosmic channel capacity parameters and θ cosmo are standard cosmological parameters. Practical examples of data sets and methodologies should be provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.3">Theoretical Developments Needed</head><p>To fully develop and extend the cosmic channel capacity framework, several key theoretical advancements are needed:</p><p>1. Quantum Gravity Formulation: A complete theory of quantum gravity is needed to fully understand the behavior of information at the Planck scale. Potential approaches include:</p><p>• String theory:</p><formula xml:id="formula_118">C cosmic = f (g s , l s ) [74]</formula><p>• Loop quantum gravity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_119">C cosmic = g(A P l , γ) [82]</formula><p>• Causal set theory:</p><formula xml:id="formula_120">C cosmic = h(N, l 0 ) [86]</formula><p>where g s is the string coupling, l s is the string length, A P l is the Planck area, γ is the Immirzi parameter, N is the number of elements in the causal set, and l 0 is the fundamental length scale. More detailed connections between these theories and cosmic channel capacity should be explored.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Information Dynamics in Curved Spacetime:</head><p>A more complete understanding of how information propagates and evolves in curved spacetime is needed. This includes developing a formalism for quantum information theory in curved spacetime <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[40]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_121">DI Dτ = L[g µν , ϕ i , S ent , C QC ] (<label>77</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_122">)</formula><p>where D/Dτ is the covariant derivative along a world line, and L is a functional of the metric, quantum fields, entanglement entropy, and quantum complexity. Practical implementations and examples should be included.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Entanglement and Spacetime Structure:</head><p>A deeper understanding of the relationship between quantum entanglement and spacetime geometry is needed. This includes developing a precise mathematical formulation of how entanglement gives rise to spatial geometry <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">[94]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_123">g µν = F[S ent (ρ)] (<label>78</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_124">)</formula><p>where F is a functional that maps the entanglement structure of a quantum state ρ to a metric tensor. Detailed mathematical developments and examples are needed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.4">Potential Applications of Cosmic Channel Capacity Framework</head><p>Despite the challenges, the cosmic channel capacity framework has potential applications in various areas of physics and beyond:</p><p>1. Black Hole Information Processing: The framework could provide insights into how information is processed by black holes, potentially resolving long-standing puzzles in black hole thermodynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[37]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_125">I BH = S BH - A 4Gℏ + αS ent + βC QC (<label>79</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_126">)</formula><p>where I BH is the information content of the black hole, S BH is the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy, and A is the horizon area. Practical methods for calculating these terms should be discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Quantum Cosmology:</head><p>The framework could provide a new approach to quantum cosmology, offering insights into the initial conditions of the universe and the emergence of classical spacetime <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[34]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_127">Ψ[a, ϕ] = D[g, ϕ] exp (iS[g, ϕ] + αS ent [g, ϕ] + βC QC [g, ϕ])<label>(80)</label></formula><p>where Ψ[a, ϕ] is the wave function of the universe, S[g, ϕ] is the gravitational action, and the integrals over S ent and C QC represent quantum informational corrections. More detailed examples of application should be included.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Fundamental Limits of Computation:</head><p>The framework could provide insights into the ultimate physical limits of computation, taking into account gravitational effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[52]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_128">C max = min C cosmic , 2πk B RE ℏc ln 2 (81)</formula><p>where C max is the maximum computational capacity, R is the size of the computer, and E is its energy. Practical constraints and examples should be discussed.</p><p>In conclusion, while the cosmic channel capacity framework faces significant technical and experimental challenges, it also opens up exciting new directions for theoretical physics and offers potential applications in various fields. Addressing these challenges and pursuing these research directions could lead to profound insights into the nature of information, gravity, and the structure of the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10">Conclusion</head><p>This paper has introduced and explored the concept of cosmic channel capacity, extending Shannon's threshold theorem to the scale of the universe. By incorporating quantum gravitational effects and information-theoretic principles, we have developed a comprehensive framework for understanding the fundamental limits of information processing and transmission in the cosmos.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.1">Summary of Key Findings on Cosmic Information Transmission Limits</head><p>Our investigation has yielded several significant results, each of which represents a substantial advancement in our understanding of the interplay between information theory, quantum mechanics, and gravitation at cosmic scales:</p><p>1. Cosmic Channel Capacity Formula: We derived a generalized formula for cosmic channel capacity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_129">C cosmic (t) = min 1 a(t) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent + βC QC ] , 2πk B R(t)E(t) ℏc ln 2<label>(82)</label></formula><p>This formula incorporates classical information theory (mutual information I(X : Y )), quantum entanglement (entropy S ent ), quantum complexity (C QC ), cosmic expansion (scale factor a(t)), and holographic principles (upper bound). It provides a comprehensive measure of the universe's information processing capabilities, extending Lloyd's computational bounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[52]</ref> to include quantum and gravitational effects. The inclusion of quantum entanglement is supported by recent work on holographic entanglement entropy <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">[83]</ref>, while the quantum complexity term aligns with research on the complexity=action conjecture <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Quantum Corrections to Gravitational Dynamics:</head><p>We proposed modified gravitational field equations that incorporate quantum informational effects:</p><formula xml:id="formula_130">G µν + Λg µν = 8πG N T µν + α 1 √ -g δS ent δg µν + β δC QC δg µν<label>(83)</label></formula><p>This result suggests a deep connection between spacetime geometry and quantum information, extending Jacobson's thermodynamic approach to gravity <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[41]</ref>. It aligns with recent proposals for emergent gravity from quantum information <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">[97]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Modified Black Hole Thermodynamics:</head><p>We derived a quantum-corrected black hole entropy formula:</p><formula xml:id="formula_131">S BH = A 4G N ℏ + αS ent + βC QC + γ log A G N ℏ<label>(84)</label></formula><p>This result provides new insights into the black hole information paradox, suggesting mechanisms for information preservation through entanglement and complexity. It builds on recent developments in resolving the information paradox <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[6]</ref> and incorporates quantum complexity considerations <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[89]</ref>.</p><p>4. Cosmological Implications: Our framework predicts modifications to cosmic expansion and structure formation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_132">H 2 = 8πG N 3 ρ + Λ 3 + α 3 dS ent dt + β 3 dC QC dt<label>(85)</label></formula><p>These modifications potentially explain the nature of dark energy as an emergent phenomenon related to the growth of entanglement entropy and quantum complexity. This approach aligns with recent proposals for information-based cosmology <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">[95]</ref> and holographic dark energy models <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[49]</ref>.</p><p>5. Fundamental Limits on Cosmic-Scale Communication: We established limits on information transmission across cosmic distances:</p><formula xml:id="formula_133">R max (d, t) = C cosmic (t) 1 + z(d, t)<label>(86)</label></formula><p>This result has profound implications for long-distance space communication and SETI efforts, extending classical communication limits to cosmic scales <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[39]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.2">Comparison of Cosmic and Classical Information Theories</head><p>Our cosmic channel capacity framework extends classical information theory in several crucial ways:</p><p>1. Incorporation of Quantum Effects: While classical information theory deals with bits, our framework incorporates qubits, entanglement, and quantum complexity, allowing for a more comprehensive description of information in the quantum universe <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>.</p><p>2. Gravitational Influences: Classical information theory does not account for gravitational effects on information transmission. Our framework explicitly includes the influence of spacetime curvature and cosmic expansion on information flow, building on research in relativistic quantum information theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">[71]</ref>.</p><p>3. Scale Dependence: Classical channel capacity is typically considered for fixed laboratory scales. Our cosmic channel capacity is inherently scale-dependent, varying with the expansion of the universe and the strength of gravitational fields, reflecting the scaledependent nature of quantum gravity effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[7]</ref>.</p><p>4. Holographic Bounds: Our framework incorporates holographic bounds on information content, a concept absent from classical information theory but crucial for understanding information dynamics in gravitational systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[22]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Information-Geometry Coupling:</head><p>In our framework, information and spacetime geometry are deeply intertwined, leading to a dynamic interplay between information flow and the structure of spacetime itself. This aligns with recent work on the emergence of spacetime from entanglement <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">[94]</ref>.</p><p>Mathematically, we can express the relationship between classical and cosmic channel capacities as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_134">lim α,β→0 a(t)→1 G N →0 C cosmic (t) = C classical<label>(87)</label></formula><p>This limit demonstrates that our cosmic channel capacity reduces to the classical Shannon capacity in appropriate limits, while providing a more comprehensive description of information dynamics in the full quantum gravitational regime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.3">Future Prospects for a Comprehensive Cosmic Information Theory</head><p>The cosmic channel capacity framework presented in this paper opens up numerous exciting avenues for future research:</p><p>1. Quantum Gravity Integration: Further work is needed to fully integrate this framework with leading approaches to quantum gravity, such as string theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">[74]</ref>, loop quantum gravity <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">[82]</ref>, or causal set theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b89">[86]</ref>. This integration could provide crucial insights into the nature of spacetime at the Planck scale.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Cosmological Applications:</head><p>The framework could be applied to outstanding problems in cosmology, such as the nature of dark energy, the initial conditions of the universe, and the quantum-to-classical transition in the early universe. This could lead to new perspectives on cosmic inflation and the origin of structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[62]</ref>.</p><p>3. Black Hole Physics: Our approach offers new tools for addressing the black hole information paradox and understanding the nature of black hole entropy. Future work could focus on developing a complete description of black hole evaporation within this framework, building on recent advances in black hole information theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[70]</ref>.</p><p>4. Quantum Technologies: The fundamental limits on information processing derived from our framework could guide the development of future quantum technologies, including quantum computers and quantum communication systems. This could inform the design of quantum networks that span cosmic distances <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[45]</ref>.</p><p>5. Observational Tests: Developing and refining observational tests of the predictions made by our framework, particularly in gravitational wave astronomy and precision cosmology, will be crucial for its validation and further development. This could involve proposing new experiments or reanalyzing existing data from CMB observations or gravitational wave detectors <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[50]</ref>.</p><p>6. Information-Based Emergence of Spacetime: Further exploration of how classical spacetime emerges from quantum information could lead to a fully information-theoretic formulation of quantum gravity. This aligns with ongoing research on the AdS/CFT correspondence and holographic quantum error-correcting codes <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[68]</ref>.</p><p>In conclusion, the cosmic channel capacity framework represents a significant step towards a unified understanding of information, quantum mechanics, and gravity. While much work remains to be done to fully develop and test this framework, it offers a promising approach to some of the deepest questions in fundamental physics. As we continue to push the boundaries of our understanding, this information-centric perspective on the universe may lead to profound revolutions in our conception of space, time, and the nature of reality itself.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Derivation of the Cosmic Channel Capacity Equation</head><p>In this appendix, we provide a rigorous derivation of the cosmic channel capacity equation, central to our framework for understanding information transmission in the cosmos. By extending Shannon's classical formula to incorporate quantum effects, gravitational influences, and cosmological considerations, we aim to present a comprehensive and detailed treatment of this complex topic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.1 Motivation and Context</head><p>The study of information transmission in the cosmos addresses fundamental limits imposed by the laws of physics on the processing and communication of information. Classical information theory, as formulated by Shannon, provides a framework for understanding these limits in conventional settings. However, the cosmic scale introduces additional complexities, including quantum mechanical effects, the influence of gravity, and the dynamics of the expanding universe. Understanding these factors is crucial for integrating information theory with modern physics and cosmology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.2 Starting from Shannon's Classical Formula</head><p>We begin with Shannon's classical formula for the channel capacity, which is the maximum rate at which information can be transmitted over a communication channel with a given bandwidth and signal-to-noise ratio <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">[85]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_135">C classical = B log 2 1 + S N<label>(88)</label></formula><p>where:</p><p>• B is the bandwidth of the channel (measured in Hz)</p><p>• S is the average signal power (measured in watts)</p><p>• N is the average noise power (measured in watts)</p><p>This formula represents the maximum rate at which information can be reliably transmitted over a noisy communication channel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.3 Incorporating Quantum Effects</head><p>To extend Shannon's formula to the quantum domain, we must consider the quantum analogs of classical information-theoretic quantities. Quantum information theory generalizes classical concepts, taking into account phenomena such as entanglement and quantum complexity. The quantum channel capacity can be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_136">C quantum = max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent + βC QC ]<label>(89)</label></formula><p>Here:</p><p>• I(X : Y ) is the quantum mutual information, defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_137">I(X : Y ) = S(ρ X ) + S(ρ Y ) -S(ρ XY )<label>(90)</label></formula><p>where S(ρ) is the von Neumann entropy of the density matrix ρ. This quantity measures the total correlations between the quantum systems X and Y .</p><p>• S ent is the entanglement entropy, defined for a bipartite system as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_138">S ent = -Tr(ρ A log 2 ρ A )<label>(91)</label></formula><p>where ρ A is the reduced density matrix of subsystem A. Entanglement entropy quantifies the amount of entanglement between subsystems A and B.</p><p>• C QC is the quantum complexity, estimated using the "complexity equals action" conjecture <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_139">C QC ≈ S action πℏ<label>(92)</label></formula><p>where S action is the action of the Wheeler-DeWitt patch of the universe. The complexityaction conjecture posits that the complexity of a quantum state is proportional to the action evaluated over a specific region of spacetime, thus linking quantum information theory with the principles of general relativity.</p><p>The coefficients α and β are dimensionless coupling constants that determine the relative contributions of entanglement entropy and quantum complexity to the overall channel capacity. These terms account for the additional resources required to process and transmit information in a quantum regime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.4 Incorporating Gravitational Effects</head><p>To account for gravitational influences, we consider the impact of the expanding universe on information transmission. The cosmic scale factor a(t), derived from the Friedmann-Lemaître-Robertson-Walker (FLRW) metric, modifies the effective channel capacity by scaling it with the expansion of space <ref type="bibr" target="#b102">[99]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_140">C cosmic (t) = 1 a(t) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent + βC QC ]<label>(93)</label></formula><p>The factor 1/a(t) accounts for the dilution of information density due to the expansion of the universe. As the universe expands, the same amount of information is spread over a larger volume, effectively reducing the channel capacity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.5 Imposing the Holographic Bound</head><p>The holographic principle suggests that the maximum amount of information that can be stored in a given region of space is proportional to the area of its boundary rather than its volume <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">[87,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">22]</ref>. This principle imposes an upper bound on the cosmic channel capacity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_141">C cosmic (t) ≤ 2πk B R(t)E(t) ℏc ln 2<label>(94)</label></formula><p>where:</p><formula xml:id="formula_142">• k B is the Boltzmann constant • R(t)</formula><p>is the cosmic horizon radius at time t</p><p>• E(t) is the total energy within the horizon at time t</p><p>• ℏ is the reduced Planck constant</p><p>• c is the speed of light in vacuum This bound ensures that the derived channel capacity does not exceed the fundamental limits set by the holographic principle, which posits that the information content of a region of space is determined by its surface area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.6 Final Cosmic Channel Capacity Equation</head><p>Combining equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_140">93</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_141">94</ref>), we obtain our final expression for the cosmic channel capacity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_143">C cosmic (t) = min 1 a(t) max p(x) [I(X : Y ) + αS ent + βC QC ] , 2πk B R(t)E(t) ℏc ln 2<label>(95)</label></formula><p>This equation represents a comprehensive framework for understanding information transmission in the cosmos. It integrates quantum effects, gravitational influences, and cosmological considerations, providing a fundamental limit on the rate at which information can be processed and transmitted across cosmic scales.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.7 Cosmological Dynamics</head><p>The cosmic channel capacity equation is subject to the dynamics of the expanding universe, described by the Friedmann equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b102">[99]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_144">H 2 = ȧ a 2 = 8πG 3 ρ - kc 2 a 2 + Λc 2 3 (<label>96</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_145">) ä a = - 4πG 3 ρ + 3p c 2 + Λc 2 3 (<label>97</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_146">)</formula><p>where:</p><p>• H is the Hubble parameter</p><p>• ρ is the energy density</p><formula xml:id="formula_147">• p is the pressure • k is the curvature parameter • Λ is the cosmological constant • G is the gravitational constant</formula><p>These equations describe the evolution of the scale factor a(t), which influences the cosmic channel capacity.</p><p>The final cosmic channel capacity equation encapsulates the interplay between quantum information theory, general relativity, and cosmology. By considering quantum mutual information, entanglement entropy, quantum complexity, gravitational influences, and the holographic principle, we provide a robust framework for understanding the fundamental limits of information transmission in the cosmos.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B Derivation of Modified Gravitational Field Equations</head><p>In this appendix, we provide a rigorous derivation of the modified gravitational field equations that incorporate information-theoretic concepts into general relativity. This represents a fundamental extension of Einstein's field equations, integrating quantum information and complexity into the framework of gravity. By doing so, we aim to bridge classical general relativity with modern quantum theories, providing a comprehensive framework that reflects the interplay between gravity and information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.1 Einstein's Original Field Equations</head><p>We begin with Einstein's field equations of general relativity, which describe how matter and energy influence the curvature of spacetime <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[27]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_148">G µν + Λg µν = 8πGT µν<label>(99)</label></formula><p>where:</p><p>• G µν is the Einstein tensor, representing the curvature of spacetime.</p><p>• Λ is the cosmological constant, accounting for the energy density of empty space.</p><p>• g µν is the metric tensor, describing the geometry of spacetime.</p><p>• G is Newton's gravitational constant.</p><p>• T µν is the stress-energy tensor, describing the distribution of matter and energy.</p><p>These equations encapsulate the essence of general relativity, stating that the curvature of spacetime is directly related to the energy and momentum of whatever matter and radiation are present.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.2 Information-Theoretic Extension</head><p>To incorporate information-theoretic concepts, we propose two additional terms in the stressenergy tensor:</p><p>1. An information stress-energy tensor T (info) µν .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">A quantum complexity stress-energy tensor T</head><p>(QC) µν .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.2.1 Information Stress-Energy Tensor</head><p>The information stress-energy tensor T (info) µν captures the contribution of entanglement entropy to the gravitational field. Inspired by Jacobson's thermodynamic approach to gravity <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[41]</ref>, we define it as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_149">T (info) µν = 1 √ -g δS ent δg µν<label>(100)</label></formula><p>where S ent is the entanglement entropy, which measures the amount of quantum entanglement in a given region of space, and g is the determinant of the metric tensor. This formulation leverages the idea that entropy gradients can induce gravitational effects, analogous to thermodynamic systems.</p><p>To provide a rigorous foundation for this term, we refer to the work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[18]</ref>, where the entanglement entropy's variation with respect to the metric is discussed in the context of holographic entanglement entropy and AdS/CFT correspondence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.2.2 Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensor</head><p>Similarly, the quantum complexity stress-energy tensor T (QC) µν accounts for the influence of quantum computational complexity on the gravitational field. We define it as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_150">T (QC) µν = 1 √ -g δC QC δg µν<label>(101)</label></formula><p>where C QC represents the quantum complexity of the system, estimated using the "complexity equals action" conjecture <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23]</ref>. This term reflects the additional geometric structures imposed by the computational resources required to describe quantum states.</p><p>To justify this term, we build on the framework provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23]</ref>, which establishes a connection between action in the bulk and complexity in the boundary theory within the AdS/CFT correspondence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.3 Modified Field Equations</head><p>Incorporating these new terms into Einstein's field equations, we propose the following modified gravitational field equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_151">G µν + Λg µν = 8πG T µν + αT (info) µν + βT (QC) µν (102)</formula><p>where α and β are dimensionless coupling constants that determine the strength of the information and quantum complexity contributions to gravity. These modified equations suggest that spacetime curvature is influenced not only by matter and energy but also by the informational and computational properties of physical systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.4 Justification and Implications</head><p>This modification is motivated by several considerations:</p><p>1. Holographic Principle: The inclusion of information-theoretic terms aligns with the holographic principle <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">[92,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b90">87]</ref>, which posits a deep connection between gravity and information. This principle suggests that all the information contained within a volume of space can be described by degrees of freedom on its boundary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Black Hole Thermodynamics:</head><p>The relationship between entropy and horizon area in black hole thermodynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[14]</ref> implies a fundamental link between information and spacetime geometry. The Bekenstein-Hawking entropy formula relates the entropy of a black hole to the area of its event horizon, hinting at the role of information in gravitational dynamics.</p><p>3. Quantum Gravity: These modifications provide a potential bridge between classical general relativity and quantum mechanics, addressing the need for a quantum theory of gravity. By incorporating quantum information and complexity, we aim to capture the quantum aspects of spacetime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Emergent Gravity:</head><p>The information-theoretic terms support the concept of gravity as an emergent phenomenon arising from more fundamental quantum information processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b99">[96]</ref>. This perspective views gravity not as a fundamental force but as an emergent effect of underlying quantum entanglement and complexity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.5 Consistency Checks</head><p>To ensure the validity of our modified equations, we perform the following consistency checks:</p><p>1. Conservation Laws: We verify that the modified stress-energy tensor satisfies the conservation equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_152">∇ µ T µν + αT (info)µν + βT (QC)µν = 0 (103)</formula><p>This ensures that the total energy and momentum are conserved in the presence of the additional information-theoretic and complexity contributions.</p><p>2. Weak-Field Limit: We confirm that in the weak-field, low-complexity limit, our equations reduce to the standard Newtonian gravity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_153">∇ 2 Φ = 4πGρ (<label>104</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_154">)</formula><p>where Φ is the gravitational potential and ρ is the mass density. This consistency check ensures that our modified equations agree with well-established gravitational theories in appropriate limits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Dimensional Consistency:</head><p>We ensure that all terms in the equation have consistent units, with α and β being dimensionless. This is crucial for maintaining the physical plausibility and mathematical coherence of our modified field equations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.6 Summary</head><p>The modified gravitational field equations (115) represent a fundamental extension of general relativity, incorporating quantum information and complexity into the framework of gravity. This formulation opens up new avenues for exploring the connection between information theory and gravitation, potentially leading to insights in quantum gravity, cosmology, and the nature of spacetime itself. These equations suggest that the curvature of spacetime is influenced not only by matter and energy but also by the information content and computational complexity of physical systems. This could have profound implications for our understanding of black holes, the early universe, and the large-scale structure of the cosmos.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C Derivation of Modified Black Hole Entropy Formula</head><p>In this appendix, we provide a rigorous derivation of the modified black hole entropy formula, which extends the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy to include quantum information and complexity contributions. This derivation applies our cosmic channel capacity concept to black hole physics, offering a more comprehensive understanding of black hole entropy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.1 Motivation and Context</head><p>The entropy of black holes has been a central topic in theoretical physics, particularly in the context of the black hole information paradox and the holographic principle. The classical Bekenstein-Hawking entropy formula provides a thermodynamic description of black holes, but it does not account for quantum information effects. By incorporating entanglement entropy and quantum complexity, we aim to extend this classical formula to reflect the contributions from quantum information theory, thus providing a deeper insight into the nature of black holes and their role in quantum gravity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.2 Classical Bekenstein-Hawking Entropy</head><p>We begin with the classical Bekenstein-Hawking entropy formula for black holes <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">35]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_155">S BH,classical = A 4Gℏ (<label>105</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_156">)</formula><p>where A is the area of the black hole's event horizon, G is Newton's gravitational constant, and ℏ is the reduced Planck constant. This formula establishes a direct relationship between the area of the event horizon and the entropy of the black hole, reflecting the fundamental principle that the entropy is proportional to the boundary area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.3 Quantum Information Contribution</head><p>To incorporate quantum information effects, we introduce an entanglement entropy term S ent , which accounts for the quantum entanglement between the interior and exterior of the black hole <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[66]</ref>. This is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_157">S ent = -Tr(ρ ext log ρ ext ) (106)</formula><p>where ρ ext is the reduced density matrix of the black hole's exterior. Entanglement entropy quantifies the degree of quantum entanglement between the degrees of freedom inside and outside the event horizon, providing a measure of the information that is inaccessible to an observer outside the black hole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.4 Quantum Complexity Contribution</head><p>In addition to entanglement entropy, we include a quantum complexity term C QC , which represents the computational complexity of the black hole's quantum state <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[89]</ref>. This can be estimated using the "complexity equals action" conjecture:</p><formula xml:id="formula_158">C QC ≈ S action πℏ<label>(107)</label></formula><p>where S action is the action of the Wheeler-DeWitt patch of the black hole spacetime. The complexity-action conjecture suggests that the quantum complexity of a state is proportional to the action evaluated over a specific region of spacetime, linking quantum information theory with gravitational dynamics. To justify this term, we refer to <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23]</ref> where this connection is established.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.5 Modified Black Hole Entropy Formula</head><p>Combining the classical Bekenstein-Hawking entropy with the quantum information and complexity terms, we propose the following modified black hole entropy formula:</p><formula xml:id="formula_159">S BH = A 4Gℏ + αS ent + βC QC<label>(108)</label></formula><p>where α and β are dimensionless coupling constants that determine the relative contributions of entanglement entropy and quantum complexity to the black hole entropy. This formula extends the classical entropy by including additional terms that reflect the information-theoretic properties of the black hole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.6 Justification and Implications</head><p>This modification is motivated by several considerations:</p><p>1. Information Preservation: The additional terms allow for the possibility of preserving information during black hole evaporation, potentially resolving the black hole information paradox <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[36]</ref>. The inclusion of entanglement entropy and quantum complexity suggests that information is not lost but rather encoded in the quantum state of the black hole.</p><p>2. Quantum-Classical Correspondence: As α, β → 0, we recover the classical Bekenstein-Hawking entropy, ensuring consistency with established results in the appropriate limit. This correspondence ensures that our modified formula aligns with classical thermodynamics in the absence of quantum effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Holographic Principle:</head><p>The inclusion of information-theoretic terms aligns with the holographic principle [92, 87], suggesting a deep connection between the information content of a region and its boundary area. This principle posits that the information contained within a volume of space can be represented as a theory on the boundary of that space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>Firewall Paradox: This formulation may provide insights into the firewall paradox <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref> by accounting for the entanglement structure near the event horizon. By including the entanglement entropy term, our formula reflects the quantum correlations that could resolve the apparent conflict between quantum mechanics and general relativity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.7 Consistency Checks</head><p>To ensure the validity of our modified formula, we perform the following consistency checks:</p><p>1. Second Law of Thermodynamics: We verify that the generalized second law of black hole thermodynamics still holds:</p><formula xml:id="formula_160">δS BH + δS matter ≥ 0 (109)</formula><p>where S matter is the entropy of matter outside the black hole. This ensures that the total entropy, including both the black hole and its surroundings, does not decrease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Hawking Radiation:</head><p>We confirm that our formula is consistent with the thermal spectrum of Hawking radiation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_161">T H = ℏc 3 8πGM k B (<label>110</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_162">)</formula><p>where T H is the Hawking temperature and M is the black hole mass. This consistency check ensures that our modified entropy formula aligns with the established properties of black hole radiation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Dimensional Analysis:</head><p>We ensure that all terms in the equation have consistent units of entropy (i.e., dimensionless in natural units). This check confirms the correctness of the formula in terms of physical dimensions and units.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.8 Applications</head><p>The modified black hole entropy formula has several important applications:</p><p>1. Information Paradox Resolution: By explicitly including information-theoretic terms, this formula provides a framework for tracking information during black hole evolution, potentially resolving the information paradox. It suggests mechanisms by which information might be preserved and eventually recovered.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Black Hole Evaporation:</head><p>The formula can be used to study the evolution of black hole entropy during the evaporation process, including the late stages where quantum effects become significant. This could provide new insights into the end stages of black hole evaporation and the fate of the remaining information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Quantum Gravity Insights:</head><p>The interplay between geometry (area term) and information (entanglement and complexity terms) in this formula may provide clues about the nature of quantum gravity. Understanding this interplay could help bridge the gap between general relativity and quantum mechanics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.9 Summary</head><p>The modified black hole entropy formula (108) represents a significant extension of the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy, incorporating quantum information and complexity into black hole thermodynamics. This formulation directly applies our cosmic channel capacity concept to black hole physics, providing a more comprehensive description of black hole entropy in the context of quantum information theory. By including entanglement entropy and quantum complexity, this formula opens up new avenues for exploring the quantum nature of black holes and the fundamental relationship between information and spacetime geometry. It provides a framework for addressing longstanding problems in black hole physics, such as the information paradox and the firewall paradox, while maintaining consistency with established results in appropriate limits.</p><p>Further research is needed to determine the precise values of the coupling constants α and β, as well as to fully explore the implications of this modified entropy formula for black hole evolution, information preservation, and the emergence of spacetime from quantum entanglement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D Derivation of Information and Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensors</head><p>In this appendix, we provide a rigorous derivation of the Information and Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensors. These tensors are crucial components of our modified gravitational field equations, incorporating quantum information and complexity into the framework of general relativity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.1 Background: Stress-Energy Tensor in General Relativity</head><p>In general relativity, the stress-energy tensor T µν represents the source of the gravitational field. It is defined as the functional derivative of the matter action S m with respect to the metric tensor g µν :</p><formula xml:id="formula_163">T µν = - 2 √ -g δS m δg µν (<label>111</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_164">)</formula><p>where g is the determinant of the metric tensor. The stress-energy tensor encapsulates the density and flux of energy and momentum in spacetime, serving as the source term in Einstein's field equations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.2 Information Stress-Energy Tensor</head><p>We define the Information Stress-Energy Tensor T (inf o) µν in analogy with the classical stressenergy tensor, but using the entanglement entropy S ent instead of the matter action:</p><formula xml:id="formula_165">T (inf o) µν = 1 √ -g δS ent δg µν<label>(112)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.2.1 Justification</head><p>This definition is motivated by the following considerations:</p><p>1. Holographic Principle: The entanglement entropy S ent is closely related to the area of boundaries in spacetime, aligning with the holographic principle <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">[83]</ref>. According to the holographic principle, the information content of a volume of space can be described by the area of its boundary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Emergent Gravity:</head><p>This formulation supports the idea that gravity may emerge from underlying quantum information processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b99">96]</ref>. Jacobson's thermodynamic derivation of Einstein's equations suggests that gravitational dynamics can be derived from the laws of thermodynamics applied to horizons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Black Hole Thermodynamics:</head><p>The connection between entropy and geometry in black hole physics suggests a fundamental link between information and spacetime curvature <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[14]</ref>. Bekenstein's pioneering work showed that the entropy of a black hole is proportional to the area of its event horizon.</p><p>However, it is important to note that the functional dependence of S ent on g µν is not straightforward. Entanglement entropy typically depends on the state of a quantum field rather than the metric directly. Further work is required to rigorously establish this dependence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.2.2 Properties</head><p>The Information Stress-Energy Tensor has the following properties:</p><p>1. Symmetry:</p><formula xml:id="formula_166">T (inf o) µν = T (inf o) νµ</formula><p>, ensuring consistency with the symmetry of Einstein's field equations.</p><p>2. Conservation: ∇ µ T (inf o) µν = 0, where ∇ µ is the covariant derivative. This property is necessary for consistency with the Bianchi identities, which imply the conservation of the stress-energy tensor. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.3 Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensor</head><p>Similarly, we define the Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensor T (QC) µν using the quantum complexity C QC :</p><formula xml:id="formula_167">T (QC) µν = 1 √ -g δC QC δg µν<label>(113)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.3.1 Justification</head><p>The inclusion of quantum complexity is motivated by:</p><p>1. Complexity-Action Duality: Recent work suggests a connection between quantum complexity and gravitational action <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23]</ref>, indicating that complexity may play a role in spacetime dynamics. This duality posits that the complexity of a quantum state is proportional to the action evaluated in a corresponding region of spacetime.</p><p>2. Black Hole Information: Quantum complexity has been proposed as a key quantity in understanding the long-term evolution of black holes <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[89]</ref>. It is hypothesized that the complexity of a black hole's state grows over time, which has implications for the black hole information paradox.</p><p>3. Quantum-Classical Correspondence: Including complexity in our gravitational equations provides a potential bridge between quantum information theory and classical gravity. This approach may offer insights into how classical gravitational dynamics emerge from quantum mechanical principles.</p><p>However, the functional dependence of C QC on g µν also requires more rigorous justification. Complexity is typically associated with the quantum state rather than the spacetime geometry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.3.2 Properties</head><p>The Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensor shares similar properties with the Information Stress-Energy Tensor:</p><p>1. Symmetry: T </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.4 Combined Effect on Spacetime</head><p>The total contribution of quantum information and complexity to the spacetime curvature is given by the sum of these two tensors:</p><formula xml:id="formula_168">T (total) µν = αT (inf o) µν + βT (QC) µν (114)</formula><p>where α and β are dimensionless coupling constants that determine the relative strengths of the information and complexity contributions. These constants must be determined empirically or through further theoretical work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.5 Incorporation into Modified Einstein Field Equations</head><p>These stress-energy tensors are incorporated into our modified Einstein field equations as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_169">G µν + Λg µν = 8πG(T µν + αT (inf o) µν + βT (QC) µν ) (<label>115</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_170">)</formula><p>where G µν is the Einstein tensor, Λ is the cosmological constant, and T µν is the classical stress-energy tensor. This modification introduces quantum information-theoretic effects into the dynamics of spacetime, potentially leading to novel predictions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.6 Implications and Future Directions</head><p>The introduction of these information-theoretic stress-energy tensors has several important implications:</p><p>1. Quantum Gravity: These tensors provide a potential link between quantum information theory and gravity, offering new avenues for exploring quantum gravity. They suggest that information and complexity are fundamental components of the gravitational field.</p><p>2. Spacetime Emergence: They support the idea that spacetime geometry may emerge from underlying quantum information processes. This perspective aligns with the notion of emergent gravity, where spacetime and gravity arise from more fundamental quantum phenomena.</p><p>3. Black Hole Physics: These tensors may provide new insights into black hole information paradoxes and the nature of singularities. By incorporating information and complexity, we can better understand the information retention and loss mechanisms in black holes.</p><p>4. Cosmology: They could have implications for the early universe, dark energy, and the overall evolution of the cosmos. Quantum information-theoretic contributions might influence cosmological models, potentially addressing unresolved issues in the standard cosmological framework.</p><p>Future research directions include:</p><p>1. Developing methods to calculate S ent and C QC for realistic physical systems. Accurate computation of these quantities is essential for applying the theory to practical scenarios.</p><p>2. Exploring the consequences of these tensors for gravitational wave physics. Informationtheoretic modifications to general relativity may alter the predictions for gravitational wave signals.</p><p>3. Investigating potential observational signatures that could validate this theoretical framework. Identifying measurable effects of information and complexity on cosmological and astrophysical phenomena could provide empirical support for the theory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>Studying the interplay between these information-theoretic tensors and quantum field theory in curved spacetime. This includes examining how quantum information and complexity interact with the established principles of quantum field theory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.7 Summary</head><p>The Information and Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensors, defined in equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_165">112</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_167">113</ref>), represent a novel approach to incorporating quantum information concepts into the framework of general relativity. By treating entanglement entropy and quantum complexity as sources of spacetime curvature, these tensors open up new possibilities for understanding the fundamental nature of gravity and its relationship to quantum information. While conjectural at this stage, this framework provides a concrete mathematical formulation for exploring the connections between information, complexity, and gravitation. It sets the stage for further theoretical developments and potentially new experimental proposals to test the role of information in gravitational physics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E Derivation of Cosmic Expansion Equation with Information Terms</head><p>In this appendix, we provide a rigorous derivation of the modified cosmic expansion equation that incorporates information-theoretic concepts. This equation applies our framework to cosmology, extending the standard Friedmann equation to include the effects of cosmic information flow.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.1 Motivation and Context</head><p>The study of cosmic expansion traditionally relies on the Friedmann equations, which describe the dynamics of a homogeneous and isotropic universe. However, incorporating informationtheoretic concepts into cosmology can provide new insights into the interplay between information, energy, and cosmic expansion. This approach is motivated by the principles of quantum information theory, the holographic principle, and the potential role of information in the emergence of time and structure in the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.2 Standard Friedmann Equation</head><p>We begin with the first Friedmann equation, which describes the expansion of a homogeneous and isotropic universe <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[28]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_171">H 2 = 8πG 3 ρ - kc 2 a 2 + Λ 3<label>(116)</label></formula><p>where:</p><p>• H = ȧ/a is the Hubble parameter, describing the rate of expansion of the universe.</p><p>• G is Newton's gravitational constant, which measures the strength of gravity.</p><p>• ρ is the energy density of the universe, including contributions from matter, radiation, and dark energy.</p><p>• k is the curvature parameter, with k = 0 for a flat universe, k = 1 for a closed universe, and k = -1 for an open universe.</p><p>• a is the scale factor, which describes how distances in the universe change with time.</p><p>• Λ is the cosmological constant, representing the energy density of the vacuum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.3 Information-Theoretic Extension</head><p>To incorporate information-theoretic concepts into cosmic expansion, we introduce a new term related to the rate of change of cosmic information content. We define the cosmic information content I cosmic as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_172">I cosmic = S ent + C QC + I classical<label>(117)</label></formula><p>where:</p><p>• S ent is the entanglement entropy of the observable universe, quantifying the quantum entanglement between different regions of space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.9 Summary</head><p>The modified Friedmann equation (118) represents a novel approach to cosmic expansion that incorporates information-theoretic concepts. By including a term related to the rate of change of cosmic information content, this equation opens up new possibilities for understanding the dynamics of the universe, potentially providing insights into cosmic acceleration, the nature of time, and the interplay between information and energy on cosmic scales. This formulation provides a concrete mathematical framework for exploring the role of information in cosmology. It offers testable predictions and suggests new avenues for theoretical and observational research in cosmology and fundamental physics.</p><p>Further work is needed to fully develop the implications of this model, calculate the relevant quantities in realistic cosmological scenarios, and confront the theory with observational data. Nonetheless, this approach represents a promising direction for integrating quantum information concepts into our understanding of spacetime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F Derivation of Dark Energy as an Information Phenomenon</head><p>In this appendix, we provide a rigorous derivation of our novel interpretation of dark energy as an information phenomenon. This formulation extends the standard cosmological constant model by incorporating quantum information dynamics, providing a comprehensive framework for understanding dark energy from a quantum information perspective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.1 Standard Dark Energy Model</head><p>We begin with the standard model of dark energy, represented by a cosmological constant Λ in Einstein's field equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_173">G µν + Λg µν = 8πGT µν<label>(119)</label></formula><p>In this context, Λ acts as a constant energy density filling space homogeneously. The energy density associated with Λ is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_174">ρ Λ = Λc 2 8πG (<label>120</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_175">)</formula><p>This formulation, while successful in explaining the accelerated expansion of the universe, raises several theoretical issues such as the fine-tuning problem and the cosmological constant problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.2 Information-Theoretic Extension</head><p>To address these issues, we propose that dark energy is related to the dynamics of quantum information in the universe. Specifically, we consider two contributions to the dark energy density:</p><p>1. The rate of change of entanglement entropy dSent dt 2. The rate of change of quantum complexity dC QC dt</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.3 Modified Dark Energy Density</head><p>We propose the following formula for the dark energy density:</p><formula xml:id="formula_176">ρ DE = ρ Λ + α dS ent dt + β dC QC dt<label>(121)</label></formula><p>where:</p><p>• ρ DE is the total dark energy density</p><p>• ρ Λ is the contribution from the cosmological constant</p><p>• α and β are coupling constants</p><p>• S ent is the entanglement entropy of the observable universe</p><p>• C QC is the quantum complexity of the cosmic state</p><p>The dimensions of the coupling constants α and β must ensure dimensional consistency, but further theoretical justification is needed to define them accurately.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G.3 Derivation of the Correction Factor</head><p>To derive the form of C(f ), we consider the following quantum information concepts:</p><p>1. Entanglement Entropy: Gravitational waves may carry entanglement information between the source and the surrounding spacetime.</p><p>2. Quantum Complexity: The complexity of the quantum state of the source may influence the gravitational wave emission.</p><p>3. Holographic Principle: The information content of the gravitational waves should be consistent with holographic bounds.</p><p>Based on these considerations, we propose:</p><formula xml:id="formula_177">C(f ) = βS ent (f ) + γ dC QC (f ) df<label>(128)</label></formula><p>where:</p><p>• β and γ are dimensionless constants,</p><p>• S ent (f ) is the spectral entanglement entropy,</p><p>• C QC (f ) is the spectral quantum complexity.</p><p>This formulation integrates the entanglement entropy and the derivative of the quantum complexity, reflecting how these quantum information measures influence the gravitational wave strain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G.4 Spectral Entanglement Entropy</head><p>We model the spectral entanglement entropy as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_178">S ent (f ) = S 0 log 1 + f f c<label>(129)</label></formula><p>where S 0 is a characteristic entropy and f c is a critical frequency related to the Planck scale, f c ∼ c/l P , with l P = ℏG/c 3 being the Planck length. This logarithmic form is chosen to reflect the scaling behavior of entanglement entropy with frequency, capturing the information content encoded in the gravitational wave.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G.5 Spectral Quantum Complexity</head><p>For the spectral quantum complexity, we propose:</p><formula xml:id="formula_179">C QC (f ) = C 0 f f c δ (<label>130</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_180">)</formula><p>where C 0 is a characteristic complexity and δ is a positive exponent. This power-law form reflects how the complexity of the quantum state varies with frequency, encapsulating the computational resources required to describe the gravitational wave.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G.6 Final Form of the Correction Factor</head><p>Substituting equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_178">129</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_179">130</ref>) into (128), we get:</p><formula xml:id="formula_181">C(f ) = βS 0 log 1 + f f c + γC 0 δ f f c δ-1<label>(131)</label></formula><p>This expression captures the combined effects of entanglement entropy and quantum complexity on the gravitational wave strain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G.7 Physical Interpretation</head><p>The modified gravitational wave strain in equation (127) has several important physical implications:</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>C. 6 F</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Justification and Implications . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . C.7 Consistency Checks . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . C.8 Applications . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . C.9 Summary . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D Derivation of Information and Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensors D.1 Background: Stress-Energy Tensor in General Relativity . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.2 Information Stress-Energy Tensor . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.2.1 Justification . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.2.2 Properties . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.3 Quantum Complexity Stress-Energy Tensor . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.3.1 Justification . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.3.2 Properties . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.4 Combined Effect on Spacetime . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.5 Incorporation into Modified Einstein Field Equations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.6 Implications and Future Directions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . D.7 Summary . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E Derivation of Cosmic Expansion Equation with Information Terms E.1 Motivation and Context . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E.2 Standard Friedmann Equation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E.3 Information-Theoretic Extension . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E.4 Modified Friedmann Equation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E.5 Justification and Physical Interpretation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E.6 Dimensional Analysis . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E.7 Consequences and Predictions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E.8 Theoretical Challenges . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . E.9 Summary . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Derivation of Dark Energy as an Information Phenomenon F.1 Standard Dark Energy Model . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.2 Information-Theoretic Extension . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.3 Modified Dark Energy Density . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.4 Justification and Physical Interpretation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.5 Dimensional Analysis . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.6 Dynamics of Information-Theoretic Dark Energy . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.7 Cosmological Implications . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.8 Theoretical Challenges . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.9 Proofs and Detailed Analysis . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.9.1 Non-Negativity . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.9.2 Asymptotic Behavior . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.9.3 Quantum Error Correction and Dark Energy . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . F.10 Summary . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . G Derivation of Modified Gravitational Wave Strain G.1 Standard Gravitational Wave Strain . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . G.2 Quantum Information Correction . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . G.3 Derivation of the Correction Factor . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . G.4 Spectral Entanglement Entropy . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . G.5 Spectral Quantum Complexity . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . G.6 Final Form of the Correction Factor . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . G.7 Physical Interpretation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Redshift of last scattering: z LS ≈ 1089 • Temperature at last scattering: T LS ≈ 3000 K • Radius of last scattering surface: R LS ≈ 4.4 × 10 26 m • Total information content: I CM B ≈ 4 × 10 90 bits</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Example 3 (</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Entanglement Across the Hubble Horizon). For two entangled regions separated by the current Hubble radius: • Mutual information: I(A : B) ∼ 10 70 bits • Entanglement entropy: S ent (A : B) ∼ 10 72 bits • Preservation capacity: C EA,pres (t 0 ) ∼ 10 72 bits This illustrates how quantum entanglement could preserve vast amounts of information across cosmological distances.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Example 4 ( 1 •</head><label>41</label><figDesc>Complexity Growth in the Universe). Assuming linear complexity growth: • Complexity growth rate: dC QC /dt ∼ 10 43 s -Current age of the universe: t 0 ∼ 4.35 × 10 17 s • Current complexity: C QC (t 0 ) ∼ 4.35 × 10 60</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Dimensionality: [T (inf o) µν ] = [Energy]/[Length]3 , consistent with the classical stressenergy tensor.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>2 . 3 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Conservation: ∇ µ T (QC) µν = 0 Dimensionality: [T (QC) µν ] = [Energy]/[Length] 3</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.8 Proofs</head><p>A.8.1 Non-Negativity Theorem 6. The cosmic channel capacity C cosmic (t) is non-negative for all t ≥ 0.</p><p>Proof. We prove this by examining each component of the cosmic channel capacity equation:</p><p>1. The quantum mutual information I(X : Y ) is non-negative. This follows from the nonnegativity of von Neumann entropy and the subadditivity property: S(ρ XY ) ≤ S(ρ X ) + S(ρ Y ).</p><p>2. The entanglement entropy S ent is non-negative, as it is derived from the von Neumann entropy, which is non-negative for all density matrices.</p><p>3. The quantum complexity C QC is non-negative by construction, as it represents the computational complexity of quantum states.</p><p>4. The cosmic scale factor a(t) is positive for all t ≥ 0 in physically relevant cosmological models. This follows from the nature of the FLRW metric and the Friedmann equations.</p><p>5. The holographic bound is strictly positive, as all terms in the expression 2πk B R(t)E(t) ℏc ln 2 are positive constants or functions.</p><p>Given that all components are non-negative and that we take the minimum of two nonnegative quantities, we conclude that C cosmic (t) ≥ 0 for all t ≥ 0.</p><p>A.8.2 Asymptotic Behavior Theorem 7. In an eternally expanding universe with Λ &gt; 0, lim t→∞ C cosmic (t) = 0.</p><p>Proof. We proceed as follows:</p><p>1. In an eternally expanding universe with a positive cosmological constant, lim t→∞ a(t) = ∞. This follows from the solution to the Friedmann equations with Λ &gt; 0.</p><p>2. The holographic bound remains finite as R(t) approaches the de Sitter horizon. In a universe dominated by a cosmological constant, the de Sitter horizon is given by R dS = 3/Λ. remains finite as t → ∞.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Consider the term</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p>Taking the minimum of a term approaching zero and a finite term results in the limit approaching zero.</p><p>Therefore, we conclude that lim t→∞ C cosmic (t) = 0.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A.8.3 Quantum Error Correction</head><p>To account for quantum error correction in noisy channels, we can modify our equation to include a quantum error correction term:</p><p>ℏc ln 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b101">(98)</ref> where S QEC is the entropy cost of quantum error correction, and γ is a dimensionless coupling constant. This term accounts for the information cost of implementing quantum error correction protocols in cosmic-scale quantum communication.</p><p>• C QC is the quantum complexity of the cosmic state, which can be estimated using the complexity-action conjecture.</p><p>• I classical represents classical information content, encompassing conventional measures of information in classical systems.</p><p>The entanglement entropy S ent and quantum complexity C QC are key quantities in quantum information theory, while I classical includes traditional measures of information. However, the specific definitions and methods to calculate these quantities in a cosmological context need further elaboration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.4 Modified Friedmann Equation</head><p>We propose the following modification to the Friedmann equation to include the effects of cosmic information flow:</p><p>where γ is a coupling constant that determines the strength of the information term's contribution to cosmic expansion. This new term γ dI cosmic dt represents the influence of information dynamics on the expansion rate of the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.5 Justification and Physical Interpretation</head><p>This modification is motivated by several considerations: 1. Information-Energy Equivalence: The term γ dI cosmic dt represents the contribution of information processing to the energy content of the universe, analogous to the matter density term 8πG 3 ρ. This suggests a deep connection between information and energy in the context of cosmic dynamics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Holographic Principle:</head><p>The inclusion of an information term aligns with the holographic principle, which posits that all the information contained within a volume of space can be represented as a theory on the boundary of that space <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">[92,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b90">87]</ref>. This principle suggests a fundamental link between the information content of the universe and its geometry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Quantum Cosmology:</head><p>This formulation provides a potential link between quantum information dynamics and large-scale cosmic evolution. Quantum information theory, particularly concepts like entanglement entropy and quantum complexity, can offer insights into the behavior of the universe at both small and large scales.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Emergent Time:</head><p>The rate of change of cosmic information dI cosmic dt may be related to the emergence of time in quantum gravity theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[66]</ref>. This suggests that information dynamics could play a role in the fundamental nature of time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.6 Dimensional Analysis</head><p>To ensure consistency, we perform a dimensional analysis of equation ( <ref type="formula">118</ref>). The dimensions of each term must match those of H 2 , which has units of [T -2 ]:</p><p>] (assuming natural units where G = 1)</p><p>Therefore, the coupling constant γ must have units of [T -1 ][I -1 ], where [I] represents the units of information (typically dimensionless). Ensuring the correct units for ρ and verifying each term's consistency is crucial.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.7 Consequences and Predictions</head><p>The modified Friedmann equation ( <ref type="formula">118</ref>) has several important consequences:</p><p>1. Information-Driven Expansion: If dI cosmic dt &gt; 0, this term contributes to accelerated expansion, potentially providing an alternative explanation for cosmic acceleration usually attributed to dark energy. This suggests that information dynamics could be a driving force behind the observed acceleration of the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Information/Energy Interplay:</head><p>The equation suggests a fundamental relationship between energy, information, and cosmic expansion, potentially unifying these concepts. This could lead to a deeper understanding of the role of information in the fundamental laws of physics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Early Universe Dynamics: In the early universe, where quantum effects are significant, the dI cosmic dt term may dominate, leading to novel inflationary scenarios. This could provide new insights into the mechanisms driving the rapid expansion of the early universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>Future of the Universe: The long-term fate of the universe may depend on the evolution of I cosmic , offering new possibilities beyond the standard "heat death" scenario. This suggests that the ultimate destiny of the universe could be influenced by the dynamics of information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.8 Theoretical Challenges</head><p>Several theoretical challenges remain in fully developing this framework:</p><p>1. Calculating I cosmic : Developing rigorous methods to calculate the cosmic information content, particularly in curved spacetime. This requires a deeper understanding of quantum information in a cosmological context.</p><p>2. Quantum-to-Classical Transition: Understanding how quantum information concepts in the early universe transition to classical cosmology. This involves bridging the gap between quantum and classical descriptions of the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Covariance:</head><p>Ensuring that the modified Friedmann equation respects the principle of general covariance. This is crucial for maintaining consistency with the principles of general relativity.</p><p>4. Information Conservation: Investigating whether total cosmic information is conserved and how this relates to entropy increase. This could provide insights into the fundamental nature of information and its role in the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.4 Justification and Physical Interpretation</head><p>This modification is motivated by several considerations:</p><p>1. Entanglement and Spacetime: Recent work suggests a deep connection between quantum entanglement and spacetime geometry <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">[94]</ref>. The term α dSent dt captures the contribution of changing entanglement to cosmic acceleration.</p><p>2. Complexity and de Sitter Space: Studies have shown connections between quantum complexity and the properties of de Sitter space <ref type="bibr" target="#b91">[88]</ref>. The term β dC QC dt represents the impact of evolving quantum complexity on dark energy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Dynamic Dark Energy:</head><p>This formulation naturally leads to a dynamic dark energy model, potentially addressing fine-tuning issues in the standard ΛCDM model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Quantum-Classical Transition:</head><p>This approach provides a framework for understanding how quantum effects in the early universe might give rise to the observed classical dark energy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.5 Dimensional Analysis</head><p>To ensure consistency, we perform a dimensional analysis of equation ( <ref type="formula">121</ref>):</p><p>• The dimensions of α and β should be adjusted to ensure consistency This analysis confirms that the equation is dimensionally consistent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.6 Dynamics of Information-Theoretic Dark Energy</head><p>To understand the evolution of this information-theoretic dark energy, we need to consider the dynamics of S ent and C QC . We propose the following models for their time evolution:</p><p>where:</p><p>• H is the Hubble parameter</p><p>• S max is the maximum possible entanglement entropy</p><p>• η and κ are dimensionless constants representing the rates of change Equation (122) represents a saturation model for entanglement entropy, where S ent approaches S max over time. Equation (123) suggests exponential growth of quantum complexity, consistent with recent theoretical work <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[89]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.7 Cosmological Implications</head><p>Substituting equations ( <ref type="formula">122</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">123</ref>) into (121), we obtain:</p><p>This equation has several important implications:</p><p>1. Time-Dependent Dark Energy: The dark energy density evolves with time, potentially resolving the cosmological constant problem by providing a dynamic component to dark energy.</p><p>2. Phantom Behavior: If βκC QC &gt; αη(S max -S ent ), the effective equation of state can be w &lt; -1, allowing for phantom dark energy behavior, which could drive accelerated expansion faster than a cosmological constant alone.</p><p>3. Future de Sitter State: As S ent → S max and C QC continues to grow, the universe may approach a de Sitter state dominated by complexity growth, providing a natural end state for cosmic evolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Initial Conditions:</head><p>The early universe's entanglement and complexity structure may set the initial conditions for dark energy, potentially explaining its observed value and addressing the coincidence problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.8 Theoretical Challenges</head><p>Several theoretical challenges remain in fully developing this framework:</p><p>1. Calculating S ent and C QC : Developing rigorous methods to calculate these quantities for the observable universe, which requires advances in quantum information theory and cosmology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Coupling Constants:</head><p>Understanding the physical origin and values of the coupling constants α and β, which may require insights from quantum gravity and field theory.</p><p>3. Quantum-to-Classical Transition: Elucidating how quantum information dynamics give rise to classical dark energy behavior, providing a bridge between quantum mechanics and cosmology.</p><p>4. Consistency with Quantum Gravity: Ensuring that this model is consistent with emerging theories of quantum gravity, such as string theory or loop quantum gravity, which could provide a more fundamental basis for the proposed dynamics.</p><p>F.9 Proofs and Detailed Analysis F.9.1 Non-Negativity Theorem 8. The modified dark energy density ρ DE is non-negative for all t ≥ 0.</p><p>Proof. We prove this by examining each component of the modified dark energy density equation:</p><p>1. The cosmological constant contribution ρ Λ is positive by definition, as it represents a constant energy density.</p><p>2. The entanglement entropy rate of change dSent dt is non-negative due to the properties of entanglement entropy and the chosen model, which ensures that S ent increases over time or saturates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The quantum complexity rate of change</head><p>dC QC dt is non-negative by construction, as quantum complexity is expected to grow or remain constant over time.</p><p>4. The coupling constants α and β are assumed to be positive, ensuring that their contributions to ρ DE are non-negative.</p><p>Given that all components are non-negative, we conclude that ρ DE ≥ 0 for all t ≥ 0.</p><p>F.9.2 Asymptotic Behavior Theorem 9. In an eternally expanding universe with Λ &gt; 0, lim t→∞ ρ DE (t) = ρ Λ .</p><p>Proof. We proceed as follows:</p><p>1. As t → ∞, the entanglement entropy S ent approaches its maximum value S max , causing dSent dt → 0.</p><p>2. Similarly, the quantum complexity C QC continues to grow, but the rate of growth dC QC dt will asymptotically approach a constant value.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The contributions α dSent dt and β</head><p>dC QC dt will therefore diminish or stabilize as t → ∞.</p><p>4. Consequently, the dark energy density ρ DE will asymptotically approach the constant ρ Λ , as the dynamic terms become negligible.</p><p>Therefore, we conclude that lim t→∞ ρ DE (t) = ρ Λ .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.9.3 Quantum Error Correction and Dark Energy</head><p>To account for quantum error correction in this framework, we introduce a correction term:</p><p>where S QEC represents the entropy cost of quantum error correction, and γ is a coupling constant. This term accounts for the information cost of implementing quantum error correction protocols in the cosmic-scale quantum state.</p><p>The modified equation provides a more comprehensive understanding of dark energy, incorporating quantum information processes and error correction, thereby enhancing the robustness of the model. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F.10 Summary</head><p>The interpretation of dark energy as an information phenomenon, as expressed in equation (121), represents a novel approach to one of the most significant puzzles in modern cosmology. By linking dark energy to the dynamics of entanglement entropy and quantum complexity, this model offers a new perspective on the nature of cosmic acceleration and its connection to fundamental quantum information processes.</p><p>This formulation provides a framework for addressing longstanding issues in cosmology, such as the cosmological constant problem and the coincidence problem. It also opens up new avenues for theoretical and observational research, potentially bridging the gap between quantum information theory and cosmology.</p><p>While speculative in its current form, this approach offers testable predictions and suggests new directions for understanding the fundamental nature of space, time, and the cosmos. Further theoretical development and observational tests will be crucial for investigating the viability and implications of this information-theoretic model of dark energy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G Derivation of Modified Gravitational Wave Strain</head><p>In this appendix, we provide a rigorous derivation of the modified gravitational wave strain that incorporates quantum information effects. This equation represents a key testable prediction of our theoretical framework and aims to integrate quantum information concepts with gravitational wave physics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G.1 Standard Gravitational Wave Strain</head><p>We begin with the standard expression for the gravitational wave strain in General Relativity (GR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[61]</ref>:</p><p>where:</p><p>• h GR (f ) is the GR prediction for the gravitational wave strain,</p><p>• f is the gravitational wave frequency,</p><p>• d L is the luminosity distance to the source,</p><p>• G is Newton's gravitational constant,</p><p>• c is the speed of light,</p><p>• F(f ) is the Fourier transform of the time-dependent quadrupole moment of the source.</p><p>This formula represents the strain observed by a detector due to a gravitational wave emitted by a distant source, where the quadrupole moment F(f ) encapsulates the source's timedependent mass distribution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G.2 Quantum Information Correction</head><p>We propose a modification to the gravitational wave strain based on quantum information considerations. The modified strain is given by:</p><p>where:</p><p>• h(f ) is the modified gravitational wave strain,</p><p>• α is a dimensionless coupling constant,</p><p>• C(f ) is a frequency-dependent correction factor arising from quantum information effects.</p><p>The correction factor C(f ) encapsulates the influence of quantum information phenomena on the gravitational wave signal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Energy Conservation:</head><p>Verifying that the modified gravitational waves satisfy energy conservation laws.</p><p>4. Quantum-to-Classical Transition: Understanding how this quantum modification emerges from a full theory of quantum gravity and transitions to classical GR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G.10 Summary</head><p>The modified gravitational wave strain equation (127) represents a concrete, testable prediction of our quantum information-based extension of general relativity. By incorporating effects from entanglement entropy and quantum complexity, this formulation suggests that gravitational waves may carry signatures of quantum gravitational phenomena. This modification opens up new avenues for testing quantum gravity proposals using gravitational wave observations. It provides a bridge between the classical description of gravitational waves in general relativity and quantum information concepts, potentially offering insights into the quantum nature of gravity.</p><p>While the effects predicted by this modification may be small for current detectors, future high-precision gravitational wave experiments could potentially observe these quantum corrections. This would provide crucial empirical evidence for the role of quantum information in gravitational physics and guide the development of a full theory of quantum gravity.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">G.8 Observational Consequences . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">G.9 Theoretical Challenges . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">G.10 Summary . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . References</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum computing since Democritus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aaronson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CMB-S4 Science Case, Reference Design, and Project Plan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Abazajian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1907.04473</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observation of Gravitational Waves from a Binary Black Hole Merger</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Black holes: complementarity or firewalls</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Almheiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Marolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Polchinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sully</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">62</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bulk locality and quantum error correction in AdS/CFT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Almheiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Harlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">163</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The entropy of Hawking radiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Almheiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hartman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Maldacena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Shaghoulian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tajdini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reviews of Modern Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35002</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum-spacetime phenomenology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Amelino-Camelia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Living Reviews in Relativity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cosmology and fundamental physics with the Euclid satellite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Amendola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Living Reviews in Relativity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A master equation for gravitational decoherence: probing the textures of spacetime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Anastopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Classical and Quantum Gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">165007</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum geometry and the Schwarzschild singularity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ashtekar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bojowald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Classical and Quantum Gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">391</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aspelmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kippenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marquardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cavity optomechanics. Reviews of Modern Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1391</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cosmological breaking of supersymmetry?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Modern Physics A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">05</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="910" to="921" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Baumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:0907.5424</idno>
		<title level="m">TASI Lectures on Inflation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Black holes and entropy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bekenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2333</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Black holes and information theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bekenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contemporary Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixed-state entanglement and quantum error correction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Divincenzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Smolin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wootters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3824</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Birrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C W</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Quantum Fields in Curved Space</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of FDI on CO2 emissions in Latin America</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Blanco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oxford Development Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic scalar field cosmology in string theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Blumenhagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Klaewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lüst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spin Entanglement Witness for Quantum Gravity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">240401</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Holography in general space-times</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bousso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">06</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">28</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The holographic principle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bousso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reviews of Modern Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">825</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complexity, action, and black holes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Susskind</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Swingle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">86006</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Elements of Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expanding confusion: common misconceptions of cosmological horizons and the superluminal expansion of the Universe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lineweaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Publications of the Astronomical Society of Australia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disturbing implications of a cosmological constant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dyson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kleban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Susskind</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Die Feldgleichungen der Gravitation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Einstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1915">1915</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Field Equations of Gravitation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sitzungsberichte der Preussischen Akademie der Wissenschaften zu Berlin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="844" to="847" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Über die Krümmung des Raumes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Friedmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zeitschrift für Physik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="1922">1922</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gallager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Information Theory and Reliable Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cosmological event horizons, thermodynamics, and particle creation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gibbons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hawking</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2738</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The trouble with de Sitter space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Goheer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kleban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Susskind</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflationary universe: A possible solution to the horizon and flatness problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Guth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">347</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Error detecting and error correcting codes. The Bell System Technical</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hamming</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="1950">1950</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wave function of the Universe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hartle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hawking</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2960</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Particle creation by black holes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hawking</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications in Mathematical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breakdown of predictability in gravitational collapse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hawking</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2460</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information loss in black holes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hawking</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">84013</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Black holes as mirrors: quantum information in random subsystems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hayden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Preskill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">09</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">120</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interstellar communication. IV. Benchmarking information carriers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hippke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Astronautica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The causal structure of QED in curved spacetime: analyticity and the refractive index</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hollowood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">91</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamics of spacetime: The Einstein equation of state</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jacobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1260</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum Entanglement in Gravitational Waves</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kanno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Soda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tokuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24018</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is there a quantum gravity effect on the cosmic microwave background?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kempf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Classical and Quantum Gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15004</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do cosmological perturbations look classical to us?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kiefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Polarski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advanced Science Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The quantum internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kimble</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">453</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7198</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1030" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Life, the universe, and nothing: Life and death in an ever-expanding universe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Krauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Starkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">531</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">22</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Irreversibility and heat generation in the computing process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Landauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IBM Journal of Research and Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Un Univers homogène de masse constante et de rayon croissant rendant compte de la vitesse radiale des nébuleuses extra-galactiques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lemaître</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annales de la Société Scientifique de Bruxelles</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1927">1927</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model of holographic dark energy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics Letters B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">603</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observation of gravitational waves from a binary black hole merger</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">LIGO Scientific Collaboration ; Virgo Collaboration</orgName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capacity of the noisy quantum channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1613</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultimate physical limits to computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">406</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6799</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1047" to="1054" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational Capacity of the Universe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">237901</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">LSST Science Collaboration</orgName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1809.01669</idno>
		<title level="m">The Large Synoptic Survey Telescope: Science Drivers, Requirements, and Mission Concept</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Theory, Inference, and Learning Algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mackay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The large-N limit of superconformal field theories and supergravity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Maldacena</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Theoretical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1113" to="1133" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cool horizons for entangled black holes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Maldacena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Susskind</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fortschritte der Physik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="781" to="811" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unveiling quantum entanglement degradation near a Schwarzschild black hole</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Martin-Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Garay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">64006</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The information paradox: a pedagogical introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mathur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Classical and Quantum Gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">224001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design for minimum energy in interstellar communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Messerschmitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Astronautica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Misner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Thorne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wheeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Gravitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>W. H. Freeman</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Physical foundations of cosmology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mukhanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Quantum Computation and Quantum Information</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamical aspects of gravity: new insights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Padmanabhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reports on Progress in Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">46901</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gravity and/is Thermodynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Padmanabhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2236" to="2242" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information in black hole radiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3743</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Noise of Gravitons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Parikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wilczek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zahariade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Modern Physics D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2042001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Holographic quantum errorcorrecting codes: Toy models for the bulk/boundary correspondence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pastawski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Harlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Preskill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">149</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entanglement-enhanced matter-wave interferometry in a high-finesse cavity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pedrozo-Peñafiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">588</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7838</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="414" to="418" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entanglement wedge reconstruction and the information paradox</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Penington</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2020</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Peres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Terno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Quantum information and relativity theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">93</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Planck Collaboration</orgName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Planck 2018 results. VI. Cosmological parameters. Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="641" to="A646" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Planck Collaboration</orgName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Planck 2018 results. VI. Cosmological parameters. Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="641" to="A646" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">String theory: Volume 1, an introduction to the bosonic string</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Polchinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Apparent weight of photons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pound</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rebka</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">337</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum Computing in the NISQ era and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Preskill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Quantum, 2</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Proakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salehi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Digital Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Proakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salehi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Digital Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Einstein Telescope: a third-generation gravitational wave observatory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Punturo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Classical and Quantum Gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">194002</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual horizons in world-models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Rindler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="662" to="677" />
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinematics and World-Structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">284</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1935">1935</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum gravity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rovelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Holographic derivation of entanglement entropy from the anti-de Sitter space/conformal field theory correspondence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ryu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takayanagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">181602</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ehlers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Falco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Gravitational Lenses</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Mathematical Theory of Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bell System Technical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1948">1948</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal sets: Discrete gravity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sorkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lectures on quantum gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="327" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The world as a hologram</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Susskind</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6377" to="6396" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entanglement is not enough</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Susskind</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fortschritte der Physik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational complexity and black hole horizons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Susskind</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fortschritte der Physik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entanglement renormalization and holography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Swingle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">65007</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The search for extraterrestrial intelligence (SETI)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tarter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Astronomy and Astrophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="548" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hooft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>gr- qc/9310026</idno>
		<title level="m">Dimensional reduction in quantum gravity</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fermi Two-Atom Problem: Nonperturbative Approach via Relativistic Quantum Information and Algebraic Quantum Field Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tjoa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Martín-Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">45012</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building up spacetime with quantum entanglement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Raamsdonk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">General Relativity and Gravitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2323" to="2329" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Decoding reality: The universe as quantum information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vedral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the origin of gravity and the laws of Newton</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Verlinde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Energy Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emergent gravity and the dark universe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Verlinde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SciPost Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Milne&apos;s Theory of World-Structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the London Mathematical Society</title>
		<meeting>the London Mathematical Society</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1937">1937</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="127" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Gravitation and Cosmology: Principles and Applications of the General Theory of Relativity</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement of gravitational coupling between millimetresized masses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Westphal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">591</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7849</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Frequency Dependence: The quantum information correction introduces a new frequency dependence, potentially leading to dispersion effects in gravitational wave propagation</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Amplitude Modification: Depending on the sign of α and the form of C(f ), the gravitational wave amplitude could be enhanced or suppressed compared to the GR prediction</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Content: The modification suggests that gravitational waves carry quantum information, potentially providing a new probe of quantum gravity effects</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Scale Dependence: The correction becomes more significant at high frequencies (approaching the Planck scale)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>while recovering standard GR at low frequencies</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Observational Consequences The modified gravitational wave strain leads to several potentially observable effects: 1. Waveform Distortion: The frequency-dependent correction will alter the shape of the gravitational waveform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>particularly in the high-frequency regime</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Polarization Effects: The quantum information correction may introduce new polarization modes beyond the standard plus and cross polarizations of GR</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b110">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gravitational Wave Echoes: The frequency-dependent propagation could lead to gravitational wave echoes, particularly for signals from extreme environments like black hole mergers</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b111">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The cumulative effect of these modifications could alter the spectrum of the stochastic gravitational wave background</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stochastic</forename><surname>Background</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b112">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Theoretical Challenges Several theoretical challenges remain in fully developing this framework: 1. Coupling Constant: Determining the value and physical origin of the coupling constant α</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b113">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Consistency with GR: Ensuring that the modification respects the core principles of general relativity</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>such as general covariance</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
