<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">How multiple learning systems contribute to naturalistic patch foraging</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kasarda</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jyotika</forename><surname>Bahuguna</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire de Neurosciences Cognitives et Adaptatives (LNCA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universit é de Strasbourg</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Facult é de Psychologie</addrLine>
									<settlement>Strasbourg</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Angela</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Entertainment Technology Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hua</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Entertainment Technology Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yuan</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Entertainment Technology Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ruizi</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Entertainment Technology Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tarr</surname></persName>
							<email>michaeltarr@cmu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Neuroscience Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><surname>Verstynen</surname></persName>
							<email>timothyv@andrew.cmu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Neuroscience Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15213</postCode>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">How multiple learning systems contribute to naturalistic patch foraging</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B9F11EBF59961523756A4B11B8D1779E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T14:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Optimal patch foraging requires the ability to discern valuable resources and harvest them efficiently. This process requires integrating across multiple learning systems, including perceptual, structural, and value-based mechanisms. We explored how these varied learning systems contribute to foraging efficiency through a novel virtual foraging videogame. Human participants (N=60) navigated a virtual world with four neighborhoods (patches) populated with houses, searching for "bitter Oomplets," characterized by the union of specific body colors and textures. Each neighborhood had a different overall probability of containing bitter Oomplets and, within each, specific house locations predicted the relative rate of bitter Oomplets. Participants proficiently learned to discriminate Oomplet types and strategically allocate their time to higher-probability neighborhoods. However, they did not learn the spatial predictors within neighborhoods. Importantly, we found no interaction between these two distinct learning abilities in determining foraging ability, suggesting that the impact of the perceptual and reward learning systems are independent of one another in human foraging efficiency.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main</head><p>Patch foraging is one of the most ubiquitous behaviors in nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> . Consider, for example, a lemur searching for ripe fruit in a forest. She must first decide which tree to climb and search, with each serving as a potential resource patch. Once in the tree, she needs to discriminate ripe fruit from unripe fruit by its appearance and infer where clusters of ripe fruit are most likely to be found. Eventually, she faces a decision: continue harvesting from the current tree or move to a new one in search of a potentially more abundant yield.</p><p>This scenario represents a nested patch foraging problem. More generally, patch foraging is a distinct type of decisionmaking challenge that can be represented as an acyclic graph of choices <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> , including how to search for patches, whether to accept a discovered patch for harvesting, and when to stop harvesting and move on. In the nested version of patch foraging, the harvesting phase itself contains another acyclic graph of explore → patch select → harvest decisions. While the ecological literature has typically examined these decisions only in terms of the overt behavior, such as the optimality of Lévy flights during search <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> or the optimal timing to stop harvesting <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> , cognitive science and related fields have focused more on the learning mechanisms that support the foraging and decision-making process. This research often treats patch foraging as a variant of the standard reinforcement learning problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> , particularly one that involves managing the speed-accuracy tradeoff during decision-making <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> . This value learning framework has been used to explain foraging patterns across a wide range of species, including bees <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> , bats <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> , humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> , and machines <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> .</p><p>Beyond reinforcement learning, naturalistic foraging scenarios, like the one faced by our hypothetical lemur, also interact with other learning systems. To forage efficiently, she must learn to make accurate perceptual judgments about the ripeness of the fruit <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> and develop knowledge of the internal structure of the trees <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> in order to identify the best locations for harvesting. How well she learns these skills is likely have a substantial impact on the speed and accuracy of harvesting decisions and, in turn, on overall patch foraging efficiency. Perceptual foraging paradigms suggest that value learning and perceptual expertise may interact with each other <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> ; however, in the typical experimental paradigm, the perceptual discrimination and foraging actions exist in the same space (i.e., visual representations). As such, we still do not fully understand how these other learning interact with value learning to shape optimal foraging behavior in traditional patch foraging tasks.</p><p>In this study, we examine how learning about the environment supports and shapes foraging decisions in a naturalistic foraging paradigm. We use a novel video game, "BitterBuster", in which participants navigate a virtual candy-themed world in search of candy creatures known as "Oomplets". Oomplets are distinguished as bitter or sweet by perceptual features that participants must learn through trial and error <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> . Players explore four neighborhoods (corresponding to foraging patches) containing various houses, visiting each house individually to collect bags of candy and search for bitter Oomplets. Each neighborhood has a different overall probability of containing bitter Oomplets, and within each neighborhood, the likelihood of encountering bitter Oomplets depends on the location of a house within the neighborhood. By analyzing behavior in these exploration and selection tasks, we are better able to understand how environmental factors influence foraging proficiency and to identify the neural systems that guide naturalistic foraging decisions. To play BitterBuster, participants are instructed to find and correctly identify as many bitter Oomplets as possible within the time allotted for each round of testing. To accomplish this, participants explore four neighborhoods within a virtual candy world (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>). Starting in the central arena, participants select a neighborhood (patch selection) and approach one of the houses scattered around the area (represented by colored circles in the inset of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>). A house can be explored by entering it, at which point the participant may begin harvesting Oomplets. Upon entering, the screen displays a new window where participants are serially presented with images of Oomplets that may be either bitter (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>) or sweet (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>). Participants make a binary classification based on the perceptual features of each Oomplet and are then given feedback on whether their selection was correct or not.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Participants can choose to exit the house at any point or can continue classifying Oomplets until all Oomplets inside a given house have been categorized. Participants are not told how many Oomplets are in a house, with the number Oomplets per house ranging from 8-12. After exiting, the view returns to the neighborhood screen, where participants can either continue to another house or leave the neighborhood altogether. A selection round ends when either all available Oomplets have been harvested across all neighborhoods or the time limit has been reached. At the end of each round, participants receive feedback indicating the proportion of bitter Oomplets they correctly identified (hit rate) and proportion of sweet Oomplets incorrectly identified as bitter (false alarms). On the next round all houses are repopulated with Oomplets using the same sampling probability for all testing rounds. Participants in our sample (N=60) were tested across three rounds of varying lengths (20 minutes, 10 minutes, 10 minutes). Participants were informed of the round durations before testing. The first round was afforded more time in order to give participants sufficient opportunity to explore the virtual world as thoroughly as possible.</p><p>For the purposes of our analyses each visit to a house was considered a trial and each correctly classified bitter Oomplet was considered a reward. Looking at the average rewards collected, relative to the time when a neighborhood was abandoned, we see two relevant patterns (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>). First, the overall average rewards collected increases with training, regardless of the trial relative to patch abandonment. Second, the average number of collected rewards (black line in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>) shows a slight dip around the time of patch abandonment, but the magnitude of this drop is not particularly large. This reflects a drop in harvesting rate as participants make their way through a patch.</p><p>According to the Marginal Value Theorem 6 (MVT), optimal foraging necessitates balancing rate of reward collection against expected effort to travel to new resource patches. To capture this balance, we created a measure called effective reward rate (see Methods). This reflects the immediate return on rewards (i.e., correctly identified bitter Oomplets), normalized by the distance between houses, approximating the effort to transit to another sample of Oomplets. As participants approached the decision to leave a neighborhood (or patch), the effective reward rate declined, and then increased again after switching to a new neighborhood (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>). The drop in the effective reward rate near patch abandonment was significantly higher than the drop in the overall collected reward, indicating that participants were tracking the effort needed to get to a new patch of bitter Oomplets when making their harvesting decisions.</p><p>When we compare the effective reward rate at the trial just before a neighborhood abandonment, against the average reward collected on that trial, we see that this non-monotonic relationship saturates at higher rates of effective rewards (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A-C</ref>). This relationship also strengthens with training, revealing two important patterns. First, this shows how harvesting becomes less efficient at the end of a patch harvest. Both premature exit of the patch (effective rewards of 0.00 -0.02), as well as lingering on the patch too long (effective reward &gt; 0.08), both lead to lower collected rewards. Second, this bottleneck on harvesting efficiency gets stronger with learning, suggesting that participants are learning the return rate for each patch.</p><p>The results shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> indicate that the effective reward rate increases with practice. To quantify this effect, we looked at the overall average effective reward rate across rounds. As training progressed, the average effective reward rate increased from a mean of 0.078 in the first round to 0.117 in the final round (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>). This effect was reliable across participants as determined as a main effect of round in a linear, mixed-effects regression model (β = 0.02, SE = 0.003, p &lt; 0.001 Supplementary Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). This confirms that, with three rounds of practice, participants were able to learn to forage effectively in our naturalistic foraging task.</p><p>Subsequent to confirming that human participants can learn to forage effectively in the BitterBuster environment, we next examined perceptual, value, and structure learning during the foraging task. To assess perceptual sensitivity over time, we calculated the d ′ for Oomplet classification (see Methods). Perhaps unsurprisingly, d ′ values increased with practice, beginning with an average of 1.55 in Round 1 and rising to 3.01 in Round 3 (β = 0.72, SE = 0.07, p &lt; 0.001 Supplementary Table <ref type="table">2</ref>; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>). These results indicate that participants were able to learn the perceptual features that distinguish bitter from sweet Oomplets, thereby improving their classification ability over time (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> ).</p><p>To estimate value learning, we calculated a neighborhood bias score (see Methods) reflecting the proportion of time spent in each neighborhood weighted by that neighborhood's overall bitter Oomplet probability. This bias score ranges from 0 to 1, with higher values indicating that a participant spent more time in neighborhoods with higher probabilities of bitter Oomplets. On average, neighborhood bias increased with practice, rising from 0.50 in Round 1 to 0.62 in Round 3 (β = 0.23, SE = 0.01, p &lt; 0.001 Supplementary Table <ref type="table">3</ref>; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C</ref>). These results indicate that participants successfully learned to identify and value neighborhoods with higher likelihoods of having bitter Oomplets.</p><p>Finally, at a more granular level, we examined whether participants could learn the within-neighborhood structural patterns that predicted bitter Oomplet probability. To assess this, we created a house bias score. This was calculated by ranking each house within a neighborhood according to its actual bitter probability and comparing that to the participant's search order using a Spearman's rank-order correlation coefficient to quantify their alignment (see Methods). In contrast to neighborhood bias, house bias did not show significant improvement with practice. The mean value was maintained at 0.66 through Rounds 1 to 3 (β = 0.00, SE = 0.01, p = 0.684 Supplementary Table <ref type="table">4</ref>; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D</ref>). These results indicate that while participants were able to detect global patterns across neighborhoods, the finer-grained spatial patterns within neighborhoods were not reliably learned during the period of time allotted in our study (a single day of training on the BitterBuster task).</p><p>To summarize our results to this point, we show that overall foraging efficiency in the BitterBuster task improves with practice. This improvement coincides with gains in perceptual discrimination and patch value learning, but not with learning of within-patch latent structure. While providing some insight into human patch foraging behavior, we are primarily interested in understanding how disparate learning abilities contribute to patch foraging effectiveness. To this end, we examined how effective reward rate relates to perceptual and value learning -the two cognitive abilities that exhibited practice-related improvements. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref> illustrates the relationships between d ′ , neighborhood bias, and effective reward rate across all three training rounds. These plots reveal a clear emergence of correlations between d ′ and neighborhood bias in their contribution to effective reward, from early in training (Round 1) to later in training (Round 3). This trend suggests that both perceptual and value learning may independently relate to foraging ability, but may also interact with one another.</p><p>In order to formally test this possibility, we conducted a linear mixed-effects regression analysis to assess the influence of d ′ and neighborhood bias on effective reward (see Methods). The results showed a significant main effect of d ′ (β = 0.01, SE = 0.00, p = 0.001) and a strong main effect of neighborhood bias (β = 0.20, SE = 0.02, p &lt; 0.001; Supplementary  <ref type="table">5</ref>). However, we did not observe a significant interaction between these two factors (β = -0.003, SE = 0.00, p = 0.68). This indicates that overall foraging effectiveness (i.e., effective reward ) in the BitterBuster task most likely reflects the additive contributions of perceptual and value learning independently.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>To understand the relative contributions of perceptual, value, and latent structure learning to human foraging efficiency, we developed a novel patch foraging task within a virtual environment. Our findings indicate that, even within a relatively short period of time, humans effectively learn the perceptual features that reliably discriminate viable resources (bitter Oomplets) and how to predict the relative value (probability of bitter Oomplets) of different patches. Interestingly, we did not observe reliable structure learning (house location predicting bitter Oomplet probability) within the allotted testing time, suggesting that if this ability manifests during foraging it requires more extensive experience than provided in our study. Most importantly, with respect to our primary hypothesis, we found that perceptual and value learning abilities function independently in enabling foraging effectiveness, suggesting that the cognitive processes contributing to patch foraging do not interact with one another.</p><p>Participant choices in our task mirrored the feedback-driven strategies expected in patch-foraging contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> . While this does establish the ecological validity of foraging behavior in our virtual environment, one might also be concerned that value learning here is governed by a generic reinforcement-learning (RL) rule. However, prior work paints a more nuanced picture. For example, Constantino and Daw (2015) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> found that a policy incorporating the opportunity costs emphasized by the MVT explained human foraging choices better than a standard RL model. Echoing this result, we observed a sharp decline in participants' effective reward rate (current returns + anticipated travel-time costs) as patch residence time increased, even though cumulative rewards continued to rise. This divergence supports the idea that feedback-driven learning during foraging integrates explicit cost terms into its value computations, rather than relying on a purely reward-based policy.</p><p>In our view, the most surprising outcome of our study is the apparent independence of perceptual and value learning in predicting patch foraging performance. At first glance, this seems to contradict a large body of work showing a tight coupling between these processes in perceptual-foraging settings. Bella-Fernández et al. (2022) review tasks in which observers search visually presented clustered targets and decide when to abandon a patch (i.e., look away). In these sorts of visual foraging tasks, sharper perceptual discrimination narrows uncertainty in value estimates, leading to better patch-leaving thresholds <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> . However, Wolfe and colleagues (2018) report the reverse: in a hybrid foraging task, learned target values steer visual attention, accelerating both search and departure decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> . Together these studies suggest a reciprocal facilitation between perception and valuation. In this context, why did we not observe such an interaction? One possibility is that the Oomplet classification task is perceptually trivial with a reward mapping that is explicit and stationary. Given such low uncertainty in the Oomplet classification subtask, joint updating provides a minimal advantage. More specifically, keeping perceptual and value learning independent may be computationally less expensive under such low-complexity conditions. That is, the independence of patch and target features allows for rapid, independent convergence in each learning domain separately.</p><p>Another critical distinction between perceptual foraging and the type of foraging that we studied here may be in how value is represented. In visual foraging tasks, the reward is intrinsic and yoked with the process of visual recognition itself. Indeed, these sorts of tasks are more akin to basic visual search problems than more traditional foraging paradigms. This is very different from foraging tasks studied in ecological contexts (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> for review), a context which BitterBuster was designed to more closely emulate. In these scenarios the perceptual subtask, identifying viable targets to harvest, is more cognitively distinct, in both representation and implementation, from the exploration subtask of physically moving between patches. The rewards are also presented as more tangible points, rather than intrinsic recognition values. These differences may explain why perceptual learning and value learning were not found to interact in contributing to foraging effectiveness within our study.</p><p>Another area where our results diverge from prior literature is our failure to observe spatial structure learning within patches. Latent learning in spatial navigation involves forming internal cognitive maps without explicit instruction, but not necessarily without motivation. While Tolman originally argued that such learning occurs without rewards <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> , more recent research suggests that reward signals shape and prioritize what is encoded. For instance, Doeller et al. (2008) found that the hippocampus integrates spatial cues, but reward-related regions such as the striatum also play a role in structuring that information <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> . Likewise, a review by Gershman and Daw (2017) observed that dopaminergic signals, often tied to reward prediction, can enhance memory consolidation and structure learning in spatial tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> . Schuck et al. (2016) demonstrated that even abstract state representations in the orbitofrontal cortex reflect latent structures that align with learned reward contingencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> . Thus, while latent structure learning can begin without feedback, rewards help to reinforce and stabilize the emerging cognitive maps. However, a single session may not provide enough reinforcement opportunities for these systems to prioritize and consolidate meaningful structure (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> ), which could explain why we were unable to detect latent structure learning in our current study.</p><p>Future research on this topic should note a key shortcoming in our experiment's design. Although our findings were robust, we observed a strong average signal bias that emerged prior to the completion of the first round. The average d ′ scores increased significantly during the next two rounds, but the practical increase in the bias strength represented is marginal. Perhaps changing the Oomplet characteristics used in the perceptual discrimination task to be more difficult to detect (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> ) could extend the learning window to match that of spatial navigation. We leave this to future studies.</p><p>In summary, we show that in a modular learning architecture for ecologically-valid foraging humans rapidly acquire perceptual cues and cost-sensitive value policies, but these streams appear to operate in parallel rather than an integrated fashion. We also observe that, within Bitterbuster, a single session potentially provides too little reinforcement for latent spatial maps to fully crystallize. This dissociation contrasts with classic visual-search foraging paradigms, suggesting that when perceptual classification is relatively straightforward and travel incurs meaningful costs, integrating perception and valuation yields no additional advantage. By identifying when learning systems act cooperatively versus independently, our findings refine theoretical boundaries of optimal foraging theory 6 , underscoring the role of opportunity-cost signals in guiding patch-leaving decisions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>Participants A total of 62 participants were initially recruited from the Carnegie Mellon University Psychology Department SONA System and compensated at a rate of 1 credit per hour. Data from two participants were excluded from the analysis due to software misconfiguration or failure to perform the task, leading to a final sample of 60 participants (23 male, mean age = 18.70 years). All procedures were approved and monitored by the local Institutional Review Board at Carnegie Mellon University.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental design</head><p>At the start of each round, participants began in a small circular room in the middle of a candy kingdom with four doors leading to separate neighborhoods. Each neighborhood contained nine to twelve houses inhabited by candy-like creatures called Oomplets. Oomplets are configurable humanoid characters that can be optimized for complex perceptual discrimination tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> . The task was to find and correctly identify as many bitter Oomplets as possible, based solely on their perceptual features. Participants were not instructed on how to discriminate between bitter and sweet Oomplets, using only in-game feedback learning to guide their decisions. Each neighborhood had its own maximum likelihood of having bitter Oomplets: 1.0, 0.75, 0.50, and 0.25. In addition, within each neighborhood, each house had a different probability of having bitter Oomplets. The house probability was multiplied by the neighborhood probability to determine the likelihood of bitter Oomplets at each house.</p><p>Within a neighborhood, the probability of bitter Oomplets at a house reduced in a clockwise direction relative to the entry point of that neighborhood (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>). The color of each house's mailbox was a cue as to the relative percentage of bitter Oomplets present in the house. Each mailbox used the same 3D model, but its hue was changed along a blue-to-orange spectrum, corresponding to the portion of bitter Oomplets in that house. Bluer hues reflected higher bitter Oomplet probability such that a deep blue/purple mailbox would correspond to a patch with mostly bitter Oomplets, a pink mailbox to an even distribution, and a light orange mailbox to mostly sweet Oomplets. Participants were not explicitly informed about either the mailbox color or clockwise probability cues -thus, exploration was necessary to learn their significance.</p><p>The exploration of the candy kingdom was periodically interrupted by the selection task. This task began when participants entered a house by pressing the e key when they were in close proximity to the door. During this time, the screen would switch to a 2D display (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B&amp;C</ref>) where Oomplets were presented one at a time and participants were asked to classify them by pressing the f key for bitter and j key for sweet. Immediately after each selection participants were given visual feedback on the accuracy of their selection. An Oomplet's category was determined by two of ten possible attributes: hue and pattern. Bitter Oomplets were those which had a bluish hue and a spotted background <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> . All Oomplets with other colors and/or backgrounds were classified as sweet. When a participant correctly identified a bitter Oomplet, a reward sound played to accompany the visual feedback icon. In addition, an accuracy counter was updated in the upper right part of the screen. A total of eight to twelve Oomplets were displayed in sequential fashion before the participant was returned to the neighborhood.</p><p>Each session consisted of three rounds: 20 minutes for Round 1 and 10 minutes for Rounds 2 and 3. Other than these time limits, all rounds were identical in form. The extended duration of Round 1 was meant to give participants time to familiarize themselves with both the game's keyboard controls and the game world layout. At the same time, Rounds 2 and 3 were shortened to increase the urgency of search with the aim of revealing selection biases in the participant's behavior. If a participant visited all the houses in every neighborhood before reaching the round time limit, the round would end early. We observed that 29 participants in Round 1, and one participant in Rounds 2 and 3 visited every house, ending the respective round early.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures and Analysis</head><p>To measure participants' overall game performance, we calculated their effective reward rate, R e , that measures the total amount of reward collected per unit of linear distance traveled by the participant.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">R e = ∑ R house ∑ ∆d j-i = R T D T<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Here R t is the running total of collected rewards (i.e., correctly identified Oomplets) up until the current moment in the round and D T is the running total of distances between house visits, ∆d j-i , up until the current house. By using effective reward, we were able to observe performance improvements in both the exploration and selection tasks, and account for different time limits across the different rounds. In the case of the first patch visit, the coordinates of the previous patch were the center of the game world, where the player began each round. In cases where the patches were located in separate neighborhoods, the players had to travel back to the center of the arena before entering a new neighborhood. Hence, the distance between the houses in separate neighborhoods was calculated as a sum of distances from each house to the center point.</p><p>Perceptual learning was tracked using signal detection, d ′ . This measure is the difference of the z-scores for a participant's false alarm rate and hit rate.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">d ′ = Φ -1 (hit) -Φ -1 (FA)<label>(2)</label></formula><p>False alarm (FA) rate was computed the proportion of total selection task events where a sweet Oomplet was shown, and bitter was the incorrectly selected category. The hit rate was the proportion of these events where a bitter Oomplet was shown, and bitter was correctly selected. A d ′ &gt; 0 indicates sensitivity in the intended direction, with increasingly stronger sensitivity as d ′ → 1, a d ′ ≈ 0 indicates no sensitivity, and a d ′ &lt; 0 one would indicate sensitivity in the opposite of the intended signal.</p><p>To measure how well participants learned the value of each neighborhood, we introduced a neighborhood bias (nb) score. This was calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">nb = ∑ b n t n t T<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where b n is the bitter probability of neighborhood n, t n is the time spent in neighborhood n, and t T is the total round time. This weighs each neighborhood probability value against the time spent in the corresponding neighborhood and sums these weighted probabilities, resulting in a value between 0 and 1. nb was observed to be highest in rounds where a participant spent most of their exploring time in a high-value neighborhood.</p><p>To measure how well participants learned to detect the within-neighborhood spatial predictor of bitter Oomplet probability, we calculated a Spearman rank-order correlation coefficient ρ S between the order that a participant selected a house in a neighborhood rank select and that house's rank order of bitter Oomplet probability rank house :</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">hb = ρ S (rank select , rank house )<label>(4)</label></formula><p>We refer to this as the house bias (hb) score. The magnitude of this value indicated how strictly a participant adhered to the optimal exploration pattern inside of a neighborhood. hb is highest in cases where the highest probability house patch that is currently unexplored and unharvested is always prioritized.</p><p>All analyses of learning effects across rounds and associations between measures were performed using linear mixed-effects regression models. Participants were used as the random effects term.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. (A) Top down view of the Oomplet kingdom, and screenshots of its four neighborhoods. (B) A bitter Oomplet in the selection task window. (C) A sweet Oomplet in the selection task window.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,56.69,224.53,498.61,195.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Effective foraging rate. (A) Collected rewards -correctly classified bitter Oomplets -on each house visit time locked to the decision to leave a neighborhood (abandonment). Color hue indicates round and black line indicates average performance across rounds. (B) Expected reward rate -the rate of correctly classified bitter Oomplets relative to distance between houses -time-locked to patch abandonment. Same color coding scheme as in panel A.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,206.28,63.78,199.44,359.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Effective foraging rate. The relationship between average collected rewards and average effective reward rate for the first (A), second (B), and third (C) round of training. Each point represents the average effective reward before patch abandonment and the total average reward acquired per participant in a given round.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,56.69,63.78,498.63,178.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Performance measure means and distributions for all participants across all three rounds. Measures include: (A) Overall performance measured by Effective Reward, (B) perceptual discrimination measured by d ′ , (C) patch value learning measured by Neighborhood Bias, and (D) patch structure learning measured by House Bias. *** p &lt; .001</figDesc><graphic coords="5,106.55,63.78,398.89,294.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Effective Reward plotted against task performance measures for each training round. (A-C). Exploration performance -Neighborhood Bias -for Rounds 1, 2, and 3. (D-F). Selection performance -d ′ -for Rounds 1, 2, and 3. Color hue represents the performance measure value from the complementary task.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,56.69,63.78,498.62,338.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data availability</head><p>The code and assets used to create and build the BitterBuster game are available on GitHub:</p><p>(https://github.com/CoAxLab/BitterBusterForagingPaperRelease).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions statement</head><p>TV and MJT conceived of the design of the project, oversaw the completion of the project, and contributed to the writing of this paper. JPK collected all the data and managed the experimental code revisions.JPK and JB analyzed the results, and contributed to the writing of this paper. AZ, HT, RW, and YT implemented the original Oomplet design and game code. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Information</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stephens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Krebs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Foraging theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>Princeton university press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The ecology of foraging behavior: implications for animal learning and memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kamil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Roitblat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A brief history of optimal foraging ecology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Schoener</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Foraging behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="67" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is foraging?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Barack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. &amp; Philos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The lévy flight paradigm: random search patterns and mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rhodes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="877" to="887" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal foraging, the marginal value theorem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Charnov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theor. population biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution of reinforcement learning in uncertain environments: A simple explanation for complex foraging behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Niv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Joel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Meilijson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ruppin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adapt. Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kolling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Akam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. opinion neurobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>reinforcement?) learning to forage optimally</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Foraging decisions as multi-armed bandit problems: Applying reinforcement learning algorithms to foraging data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. theoretical biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Saccade vigor and the subjective economic value of visual stimuli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jaleel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shadmehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. neurophysiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2161" to="2172" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model of resource partitioning between foraging bees based on learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pasquaretta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Barron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gautrais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lihoreau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1009260</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reinforcement learning enables resource partitioning in foraging bats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goldshtein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4096" to="4102" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of reward and effort history on decision making and movement vigor during foraging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sukumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shadmehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="638" to="651" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning the opportunity cost of time in a patch-foraging task</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Constantino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Daw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cogn. Affect. &amp; Behav. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="837" to="853" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combining imitation and deep reinforcement learning to human-level performance on a virtual foraging task</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Giammarino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adapt. Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="263" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adaptive patch foraging in deep reinforcement learning agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wispinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2210.08085</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of tactile and visual cues in consumer judgments of apple ripeness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Richardson-Harman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Phelps</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mcdermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gunson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. sensory studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognitive maps in rats and men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tolman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol. review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">189</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1948">1948</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Foraging behavior in visual search: A review of theoretical and mathematical models in humans and animals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bella-Fernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Suero Suñé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gil-Gómez De Liaño</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol. research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="349" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The oomplet dataset toolkit: A flexible and extensible system for large-scale, multi-category image generation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kasarda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Verstynen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tarr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Central place foraging in starlings (sturnus vulgaris). i. patch residence time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kacelnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The J. Animal Ecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Economics of information and job search</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Q. J. Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Humans&apos; choices in situations of time-based diminishing returns: effects of fixed-interval duration and progressive-interval step size</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hackenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. experimental analysis behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural mechanisms of foraging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kolling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Behrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mars</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rushworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">336</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hybrid value foraging: How the value of targets shapes human foraging behavior. Attention, Perception, &amp; Psychophys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wolfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alaoui-Soce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="609" to="621" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decision ecology: foraging and the ecology of animal decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stephens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cogn. Affect. &amp; Behav. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parallel striatal and hippocampal systems for landmarks and boundaries in spatial memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Doeller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5915" to="5920" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reinforcement learning and episodic memory in humans and animals: an integrative framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gershman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Daw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. review psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human orbitofrontal cortex represents a cognitive map of state space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Schuck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Niv</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1402" to="1412" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What learning systems do intelligent agents need? complementary learning systems theory updated</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kumaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hassabis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mcclelland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends cognitive sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="512" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
