<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Multiple jobholding as Identity: Investigating an emerging shift among younger workers toward &quot;Mosaic Careers&quot;</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Amanda</forename><surname>Welsh</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northeastern University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Boston College</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jenna</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northeastern University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Boston College</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Multiple jobholding as Identity: Investigating an emerging shift among younger workers toward &quot;Mosaic Careers&quot;</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">97F1454216ABE69E5C32F8AC53DDF286</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Multiple jobholding (MJH)-the practice of maintaining more than one paid position simultaneously-is experiencing unprecedented growth, driven by digital platforms, remote work normalization, and the expanding gig economy, which have all democratized access to diverse work opportunities. This expansion has altered the demographics of multiple job holders, shifting from predominantly low-wage workers seeking economic survival to include professionals across the income spectrum pursuing varied employment arrangements. Exploration of MJH has typically been dichotomized into two perspectives: those who view it as an unfortunate necessity forced upon the economically vulnerable and those who celebrate it as empowering "side hustles" that provide supplemental income and personal fulfillment. To examine workers' actual preferences and motivations, we fielded a survey (n=254) investigating whether workers actively desire MJH arrangements, whether financial considerations alone drive these preferences, and what other factors influence their appeal. Results revealed that workers across demographic groups express a genuine preference for MJH arrangements, transcending economic boundaries. While compensation remains important, workers value MJH for the flexibility and autonomy it provides. In contrast to the universal appeal of these characteristics, the youngest generation (Gen Z) is distinguished by significantly higher interest in using multiple roles to maintain different professional identities and build diverse networks (p &lt; 0.05). These findings suggest the emergence of what we term the "Career Mosaic"-a deliberate construction of professional identity through intentionally curated work experiences that together create a more complete expression of self. This shift from viewing careers as linear progressions to seeing them as multifaceted compositions among the next generation of workers has profound implications for employment policy, workforce development practices, HR technology, and organizational strategy, all of which were designed for a single-employer paradigm that may no longer reflect workers' evolving relationship with work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The rise of multiple jobholding</head><p>According to recent labor studies and media coverage, US workers are increasingly moving away from traditional conceptions of work as a single, full-time job. (</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>jobs (MJH) is at a record high, with roughly 5% of the population working more than one job, a rate not seen since the Great Recession in 2009. (U.S. <ref type="bibr">Bureau of Labor Statistics, 2025)</ref>. As high as these current numbers appear to be, however, traditional BLS measures may undercount the true prevalence of MJH due to narrow definitional constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bailey &amp; Spletzer, 2021)</ref>. While the BLS considers multiple job holders to be employees who have at least two jobs during the reference week, with at least one of those jobs being a wage or salary job, other studies define MJH more liberally, allowing for multiple work activities to occur over longer periods of time and to include the self-employed <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Burmeister-Lamp, 2012)</ref>. These other studies suggest that anywhere from one-fifth to one-third of Americans work at more than one job. The Survey of Income and Program Participation (SIPP) found that 18.2% of households held multiple jobs <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Scott et al., 2020)</ref>. Estimates from the McKinsey American Opportunity Survey (AOS) suggest that up to 36% of Americans identify as independent workers, engaging in gigs, contracts, freelance work, or temporary jobs while also maintaining permanent employment <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Dua et al., 2022)</ref>.</p><p>In addition to indicating that MJH is more widespread, the more expansive definition of MJH also introduces marked shifts in the demographics of job holders. The U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (2025) reports that multiple job holders are more likely to be women (5.8% of women were multiple job holders in 2024 compared to 4.7% of men), and Black or African American (6.1% compared to 5.2% of white workers). Once a more expansive definition is adopted, the average consistent multiple jobholder (who works multiple jobs at least 50% of work months) is white, around 39.2 years old, and has a smaller-thanaverage family size <ref type="bibr">(Scott et al., 2022)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Birinci &amp; Garriga (2025)</ref>, using a similarly expansive definition, estimate that approximately half of all multiple jobholders hold college degrees. This view suggests that MJH is not primarily concentrated among lower-skilled workers but has expanded across educational and skill levels <ref type="bibr">(Lale, 2015)</ref>. This increasingly well-documented shift toward more, and more intentional, MJH challenges fundamental assumptions that underpin our entire employment ecosystem. Government agencies must grapple with social safety nets and worker protections designed for single-employer relationships that no longer capture how growing numbers of workers structure their professional lives. Workforce development professionals face the challenge of aligning their traditional success metrics-focused on full-time job placement-with workers' increasing preference for flexible, varied employment arrangements. Meanwhile, the private sector confronts its own transformation: HR technology companies must bridge the artificial divide between employee and contractor management systems, while employers must reconsider policies that discourage outside work when their employees may view multiple roles as essential to professional fulfillment. This systemic misalignment between institutional structures and worker preferences creates inefficiencies and vulnerabilities that will only intensify as MJH becomes normalized, particularly among younger workers entering the workforce with fundamentally different expectations about career construction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The increase of MJH opportunity</head><p>The rise in both the number and types of MJH workers is likely due, in part, to the increase in opportunities for work. Gig work has been growing in popularity since the first Uber trip in 2010 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Scott et al., 2020)</ref>. Gig work refers to non-traditional work like freelance and contract jobs, as well as short-term, app-mediated tasks. Much of the recent academic and legal discussion focuses specifically on the platform or sharing economy, encompassing ride-share apps such as Uber and Lyft, and short-term rental platforms such as Airbnb.</p><p>Since the mid-2010s, the term "side hustle" has experienced rapid adoption in contemporary discourse, with searches for side hustle information peaking in 2022 and 2023 <ref type="bibr">(Google Trends, n.d.)</ref>. In some cases, the sudden loss of a job due to COVID restrictions inspired a creative reinvention of income-generating activity. In other cases, the ability to work from home created environments where workers could manage more than one position without getting caught. In popular culture, side hustles have been increasingly promoted through mainstream media, with articles such as Money Magazine's "The side hustle revolution" and the Harvard Business Review's "How to figure out what your side hustle should be" guiding readers how to start side businesses while also working as professional, full-time workers <ref type="bibr">(Field, 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Clark, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>Another term gaining more recent prominence is portfolio career, which refers to self-directed career management involving a series of temporary work arrangements <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Stokes, 2021)</ref>. Portfolio careers have long been a necessity for artistic and cultural workers, who are typically employed on a project basis and must maintain a representation of prior work-a portfolio-to get their next job. More recently, the term has been co-opted by researchers to refer to white-collar executives who consciously seek to feed a desire for work freedom with a range of part-time activities. <ref type="bibr">(Haapakorpi, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Stokes, 2021)</ref>. According to the Portfolio Collective, a professional organization supporting multiple jobholders, people with portfolio careers identify in a variety of ways, from freelancers (31%) to multi-hyphenates (21%) to focused experts (18%) and side hustlers (9%). The remaining 21% of portfolio professionals described themselves as entrepreneurs, business-builders, investors, mentors, and more <ref type="bibr">(The Portfolio Collective, 2024)</ref>.</p><p>MJH in white collar work has also emerged in recent years through concepts of fractional executive leadership and executive-level MJH. The fractional executive leadership model allows veteran C-suite executives to contribute to an organization part-time, a strategy that is amplified by the rise in hybrid and remote work post-pandemic, higher turnover rates among executives, and talent shortages and skills gaps among senior leaders, especially due to the rapid pace of technology changes. According to workforce analytics firm Revelio Labs, the number of executive job postings for fractional work has tripled since 2018 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Colletta, 2025)</ref>. Similarly, it is becoming increasingly common for executive-level employees to hold multiple job titles, as companies offer additional functions to proven performers rather than expanding their C-Suite <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Cohen, 2024)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Economic necessity or self-realization</head><p>The expansion in the range of options for work has generated a rich but fragmented vocabulary in academic and popular discourse. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Campion (2022)</ref> calls out the different disciplines interested in understanding work patterns and how this lends itself to different perspectives: economists look at laborleisure tradeoffs in financial systems, sociologists consider MJH as a mechanism for poverty alleviation, and management scholars focus on how employee management needs to adapt to changing employee needs. These perspectives give rise to terms such as moonlighting, overemployment, side hustle, portfolio career, gig work, and precarious employment. Notably, each term implicitly frames MJH as either an undesirable necessity or a liberating privilege <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Patterson, 2025;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Webster et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Haapakorpi, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Stokes, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Birinci &amp; Garriga, 2025;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Dundon et al., 2017)</ref>. Indeed, a central tension in most discussions of MJH work arrangements is what role, if any, a job is assumed to play beyond financial wellbeing. It seems reasonable to stipulate that most workers seek employment for financial support, and evidence from prior studies certainly suggests that economic necessity remains a primary driver. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bailey &amp; Spletzer (2021)</ref> found that a clear majority (63.7%) of multiple jobholders cited financial motivations as their main reason for working multiple jobs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Patterson (2025)</ref> reports that 48% of Boomers, 55% of Gen X, 61% of Millennials, and 72% of Gen Z believe that because a "stable full-time job" is a myth, multiple streams of income are necessary to survive.</p><p>While work arrangements have often been framed solely as strategies to alleviate economic pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Vaalavuo &amp; Sirniö, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">McBride &amp; Smith, 2021)</ref>, new MJH opportunities have also sparked a different conversation. Much of the discussion of "side hustles" assumes that projects stem from reasons other rather than economic necessity <ref type="bibr">(Field, 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Clark, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Sessions et al., 2021)</ref>. Research examining work in creative industries reveals that cultural workers see career portfolios as driven by motivation for creative freedom and authenticity (two-thirds of participants) as well as economic reasons (three-quarters of surveyed participants) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Stokes, 2021)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Zwick &amp; Spicer (2019)</ref> find that Uber is desirable employment for logistic reasons, citing interviews with drivers in Toronto and New York City, who appreciated the low barrier to entry, flexible hours, and networking opportunities provided by the platform. A comprehensive mixed-methods study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Campion and Csillag (2022)</ref> organized these additional motivations into eight different categories. Through analysis of qualitative input from 801 multiple job holders, they identified distinct motivators that include financial need but also careeradvancement, personal interest, flexibility, serendipity (receiving an unsolicited offer), and serving a calling (their example is a writer who pays bills with ghostwriting but counts continuing development of his own projects as an additional job). Collectively, these works provide strong support for a belief that multiple job arrangements help address worker preferences for non-traditional employment structures as a means of self-realization in addition to income.</p><p>What is most intriguing about the work from <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Campion and Csillag (2022)</ref> is their identification of one motivation category which they termed "momentum." Momentum captures the recognition that working multiple jobs has become a part of the worker's concept of identity. Workers evidencing MJH momentum are exemplified by this quote:</p><p>"In a way, I've always had the mindset to work multiple jobs. The idea of aiming for 'one dream job' wasn't fully clear to me growing up and as I began my undergraduate study. Subsequently, as my interests and apparent abilities have developed and clarified themselves, I've realized that the kind of impact I want to have on the world and what brings me motivation seems to involve having my energy spread across multiple disciplines and focal points. I had identified my identity, or at least a way to tap into it." <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Campion &amp; Csillag, 2022</ref><ref type="bibr">, p. 1266)</ref> Notably, in Campion and Csillag's sample, momentum appears to be slightly negatively correlated with age. This, along with existing research documenting Gen Z desire for flexible work alternatives that diverge from traditional employment structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bloomgarden, 2022)</ref> and lower willingness to climb corporate ladders <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Walters, 2024)</ref>, raises the question of whether younger workers are adopting a fundamentally different relationship to work that will persist throughout their careers.</p><p>To begin to explore this question, we fielded a survey to both multiple and single jobholders across generations and income categories, designed to explore the full spectrum of motivations driving MJH without forcing artificial trade-offs between economic and non-economic factors. Our survey tests two hypotheses regarding MJH patterns. First, we establish whether workers deliberately seek to segment their employment across different opportunities rather than concentrating their efforts in a single position. Second, we investigate whether there are any indications of strong generational differences in how MJH is approached that might suggest an enduring shift.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data</head><p>The survey, administered through Prolific, collected information from 288 adults working in the U.S. Because respondents were part of a panel of paid survey takers, we correctly assumed that they constituted a workforce characterized by employment flexibility and multiple job arrangements. While 52% identified as holding a single job (excluding their activity on Prolific), 48% described themselves as engaging in multiple employment, with 33% holding two jobs and 15% managing three or more positions. Respondents who engaged in unpaid activities as volunteers, caregivers, or full-time students with no organized revenue-generating activity outside of taking Prolific surveys were excluded from the analysis.</p><p>In our sample, freelance work constitutes the dominant employment arrangement, serving as the primary work mode for 61% of respondents, while traditional full-time and part-time employment each account for only 19% of primary jobs. The distribution of sector focus shows no single dominant category, though computer-based and flexible-schedule positions predominate. Knowledge work (26%) and gig work (26%) represent the largest categories of primary employment, followed by service work (20%) and creative work (17%).</p><p>The survey data includes a variety of age groups, including Gen Z <ref type="bibr">(born 1997</ref><ref type="bibr">(born -2012</ref><ref type="bibr">(born ), Millennials (born 1981</ref><ref type="bibr">(born -1996))</ref>, and Gen X and earlier (born before 1981), which we describe as Gen X in our analysis. We also collected data on annual household income and defined "affluent" as respondents reporting household income over $75,000 per year. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> summarizes the basic demographic characteristics of respondents by whether they held multiple jobs. Our respondents clearly represent a diverse range of demographic characteristics across single and multiple employment arrangements, making them particularly well-positioned to provide insights into the motivations and decision-making processes that drive individuals to consider multiple jobholding strategies. While our sample cannot be reliably generalized to the broader workforce due to recruitment methods, the concentration of non-traditional workers in our sample offers valuable perspectives on the factors that influence modern employment choices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Financial necessity</head><p>We examined the importance of eight different factors in multiple jobholders' decisions to work multiple jobs, revealing that while many motivations are shared across demographic groups, several meaningful differences emerge. The first and most important factor to address is confirmation of the basic assumption that the initial motivator to seek a work arrangement is financial want or need. 76% of those holding more than one job rated financial reasons as extremely or very important.</p><p>Additionally, our data showed that those with greater financial need place greater emphasis on adding jobs to address money issues. Non-affluent workers were significantly more likely to cite financial necessity for basic needs as extremely or very important (M=4.371) compared to affluent workers (M=3.691, Mann-Whitney p &lt; 0.01). Similarly, additional income for lifestyle goals shows a weak but expected income split, with affluent workers (M=3.985) placing higher importance on this factor than non-affluent workers (M=3.719, Mann-Whitney p &lt; 0.1).</p><p>Contrary to expectations, however, single job holders rated meeting financial needs as significantly more important (M = 4.35) than multiple job holders (M = 3.98, Mann-Whitney p &lt; 0.05). This pattern held true even when only the subset of respondents who fell into the non-affluent category were considered (Single non-affluent job holders M=4.654; Multiple non-affluent job holders M=4.171, Mann-Whitney p &lt;.05). One interpretation is that multiple job holders may have already taken meaningful steps to address their financial needs through multiple income streams, so it's less of a pressing concern. This is consistent with descriptive evidence showing that multiple job holders tend to earn less per hour but more income per year than single job holders <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bailey &amp; Spletzer, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>We conclude that while it should be noted that financial gain was highly prioritized by a plurality of respondents and earning income appears to be a driver for seeking employment generally, it was less clear that seeking income was any more of a specific driver for multiple than single job holders. This reinforces the value of considering what other factors of MJH might hold appeal for workers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Do people want to hold more than one job?</head><p>To address the question of whether workers prefer MJH over other job arrangements, the beginning point was to evaluate the basic appeal of work arrangements beyond a traditional full-time role. Analysis reveals strong, statistically significant associations between current primary job type and ideal work preferences, with three key patterns emerging even after Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons. The most robust finding shows that 62.3% of freelancers idealize "multiple small projects and gigs" as their preferred work arrangement, compared to only 8.2% of full-time and 16.7% of part-time workers (χ² = 62.59, p &lt; 0.001, Cramér's V = 0.496). The large effect size indicates this preference is substantial and meaningful. Similarly, nearly half (49%) of current full-time employees prefer "one traditional full-time job with benefits," while only 9.1% of freelancers express this preference. Part-time workers show moderate interest (29.2%), suggesting some aspiration toward full-time stability (χ² = 39.68, p &lt; 0.001, Cramér's V = 0.395). Exclusively part-time workers (10.4%) express preference for "one traditional part-time job," with zero preference from freelancers or full-time workers (χ² = 21.89, p &lt; 0.001, Cramér's V = 0.294). This finding, though based on smaller numbers, suggests part-time work serves distinct needs not met by other arrangements. These results demonstrate strong path dependency in work preferences-respondents generally idealized arrangements similar to their current employment mode, suggesting either successful self-selection into preferred work types or adaptation of preferences to current circumstances.</p><p>What becomes interesting is that even though full-time workers prefer the single category of fulltime work most, fully half of full-time workers identify less traditional opportunities-adding freelance gigs to their full-time job or combining non-full-time options -as their ideal (Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). Two-thirds of part-time workers express a preference for a work arrangement outside of a traditional single full-time role.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Ideal job arrangement by current primary role type (N=254)</head><p>Having an opportunity to hold more than one full-time job does, in fact, appear to be appealing.</p><p>The type of non-traditional work arrangement that is valued, however, may not be uniformly distributed across the different groups. Consistent with earlier findings on financial need, economic status shows surprisingly little impact (Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>). Affluence demonstrates no significant relationship with any work arrangement preference. In contrast, generational cohort emerges as the most influential predictor (χ² = 12.17, p &lt; 0.05, Cramér's V = 0.219), offering the first glimpse that the youngest generation of workers is different. Gen Z reports the strongest preference for combining full-time work with freelance opportunities at 27.7% compared to just 6.7% for Millennials. Interestingly, the Gen Z respondents in this sample appeared to place some value on benefits and stability by favoring an alternative that combined full-time work with outside pursuits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2. P-values for work characteristics across different analyses (N=254)</head><p>The findings thus far affirm that MJH is an attractive option independent of financial necessityworkers actively desire non-traditional structures, driven by generational values and positive experiences with an existing arrangement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The appeal of MJH</head><p>The essential appeal of MJH was further manifest in responses to exploration of what aspects of MJH were attractive (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>). The fact that only 4% of our respondents see "nothing" of value in multiple jobs indicates an overwhelming recognition of at least some benefits to this arrangement, even among those who might not choose it themselves. Looking more closely at specifics, we find that the top two benefits-"Flexibility in scheduling"(26%) and "Independence/autonomy" (22%)-together account for nearly half of all perceived benefits, highlighting that control over one's work life is the paramount advantage of multiple job arrangements. This was also evident in the comparison of different subgroups, summarized in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">4</ref>. Between those who already held multiple jobs and single job holders, flexibility in scheduling is the sole factor that emerges as a significant difference (χ² = 13.17, p &lt; 0.001, Cramér's V = 0.228). Not only is the flexibility highly prized by respondents, but it may also be the primary motivator for workers who seek an MJH arrangement.</p><p>Three benefits cluster in a middle tier, each selected by roughly 11-12% of respondents overall: "The variety and stimulation," "Creative outlets alongside stable work," and "Skill development opportunities." While flexibility and autonomy show universally high appeal across all subgroups, these middle-tier benefits reveal more nuanced patterns. Non-affluent workers show a stronger preference for "Variety and stimulation" (33.7% vs. 21.6% for affluent workers), whereas affluent workers lean toward valuing different professional identities. It should be acknowledged that neither difference reaches strong statistical significance (p = 0.081 and p = 0.083, respectively), suggesting trends worthy of further investigation rather than definitive patterns. What is perhaps most surprising is that, when examined by generation, approximately one-third of each cohort values these middle-tier benefits, indicating that the desire for variety and skill development through work transcends generational divides. Generational differences only emerge in consideration of the final tier of benefits that revolve around identity. Though valued the least by the respondents overall, segmentation reveals that the numbers are driven largely by Gen Z. Gen Z stands out as the most identity-focused generation, ranking professional network diversity nearly twice as high as other generations (23.4% vs. 13.3% of Millennials and 6.9% of Gen X; χ² = 9.39, p &lt; 0.05, Cramér's V = 0.192) and showing the strongest interest in maintaining different professional identities (23.4% compared to 9.5% of Millennials and only 8.9% of Gen X; χ² = 8.08, p &lt; 0.05, Cramér's V = 0.178).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>From Linear Careers to Career Mosaics</head><p>Our findings reveal initial evidence of a fundamental shift in how younger generations conceptualize and construct their professional lives. While MJH has historically been viewed through the lens of economic necessity or as a transitional state toward traditional full-time employment, our data supports recent research indicating something more profound: workers actively desire these arrangements as a means of self-actualization. What is noteworthy from the respondents in this study is that the underlying desire for creative expression through work transcends generational boundaries, with roughly one-third of all age cohorts valuing the variety, stimulation, and creative outlets that MJH provides. Indeed, it is only the connection of MJH to identity that appears particularly strong for the youngest generation. GenZ workers demonstrate significantly higher interest in maintaining different professional identities (23.4% vs. 9.5% of Millennials) and building diverse professional networks. This may signal the emergence of what we term the "Career Mosaic," a deliberate crafting of professional identity through the intentional combination of diverse work experiences, each piece contributing to a larger, more complete picture of the self. While we might imagine that someone early in their overall career journey is prioritizing exploration over refinement of an established choice, the fact that other motivators are represented consistently throughout a career journey offers a preliminary indication that this interest may indicate a transformational perspective that will endure. Gen Z may be pioneering the Career Mosaic approach, but the fundamental human need it addresses-the desire for work that reflects our full, complex selves-is universal. The force of that desire should continue to reinforce the mosaic approach to career construction as the younger workers mature.</p><p>The timing of this shift is critical. Gen Z's formative career years coincide with an unprecedented expansion of MJH opportunities through digital platforms, remote work normalization, and the gig economy's maturation. Unlike previous generations who may have viewed multiple jobs as a choice, Gen Z enters a workforce where MJH is increasingly normalized and technologically supported. This convergence of desire and opportunity may create lasting change in career construction patterns. Just as Millennials' early adoption of social media fundamentally altered professional networking, Gen Z's embrace of the Career Mosaic during their formative years may establish a new paradigm for career development that persists as they advance professionally. Of course, investment in longitudinal studies that follow the evolution of perspective among our youngest working cohort will be needed to validate this further.</p><p>The implications of this shift toward Career Mosaics extend far beyond individual career management, challenging fundamental assumptions embedded in our employment infrastructure. Most government systems-from social safety nets to worker protection laws-were designed around the presumption of single employment relationships. Unemployment insurance, healthcare benefits, retirement contributions, and labor regulations are all based upon a worker's full-time status that fails to capture the nuanced reality of workers maintaining multiple concurrent roles. This misalignment creates both vulnerabilities and inefficiencies that will only intensify as Career Mosaics become more prevalent.</p><p>For workforce development professionals, this shift presents a particular challenge: their traditional success metrics of placing clients in stable, full-time positions may increasingly conflict with workers' own preferences for flexible, varied work arrangements. This tension necessitates not just adjusted expectations but fundamentally reimagined tracking systems that can capture the complexity of modern employment outcomes-measuring not just job placement but the successful construction and maintenance of sustainable work portfolios. Policy makers must advocate for modernized employment measures that better reflect this reality, distinguishing between involuntary underemployment and intentional Career Mosaic construction while ensuring protections extend to workers regardless of how they structure their professional lives.</p><p>The private sector faces equally profound adaptations. HR technology companies must develop integrated platforms that transcend the current artificial divide between "employee" and "contractor" management systems, creating tools that can seamlessly handle workers who may be full-time employees in one context while simultaneously freelancing in another. These platforms must also address the perpetual job-seeking inherent in Career Mosaic construction-when workers maintain multiple roles, they are essentially always in the market for their next opportunity, requiring more dynamic and continuous matching systems than traditional job boards provide.</p><p>For employers, embracing the Career Mosaic paradigm means moving beyond merely tolerating outside work to actively facilitating employees' mosaic-building efforts. This could involve reimagining benefits structures to accommodate partial employment, creating more granular and flexible scheduling options, or even helping employees identify complementary external opportunities that enhance rather than diminish their primary role performance. Forward-thinking organizations might discover that employees who successfully maintain Career Mosaics bring enhanced creativity, broader networks, and diverse perspectives that benefit their primary employer. The Career Mosaic thus represents not merely a new pattern of working but a fundamental restructuring of the employment relationship-one that requires systemic adaptation across government, nonprofit, and private sectors to fully realize its potential while protecting worker welfare.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Actual or perceived benefits of MJH (N=254)</figDesc><graphic coords="8,220.00,397.23,207.75,144.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. P-values for work characteristics across different analyses (N=254)</figDesc><graphic coords="9,173.27,188.14,301.45,203.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="7,168.30,319.98,311.37,204.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Demographic Characteristics of Single versus Multiple JobholdersRacial/ethnic categories include both single race and multiracial identifications as reported by respondents b Includes all combinations of two or more racial/ethnic identities Note: Percentages represent column proportions within each jobholding category. Some categories may not sum to 100% due to rounding or missing responses.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>Holds One Job</cell><cell>Holds More Than One Job</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>N=121</cell><cell>N=133</cell></row><row><cell>Generation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Generation X</cell><cell>36.1%</cell><cell>44.6%</cell></row><row><cell>Generation Z</cell><cell>21.1%</cell><cell>15.7%</cell></row><row><cell>Millennials</cell><cell>42.9%</cell><cell>39.7%</cell></row><row><cell>Education</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>High School</cell><cell>22.6%</cell><cell>21.5%</cell></row><row><cell>Some College</cell><cell>32.3%</cell><cell>41.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Bachelor's Degree</cell><cell>34.6%</cell><cell>24.8%</cell></row><row><cell>Graduate Degree</cell><cell>10.5%</cell><cell>12.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Annual Income</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Under $25K</cell><cell>21.1%</cell><cell>23.1%</cell></row><row><cell>$25-50K</cell><cell>27.1%</cell><cell>27.3%</cell></row><row><cell>$50-75K</cell><cell>17.3%</cell><cell>17.4%</cell></row><row><cell>$75-100K</cell><cell>13.5%</cell><cell>11.6%</cell></row><row><cell>Over $100K</cell><cell>17.3%</cell><cell>15.7%</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>58.6%</cell><cell>66.1%</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>35.3%</cell><cell>32.2%</cell></row><row><cell>Non-binary</cell><cell>6.0%</cell><cell>0.8%</cell></row><row><cell>Race/Ethnicity a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Asian</cell><cell>6.8%</cell><cell>4.1%</cell></row><row><cell>Black</cell><cell>13.5%</cell><cell>8.3%</cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic</cell><cell>8.3%</cell><cell>2.5%</cell></row><row><cell>Native American</cell><cell>0.8%</cell><cell>0.8%</cell></row><row><cell>White</cell><cell>58.6%</cell><cell>69.4%</cell></row><row><cell>Multiple races b</cell><cell>10.5%</cell><cell>14.1%</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>1.5%</cell><cell>0.8%</cell></row></table><note><p>a</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new measure of multiple jobholding in the U.S. economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Spletzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.labeco.2021.102009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.labeco.2021.102009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Labour Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-08">2021, August</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Birinci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Garriga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.stlouisfed.org/on-the-economy/2025/mar/beyond-9-5-decoding-overemployment-trend" />
		<title level="m">Beyond the 9 to 5: Decoding the overemployment trend</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025-03">2025, March</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>On the Economy Blog</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bloomgarden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.weforum.org/stories/2022/05/gen-z-don-t-want-to-work-for-you-here-s-how-to-change-their-mind/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Gen Z and the end of work as we know it</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-05">2022, May</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are entrepreneurs influenced by risk attitude, regulatory focus, or both? An experiment on entrepreneurs&apos; time allocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Burmeister-Lamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lévesque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbusvent.2011.12.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbusvent.2011.12.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business Venturing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="456" to="476" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2025, May. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Gen Z and boomers are driving a leadership vacuum that&apos;s threatening productivity and morale at work. Fortune</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple jobholding: An integrative systematic review and future research agenda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Campion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Caza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Moss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0149206319882756</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0149206319882756" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple jobholding motivations and experiences: A typology and latent profile analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Campion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Csillag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/apl0000920</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/apl0000920" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1261" to="1287" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to figure out what your side hustle should be</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://hbr.org/2018/01/how-to-figure-out-what-your-side-hustle-should-be" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-01">2018, January</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The rise of the &apos;And Job&apos;: Why so many executives have two titles now</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-05">2024, May</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Chief</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://chief.com/articles/the-rise-of-the-and-job-why-so-many-executives-have-two-titles-now" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Colletta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://hrexecutive.com/the-rise-of-fractional-executive-leadership-whats-driving-the-interest/?utm_source=omeda&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Newsletter-20250725&amp;om_id=1116900781&amp;om_eid=4013B3554089A8" />
		<title level="m">The rise of fractional executive leadership: What&apos;s driving the interest? HR Executive</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-07">2025, July. Y&amp;oly_enc_id=4013B3554089A8Y</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ellingrud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hancock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Luby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Madgavkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pemberton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/sustainable-inclusive-growth/future-of-america/freelance-side-hustles-and-gigs-many-more-americans-have-become-independent-workers#/" />
		<title level="m">Freelance, side hustles, and gigs: Many more Americans have become independent workers</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McKinsey &amp; Company</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022-08">2022, August</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Power dynamics in work and employment relationships: The capacity for employee influence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dundon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Howcroft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Martinez Lucio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/321530182_Power_Dynamics_in_Work_and_Employment_Relationships_the_capacity_for_employee_influence" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-11">2017, November</date>
			<publisher>CIPD</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Chartered Institute of Personnel Development</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The quality of a professional portfolio career in the post-industrial era</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wrzesniewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13639080.2022.2073340</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13639080.2022.2073340" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Education and Work</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="454" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-07-30">2020, March. 2024, August. 2004. July 30, 2025. 2022. May</date>
			<pubPlace>Side hustle, United States</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The side hustle revolution Money Magazine Google Trends to present What job crafting looks like Harvard Business Review</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Josh</forename><surname>Bersin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Company</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/new-jbc-research-urges-employers-to-create-new-non-linear-career-pathways-to-build-tomorrows-workforce-301647421.html" />
		<title level="m">New JBC research urges employers to create new nonlinear career pathways to build tomorrow&apos;s workforce</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>PR Newswire</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022-10">2022, October</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lalé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ftp.iza.org/dp10355.pdf" />
		<title level="m">The evolution of multiple jobholding in the U.S. labor market: The complete picture of gross workers flow</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Institute for the Study of Labor</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Discussion Paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">I feel like I&apos;m in poverty. I don&apos;t do much outside of work other than survive&apos;: In-work poverty and multiple employment in the UK</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcbride</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0143831X211016054</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0143831X211016054(Originalwork" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economic and Industrial Democracy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1440" to="1466" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Patterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://portfolio-collective.com/content/articles/state-of-portfolio-careers-in-2024/" />
		<title level="m">Beyond the 9-to-5: How economic pressure is redefining what American workers need</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-02">2025, June. 2024, February</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Checkr</note>
	<note>The state of portfolio careers in 2024</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Walters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.robertwalters.co.uk/insights/news/blog/conscious-unbossing.html" />
		<title level="m">Conscious unbossing -52% of Gen-Z professionals don&apos;t want to be middle managers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-09">2024, September</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moonlighting to the side hustle: The effect of working an extra job on household poverty for households with less formal education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stanczyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1044389420910664</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1044389420910664" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Families in Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2020-01">2020. January</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do the hustle! Empowerment from side-hustles and its effects on full-time work performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sessions</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Nahrgang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vaulont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bartles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5465/amj.2018.0164</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5465/amj.2018.0164" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="264" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Masters of none? How cultural workers use reframing to achieve legitimacy in portfolio careers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stokes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0950017020977324</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0950017020977324" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Work, Employment and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="350" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2021-01">2021, January</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.bls.gov/cps/cpsaat36.htm" />
		<title level="m">Multiple jobholders by selected characteristics (Table A-36)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2025-01">2025, January</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Labor Force Statistics from the Current Population Survey</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Concepts and definitions: Wage and salary workers</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.bls.gov/cps/definitions.htm#" />
		<title level="m">multiple jobholders</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-10">October 2024. July 30, 2025</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>U.S. Department of Labor</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Last updated</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Jobs against poverty: a fixed-effects analysis on the link between gaining employment and exiting poverty in Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vaalavuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sirniö</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14616696.2022.2088821</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14616696.2022.2088821" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Societies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="462" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How part-time jobs became a trap</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Waldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.theatlantic.com/economy/archive/2025/05/part-time-jobs-underwork/682768/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Atlantic</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-05">2025, May</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is holding two jobs too much? An examination of dual jobholders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10869-018-9540-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10869-018-9540-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business and Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2019-05">2019. May</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blight or remedy: Understanding ridehailing&apos;s role in the precarious &quot;gig economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Spicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14649357.2019.1629197</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14649357.2019.1629197" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Planning Theory &amp; Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="2019-07">2019, July</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
