<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Meta-Research Framework for Transparent, Ethically Accountable Integration of CAM Author</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Kenjiro</forename><surname>Shiraishi</surname></persName>
							<email>kenjiroushiraishi@hotmail.co.jp</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Tanashi Kitaguchi Acupuncture and Moxa Clinic Nozaki</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-9-6 Tanashicho</addrLine>
									<postBox>Building 301</postBox>
									<postCode>188-0011</postCode>
									<settlement>Nishitokyo-shi Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Tanashi Kitaguchi Acupuncture and Moxa Clinic Nozaki</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-9-6 Tanashicho</addrLine>
									<postBox>Building 301</postBox>
									<postCode>188-0011</postCode>
									<settlement>Nishitokyo-shi Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Meta-Research Framework for Transparent, Ethically Accountable Integration of CAM Author</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E1DF83B8EF545669FADCB7B4CE324A4E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>meta-research</term>
					<term>research transparency</term>
					<term>reproducibility</term>
					<term>open science</term>
					<term>auditability</term>
					<term>research ethics</term>
					<term>reporting standards</term>
					<term>AI-use disclosure</term>
					<term>CAM</term>
					<term>patient values</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The author is a licensed acupuncturist and the owner of a private acupuncture and moxibustion clinic in Tokyo. The author previously sold dietary supplements on a small scale, but is no longer engaged in any supplement sales. These professional activities are disclosed for transparency.</p><p>The author declares that no financial, commercial, or personal relationships have influenced the content, analysis, or conclusions of this Commentary.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work is positioned as meta-research: our primary aim is to design and evaluate transparent, reproducible, and auditable processes for making and communicating clinical claims under open-science practices, rather than to argue for or against any specific CAM intervention.</p><p>Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM), including acupuncture, is used by millions worldwide, yet remains insufficiently integrated into healthcare systems. This gap is becoming increasingly urgent, not only because CAM has long been part of the global health landscape, but because the accelerating adoption of artificial intelligence (AI) in clinical decision-making will inevitably intersect with CAMmaking it essential to establish a robust integration framework before unsafe practices take root.</p><p>First, declining trust in healthcare institutions and the spread of health misinformation-exemplified by the global rise in vaccine hesitancy-have increased the appeal of CAM【1,2】. Such distrust can drive patients toward interventions that lack robust evidence and may delay or replace effective treatment.</p><p>Second, rising healthcare costs are placing greater financial burdens on individuals, prompting some to seek care options perceived as more affordable or accessible, including CAM【3】. In Canada, for example, high out-of-pocket costs for prescription drugs have been shown to create inequities in access and lead patients to delay or forgo necessary conventional care【4】. Such financial barriers can make lower-cost or perceived-accessible options, including CAM, more attractive, even when those options lack strong evidence.</p><p>Third, the rapid clinical adoption of AI in diagnosis and treatment recommendations makes CAM integration an urgent policy and safety issue. AI will inevitably enter the CAM space, but without a clear decision-making framework, it risks amplifying existing biases and promoting unsafe practices.</p><p>A recent case report illustrates this danger: a patient developed bromism after following ChatGPT's advice to substitute sodium chloride with sodium bromide, obtained online【5】. The AI-generated suggestion lacked contextual risk assessment or appropriate health warnings. This led to months of bromide ingestion, resulting in neuropsychiatric symptoms, electrolyte disturbances, and hospitalization. The case underscores how AI can provide decontextualized, inaccurate health information, potentially leading to preventable harm-particularly when patients are seeking "natural" or alternative solutions.</p><p>Although the cultural expressions and regulatory environments surrounding CAM vary-from Europe's formalized herbal pharmacopoeias to rapidly expanding CAM markets in the Global South-the underlying challenges of ensuring safety, evidence-based practice, and ethical integration are strikingly consistent across regions.</p><p>These converging factors make it imperative to redefine how CAM is structured within modern healthcare. We propose a tripartite model balancing evidence-based shared decision making (SDM), respect for patient values, and ethical accountability.</p><p>This model provides a safeguard for responsible CAM integration and a necessary foundation for safe, trustworthy AI-assisted decision support.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2,Current challenges in CAM integration</head><p>Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) encompasses a wide range of culturally rooted practices. The World Health Organization (WHO) defines CAM as "approaches that often complement or substitute for mainstream medicine"【6】, while the U.S. National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) distinguishes between "complementary" methods-used alongside conventional treatments-and "alternative" methods, which are used in place of them【7】.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 1 summarizes common categories and examples of CAM modalities relevant</head><p>to this discussion.</p><p>Despite their diversity and popularity, CAM modalities face persistent challenges that hinder their ethical and effective integration into healthcare systems: 2-1.Lack of standardized protocols Acupuncture techniques and herbal formulations vary widely, with limited regulation of quality, dosage, or preparation【8】. This variability undermines reproducibility and complicates the generation of high-quality evidence【9】.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2-2.Dependence on contextual and placebo-related effects</head><p>Treatment outcomes in CAM are strongly influenced by cultural narratives, therapeutic rituals, and the patient-practitioner relationship. Furthermore, research in medical communication has shown that the way information is conveyed and the process by which patients participate in decision-making can themselves affect therapeutic outcomes through placebo effects【10】.</p><p>Such insights are applicable to the design and practice of shared decision making (SDM) in CAM, offering important guidance for balancing cultural elements with evidence-based approaches. In conditions that remain difficult to manage with conventional medicine-such as chronic dizziness, persistent night sweats, or medically unexplained fatiguepatients often turn to CAM【6,7,12,13】. Without a structured decision-making model, these choices can be inconsistent, ethically ambiguous, and potentially unsafe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3,The tripartite model</head><p>We propose a tripartite model for the ethical integration of CAM into modern healthcare, comprising three interdependent pillars: 3-1.Evidence-based shared decision making (SDM) Shared decision making (SDM) is a collaborative process in which clinicians and patients exchange the best available evidence to arrive at treatment choices that align with the patient's values and preferences【14】. In the context of CAM, it is essential to present biomedical evidence pertaining to conventional standard-of-care interventions alongside CAM-specific evidence, including a transparent discussion of their respective limitations. This balanced presentation ensures that patients can make informed decisions within a clear evidentiary framework. The foundation of this process rests on evidence-based medicine (EBM), which demands that clinical decisions be grounded in transparent, reproducible, and reliable data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3-2.Respect for patient values</head><p>Patients bring unique cultural perspectives, life experiences, and treatment goals to clinical encounters. These values can strongly influence their openness to CAM. In East Asian contexts, concepts such as Qi stagnation or blood deficiency may serve as explanatory models that foster patient engagement【15】. However, such concepts should be framed as interpretive tools rather than biomedical diagnoses, and they must not replace biomedical assessment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3-3.Ethical accountability</head><p>Clinicians have a responsibility to communicate uncertainties, avoid deception, and ensure that patients are not misled by overpromising outcomes. This is especially important in CAM, where reproducibility of results can be limited and patient expectations are often shaped by anecdote or cultural narratives【10】. Ethical accountability also encompasses recognizing the limits of one's professional scope and, when appropriate, referring patients to conventional medical care. This obligation is supported by ethical and legal frameworks that require CAM practitioners to make such referrals when a patient's condition falls outside their area of competence【16】.</p><p>Neglecting any one of these pillars undermines the quality, safety, and social value of CAM integration. For example, focusing solely on patient preference without sufficient evidence risks promoting interventions that are ineffective or harmful; conversely, focusing exclusively on evidence without cultural sensitivity may erode trust and reduce adherence【17，18】. To enhance transparency, a patient-facing reflection worksheet was provided to clarify the patient's understanding, expectations, and concerns. This approach aligns with best-practice shared decision making【14】 and with CONSORT 2025 guidance to document care processes in addition to reporting outcomes【19】.</p><p>Based on the EVA schema and its documentation artifacts, we outline a four-step framework for ethically integrating CAM into modern medicine (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>). Looking ahead, embedding this framework into AI-assisted decision-support tools could help mitigate bias, ensure cultural sensitivity, and maintain patient trust. By explicitly integrating evidence, values, and ethical safeguards, AI could support-not undermine-responsible CAM use.</p><p>These artifacts are domain-agnostic; CAM serves only as a testbed to surface reproducibility and governance challenges that the framework addresses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.Conclusion</head><p>The ethical integration of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) into modern healthcare demands more than respect for patient preferences. Without robust structural safeguards, CAM use risks inconsistency, ethical ambiguity, and patient harm-risks that will only grow as artificial intelligence (AI) enters the clinical decisionmaking space.</p><p>Our tripartite model-balancing evidence-based shared decision making (SDM), respect for patient values, and ethical accountability-offers a practical foundation to address these challenges. Applied through a four-step framework, it promotes safety, transparency, and trust while ensuring CAM complements, rather than replaces, effective biomedical care.</p><p>Beyond improving care quality, this approach can help rebuild public trust, align CAM</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>accountability 1 ,</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Introduction (enhanced with AI-related adverse event)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>2- 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Over-reliance on patient preference without adequate safeguards Patient values are central to person-centered care, but uncritical deference can lead to ethically and clinically problematic situations, such as substituting CAM for proven treatments, delaying diagnosis, or promoting costly but ineffective therapies【11】.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. The Tripartite Model for CAM Integration.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="7,72.00,80.07,451.30,253.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="11,72.00,152.07,451.30,253.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="13,72.00,302.07,451.30,253.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Four-step framework for ethical integration of CAM into modern medicine This framework serves dual purposes:</figDesc><table><row><cell> Clinical safety: Ensures CAM use complements, rather than replaces,</cell></row><row><cell>effective biomedical care.</cell></row></table><note><p> Ethical transparency: Creates a clear, auditable record of the decision-making process.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>practices with health system priorities, and create a safer environment for AI-assisted recommendations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key messages</head><p> Ethical CAM integration requires evidence-based SDM, respect for patient values, and ethical accountability in equal measure.</p><p> Communicate limitations and uncertainties as clearly as benefits.</p><p> A four-step framework can translate these principles into daily clinical practice.</p><p> Embedding this model in AI-driven recommendations is essential to protect patients and maintain trust.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The State of Vaccine Confidence 2022: Global Insights Through a 10-Year Lens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EClinicalMedicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101710</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping global trends in vaccine confidence and investigating barriers to vaccine uptake: a large-scale retrospective temporal modelling study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">396</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="898" to="908" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020. 10255</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Health at a Glance</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023. 2023</date>
			<publisher>OECD Publishing</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Universal Pharmacare in Canada: A Prescription for Equity in Healthcare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hajizadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Edmonds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.15171/ijhpm.2019.93</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Health Policy and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="666" to="669" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A case of bromism influenced by use of artificial intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eichenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thielke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Van</forename><surname>Buskirk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7326/aimcc.2024.1260</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Intern Med Clin Cases</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Health Organization. Traditional, Complementary and Integrative Medicine</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Accessed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.who.int/health-topics/traditional-complementary-and-integrative-medicine" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-07-21">July 21, 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Complementary, Alternative, or Integrative Health: What&apos;s In a Name</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.nccih.nih.gov/health/complementary-alternative-or-integrative-health-whats-in-a-name" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-07-21">July 21, 2025</date>
			<publisher>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ethical considerations for acupuncture and Chinese herbal medicine clinical trials: A cross-cultural perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zaslawski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Complement Ther Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acupuncture for chronic pain: An individual patient data metaanalysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">172</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1444" to="1453" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The placebo phenomenon: Implications for the ethics of shared decision-making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Brody</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Colloca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Gen Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="646" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Do You Believe in Magic? The Sense and Nonsense of Alternative Medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Offit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Harper</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of complementary and alternative medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ernst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">321</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1133" to="1135" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acupuncture for paraneoplastic night sweats due to pancreatic cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ramasamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Acupunct Meridian Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shared decision making: A model for clinical practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Elwyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Frosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Joseph-Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kinnersley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Gen Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1361" to="1367" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The illness narratives: Suffering, healing, and the human condition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kleinman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Committee on the Use of Complementary and Alternative Medicine by the American Public. An Ethical Framework for CAM Research, Practice, and Integration</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK83792/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>National Academies Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington (DC; US</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient centeredness, cultural competence and healthcare quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Beach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Natl Med Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1275" to="1285" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implementing shared decision-making: consider all the consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Elwyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Frosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kobrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Implement Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">114</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CONSORT 2025 statement: Updated guideline for reporting randomised trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hopewell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hróbjartsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">388</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
