<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">When Lack of Control Leads to Uncertainty: Explaining the Effect of Anomie on Support for Authoritarianism</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Jasper</forename><surname>Neerdaels</surname></persName>
							<email>jasper.neerdaels@kuleuven.be</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kühne Logistics University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Greifswald</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ali</forename><surname>Teymoori</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bergen</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Tröster</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kühne Logistics University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Niels</forename><surname>Van Quaquebeke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Kühne Logistics University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Political Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Political Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Exeter</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">KU Leuven</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">KU Leuven</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Parkstraat 45 -bus 3602</addrLine>
									<postCode>3000</postCode>
									<settlement>Leuven</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">When Lack of Control Leads to Uncertainty: Explaining the Effect of Anomie on Support for Authoritarianism</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">09779AF3FDA27533C7EC057D6E089AD8</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:55+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>anomie</term>
					<term>authoritarianism</term>
					<term>control</term>
					<term>uncertainty</term>
					<term>leadership</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Studies have shown that anomie, i.e., the perception that a society's leadership and social fabric are breaking down, is a central predictor of individuals' support for authoritarianism.</p><p>However, causal evidence for this relationship is missing. Moreover, previous studies are ambiguous regarding the mediating mechanism and lack empirical tests for the same. Against this background, we derive a set of integrative hypotheses: First, we argue that perceptions of anomie lead to a perceived lack of political control. The repeated failure to exert control in the political sphere leads to feelings of uncertainty about the functioning and meaning of the political world. This uncertainty heightens people's susceptibility to authoritarianism because, we argue, the latter promises a sense of order, meaning, and the guidance of a 'strong leader'.</p><p>We support our hypothesis in a large-scale field study with a representative sample of the German population (N = 1504), while statistically ruling out alternative explanations. Adding internal validity, we provide causal evidence for each path in our sequential mediation hypothesis in three preregistered, controlled experiments (conducted in the U.S., total N = 846). Our insights may support policymakers in addressing the negative political consequences of anomie.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Authoritarianism is on the rise. In Europe alone, support for authoritarian leaders has more than doubled since the 1960s, while their parties' share of seats in parliaments has tripled <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">(Norris &amp; Inglehart, 2019)</ref>. A large body of theoretical and empirical work suggests that a central predictor of people's support for authoritarianism is anomie (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Fromm, 1941;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Merton, 1938;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Scheepers et al., 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sprong et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Srole, 1956)</ref>, a social condition characterized by the perceived deregulation and disintegration of the normative structure of society <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>The literature hints at two potential explanatory mechanisms for why anomie may lead to authoritarianism, defined as a preference for oneness, sameness, and group cohesion <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Duckitt, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Stenner, 2005)</ref>, however, no empirical test exists. Some claim that anomie leads to a perceived lack of political control (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b116">Zhelnina, 2020)</ref>, i.e., an enduring loss of influence over political processes or outcomes <ref type="bibr">(Kofta et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref>, which in turn may increase support for authoritarianism as a compensatory control mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Kay et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Landau et al., 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Other scholars speculate that perceptions of anomie come with political uncertainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Chang &amp; Arkin, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Swader, 2017)</ref>, i.e., the feeling that the political world is confusing, unpredictable, and meaningless <ref type="bibr">(Kofta et al., 2020)</ref>, which may increase support for authoritarianism because the latter functions as a psychological sense-making mechanism (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Jost et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b114">Womick et al., 2019</ref>). However, these potential explanations have largely treated lack of control and uncertainty as independent, ignoring the fact that typically they are causally related <ref type="bibr">(Weary et al., 2010)</ref>. Furthermore, previous conceptualizations have confounded the concepts anomie, uncertainty, and lack of control (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Blank, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Heydari et al., 2012)</ref>. And in any case, previous evidence on the effect of anomie on authoritarianism was merely correlational, rendering causal claims impossible (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Sprong et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Heydari et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Lutterman &amp; Middleton, 1970)</ref>.</p><p>With the present paper, we seek to settle the debate and integrate these two streams of research to explain the effect of anomie on authoritarianism. To do so, we disentangle anomie from its previously confounded psychological consequences, lack of political control and uncertainty, and provide experimental tests that allow causal inferences. Conceptually, and contrary to the previous explanations, we show that the two psychological mechanisms of perceived lack of control and uncertainty are inextricably intertwined in a sequential mediation.</p><p>Our arguments are rooted in the Causal Uncertainty Model <ref type="bibr" target="#b107">(Weary &amp; Edwards, 1994)</ref> which postulates that constant feelings of lack of control lead individuals to feel uncertain regarding the operating principles of the social world. Individuals seek to avoid this highly distressing uncertainty, for example by searching for sense-making strategies rendering the world more predictable <ref type="bibr">(Weary et al., 2010)</ref>. Following this logic, we argue that anomie leads to a pervasive feeling that one cannot make an impact on the political process or achieve one's political goals, hence a lack of political control <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ådnanes, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Bjarnason, 2009)</ref>. This repeated failure to exert control further leads to the perception that one can neither understand nor predict political matters, thus causing political uncertainty <ref type="bibr">(Edwards &amp; Weary, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b107">Weary &amp; Edwards, 1994)</ref>. Attempting to escape this aversive uncertainty, individuals show heightened support for authoritarianism, which promises a sense of predictability, structure, and meaning by providing a belief system with a rigid worldview, clear social rules, and the guidance of a 'strong leader <ref type="bibr">' (e.g., De Hoogh et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Jost et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b114">Womick et al., 2019)</ref>.</p><p>We test our sequential mediation hypothesis in a series of studies-including an analysis of representative German survey data and three preregistered experiments testing each link of the hypothesized model to establish causal evidence for the hypothesized mediated pathway. While doing so, we also test for other sensible pathways.</p><p>Altogether, we conceptually integrate previous contradicting notions that have explained this effect either via a lack of control or feelings of uncertainty (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abse &amp; Jessner, 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Betz, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Calhoun, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref>, but to the best of our knowledge, by way of our study designs, we are the first to empirically show that, and why, anomie leads to authoritarianism. Notably, in doing so, we also disentangle anomie from its previously confounded psychological consequences and thus advance our understanding of this construct. Theoretically speaking, by showing that political uncertainty is directly related to support for authoritarianism, the present paper supports notions that view authoritarianism as a psychological security and sense-making mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Jost et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b114">Womick et al., 2019)</ref>. At the same time, the present conceptual framework favors an indirect effect of perceived lack of control on authoritarianism via uncertainty rather than a direct effect. This suggests that authoritarianism is (only) a compensatory control mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Friesen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Kay et al., 2008)</ref> because it addresses the uncertainty that typically results from feelings of lack of control. As such, the present research also may feature practical utility for policymakers and civic actors who need an understanding of why anomie leads to support for authoritarianism to craft effective countermeasures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Effect of Anomie on Support for Authoritarianism</head><p>In this study, we define authoritarianism as a general preference for oneness, sameness, and intense group cohesion over individual freedom and autonomy <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Duckitt, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Stenner, 2005)</ref>. While this conceptualization aligns with the concept of Right-Wing Authoritarianism (RWA; <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Altemeyer, 1996)</ref> and its attitudinal clusters conventionalism, submission, and aggression, unlike actual RWA, this definition does not conflate authoritarianism with its consequences, such as prejudice or intolerance <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Duckitt, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Stenner, 2005)</ref>. Thus, the present definition of authoritarianism refers to a general authoritarian tendency but is not restricted to a political spectrum such as right-or left-wing.</p><p>Authoritarianism has been characterized as a psychological reaction to various forms of threat (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Asbrock &amp; Fritsche, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Doty et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Mirisola et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">Neerdaels et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Oesterreich, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b87">Sales, 1972</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b88">Sales, , 1973))</ref>. This reaction can take various forms, such as heightened submission to authoritarian leaders and regimes, hostility, and aggression toward 'deviants', or orientation toward conformity (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Duckitt, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Oesterreich, 2005)</ref>. As such, the authoritarian reaction can be situationally evoked as a "flight into security" in response to a perceived threat <ref type="bibr">(Oesterreich, 2005, p. 275</ref>; see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Arendt, 1973)</ref>, for example, by providing a sense of certainty and meaning <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(De Hoogh et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b115">Womick et al., 2022)</ref>.</p><p>A central "threat" factor that fosters support for authoritarianism is argued to be people's sense of anomie <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Blank, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">McDill, 1961;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Scheepers et al., 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sprong et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Srole, 1956)</ref>. Originally a sociological concept, anomie refers to a state of a society undergoing drastic social and/or political changes characterized by deregulation and disintegration of the normative structure in society <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Durkheim et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Hartwich &amp; Becker, 2019)</ref>. Psychologically, anomie refers to the perception that the normative structure of society, i.e., its social fabric and leadership, is breaking down <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Scholars have frequently examined the effect of anomie on authoritarianism, with most studies showing a medium-size effect (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Alietti &amp; Padovan, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Blank, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Dekker &amp; Ester, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Heydari et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Lutterman &amp; Middleton, 1970;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Scheepers et al., 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sprong et al., 2019)</ref>. However, theoretical and methodological problems with the extant literature render previous findings ambiguous. First, all the abovementioned evidence is correlational, which makes it possible that unobserved third or confounded variables drive the detected relationship between anomie and authoritarianism, or that the relationship is reversed such that authoritarianism leads to anomie. Second, we do not know why anomie would lead to authoritarianism, limiting theoretical understanding and the development of effective interventions to mitigate the rise of authoritarianism.</p><p>Theoretically, scholars have proposed two general reasons for why anomie has an effect on authoritarianism -uncertainty and a lack of control (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Frankl et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Fromm, 1941;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Swader, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b116">Zhelnina, 2020)</ref>. However, there is a lack of empirical evidence examining these mechanisms. Moreover, previous scholars have confounded anomie with these two (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Blank, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Heydari et al., 2012)</ref>. For instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Heydari et al. (2012)</ref> reported a direct effect of anomie on authoritarianism using a scale that measured anomie in terms of feelings of personal uncertainty and perceived powerlessness regarding state institutions, thus conflating anomie with feelings of lack of political control and uncertainty. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Blank (2003)</ref> measured anomie using items tapping into uncertainty, for example, "Nowadays, I do not comprehend what really happens." <ref type="bibr">(Blank, 2003, p. 273)</ref>.</p><p>Accordingly, the goal of the present research is to theoretically and methodologically disentangle anomie from its confounding factors and examine whether and through which psychological mechanisms anomie leads to authoritarianism. In the following, we discuss the two proposed central mechanisms in more detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lack of Political Control and Political Uncertainty as Possible Mechanisms:</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Similarities and Differences</head><p>Both concepts of lack of political control and uncertainty reflect an aversive state of arousal, resulting from a deficit in an important area of life: A deficit in agency (lack of control) and a deficit in understanding (uncertainty), both of which have been related to fundamental human needs <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Greenaway et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kofta et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">Proulx, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b113">Williams, 2009)</ref>. Both domains, i.e., the ability to exert control and to understand and predict, are fundamental to human existence because, ultimately, they are prerequisites to survival <ref type="bibr">(Weary et al., 2010)</ref>.</p><p>However, differentiating lack of control and uncertainty is important, for several reasons. Most importantly, they represent different fundamental human needs, whose deprivation has very different consequences: Lack of political control signals a threat to our innate need to control, i.e., to be able to reach our goals and to avoid undesired consequences <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Greenaway et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kofta et al., 2020)</ref>. Political uncertainty threatens the fundamental need for predictability, knowledge, and a shared reality and thus signals a sense-making deficit <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Greenaway et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kofta et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Kruglanski &amp; Orehek, 2012)</ref>. Accordingly, these two affective responses require fundamentally different efforts to reduce them and, by extension, to reduce support for authoritarianism. Thus, it's important to understand which of the two factors explains the effect of anomie on support for authoritarianism. First, we will review the literature discussing how each, a lack of political control and uncertainty, explains the effect of anomie on authoritarianism, including our concerns with these models. Then, we will present our theoretical integration, a sequential mediation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Political Uncertainty as Potential Psychological Mechanism Behind Anomie's Effect on</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Authoritarianism</head><p>Scholars have offered several theoretical arguments for why uncertainty explains the effect of anomie on support for authoritarianism: According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Swader (2017)</ref>, perceptions of anomie lead to uncertainty about societal values and norms, prompting individuals to seek structure, meaning, and certainty through authoritarian regimes. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Moghaddam (2019)</ref> ties the rise in autocracy to living in an "age of uncertainty" (p. 1). <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Calhoun (1988;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Elchardus &amp; Spruyt, 2016)</ref> links support for populism to a need for predictability during disruptive times, while <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Betz (1990)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Heitmeyer (1997)</ref> explain the rise of authoritarianism in Germany during the 80s and 90s through uncertainty caused by the shifting European political landscape.</p><p>However, we argue that aforementioned notions discussing the link between anomie, uncertainty, and authoritarianism are overlooking how anomie impairs one's ability to act: Social psychological studies on threat suggest that various types of broader social and economic instabilities, social change, or existential threats have psychological consequences because they create a sense of loss of control <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Fritsche et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Greenaway et al., 2014)</ref>. Hence, anomie, as a particular type of societal instability, primarily compromises the sense of control. The constant experience of control loss then almost inevitably leads to the sense that one can neither understand nor predict political events <ref type="bibr">(Weary et al., 2010)</ref>:</p><p>Political uncertainty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lack of Political Control as a Potential Psychological Mechanism Behind Anomie's</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effect on Authoritarianism</head><p>Major theories of anomie highlight its impact on control. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Durkheim (2005)</ref> described how rapid societal change leads to feelings of helplessness, while <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Merton (1938)</ref> linked anomie to the failure to achieve societal goals, fostering hopelessness. Later scholars echoed this view: <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Bjarnason (2009)</ref> discussed anomie's effect on the inability to influence one's environment. Empirical studies conducted in the U.S. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Geis &amp; Ross, 1998)</ref> and Bulgaria <ref type="bibr">(Ådnanes, 2007)</ref> found that individuals in disorderly, anomic environments perceive less control over their lives.</p><p>Most individuals find lack of control highly distressing and want to avoid it (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Friesen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Guinote et al., 2006)</ref>. When people lose their sense of control, they turn to strategies to regain it, even in domains that are unrelated to the control-reducing event. For instance, a sense of lost control results in a heightened desire for hierarchy <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Friesen et al., 2014)</ref> and authorities, like God or the government (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Kay et al., 2008)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Kay and colleagues (2008)</ref> argue that perceiving the world as uncontrollable is related to anxiety, which can then be alleviated by hierarchy and authority (as they provide a sense of structure and societal order).</p><p>Following this reasoning, several authors indicate that a lack of control could explain the effect of anomie on authoritarianism. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abse and Jessner (1962)</ref> argued that authoritarian leadership alleviates the helplessness evoked by anomie. Similarly, <ref type="bibr">Teymoori and colleagues (2017)</ref> contended that perceptions of anomie can threaten individuals' fundamental need for control, which in turn heightens their endorsement of control-restoring ideologies and authoritarian reactions. Finally, qualitative evidence from Russia indicates that support for authoritarianism can be explained by a perceived lack of control in the political sphere, stemming from perceptions of anomie <ref type="bibr" target="#b116">(Zhelnina, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Amidst this evidence for a relationship between anomie and a lack of control, we nevertheless have reasons to doubt a direct relationship between a lack of control and support for authoritarianism. First, while most approaches advocating such a relationship are merely theoretical or anecdotal <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b116">Zhelnina, 2020)</ref>, the empirical evidence is inconclusive. Some studies have found evidence indicating a relationship between lack of control and constructs related to authoritarianism (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Kay et al., 2008)</ref>, but others have not <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">(Nicol, 2007)</ref>. Second, conceptually, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Altemeyer (1998)</ref> suggested that authoritarianism is unlikely to be a reaction to control deprivation because submitting to authority rather insinuates giving up control. Accordingly, seminal studies on authoritarianism find the construct of authoritarianism unrelated to the desire to exert control <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Altemeyer, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Duriez &amp; Van Hiel, 2002)</ref>. Finally, and perhaps most importantly, some of the works that advanced support for authority (like hierarchy, god, or the government) as a compensatory control mechanism seem to have argued for an indirect effect via uncertainty (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Kay et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Landau et al., 2015)</ref>. For example, <ref type="bibr">Kay and colleagues (2008)</ref> suggest that when people experience lower levels of control, they are increasingly likely to desire authorities, like god or the government, due to a longing for "clear rules, guidelines, norms, and structure" as well as a sense of "order" (p. 21). Arguably, such wording is more descriptive of uncertainty than a lack of control, as political uncertainty specifically refers to a perceived lack of structure and order in the political world, coupled with a sense of confusion about political affairs and events (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Kofta et al., 2020)</ref>. This potential confound, we argue, allows for another interpretation of the results found in studies on compensatory control: A lack of control increases submission to authorities because it leads to uncertainty. The work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Agroskin and Jonas (2010)</ref> supports this notion by providing correlational evidence showing that a lack of political control had an indirect effect on right-wing authoritarianism via the need for cognitive closure, which, the authors argued, signals a high need to reduce uncertainty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Our Hypothesis: A Sequential Mediation Mechanism</head><p>While previous notions argue for either lack of control or uncertainty explaining the effect of anomie on authoritarianism, we theorize a sequential mediation in that a lack of political control caused by anomie can lead to a feeling of political uncertainty, which in turn heightens susceptibility to authoritarianism and its promises of psychological certainty and meaning <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Jost et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b114">Womick et al., 2019)</ref>. To support our argument, we refer to the Causal Uncertainty Model <ref type="bibr">(Edwards &amp; Weary, 1998)</ref>, as it helps to clarify the relationship between these two mediators. According to this model, the repeated and pervasive feeling of control loss leads to uncertainty: An individual who repeatedly fails to exert control and reach their goals in the social world, despite trying, is likely to start questioning their ability to understand what is going on around them, how the social world functions, and feel uncertain about what the future may bring <ref type="bibr">(Edwards &amp; Weary, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">Weary et al., 2010)</ref>. As uncertainty is a highly aversive experience, individuals will go to great lengths to reduce these feelings, looking for strategies to render the world more understandable, coherent, and predictable.</p><p>We argue that the context of anomie leads to a pervasive sense of lacking political control <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ådnanes, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Bjarnason, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Geis &amp; Ross, 1998)</ref> because the fragmentation of society, a shared sense of apathy, and distorted communication hampers the ability of the public to work toward common political goals <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Habermas, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Katz, 1983)</ref>. At the same time, the perceived inability and ineffectiveness of the political establishment make it seem impossible to achieve sustainable change <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>The repeated failure to exert control in the political sphere should produce a sense of political uncertainty for several reasons. First, the perception that one cannot exert political influence leads to uncertainty regarding one's understanding of the causes of political events, relations, and decisions <ref type="bibr">(Weary et al., 2010)</ref>. A person who repeatedly feels unable to get something done politically is eventually going to question their ability to understand how anything gets done in the political realm, for example, what the causes are behind political events and how political decisions are made. Supporting this notion, a range of studies on the causal uncertainty model shows how feelings of lack of control heighten uncertainty regarding one's understanding of causal relationships (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Weary et al., 2010)</ref> or solutions to tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Kofta &amp; Sedek, 1999)</ref>.</p><p>Second, lack of political control leads to political uncertainty because it makes it hard to predict the political future: Being constantly unable to exert political control is likely leading to the conclusion that political control is in the hands of others, perhaps even unknown forces. And what these others want, what their goals are, and what they will do in the future, is likely perceived as uncertain. This notion is supported by a body of research on learned helplessness, which suggests that feeling a lack of control is related to a perceived inability to predict the future <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Burger &amp; Arkin, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b90">Seligman, 1975)</ref> and, accordingly, leads to increased belief in precognition, likely to attenuate the unpredictability caused by a lack of control <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Greenaway et al., 2013)</ref>. In the same vein, the literature in developmental psychology on harsh environments shows that a lack of control over one's immediate environment shifts one's attention to the uncertainty of the present and leads to a perceived difficulty in predicting the future <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Frankenhuis et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Finally, in general, lack of political control leads to uncertainty because it makes people skeptical and confused about the general meaning and purpose of politics. Research suggests that individuals tend to question the meaning of events they have no control over <ref type="bibr">(e.g., Hohmann &amp; Hogg, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Newcomb &amp; Harlow, 1986)</ref>. This is especially likely in a political, democratic context, as we attach moral and ethical expectations to political institutions. Political leaders that seem detached from, and indifferent to, the will of citizens are, therefore, likely perceived as meaningless and senseless. Supporting this notion, studies show that lack of control is related to perceived meaninglessness in life <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">(Newcomb &amp; Harlow, 1986</ref>) and leads to illusory pattern recognition, reflecting a heightened desire for meaning and certainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b111">(Whitson &amp; Galinsky, 2008)</ref>.</p><p>Uncertainty, in turn, will heighten individuals' susceptibility to authoritarianism for several reasons, as we argue: Authoritarianism promises order, structure, and clarity by establishing social hierarchies and clear differentiation between in-and outgroups <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Jost et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b114">Womick et al., 2019)</ref>. Moreover, authoritarianism offers a sense of guidance via a moral framework, norms and convention, and 'strong' leadership. At the same time, the ideology of authoritarianism encompasses clear ideas on how society should function, which may further reduce uncertainty about the future. Altogether, the perceived psychological benefits of order, guidance, and predictability may lead individuals to voluntarily trade freedom for an authoritarian regime <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Arendt, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Fromm, 1941;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b91">Schwartz, 2000)</ref>. Empirical evidence supports this notion, showing that authoritarianism is associated with a heightened need for cognitive closure and structure, cognitive rigidity, low tolerance of ambiguity, and pervasive feelings of uncertainty (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Jost et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Frenkel-Brunswik, 1949;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Kemmelmeier, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>In summary, reviewing extant theorizing and empirical results, we argue that a lack of political control and political uncertainty will sequentially mediate the effect of perceived anomie on support for authoritarianism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis:</head><p>The effect of perceived anomie on support for authoritarianism is sequentially mediated by a lack of political control and political uncertainty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Overview</head><p>We tested our hypothesis in four studies following a full research cycle <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Mortensen &amp; Cialdini, 2010)</ref>. This involves identifying a real-world phenomenon with societal relevance and then examining the model's elements in controlled, experimental environments.</p><p>Therefore, we first test the hypothesized effect in a field study with high external validity, using a sample representative of the German population (Study 1). Subsequently, we validate these results in a controlled, experimental setting to explore the phenomenon with high internal validity. To this end, we ran a series of three preregistered experiments with U.S. participants (Studies 2-4) to generate causal evidence for our hypothesized sequential mediation model <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">(Spencer et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Stone-Romero &amp; Rosopa, 2008)</ref>. We can claim evidence for a causal mediation effect when the independent variable (X) has an effect on the measured first mediator (M1) (see Study 2), the manipulated first mediator (M1*) affects the measured second mediator (M2) (Study 3), and the manipulated second mediator (M2*) has an effect on the DV (Study 4) <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(Pirlott &amp; MacKinnon, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b93">Spencer et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Stone-Romero &amp; Rosopa, 2008)</ref>. Additionally, evidence for the causal mediation effect is provided when manipulation checks show an effect of each manipulated construct on the same scale that was used to measure that same construct in the previous experiment. This indicates that the operationalization of each construct, whether manipulated or measured, is similar <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">(Spencer et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Stone-Romero &amp; Rosopa, 2008)</ref>.</p><p>All procedures presented throughout the manuscript (Studies 1-4) comply with the current APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct. We report all manipulations, measures, and exclusions in the respective studies and follow JARS <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Appelbaum et al., 2018)</ref>. Studies 2-4 were preregistered (see links in respective sections). All data, analysis code, and research materials are available here: <ref type="bibr">[link]</ref>. We managed all data using the software package Stata 15 <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">(StataCorp., 2017)</ref> and performed mediation analyses following recommendations by <ref type="bibr">Hayes and Preacher (2014)</ref> and used the STATA syntax provided by <ref type="bibr">UCLA: Statistical Consulting Group (2021a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b105">, 2021b)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 1 (Field Data): Testing our Hypothesis in a Panel Survey</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Representative of the German Population</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>Sample. To test our hypothesis in a natural environment, we analyzed data from the German General Social Survey (ALLBUS; GESIS -Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften, 2011). The ALLBUS is a study surveying the attitudes, behaviors, and social structure of German residents. Data for the ALLBUS are collected every two years and are representative of the German population. To ensure representativity, the sampling process encompasses two stages: First, German municipalities are selected with a probability proportional to their number of adult residents. In the second sample stage, individual persons are randomly selected from the municipal registers of residents. The data for our variables of interest were available for the year 2006 (GESIS -Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften, 2011). Data and codebook can be downloaded via the following link: <ref type="url" target="https://search.gesis.org/research_data/ZA4500">https://search.gesis.org/research_data/ZA4500</ref>. See Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> for an overview of the descriptive statistics and correlations for our study variables. Our total sample consisted of 1,504 participants with a mean age of 49.70 years, SD = 17.39. The average household monthly net income reported was €2087.14, SD = 1246.23. Of the participants, 52% were women, 62% were married, and 11% reported having a university degree. Since the items measuring authoritarianism were only presented to German citizens in the ALLBUS, all of the participants in the present sample have German citizenship.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Support for Authoritarianism. The ALLBUS study of 2006 includes two items designed to measure authoritarianism. These items are part of the Authoritarianism Short Form <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Hübner et al., 1997)</ref>, a scale designed to measure general authoritarianism while building on <ref type="bibr">Adorno and colleagues (2019)</ref>. The items present in the ALLBUS are: "We should be grateful for our leaders who can tell us exactly what we should do and when" and "Generally, it is beneficial for a child later in life if it is being forced to adapt to its parents' views." Participants are asked to indicate their agreement on a scale ranging from 1 (not at all) to 7 (completely, a = .45).</p><p>Anomie. The ALLBUS data of 2006 contained four items measuring anomie that are based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">Srole's (1956)</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lack of Political Control.</head><p>In the present data, lack of political control was measured via two items designed to assess "respondents' belief in the effect of their own political participation on the government's actions" <ref type="bibr">(Bechert &amp; Quandt, 2009, p. 81)</ref>. Participants were asked to indicate their agreement on a 5-point scale (1 = do not agree at all; 5 = completely agree). The items were "People like me don't have any say about what the government does" and "The average citizen has considerable influence on politics" (reverse scored, a = .52) 1 .</p><p>Political Uncertainty. In the present data, political uncertainty was measured via two items which were designed to measure participants' "understanding of politics <ref type="bibr">[and]</ref> personal level of information, compared to others" <ref type="bibr">(Bechert &amp; Quandt, 2009, pp. 83-84)</ref>. Participants are asked to indicate their agreement on a 5-point scale (1 = do not agree at all; 5 = completely agree). The items: "I feel that I have a pretty good understanding of the important political issues facing our country" (reverse scored) and "I think most of the people are better informed about politics and government than I am" (a = .60) 1 .</p><p>1 To test the adequacy of these proxy items, we ran a preregistered study (Supplemental Material A) and compared them to an established scale by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref> that we also used in Studies 2 and 3. The results indicated that participants did not discriminate between these items and the scale used by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref>.</p><p>Covariates. We included several variables that are likely to be correlated with anomie and/or authoritarianism that could bias our findings. We controlled for income (household monthly net income) and education (measured as the highest level of education) because of these variables' negative relationship with anomie (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Heydari et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b89">Scheepers et al., 1992)</ref>. Furthermore, we controlled for citizenship (German only versus several citizenships, as a proxy for an ethnic group) and gender because studies indicate that (some) ethnic minorities <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Henry, 2011)</ref> and women are more likely to be authoritarian, the latter especially in societies with high gender inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Brandt &amp; Henry, 2012)</ref>. We also included age as a covariate because of its positive relationship with authoritarianism <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">(Ruffman et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Finally, we controlled for political views (left versus right) as a potential predictor of support for authoritarianism <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Altemeyer, 1996)</ref>. We conducted analyses with and without these covariates and found no major influence on the magnitude or pattern of effects. We therefore present all results for Study 1 including the covariates. Results excluding covariates can be found in the Supplemental Material B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>To facilitate interpretation and comparison between coefficients, we standardized all continuous independent variables. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> summarizes the correlations and descriptive statistics of unstandardized study variables. We detected no multivariate outliers when using the BACON method <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Billor et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">software by Weber, 2010)</ref>. We used weights provided by the ALLBUS (GESIS -Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften, 2011) to account for the oversampling of participants from East Germany. To test our hypothesis, we interpreted the 95% bias-corrected confidence intervals from 10,000 bootstrapping samples. This indicated a significant indirect relationship between perceived anomie and support for authoritarianism via, sequentially, lack of control in the political sphere and political uncertainty (b = 0.007, 95% CI = [0.002, 0.01]). The calculation of completely standardized effects <ref type="bibr">(Hayes, 2013)</ref> indicated a small effect size of 0.005 <ref type="bibr">(Preacher &amp; Kelley, 2011)</ref>. See Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> for an overview of path coefficients. In summary, we found support for our hypothesis.</p><p>Importantly, however, as Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows, there was no significant relationship between anomie and support for authoritarianism directly. This evidence, of course, is merely correlational. In order to clarify the relationship between anomie and authoritarianism via causal evidence, we sought to test this effect in a subsequent experiment. Study 1: Path Model Depicting the Regression Coefficients of the Hypothesized Model: The Effect of Perceptions of Anomie on Support for Authoritarianism Sequentially Mediated by Lack of Political Control and Political Uncertainty Perception of Anomie Support for Authoritarianism Political Uncertainty Lack of Political Control b = 0.26 SE = 0.02 p &lt; .001 η2 = 0.08 b = 0.11 SE = 0.03 p &lt; .001 η2 = 0.02 b = 0.23 SE = 0.05 p &lt; .001 η2 = 0.02  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 2 (Experiment): The Effect of Anomie on Lack of Political Control</head><p>Study 1 found correlational evidence for our hypothesized model using survey data, thus establishing external validity. For Study 2, our goal was to provide causal evidence for the total effect of anomie on authoritarianism as well as for the first path of the hypothesized model, the effect of anomie on lack of political control. This study was preregistered <ref type="bibr">[link]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>Sample. Following a power analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Faul et al., 2007)</ref>, we recruited 558 participants to detect an effect of f = .17 (of anomie on support for authoritarianism, as detected in a previous study<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> ) at α &lt; .05 with 95% power. Participants were recruited via Prolific and received a compensation of $0.77. Participants had to be at least 21 years old to ensure a community sample with increased representativity, as students are overrepresented on Prolific in the 18-20 age group <ref type="bibr" target="#b112">(Wild et al., 2022)</ref>. Additionally, due to the study's focus on U.S.</p><p>social and political issues, participants had to be U.S. citizens and native English speakers.</p><p>We excluded 15 participants for failing an attention check. In the final sample, consisting of 543 participants, the average age was 42.31 years, SD = 13.22; of those participants, 271 identified as female, 265 as male, and 7 as 'other'; 56% reported being married; 9% reported being unemployed; 67% identified as White and 60% held a university degree. The reported median household income category was $55,001-$65,000. See Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> for a complete overview of the study variables and demographics across conditions.</p><p>Procedure. After participants had agreed to a study consent form and had read a short welcome note, they were randomly assigned to one of three conditions. The design followed a one-factor (high vs. low anomie vs. control condition) between-subjects design. Afterward, participants filled in scales measuring lack of political control and support for authoritarianism. After that, they reported their demographics (age, gender, education, employment status, marital status, household income, political leaning (right-versus leftwing), and ethnic group).</p><p>Manipulation of Perception of Anomie. Building on previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Duckitt &amp; Fisher, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Hartwich &amp; Becker, 2019)</ref>, we manipulated the perception of anomie by asking participants to read a vignette describing the society of the United States 10 years into the future (Supplemental Material C). In all conditions, we then asked participants to write down a few sentences on how they imagined this future society.</p><p>Following our conceptualization of anomie as perceived deregulation and disintegration of society, the text in the high-anomie condition described the United States as a society with a disintegrating social fabric and ineffective political leadership 10 years from now and reversed the wording for the low-anomie condition. Both experimental conditions were carefully worded in alignment with the theoretical construct <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2016</ref><ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., , 2017))</ref>, so that they would only manipulate participants' perceptions of society, but not unintentionally manipulate other constructs. Here is an excerpt of the manipulation text: "It seems like society is falling apart. There are no more moral standards to follow, and people do not seem to care about what is right and wrong. (…) [P]olitical leaders and their policies are generally perceived as illegitimate."</p><p>In the low-anomie condition, by contrast, the future U.S. was described as a highly In order to examine baseline levels of anomie, we included a control condition which consisted of a neutral vignette (of similar length as the experimental conditions) describing the architecture of the future United States. However, importantly, perceptions of anomie (and, by extension, political uncertainty and lack of political control) are context-sensitive <ref type="bibr">(Sprong et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref> and, therefore, likely to fluctuate considerably.</p><p>This makes the measurements of these baselines in the control conditions likely to vary extensively, too. For this reason, we tested our hypothesis by comparing the high-versus the low-experimental conditions in all experimental studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Support for Authoritarianism. We measured support for authoritarianism with a scale designed by <ref type="bibr">Sprong and</ref><ref type="bibr">colleagues (2019, validated by Lima et al., 2021)</ref> to assess a "wish for a strong leader." The scale consists of seven items using a 7-point response format</p><p>(1 = strongly disagree to 7 = strongly agree). The scale has a good internal consistency (a =</p><p>.92) in our study and includes the following: "America needs a strong leader who is willing to challenge democratic values and practices."</p><p>We chose this scale for several reasons: In order to avoid confounding authoritarianism with (conservative) political orientation, recent scholars have favored measuring (support for) authoritarianism as the desire for, and readiness to submit to, antidemocratic regimes, such as a 'strong leader' <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">(Nilsson &amp; Jost, 2020)</ref>. This is also in line with the situational account of authoritarian reactions, which posits that specific social perceptions, such as a perceived threat, lead individuals to rely on strategies for a "flight into security" (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Oesterreich, 2005, p. 275)</ref>. This approach considers a general form of authoritarian reaction beyond individuals' political belief systems. Moreover, the unconditional submission to a 'strong leader', who is decidedly undemocratic and thus likely to limit the freedom of their supporters, clearly reflects a preference for group cohesion and sameness at the expense of individual freedom and autonomy -the definition of authoritarianism used throughout the manuscript <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Duckitt, 1989)</ref>.</p><p>Lack of Political Control. We measured lack of political control with a scale developed by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref>. The scale consists of four items asking participants for their agreement with several statements on a 5-point scale (1 = strongly disagree; 5 = strongly agree). An example question: "People like me have no control over government actions" (a = .93).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manipulation Check</head><p>Following recommendations <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Fayant et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Hauser et al., 2018)</ref>, we conducted a manipulation check with an independent sample (N = 94) on Prolific. In this way, we sought to avoid the risk of the manipulation check itself exerting an additional manipulation or demand effect. We randomly assigned participants to one of the three experimental conditions used in the main study. Participants then rated the level of perceived anomie using the Perceived Anomie Scale (PAS; <ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2016)</ref>. This scale operationalizes this concept as individuals' perception that society is breaking down in terms of its regulatory structure and its social fabric <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2016)</ref>. These aspects relate to a higher-order factor about the generalized perception that the normative structure of society is breaking down <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref>. This robust higher-order factor has been empirically shown across diverse social settings <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>The PAS <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2016)</ref> has 12 items: Half deal with the breakdown of leadership (i.e., its perceived illegitimacy and ineffectiveness) and the other half concern the breakdown of the social fabric (i.e., the interpersonal distrust and confusion around moral standards). All items were measured on a 7-point scale (1 = strongly disagree; 7 = strongly agree), with a higher score indicating higher perceived anomie. Sample items are: "Politicians don't care about the problems of the average person" and "Most of the people think that if something works, it doesn't really matter whether it is right or wrong" (a = .95). The results of an ANOVA test indicated that there was a significant overall effect of the manipulation on Generally, we suspect that feelings of anomie are rather context-sensitive and likely to vary substantially in the current climate of frequent controversies and intense polarization in U.S.</p><p>politics. However, while the baseline of anomie appears relatively low in this sample, the present results show that we successfully manipulated high levels of anomie.</p><p>Together, the present results provide support for the validity and efficacy of the manipulation used in Study 2<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">foot_1</ref> . However, given the likely content overlap between the constructs that were manipulated in Studies 2-4 (perceived anomie, lack of political control, and political uncertainty), we ran an additional, extended manipulation check in order to uncover unexpected confounding which may result in alternative explanations for our results</p><p>(Supplemental Material E). We found no indication of confounding beyond the intended effects of the three manipulations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis testing. Table 2 depicts all descriptive statistics for all unstandardized</head><p>variables in Study 2. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> shows the correlation coefficients of unstandardized variables across conditions. We detected no multivariate outliers when using the BACON method <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Billor et al., 2000</ref>; software by <ref type="bibr" target="#b109">Weber, 2010)</ref>. There was a significant overall effect of the In summary, the results show that higher anomie leads to more lack of political control and support for authoritarianism than low anomie, therefore indicating first support of our hypothesis.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">foot_2</ref>  Notes. a Measured in 10 categories/steps of $10,000, ranging from 1 (less than $15,000) to 10 (more than $95,000); b No college degree = 0, college degree or higher = 1;</p><p>c Not married = 0, married = 1; d Two items measuring political leaning on social and economic issues, scale ranging from 1 (strongly left) to 7 (strongly right; a = .92).</p><p>Marital Notes. N = 543; *** p &lt; .001, ** p &lt; .01, * p &lt; .05; a Measured in 10 categories/steps of $10,000, ranging from 1 (less than $15,000) to 10 (more than $95,000); b No college degree = 0, college degree or higher = 1; c Not married = 0, married = 1; d Two items measuring political leaning on social and economic issues, scale ranging from 1 (strongly left) to 7 (strongly right; a = .92).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Variables</head><p>(1) (2) (3) (4) (5) (6) (7) (8) (9) (10) (11) (12) (13) (14) (15) (16) (17) (18) (1) Support for authoritarianism 1.000 (2) Political uncertainty .55*** 1.000 (3) Lack of political control .47*** .72*** 1.000 (4) Age in years -.04 .02 -.03 1.000 Gender (5) Female .03 .06 -.03 .12** 1.000 (6) Male -.01 -.05 .02 -.10* -.97*** 1.000 (7) Non-binary -.11* -.03 .01 -.08 -.11** -.11** 1.000 (8) Household income (annual) a -.03 -.03 -.04 .01 .005 .01 -.05 1.000 (9) College degree b -.04 -.003 -.001 -.03 -.06 .06 -.01 .40*** 1.000 (10) Unemployed -.06 -.07 -.05 -.07 -.05 .03 .08 -.25*** -.16*** 1.000 Ethnic group (11) Native/ American Indian .03 0.00 .03 0.00 .03 -.02 -.01 -.10* -.04 -.02 1.000 (12) Asian/Asian American -.03 .02 -.05 -.15*** -.05 .06 -.03 .07 .12** .05 -.02 1.000 (13) Black/African American .22*** .11* .001 -.002 -.06 .07 -.06 .02 .13** -.06 -.04 -.12** 1.000 (14) Hispanic/Latin (a/o/x) -.02 -.01 .01 -.11** -.11** .08 .14*** -.06 -.08 .04 -.02 -.05 -.11* 1.000 (15) Other -.12** -.04 -.02 -.06 -.09* .09* -.01 -.01 -.02 .12** -.01 -.02 -.05 -.02 1.000 (16) White -.16*** -.10* .02 .13** .14** -.14** .01 -.01 -.13** -.01 -.11* -.34*** -.76*** -.30*** -.12** 1.000 (17) Marital status (married) c .01 .03 .06 .23*** .03 -.04 .04 .39*** .13** -.12** -.08 -.08 -.02 -.06 .03 .09* 1.000 (18) Political ideology (rightwing) d .26*** .08 .07 .04 -.09* .11* -.09* .07 -.05 -.11* -.04 -.09* -.002 -.03 -.04 .07 .15*** 1.000</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 3 (Experiment): The Effect of Lack of Political Control on Political Uncertainty</head><p>The results thus far indicate that the effect of anomie on support for authoritarianism is sequentially mediated by lack of political control and uncertainty (Study 1). However, they only provide causal evidence for the model's first path-the effect of anomie perceptions on lack of political control (Study 2). To establish causality for the second path in our hypothesized model (the effect of a lack of political control on political uncertainty), we ran a second experiment (Study 3), which was also preregistered <ref type="bibr">[link]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>Sample. We recruited 171 US participants from Prolific who took part in the study in exchange for $1.50. According to our power analysis, we needed at least 117 participants to detect a medium effect of f² = .15 at α &lt; .05 with 95 % power (we oversampled to account for potential participant dropout). Again, we required all participants to be U.S. citizens, English native speakers, and at least 21 years old. Of the 171 participants, 82 identified as female, 84</p><p>as male, and 4 as non-binary (one participant did not reveal their gender). The average age was 39.19 years, SD = 13.06; 42% reported being married; 7% reported being unemployed; 74% identified as White; and 54% held a university degree. The reported median household income category was $55,001-$65,000. See Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref> for a complete overview of the unstandardized study variables and demographics across conditions.</p><p>Procedure. After participants agreed to a consent form and read a short welcome note, they were randomly assigned to one of three conditions. The design followed a onefactor (high vs. low lack of political control vs. control condition) between-subjects design.</p><p>Participants then filled in a scale measuring political uncertainty. After that, respondents reported their demographics (age, gender, education, employment status, marital status, household income, political leaning (right-versus left-wing), and ethnic group). confounding (lack of) political control with other concepts, we kept the wording between both experimental conditions very similar and made sure to only vary isolated words wherever possible, for example, "…no control over politics…" (high lack of political control condition)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manipulation of</head><p>versus "…much control over politics…" (low lack of political control condition). Similar to Study 2, the control condition consisted of a neutral vignette (of similar length as the experimental conditions) describing the architecture of the future United States. In all conditions, participants were asked to write down a few sentences on how they imagined this future society.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Political Uncertainty. We measured political uncertainty via a scale developed by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref>. The scale consists of four items asking participants for their agreement with several statements on a 5-point scale (1 = strongly disagree; 5 = strongly agree). An example: "Lately it has been hard to understand what politicians want" (a = .88).<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">foot_3</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Manipulation Check. Like in Study 2, we conducted a manipulation check with an independent sample (N = 93). Participants were randomly assigned to one of the three experimental conditions. We measured lack of political control with the same scale used in States heightened these feelings, likely due to the sensitive nature of political control in the current climate of frequent controversies and intense polarization. Thus, while the baseline of lack of political control is high, these results show that we successfully manipulated high levels and low levels of lack of political control.</p><p>Hypothesis testing. Our hypothesis predicted that a lack of control in the political sphere would lead to feelings of political uncertainty. We detected no multivariate outliers when using the BACON method <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Billor et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">software by Weber, 2010)</ref>. The results of an ANOVA indicated an overall effect of the lack of political control manipulation on a complete overview of gathered variables. Notably, these scales were collected sequentially after the focal measures for the present study so that they could not influence present results. In summary, the results of Study 3 provide causal evidence that a higher lack of control leads to more political uncertainty than a lower lack of control, further supporting our hypothesis.  Experiment): The Effect of Political Uncertainty on Support for Authoritarianism Study 2 provided causal evidence for the first path of the hypothesized model, showing that high anomie leads to more lack of control and support for authoritarianism than low anomie. Study 3, in turn, showed that a high lack of political control leads to more political uncertainty than a low lack of political control. Consequentially, Study 4 was designed to provide causal evidence for the final path in our hypothesized model: the effect of political uncertainty on support for authoritarianism. Study 4 was also preregistered [link] 6 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>Sample. According to a power analysis, we needed at least 117 participants to detect a medium effect of f² = .15 at α &lt; .05 with 95 % power. To account for potential dropouts, we recruited 170 participants from Prolific, who received compensation of approximately $0.93.</p><p>Again, we required all participants to be U.S. citizens, English native speakers, and at least 21 years old. One participant was excluded for failing an attention check. In the final sample, consisting of 169 participants, the average age was 41.43 years, SD = 12.87; 82 participants identified as female, 84 as male, and three as non-binary. Furthermore, 50% reported being married, 7% reported being unemployed, 82% identified as White, and 60% held a university degree. The reported median household income category was $55,001-$65,000. See Table <ref type="table">6</ref> for a complete overview of the unstandardized study variables and demographics across conditions and Table <ref type="table">7</ref> for correlations of all unstandardized study variables.</p><p>Procedure. After agreeing to a study consent form and reading a short welcome note, participants were randomly assigned to one of three conditions (high political uncertainty condition, low political uncertainty condition, control condition). The procedure thus, again,</p><p>6 Study 4 was preregistered before data collection. However, the preregistration includes a PDF that contains the names of the authors (which cannot be removed). Therefore, we created an anonymized copy of the original preregistration document (solely for the purpose of peer review), which can be found under the link above. Of course, the original (non-anonymous) preregistration is and stays available to the public.</p><p>utilized a one-factor between-subjects design. After the experimental manipulation, participants completed the scale of the dependent variable (support for authoritarianism).</p><p>Afterward, respondents provided their demographic details (age, gender, education, marital status, annual household income, ethnic group, employment status, and political leaning (leftversus right-wing)).</p><p>Manipulation of Political Uncertainty. Following Studies 2 and 3, we manipulated political uncertainty by asking participants to read a vignette describing the society of the United States 10 years into the future (Supplemental Material I; <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Duckitt &amp; Fisher, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Hartwich &amp; Becker, 2019)</ref>. The vignette closely resembled the political uncertainty scale by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref> used in Study 3 and thus was intended to induce a "lack of certainty about the course of political events and the inability to predict what will happen" <ref type="bibr">(Kofta et al., 2020, p. 901</ref>). An excerpt of high political uncertainty is: "In the United States of the future, the political landscape makes people feel very uncertain. For example, it is very hard to understand what politicians want." In the low political uncertainty condition, the future United States was described as a country where citizens felt very certain about the political landscape: "In the United States of the future, the political landscape makes people feel very certain. For example, it is very easy to understand what politicians want." Again, to ensure comparability between the experimental conditions and avoid confounding political (un)certainty with other concepts, we kept the wording between both experimental conditions very similar and made sure to only vary isolated words wherever possible, for example "…their actions are largely (un)predictable. (…) It is very hard (easy) to comprehend (…)".</p><p>Similar to Studies 2 and 3, the control condition consisted of a vignette describing the architecture of the future United States. In all conditions, participants were asked to write down a few sentences on how they imagined this future society.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Support for Authoritarianism. Like in Studies 2 and 3, we measured support for authoritarianism with the "wish for a strong leader" scale <ref type="bibr">(Sprong et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">a = .90)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Manipulation Check. Like in Studies 2 and 3, we conducted a manipulation check with an independent sample (via the extended manipulation check, see Supplemental Material E; N = 345). Participants were randomly assigned to one of the three experimental conditions.</p><p>We measured political uncertainty with the same scale used in Study 3 <ref type="bibr">(Kofta et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">a = .91)</ref>. The results of an ANOVA indicated that there was a significant overall effect of the Hypothesis testing. Our hypothesis predicted that political uncertainty would directly lead to support for authoritarianism. Again, we detected no multivariate outliers when using the BACON method <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Billor et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">software by Weber, 2010)</ref>. The results of an .013, Cohen's d = 0.58). There was no significant difference between the low and the control condition (p = 1.00). In summary, the results show that higher political uncertainty leads to more support for authoritarianism than low political uncertainty, further supporting our hypothesis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General Test of Alternative Models</head><p>Although we have strong theoretical and empirical reasons to support our sequential mediation hypothesis, using the Causal Uncertainty Model <ref type="bibr">(Weary et al., 2010)</ref> to underpin the psychological mechanisms behind the impact of anomie on authoritarianism, we also examined alternative models and compared their fit to the data with our sequential mediation model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Test of Parallel Mediation</head><p>Since previous, speculative explanations of the effect of anomie on authoritarianism focused on uncertainty (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Elchardus &amp; Spruyt, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b102">Swader, 2017)</ref> or control (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Ådnanes, 2007)</ref> separately, we compared our hypothesized sequential mediation model with a parallel mediation model. Doing so, we followed recommendations <ref type="bibr">(Hayes, 2018)</ref> to test both mediators in the same model, so as to separate spurious and epiphenomenal relationships from potential causal associations. According to <ref type="bibr">Hayes (2018)</ref>, this approach is advisable when potential mediators are correlated, which is the case in Study 1 (r(1502) = .19, p &lt; .001)</p><p>and Study 2 (r(541) = .72, p &lt; .001). Thus, we first conducted parallel mediation analyses that included both political uncertainty and lack of control. Afterward, we aimed to assess whether our hypothesized (sequential mediation) model provided a better fit to the data than the alternative, parallel model. Study 2. Mediation analysis testing the reverse order of mediators yielded no significant results, neither when comparing the high-and the low-anomie condition (b = 0.12, 95% CI = [-0.10, 0.39]), nor when comparing the high-and the control condition (b = 0.04, 95% CI = [-0.03, 0.12]).</p><p>Study 3. Moreover, Study 3 showed no effect of lack of political control on support for authoritarianism [F (2, 168) = 0.26, p = .774], providing causal evidence against a reverse order of mediators and lack of control alone explaining the effect of anomie on authoritarianism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reverse Order of Complete Model</head><p>We also tested the reverse order of the complete model. As indicated in Supplemental Material E, experimental data from our extended manipulation check showed an effect of political uncertainty on lack of political control (b = 0.78, p = .001) and an effect of the latter on anomie (b = 1.04, p &lt; .001). Moreover, mediation analysis using the correlational data from Study 1 indicated a significant indirect effect of authoritarianism on anomie via political uncertainty and lack of political control (b = 0.0009, 95% CI = [0.005, 0.002]).</p><p>In sum, while there is also partial evidence for reverse causality, these results show that the sequential mediation model that we hypothesize was superior to alternative models.</p><p>Moreover, we find that lack of control is not sufficient to explain the link between anomie and support for authoritarianism. Instead, and in line with our hypothesis, lack of control links anomie to uncertainty, meaning that uncertainty but not lack of control is the proximal cause for the link between anomie and support for authoritarianism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transparency and Openness Statement</head><p>Studies 2-4 were preregistered (see links in respective introductory sections). All data, analysis code, and research materials are available here: <ref type="bibr">[link]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 6 911</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Descriptive Statistics for Variables across Conditions in Study 4 912 913</head><p>Notes. a Measured in 10 categories/steps of $10,000, ranging from 1 (less than $15,000) to 10 (more than $95,000); b No college degree = 0, college degree or higher = 1; 914 c Not married = 0, married = 1; d Two items measuring political leaning on social and economic issues, scale ranging from 1 (strongly left) to 7 (strongly right; a = .84).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>915</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Baseline characteristic</head><p>High political uncertainty condition Low political uncertainty condition Control condition Total M SD n % M SD n % M SD n % M SD n % Support for authoritarianism 4.78 1.29 59 4.01 1.60 56 3.99 1.46 54 4.27 1.49 Political uncertainty 3.59 0.98 59 3.39 1.09 56 3.07 1.13 54 3.36 1.08 Age in years 41.03 12.48 59 41.88 13.65 56 41.39 12.68 54 41.43 12.87 Gender Female 30 51 25 45 27 50 49 Male 27 46 30 54 27 50 50 Non-binary 2 3 1 2 0 0 2 Household income (annual) a 6.63 3.15 59 5.63 3.24 56 6.07 3.21 54 6.12 3.21 College degree b 37 63 33 59 32 59 60 Unemployed 2 3 6 11 4 7 7 Ethnic group Asian/Asian American 1 2 2 4 3 6 4 Black/African American 6 10 6 11 4 7 9 Hispanic/Latin(a/o/x) 3 5 2 4 1 2 4 Other 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 White 48 81 45 80 45 83 82 Marital status (married) c 28 47 31 55 26 48 50 Political ideology (right-wing) d 3.31 1.73 59 3.51 1.57 56 3.45 1.79 54 3.42 1.70</p><p>Table 7 Correlations of Unstandardized Variables in Study 4</p><p>Note. N = 169; *** p &lt; .001, ** p &lt; .01, * p &lt; .05; a Measured in 10 categories/steps of $10,000, ranging from 1 (less than $15,000) to 10 (more than $95,000); b No college degree = 0, college degree or higher = 1; c Not married = 0, married = 1; d Two items measuring political leaning on social and economic issues, scale ranging from 1 (strongly left) to 7 (strongly right; a = .84).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Variables</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">(1) (2) (3) (4) (5) (6) (7) (8) (9)<label>(10)</label></formula><p>(11) (12) (13) (14) (15) (1) Support for authoritarianism 1.000 (2) Political uncertainty .26*** 1.000 (3) Age in years -.08 .001 1.000 Gender (4) Female .16* .16* -.05 1.000 (5) Male -.12 -.17* .07 -.97*** 1.000 (6) Other/Nonbinary -.14 .04 -.06 -.13 -.13 1.000 (7) Household income (annual) a -.07 -.06 .10 -.08 .12 -.17* 1.000 (8) College degree b -.05 -.12 -.05 -.06 .08 -.07 .60*** 1.000 (9) Unemployed .04 .04 -.16* -.22** .19* .14 -.16* -.06 1.000 Ethnic group (10) Asian/Asian American -.05 -.10 -.14 -.06 .07 -.03 .11 .16* .07 1.000 (11) Native American -.04 -.02 -.05 -.04 .05 -.02 .15 .11 -.04 -.03 1.000 (12) Black/African American .001 .08 -.05 .09 -.08 -.04 -.07 .01 -.01 -.06 -.04 1.000 (13) Hispanic/Latin (a/o/x) .08 .05 -.12 .01 .001 -.03 .10 .02 -.05 -.04 -.03 -.06 1.000 (14) White -.002 -.03 .18* -.03 .01 .06 -.10 -.13 .01 -.40*** -.28*** -.68*** -.41*** 1.000 (15) Marital status (married) c .01 -.02 .09 .04 -.01 -.14 .39*** .24** -.14 -.07 .13 -.04 .06 -.01 1.000 (16) Political ideology (right-wing) d .16* .06 .11 -.13 .15* -.07 -.02 -.01 .09 -.12 .05 -.07 -.07 .13 -.002</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theoretical Contributions</head><p>The present paper illuminates the effect of anomie on authoritarianism in several ways. First, while previous evidence on this effect was merely correlational, we provide causal evidence indicating that anomie does, in fact, lead to support for authoritarianism.</p><p>Second, while previous notions speculated about either lack of control or uncertainty explaining the effect of anomie on authoritarianism, we settle this debate and show, via a causal chain <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">(Spencer et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Stone-Romero &amp; Rosopa, 2008)</ref>, that lack of control and uncertainty sequentially explain the effect of anomie on support for authoritarianism. Our results further suggest that this model was superior to alternative explanations. Third, we clarify the concept of anomie by showing that control and uncertainty are not aspects, but consequences of anomie, contrasting previous scholars who have confounded these three constructs <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Blank, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Heydari et al., 2012)</ref>.</p><p>The present results support recent notions that view authoritarianism as a psychological reaction to a deprivation of human needs, such as control and certainty and, therefore, potentially expand our understanding of authoritarianism as a sense-making mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">( Greenaway et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Jost et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Kruglanski &amp; Orehek, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b114">Womick et al., 2019)</ref>. For example, while previous, correlational studies have indicated that authoritarians experience their lives as more certain, coherent, and meaningful (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b114">Womick et al., 2019)</ref>, the present experimental evidence complements this view by indicating that feelings of uncertainty can also lead to a retreat to authoritarianism.</p><p>Importantly, the present findings also provide indirect support for the compensatory control model (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Kay et al., 2008)</ref>. According to our results, feelings of lack of control can increase support for authoritarianism, which may function as a compensatory control mechanism. However, based on our results, they do so only indirectly inasmuch -i.e., because -they lead to feelings of political uncertainty.</p><p>Moreover, by disentangling anomie, lack of control, and uncertainty we support recent notions emphasizing that anomie describes a perceived state of society and not a set of affective reactions <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref>. Thus, experiencing anomie can, but does not have to, lead to negative psychological reactions in an individual. This differentiation is important, as an individual's perception of society may be difficult to alter, especially if that perception is shared. However, the way individuals react to anomie may be more efficiently addressed by practitioners aiming to protect democracy (see below).</p><p>Generally, while previous theories focus on individual experiences in explaining authoritarianism, the present results show that support for authoritarianism can also be caused by perceptions of society and thus remind us of the importance of considering the broader social context. In the same vein, the present results potentially add a new perspective to views considering authoritarianism as a system justification ideology (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Jost et al., 2004</ref>): More specifically, our results suggest that authoritarianism is not only a psychological mechanism justifying the status quo, but also a psychological security mechanism reacting to a system perceived as breaking down.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Practical Implications</head><p>By explaining why anomie leads to support for authoritarianism, we aim to support practitioners in politics and society who want to tackle the negative consequences of anomie more efficiently. For example, the present findings indicate that anomie perceptions are related to both lack of control and uncertainty in the political sphere. However, it is only when individuals feel politically uncertain that they show a heightened susceptibility to authoritarianism. Thus, our results provide evidence challenging the widespread notion that people support authoritarianism mainly because they believe that they do not have a way of exerting political control, and therefore hope for a 'strong leader' to swiftly take control and 'get things done'. For practitioners, this may mean that authoritarianism is more effectively countered through measures that decrease, or help to cope with, uncertainty, for example, by offering sense and purpose. This may be communication clarifying 'the why' of political actions, explaining the sense of policies, or highlighting the values that political decisions are guided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">(Quilter-Pinner et al., 2021)</ref>. Similarly, political rhetoric conveying confidence may reduce uncertainty, and thus support for authoritarianism <ref type="bibr" target="#b110">(White &amp; Shullman, 2010)</ref>. Or, somewhat counterintuitively, it might be that politicians who communicate openly about their own feelings of uncertainty can help individuals acknowledge -and thus cope with -their feelings of political uncertainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Kruglanski &amp; Ellenberg, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b110">White &amp; Shullman, 2010)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations and Directions for Future Research</head><p>The present set of studies is of course also not without limitations. For example, study samples involved only Western participants, limiting generalizability beyond such contexts.</p><p>Also, it is worth noting that Study 1 did not indicate a significant total effect of anomie on authoritarianism. While this data was only correlational, and Study 2 does provide causal evidence for such an effect, this potential difference may be interesting to investigate for future studies. For example, it is conceivable that in Germany, with its particular history regarding authoritarianism, the relationship between anomie and authoritarianism is more indirect than in the United States.</p><p>Moreover, the present causal evidence for the hypothesized effect does not rule out the possibility of reverse causality. For example, correlational evidence from Study 1 shows a significant, indirect effect of authoritarianism on anomie via, in sequence, political uncertainty and lack of political control. Moreover, results from our extended manipulation check (Supplemental Material E) indicate that uncertainty also heightens lack of control, which also significantly affects anomie perceptions. Thus, safe the effect of authoritarianism on uncertainty, for which we have no causal test, our results suggest that uncertainty may also affect anomie via control. Importantly, however, the same manipulation check emphasizes that the present manipulations of anomie, lack of political control, and political uncertainty did not confound these three constructs.</p><p>Accordingly, it is possible that the constructs tested here also relate to each other in different sequences. For example, it seems conceivable that individuals' frustration about the perceived impossibility of exerting political influence, and/or their pervasive sense of confusion regarding political matters, increases individuals' perception of society breaking down, potentially contributing to a concerning feedback loop threatening democracy.</p><p>Clarifying these relationships further, we believe, is an important endeavor for future studies.</p><p>At the same time, due to the absence of a direct causal effect of lack of political control on support for authoritarianism (as indicated by our test of alternative models), the present results do rule out some alternative pathways: 1) the possibility that only lack of control mediates the effect of anomie on authoritarianism and 2) a reversed order of the mediators (uncertainty preceding lack of control). Accordingly, the present results indicate that lack of control (only) leads to support for authoritarianism to the extent that it leads to uncertainty.</p><p>Importantly, even though we consider anomie as a key precursor to authoritarianism, it is likely that a range of factors can initiate the causal chain discussed throughout the manuscript. For example, historical observations and major theorists like <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Durkheim (2005)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Fromm (1941), and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Arendt (1973)</ref> suggest that various triggers related to societal disarray and normative confusion-characteristics of anomie-often precede societal changes and the rise of authoritarian leaders who promise to restore order. Thus, it might be that the mechanism presented in the present manuscript can be initiated or fostered by, for example, economic crises (e.g., Greece), deep-seated ethnic or religious conflicts (e.g., Israel, Syria), external or civil wars (e.g., Iraq), and populists zeitgeist. Also, during the COVID-19 pandemic, feelings of a lack of control associated with the spread of the virus <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(Marmarosh et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b96">Šrol et al., 2021)</ref> likely led to confusion and uncertainty, which then fostered authoritarian reactions in many nations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Filsinger &amp; Freitag, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b85">Roccato et al., 2021)</ref>. To what extent such factors relate to a causal chain leading to authoritarianism presents an empirical question that we believe provides promising avenues for future research.</p><p>authoritarianism via, sequentially, lack of political control and political uncertainty (b = 0.007, 95% CI = [0.003, 0.01]). The calculation of completely standardized effects <ref type="bibr">(Hayes, 2013)</ref> indicated an effect size of 0.005, which may be interpreted as a small-size effect <ref type="bibr">(Preacher &amp; Kelley, 2011)</ref>. It seems like society is falling apart. There are no more moral standards to follow, and people do not seem to care about what is right and wrong. The only thing that matters for most people is to have money and power. To achieve that, people think that honesty doesn't work all the time; dishonesty is sometimes a better approach to getting ahead. Everyone only does what is best for themselves, even if it means lying or cheating. Accordingly, there is very little trust among people and people are friends with others for their own benefit. Everyone fends for themselves; people rarely cooperate and help one another.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental</head><p>Just like the social fabric is breaking down, so is the leadership of the country.</p><p>Politicians seem unable and unwilling to better the lives of the people. Due to social and class division, nepotism, and corruption, most people distrust politicians and think that they use their power illegitimately. Therefore, many laws are regarded as unfair. The government's laws and policies are not effective, and politicians do not seem to care at all about the problems of the people. Accordingly, political leaders and their policies are generally perceived as illegitimate.</p><p>Low-Anomie Condition. Imagine that you are 10 years in the future. While your personal affairs have not changed unexpectedly, there have been dramatic and far-reaching changes in the United States, the country in which you live.</p><p>It seems like society is united and cohesive. There are clear and agreed-upon moral standards to follow and people seem to care strongly about what is right and wrong. What matters for most people is to support and care for each other and to strive as a community. To achieve that, people think that honesty works best; dishonesty as an approach to getting ahead is strongly rejected. Everyone tries to do what is best for society, even if it means having to cut back themselves. Accordingly, there is great trust among people and people are generally friendly toward one another. Everyone fends for the community; people frequently cooperate and help one another.</p><p>Just like the social fabric is flourishing, so is the leadership of the country. Politicians seem capable and willing to better the lives of the people. Due to most politicians' sense of fairness, integrity, and equality, most people trust politicians and think that they use their power legitimately. Therefore, most laws are regarded as fair. The government's laws and policies are effective, and politicians seem to care deeply about the problems of the people.</p><p>Accordingly, political leaders and their policies are generally perceived as legitimate.</p><p>Control Condition. Imagine that you are 10 years in the future. Your personal affairs have not changed unexpectedly. You still live in the United States, which is much as they are today.</p><p>In the United States of the future, some buildings look more modern than today.</p><p>Depending on the architect, some buildings have what one would call a rather futuristic look, for example, lots of glass, metal structures, and daring shapes. However, overall, the look of towns, villages, and cities has not changed a lot.</p><p>In that future, some of the roads, bridges, and train systems have been renewed, others need some work. There is somewhat more public transport than today, but not much. New train connections are established, and some metro systems in the cities are extended and running more frequently. Because people order goods online even more than today, you can see more delivery trucks, bikes, and workers on the streets than today.</p><p>Just like today, there will be a growing number of high-rise buildings in the cities. Due to new technology and knowledge, many of these skyscrapers are even taller than today. At the same time, a lot of older buildings stay preserved, so that most towns and cities have kept an appearance that is somewhat balanced between old and new structures, just like today.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental Material D: Testing the Higher-Order Factor of the Anomie Scale and</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manipulation</head><p>We conducted several analyses in order to empirically determine whether the Perception of Anomie Scale (PAS; <ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref> in the manipulation check consisted of one factor or more. As expected, exploratory factor analysis (EFA) revealed that anomie measured with the PAS <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2017)</ref> represents a unidimensional construct: EFA indicated that there was only one factor with an eigenvalue higher than 1, on which all items loaded with at least .71, indicating that the scale measured a single underlying construct <ref type="bibr" target="#b119">(Briggs &amp; Cheek, 1986)</ref>.</p><p>Additionally, we tested whether the manipulation had different effects on the PAS subscales "leadership" and "social fabric", respectively. Supporting our prediction, results of a Wald test confirmed that the effects of the anomie manipulation (high versus low condition) on the "leadership" subscale did not differ significantly from the effect on the "social fabric" subscale: F(1, 61) = 0.09, p = .767. Together, these results support the notion that anomie, as measured and manipulated in the present manuscript, represents a unidimensional construct.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental Material E: Extended Manipulation Check</head><p>Since it is likely that there is an overlap in content between the constructs anomie, lack of political control, and political uncertainty, we ran an additional, extended manipulation check with an independent sample (n = 345) on Prolific. The goal was to check for unexpected confounding. For example, one may be concerned that the manipulation of political uncertainty led to support for authoritarianism (Study 3) because in reality, and unintendedly, said manipulation heightened perceived lack of control rather than uncertainty. This, of course, would invalidate our conclusions. However, ruling out such concerns empirically is somewhat complicated in the present context because 1) a shared variance of these three constructs (political uncertainty, lack of political control, and perceived anomie) is to be expected <ref type="bibr">(Kofta et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Weary et al., 2010)</ref> and, partly, hypothesized. For example, according to our hypothesis, an effect of the manipulation of perceived anomie on feelings of a lack of political control is to be expected. At the same time, such an effect may be interpreted as an indication that our manipulation of anomie is confounded with lack of political control. Addressing this issue, we followed guidance by <ref type="bibr" target="#b118">Baron and Kenny (1986;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> see also <ref type="bibr">Hayes, 2018)</ref> and used statistical control in order to examine whether our manipulations showed indications of confounding beyond the effects that are expected. For example, we would expect participants in the high-anomie condition to indicate heightened perceived lack of political control (compared to the low-anomie condition). However, we would not expect such an effect when we control for anomie (as measured with the Perception of Anomie Scale (PAS; <ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2016)</ref>, since the anomie manipulation should only lead to perceived lack of political control because it leads to perceived anomie. Thus, if we hold the manipulation's effect on (measured) perceived anomie constant, there should be no effect on lack of control (or political uncertainty, respectively).</p><p>If, however, the manipulation of perceived anomie leads to lack of political control even while controlling for anomie (as measured with the PAS; <ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2016)</ref>, one may conclude that the manipulation of anomie manipulates lack of control above and beyond its intended effect on anomie -in other words: that anomie and lack of control are confounded.</p><p>In the extended manipulation check, participants were each randomly assigned to one of the seven experimental conditions used in Studies 2-4: High-anomie condition; low-anomie condition, high lack of political control condition; low lack of political control condition; high political uncertainty condition; low political uncertainty condition; control condition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manipulation of Perception of Anomie.</head><p>Results of an ANOVA indicated that there was a significant overall effect of the manipulation on perceived anomie, as measured by the PAS <ref type="bibr">(Teymoori et al., 2016), [F(6, 338)</ref> = 11.45, p &lt; .001]. Bonferroni-corrected post hoc tests revealed that participants in the high-anomie condition scored significantly higher on the perceived anomie scale (M = 4.86, SD = 1.23) than participants in the low-anomie condition (M = 3.36, SD = 1.48, p &lt; .001). There was a significant difference between the control condition (M = 4.50, SD = 1.16) and the low-anomie condition (p &lt; .001) but not the highanomie condition (p = 1).</p><p>Since we planned to include continuous control variables, we conducted OLS regression for the remaining analyses. In line with our mediation hypothesis, the manipulation of perceived anomie (low versus high condition) had a significant effect on perceived lack of political control (as measured by the lack of political control scale by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref>, b = 1.22, p &lt; .001). However, when controlling for anomie (as measured by the PAS; <ref type="bibr">Teymoori et al., 2016)</ref>, there was no significant effect of the anomie manipulation on lack of political control (b = 0.24, p = .162).</p><p>Similarly, the manipulation of perceived anomie (low versus high condition) had a significant effect on political uncertainty (as measured by the political uncertainty scale by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref>, b = 0.83, p &lt; .001). However, again, when controlling for anomie, there was no significant effect of the anomie manipulation on political uncertainty (b = 0.15, p = .465).</p><p>In sum, it can be concluded that the present manipulation of perceived anomie increases lack of political control and political uncertainty (only) because it leads to perceived anomie. In other words, the results indicate that there is no unintended confounding of the present experimental manipulation of anomie, neither with political uncertainty nor with perceived lack of political control.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manipulation of Perceived Lack of Political Control.</head><p>Results of an ANOVA indicated that there was a significant overall effect of the lack of political control manipulation on perceived lack of political control [F(6, 338) = 12.62, p &lt; .001]. Bonferroni-corrected post hoc tests revealed that participants in the high lack of political control condition scored significantly higher on the perceived lack of political control scale (M = 4.38, SD = 0.79) than participants in the low lack of political control condition (M = 3.10, SD = 1.43, p &lt; .001). There was a significant difference between the control condition (M = 3.57, SD = 1.10) and the high lack of political control condition (p = .006) but not the low lack of political control condition (p = .846).</p><p>Results of OLS regression analyses showed that, in line with our mediation hypothesis, the manipulation of perceived lack of political control (low versus high condition) had a significant effect on political uncertainty (b = 0.65, p = .003). However, when controlling for lack of political control, there was no significant effect of the lack of political control manipulation on political uncertainty (b = 0.03, p = .887).</p><p>Similarly, the manipulation of perceived lack of political control (low versus high condition) had a significant effect on perceived anomie (b = 1.04, p &lt; .001). However, again, when controlling for lack of political control, there was no significant effect of the lack of political control manipulation on perceived anomie (b = -0.03, p = .882).</p><p>In sum, again it can be concluded that the present manipulation of lack of political control increases political uncertainty/perceived anomie only inasmuch it leads to perceived lack of political control. In other words, the results indicate that there is no unintended confounding of the present experimental manipulation of lack of political control, neither with political uncertainty nor with perceived anomie.</p><p>Manipulation of Political Uncertainty. Results of an ANOVA indicated that there was a significant overall effect of the uncertainty manipulation on political uncertainty [F(6, 338) = 11.33, p &lt; .001]. Bonferroni-corrected post hoc tests revealed that participants in the high political uncertainty condition scored significantly higher on the political uncertainty scale (M = 4.05, SD = 0.97) than participants in the low political uncertainty condition (M = 2.58, SD = 1.18, p &lt; .001). There was a significant difference between the control condition (M = 3.11, In line with our predictions, the results indicated a significant, positive relationship between high perceptions of anomie (compared to the low-anomie condition) and lack of political control (b = 1.99, p &lt; .001, η2 = 0.47), as well as between the latter and political uncertainty (b = 0.81, p &lt; .001, η2 = 0.34), and between political uncertainty and support for authoritarianism (b = 0.71, p &lt; .001, η2 = 0.11, see Supplemental Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">2</ref>). Mediation analysis supported our hypothesis: Participants in the high-anomie condition (compared to the low-anomie condition) showed increased support for authoritarianism, sequentially mediated by perceived lack of political control and political uncertainty (b = 1.13, 95% CI = [0.82, 1.51]). The calculation of partially standardized effects <ref type="bibr">(Hayes, 2013)</ref> indicated a large effect size of 0.68 <ref type="bibr">(Preacher &amp; Kelley, 2011)</ref>. Comparing the high-and the control condition also revealed a significant, indirect effect (b = 0.34, 95% CI = [0.20, 0.49]). In summary, the results supported our hypothesis.</p><p>Finally, given the likely content overlap between lack of political control and political uncertainty, we conducted a confirmatory factor analysis in order to test whether a model that treats the items of these two scales as independent (as suggested by our theory) provides a better fit to the data than a model that combines both scales' items. A comparison of the Akaike information criterion (AIC) values and Chi-square fits showed that a two-factor model (treating both scales' items as independent) fits the data better (AIC = 11697.81) than a onefactor model (AIC = 12182.6) combining all items. The Chi-square fits of both models differed significantly, χ 2 (1, N = 543) = 486.79, p &lt; .001. These results indicate that these scales' items measure two different constructs.</p><p>Low Lack of Political Control Condition. Imagine that you are 10 years in the future. While your personal affairs have not changed unexpectedly, there have been dramatic and far-reaching changes in the United States, the country in which you live.</p><p>In the United States of the future, you feel that people like you have much control over politics and government actions. Whatever the subject, for the average citizen there always seems to be a way to change things, politically. Politicians seem to be very much in touch with the people they are elected to represent. Whenever they decide the fate of people like you, the ones in power seem to care strongly about what people want or need. When they make social or economic decisions, they always ask or consider ordinary people.</p><p>People in charge in administration seem to be very cooperative and interested in helping anyone who wants to make a positive difference. There are not many hurdles and barriers so that it always seems possible to get something done, politically.</p><p>As a result, there is a general sense of control in the political sphere among the population, and whoever is committed to making a political or social impact will be encouraged and start trying sooner or later. It feels that people like you are playing a very significant role within the machinery of politics.</p><p>Control Condition. Imagine that you are 10 years in the future. Your personal affairs have not changed unexpectedly. You still live in the United States, which is much as they are today.</p><p>In the United States of the future, some buildings look more modern than today.</p><p>Depending on the architect, some buildings have what one would call a rather futuristic look, for example, lots of glass, metal structures, and daring shapes. However, overall, the look of towns, villages, and cities has not changed a lot.</p><p>In that future, some of the roads, bridges, and train systems have been renewed, others need some work. There is somewhat more public transport than today, but not much. New train connections are established, and some metro systems in the cities are extended and Low Political Uncertainty Condition. Imagine that you are 10 years in the future.</p><p>While your personal affairs have not changed unexpectedly, there have been dramatic and farreaching changes in the United States, the country in which you live.</p><p>In the United States of the future, the political landscape makes people feel very certain. For example, it is very easy to understand what politicians want. What they do and say makes sense and seems justified and meaningful, usually. Their actions are largely predictable. It is very easy to comprehend why politicians do the things they do. Accordingly, when it comes to politics, there is a general sense of certainty and security among the people. Politics is so transparent and clear that one can easily comprehend what is happening. Altogether, the political situation in the United States, in that future, seems so sorted out that most people have a good understanding of the country's future.</p><p>Control Condition. Imagine that you are 10 years in the future. Your personal affairs have not changed unexpectedly. You still live in the United States, which is much as they are today.</p><p>In the United States of the future, some buildings look more modern than today.</p><p>Depending on the architect, some buildings have what one would call a rather futuristic look, for example, lots of glass, metal structures, and daring shapes. However, overall, the look of towns, villages, and cities has not changed a lot.</p><p>In that future, some of the roads, bridges, and train systems have been renewed and many are still the same, and others need some work. There is a mixture of private car ownership and also public transport, just like today. New train connections are established, and some metro systems in the cities are extended. Because people order goods online even</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>anomie scale. An example item: "Most people don't really care what happens to the next fellow". Participants are asked to indicate their agreement on a dichotomous scale (0 = do not agree; 1 = agree; a = .52).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>Note. N = 1504; *** p &lt; .001, ** p &lt; .01, * p &lt; .05. a Female = 1, male = 0; b Monthly household net income (in Euro); c No = 0, yes = 1; d Scale ranging from 1 (left) to 10 (right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>cohesive and cooperative society, where politicians are perceived as legitimate and effective: "It seems like society is united and cohesive. There are clear and agreed-upon moral standards to follow, and people seem to care strongly about what is right and wrong. (…) [P]olitical leaders and their policies are generally perceived as legitimate."</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc>perceived anomie [F(2, 91) = 11.09, p &lt; .001]. Bonferroni-corrected post hoc tests revealed that participants in the high-anomie condition scored significantly higher on the perceived anomie scale (M = 5.33, SD = 0.76) than participants in the low-anomie condition (M = 3.92, SD = 1.73, p &lt; .001) or those in the control condition (M = 3.93, SD = 1.31, p &lt; .001). The low-anomie and the control condition did not differ from each other (p = 1.00), suggesting that baseline levels of anomie were relatively low at the point of the data collection.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc>anomie manipulation on lack of political control, [F(2, 540) = 180.96, p &lt; .001]. In support of our predictions, post hoc tests using the Bonferroni correction showed that participants in the high-anomie condition felt a significantly higher lack of political control (M = 4.25, SD = 0.82) than participants in the low-anomie condition (M = 2.26, SD = 1.24, p &lt; .001, Cohen's d = 1.88) and the control condition (M = 3.68, SD = 0.95, p &lt; .001). Low and control conditions differed significantly as well (p &lt; .001). Moreover, ANOVA results indicated an effect of anomie on support for authoritarianism [F(2, 540) = 58.13, p &lt; .001]. In support of our predictions, post hoc tests using the Bonferroni correction indicated that participants in the high-anomie condition showed significantly higher support for authoritarianism (M = 5.22, SD = 1.27) than participants in the low-anomie condition (M = 3.51, SD = 1.78, p &lt; .001, Cohen's d = 1.10) and the control condition (M = 4.54, SD = 1.44, p &lt; .001). Low and control condition differed significantly as well (p &lt; .001).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc>Lack of Political Control. Like in Study 2, we manipulated our independent variable by asking participants to read a vignette describing the society of the United States 10 years into the future (Supplemental Material G;<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Duckitt &amp; Fisher, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Hartwich &amp; Becker, 2019)</ref>. The vignette closely resembled the lack of political control scale byKofta and colleagues (2020)  used in Study 2 to make participants feel "like a pawn and [experiencing] an enduring loss of personal influence over the political world." Here is an excerpt of the manipulation text for the high condition: "In the United States of the future, you feel that people like you have absolutely no control over politics and government actions." The low lack of political control condition, by contrast, featured this text: "In the United States of the future, you feel that people like you have much control over politics and government actions." To ensure comparability between the experimental conditions and avoid</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Study 2 (</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Kofta et al., 2020; a = .91). The results of an ANOVA test indicated that there was a significant overall effect of the manipulation on lack of political control [F (2, 90) = 25.05, p &lt; .001]. In support of our predictions, post hoc tests using the Bonferroni correction showed that participants in the high lack of political control condition felt a significantly higher lack of political control (M = 4.38, SD = 0.72) than participants in the low lack of political control condition (M = 2.65, SD = 1.30, p &lt; .001). The low lack of political control condition also differed significantly from the control condition (p &lt; .001). However, there was no significant difference between the high lack of political control condition and the control condition (M = 3.88, SD = 0.79, p = .142). With scores above the scale midpoint (3), participants in both the high lack of political control condition and the control condition experienced increased feelings of lack of political control to some extent. Just thinking about the future of the United</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><figDesc>feelings of political uncertainty[F(2, 168) = 19.13, p &lt; .001]. The results of post hoc tests using Bonferroni corrections confirmed that, as predicted, participants in the high lack of political control condition (M = 3.66, SD = 1.02) reported significantly more political uncertainty than participants in the low lack of political control condition (M = 2.50, SD = 1.07, p &lt; .001, Cohen's d = 1.11). There was no significant difference between the high lack of political control and the control condition (M = 3.22, SD = 0.96, p = .076). The neutral control condition differed significantly from the low political control condition (p = .001).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><figDesc>manipulation on a measure of political uncertainty[F(6, 338) = 11.33, p &lt; .001]. Bonferronicorrected post hoc tests revealed that participants in the high political uncertainty condition scored significantly higher on the political uncertainty scale (M = 4.05, SD = 0.97) than participants in the low political uncertainty condition (M = 2.58, SD = 1.18, p &lt; .001) and in the control condition (M = 3.11, SD = 1.02, p &lt; .001). Even though political uncertainty scores in the low condition were below the scale's mid-level (3) and in the control condition slightly above, there was no significant difference between the low and the control condition (p = .339). Similar to Studies 2 and 3, we interpret this as an indication that the political context in the United States is highly volatile and fast-changing and that, at the time of data collection, baseline levels of political uncertainty were relatively low.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><figDesc>ANOVA indicated an overall effect of the political uncertainty manipulation on support for authoritarianism [F(2, 166) = 5.56, p = .005]. The results of post hoc tests using Bonferroni corrections indicated that, as predicted, participants in the high political uncertainty condition (M = 4.78, SD = 1.29) reported significantly more support for authoritarianism than participants in the low political uncertainty condition (M = 4.01, SD = 1.60, p = .015, Cohen's d = 0.53). Likewise, participants in the control condition (M = 3.99, SD = 1.46) indicated significantly less support for authoritarianism than participants in the high condition (p =</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Study 1 .Study 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>The results from parallel mediation analysis indicated an indirect effect of anomie on authoritarianism via political uncertainty (b = 0.04, 95% CI = [0.02, 0.06]) but not via lack of political control (b = -0.004, 95% CI = [-0.03, 0.02]). Moreover, a comparison of the Akaike information criterion (AIC) values and Chisquare fits showed that our hypothesized sequential mediation model (AIC = 93366.91) was preferable to the parallel mediation model (AIC = 93387.82). The Chi-square fits of both models differed significantly, χ 2 (1, N = 1504) = 22.91, p &lt; .001, favoring our proposed model. The results from parallel mediation analysis indicated that the indirect effect of anomie on support for authoritarianism via political uncertainty was significant, both when the high-anomie condition was compared with the low-anomie condition (b = 1.11, 95% CI = [0.81, 1.46]) and with the control condition (b = 0.33, 95% CI = [0.18, 0.52]). Moreover, again there was no indirect effect of anomie on support for authoritarianism via lack of political control, both when comparing the high-anomie condition with the low-anomie condition (b = 0.22, 95% CI = [-0.18, 0.64]) and with the control condition (b = 0.06, 95% CI = [-0.05, 0.19]). Similar to Study 1, AIC values and Chi-square fits of both models showed that the hypothesized sequential mediation model (AIC = 8909.90) was preferable to the parallel mediation model (AIC = 9230.48). The Chi-square fits of both models differed significantly as well, χ 2 (1, N = 543) = 332.58, p &lt; .001, again favoring the hypothesized model. Test of reverse order Moreover, we tested another alternative model, placing political uncertainty first in the sequence and lack of political control second. Study 1. Mediation analysis showed no indirect effect of anomie on support for authoritarianism via, in sequence, political uncertainty and lack of political control (b = -0.0003, 95% CI = [-0.002, 0.001]).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Study 1: Path Model Depicting the Regression Coefficients of the Hypothesized Model Without Control Variables: The Effect of Anomie on Support for Authoritarianism Sequentially Mediated by Lack of Political Control and Political Uncertainty Condition. Imagine that you are 10 years in the future. While your personal affairs have not changed unexpectedly, there have been dramatic and far-reaching changes in the United States, the country in which you live.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><figDesc>Likewise, it is easy to understand the sense of government actions. People usually feel that they understand what the motives and goals of politicians are, how politicians make their decisions, and what they are going to do next. In general, what politicians say and do seems completely clear and sensible.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Correlations and Descriptive Statistics for Unstandardized Variables in Study 1</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>% n</cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>(6)</cell><cell>(7)</cell><cell>(8)</cell></row><row><cell>(1) Support for authoritarianism</cell><cell>3.05</cell><cell>1.49</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(2) Anomie</cell><cell>1.72</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell></cell><cell>.004</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(3) Lack of political control</cell><cell>3.79</cell><cell>0.91</cell><cell></cell><cell>.006</cell><cell>.30***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(4) Political uncertainty</cell><cell>2.85</cell><cell>1.11</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">.12*** .21*** .19***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(5) Age in years</cell><cell>49.70</cell><cell>17.39</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">.21*** .10*** .14*** .001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(6) Gender (woman) a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">52 776 -.05</cell><cell>-.02</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell cols="2">.23*** .07**</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(7) Income b</cell><cell cols="5">2087.14 1246.23 -.2318 -.05 1.74 .11*** .01</cell><cell>.04</cell><cell>.06*</cell><cell>.07**</cell><cell cols="2">-.07* .04</cell><cell>-.09***</cell></row></table><note><p>*** -.27*** -.25*** -.14*** -.05 (8) University degree c 11 158 -.08** -.24*** -.14*** -.19*** -.02 -.03 .27*** (9) Political leaning (right-wing) d 5.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 590</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Descriptive Statistics for Variables across Conditions in Study 2 591</figDesc><table><row><cell>Baseline characteristic</cell><cell cols="4">High-anomie condition</cell><cell cols="4">Low-anomie condition</cell><cell cols="3">Control condition</cell><cell></cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>n</cell><cell cols="2">% M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>% M</cell><cell></cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>% M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell>Support for authoritarianism</cell><cell>5.22</cell><cell>1.27</cell><cell>177</cell><cell></cell><cell>3.51</cell><cell>1.78</cell><cell>183</cell><cell cols="2">4.54</cell><cell>1.44</cell><cell>183</cell><cell>4.41</cell><cell>1.67</cell></row><row><cell>Political uncertainty</cell><cell>3.78</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>177</cell><cell></cell><cell>2.20</cell><cell>1.23</cell><cell>183</cell><cell cols="2">3.32</cell><cell>1.00</cell><cell>183</cell><cell>3.09</cell><cell>1.25</cell></row><row><cell>Lack of political control</cell><cell>4.25</cell><cell>0.82</cell><cell>177</cell><cell></cell><cell>2.26</cell><cell>1.24</cell><cell>183</cell><cell cols="2">3.68</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>183</cell><cell>3.39</cell><cell>1.32</cell></row><row><cell>Age in years</cell><cell cols="3">41.86 13.46 177</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">42.46 12.51 183</cell><cell cols="4">42.60 13.74 183</cell><cell cols="2">42.31 13.22</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>84</cell><cell>47</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>93</cell><cell>51</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>94</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>50</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>92</cell><cell>52</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>88</cell><cell>48</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>85</cell><cell>46</cell><cell>49</cell></row><row><cell>Other/Nonbinary</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Household income (annual) a</cell><cell>6.60</cell><cell>3.01</cell><cell>176</cell><cell></cell><cell>6.87</cell><cell>3.03</cell><cell>183</cell><cell cols="2">6.56</cell><cell>3.05</cell><cell>183</cell><cell>6.68</cell><cell>3.03</cell></row><row><cell>College degree b</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">116 66</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">107 58</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">102 56</cell><cell>60</cell></row><row><cell>Unemployed</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>7</cell><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>22</cell><cell>12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>19</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>Ethnic group c</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Native American/American Indian</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>&lt;1</cell></row><row><cell>Asian/Asian American</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>7</cell><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>12</cell><cell>7</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Black/African American</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>40</cell><cell>23</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>28</cell><cell>15</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>51</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>22</cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic/Latin(a/o/x)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>&lt;1</cell></row><row><cell>White</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">118 67</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">130 71</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">118 64</cell><cell>67</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Correlations of Unstandardized Variables in Study 2</figDesc><table><row><cell>status (married) d</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>101 57</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>100 55</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>103 56</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>304 56</cell></row><row><cell>Political ideology (right-wing) e</cell><cell>3.62</cell><cell>1.75</cell><cell>177</cell><cell>3.58</cell><cell>1.84</cell><cell>183</cell><cell>3.67</cell><cell>1.77</cell><cell>183</cell><cell>3.63</cell><cell>1.78</cell><cell>543</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 701</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Descriptive Statistics for Variables across Conditions inStudy 3 702</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">High lack of</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Low lack of</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Baseline characteristic</cell><cell cols="4">political control condition</cell><cell cols="4">political control condition</cell><cell cols="3">Control condition</cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>n</cell><cell cols="2">% M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>% M</cell><cell></cell><cell>SD</cell><cell cols="2">n % M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell>Support for authoritarianism</cell><cell>4.22</cell><cell>1.61</cell><cell>57</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.04</cell><cell>1.54</cell><cell>59</cell><cell cols="2">4.21</cell><cell>1.34</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>4.15</cell><cell>1.50</cell></row><row><cell>Political uncertainty</cell><cell>3.66</cell><cell>1.02</cell><cell>57</cell><cell></cell><cell>2.50</cell><cell>1.07</cell><cell>59</cell><cell cols="2">3.22</cell><cell>0.96</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>3.12</cell><cell>1.12</cell></row><row><cell>Age in years</cell><cell cols="3">39.28 12.89 57</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">40.24 14.43 59</cell><cell cols="4">37.98 11.76 55</cell><cell>39.19 13.06</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">28 49</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">29 50</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">25 45 0</cell><cell>82</cell><cell>48</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">28 49</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">28 48</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>28 51</cell><cell>84</cell><cell>49</cell></row><row><cell>Non-binary</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2 4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>Household income (annual) a</cell><cell>5.84</cell><cell>3.28</cell><cell>57</cell><cell></cell><cell>5.98</cell><cell>3.05</cell><cell>59</cell><cell cols="2">6.25</cell><cell>3.08</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>6.02</cell><cell>3.12</cell></row><row><cell>College degree b</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">31 54</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">31 53</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>31 56</cell><cell>93</cell><cell>54</cell></row><row><cell>Unemployed</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>7</cell><cell>12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>5 9</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>Ethnic group</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Asian/Asian American</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3</cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>4 7</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Black/African American</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>5</cell><cell>9</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>8</cell><cell>14</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>9 16</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic/Latin(a/o/x)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>4 7</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1 2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>White</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">43 75</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">47 80</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>37 67</cell><cell>74</cell></row><row><cell>Marital status (married) c</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">27 47</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">24 41</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>20 36</cell><cell>71</cell><cell>42</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Political ideology (right-wing) d 3.09</cell><cell>1.88</cell><cell>57</cell><cell></cell><cell>2.86</cell><cell>1.79</cell><cell>59</cell><cell cols="2">2.70</cell><cell>1.53</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>2.89</cell><cell>1.74</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Correlations of Unstandardized Variables in Study 3</figDesc><table><row><cell>Notes N = 171; *** p &lt; .001, ** p &lt; .01, * p &lt; .05; a Measured in 10 categories/steps of $10,000, ranging from 1 (less than $15,000) to 10 (more than $95,000); b No</cell></row><row><cell>college degree = 0, college degree or higher = 1; c Not married = 0, married = 1; d Two items measuring political leaning on social and economic issues, scale ranging</cell></row><row><cell>from 1 (strongly left) to 7 (strongly right; a = .91).</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>A different, preregistered version of the present Study 2([link]  was part of the previous version of the manuscript. However, as one of the reviewers pointed out, this study was underpowered, leading us to re-run this study with a more adequate sample.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1"><p>We ran additional analyses to examine whether we manipulate anomie as a single latent factor construct (Supplemental Material D) as our theory predicts. As expected, results indicated that anomie, as measured and manipulated in the present manuscript, represents a unidimensional construct.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_2"><p>In Studies 2 and 3, we also tested our hypothesis via mediation analyses following recommendations byHayes  (2018). All of these can be found in the online supplements (Supplemental Materials F &amp; H).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Data collected for Studies 3 and 4 also included variables for a separate research project examining the effects of anomie on normative and nonnormative/violent political actions. See respective preregistration documents for</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Notes. a Measured in 10 categories/steps of $10,000, ranging from 1 (less than $15,000) to 10 (more than $95,000); b No college degree = 0, college degree or higher = 1;</p><p>c Not married = 0, married = 1; d Two items measuring political leaning on social and economic issues, scale ranging from 1 (strongly left) to 7 (strongly right; a = .91).  <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020, r(92)</ref> = .70, p &lt; .001) and a medium-size correlation between the ALLBUS proxy scale for political uncertainty and the respective scale by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020, r(92)</ref> = .43, p &lt; .001). Moreover, results from an exploratory factor analysis revealed that all items used to measure lack of political control (i.e., four items from <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref> and two items from the ALLBUS <ref type="bibr">(Bechert &amp; Quandt, 2009</ref>)) loaded on (only) one factor with an eigenvalue higher than 1, with factor loadings of at least .51. Similarly, factor analysis showed that all items used to measure political uncertainty (i.e., four items from <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref> and two items from the ALLBUS <ref type="bibr">(Bechert &amp; Quandt, 2009</ref>)) loaded on (only) one factor with an eigenvalue higher than 1, with individual factor loadings of at least .35. This indicates that participants did not discriminate between the scales we used in Study 1 and the respective established measures. Thus, in summary, we argue that our scales measuring lack of political control and political uncertainty are valid proxies for the scales used in Studies 2-4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental Online Materials</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>When Lack of Control Leads to Uncertainty: Explaining the Effect of Anomie on</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Support for Authoritarianism</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental Material B: Results of Study 1 Excluding Control Variables</head><p>We used weights provided by the ALLBUS (GESIS -Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften, 2011) in order to account for the oversampling of participants from East Germany. See Supplemental Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> for an overview of path coefficients. To test our hypothesis without control variables, we interpreted the 95% bias-corrected confidence intervals from 10,000 bootstrapping samples. Similar to results including control variables, this analysis indicated a significant indirect relationship between anomie and support for SD = 1.02) and the high political uncertainty condition (p &lt; .001) but not the low political uncertainty condition (p = .339).</p><p>Results of OLS regression analyses showed that the manipulation of political uncertainty (low versus high condition) had a significant effect on perceived lack of political control (b = 0.78, p = .001). However, when controlling for political uncertainty, there was no significant effect of the political uncertainty manipulation on perceived lack of political control (b = -0.01, p = .960).</p><p>Similarly, the manipulation of political uncertainty (low versus high condition) had a significant effect on perceived anomie (b = 0.98, p &lt; .001). However, again, when controlling for political uncertainty, there was no significant effect of the political uncertainty manipulation on perceived anomie (b = 0.05, p = .842).</p><p>In sum, again it can be concluded that the present manipulation of political uncertainty increases perceived lack of political control/perceived anomie only inasmuch it leads to political uncertainty. In other words, the results indicate that there is no unintended confound of the present experimental manipulation of political uncertainty, neither with perceived lack of political control nor with perceived anomie.</p><p>Finally, given the likely content overlap between anomie, lack of political control, and political uncertainty, we conducted a confirmatory factor analysis in order to test whether a model that treats the items of these three scales as independent (as suggested by our theory) provides a better fit to the data than a model that combines the scales' items. A comparison of the Akaike information criterion (AIC) values and Chi-square fits showed that a two-factor model (treating the three scales' items as independent) fits the data better (AIC = 21128.94) than a one-factor model (AIC = 22016.52) combining all items. The Chi-square fits of both models differed significantly as well, χ 2 (3, N = 345) = 893.58, p &lt; .001. These results</p><p>indicate that the scales used in the present study measure three distinct constructs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental Material F: Mediation Analyses and Robustness Check Study 2</head><p>We measured political uncertainty via a scale developed by <ref type="bibr">Kofta and colleagues (2020)</ref>. The scale consists of four items asking participants for their agreement with several statements on a 5-point scale (1 = strongly disagree; 5 = strongly agree). An example:</p><p>" To test our hypothesis in Study 2 via mediation analysis, we followed the bootstrapping procedures recommended by <ref type="bibr">Hayes (2018)</ref> to estimate confidence intervals for the indirect effect of anomie perceptions on support for authoritarianism via lack of political control and political uncertainty. In doing so, we interpreted the 95% bias-corrected confidence intervals from 10,000 bootstrap samples. Moreover, in all mediation analyses, we followed recommendations by UCLA: Statistical Consulting Group (2021) who built on <ref type="bibr">Hayes and Preacher (2014)</ref>. This method uses dummy variables for all three categories, which allows the comparison of all three conditions simultaneously.</p><p>We first conducted seemingly unrelated regression (SUR) analyses to account for the likely possibility that error terms in a set of linear equations are correlated <ref type="bibr">(Srivastava &amp; Dwivedi, 1979)</ref>. SUR permits the analysis of multiple regressions while allowing their errors to be correlated <ref type="bibr" target="#b121">(Fiebig, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Srivastava &amp; Dwivedi, 1979)</ref>. SUR shares many similarities with Structural Equation Modelling (SEM) and usually leads to similar results, also in the present studies. Unlike SEM, SUR only includes measured variables (not latent ones). In the United States of the future, you feel that people like you have absolutely no control over politics and government actions. Whatever the subject, for the average citizen there never seems to be a way to change things, politically. Politicians seem to be very much out of touch with the people they are elected to represent. Although they decide the fate of people like you, the ones in power do not seem to care about what the people want or need.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental</head><p>When they make social or economic decisions, they never ask or consider ordinary people.</p><p>People in charge in administration seem to be completely uncooperative and disinterested in helping anyone who wants to make a positive difference. There are uncountable hurdles and barriers so that it seems impossible to get anything done, politically.</p><p>As a result, there is a general sense of lack of control in the political sphere, and whoever is committed to making a political or social impact will be discouraged and stop trying sooner or later. It feels that people like you are just entirely insignificant within the machinery of politics. running more frequently. Because people order goods online even more than today, you can see more delivery trucks, bikes, and workers on the streets than today.</p><p>Just like today, there will be a growing number of high-rise buildings in the cities. Due to new technology and knowledge, many of these skyscrapers are even taller than today. At the same time, a lot of older buildings stay preserved, so that most towns and cities have kept an appearance that is somewhat balanced between old and new structures, just like today.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental Material H: Hypothesis Test via Mediation Analysis in Study 3</head><p>Like in Studies 2 and 3, we measured support for authoritarianism with the "wish for a strong leader" scale <ref type="bibr">(Sprong et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">a = .91</ref>). To test our hypothesis via mediation analysis, we again followed the bootstrapping procedures recommended by <ref type="bibr">Hayes (2018)</ref>. An analysis of seemingly unrelated regression (see Supplemental Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>) showed, as predicted, a significant effect of lack of political control on feelings of political uncertainty (when compared to the low lack of political control condition, b = 1.16, p &lt; .001, η2 = 0.24) and a significant, positive relationship between political uncertainty and support for authoritarianism (b = 0.34, p = .006, η2 = 0.04). Moreover, we interpreted the 95% biascorrected confidence intervals from 10,000 bootstrap samples. As predicted, there was a significant indirect effect of lack of political control on support for authoritarianism via political uncertainty when comparing the high and the low condition (b = 0.40, 95% CI = [0.08, 0.79]) and also when comparing the high and the control condition (b = 0.25, 95% CI = [0.05, 0.56]). The calculation of partially standardized effects <ref type="bibr">(Hayes, 2013)</ref> indicated a large effect size of 0.27 <ref type="bibr">(Preacher &amp; Kelley, 2011</ref>, when comparing high-versus low condition). In summary, the results support our hypothesis. Accordingly, when it comes to politics, there is a general sense of uncertainty and insecurity among the people. Politics is so complicated and unclear that one cannot comprehend what is happening. Altogether, the political situation in the United States, in that future, seems so entangled that almost anything might happen. Just like today, there will be a growing number of high-rise buildings in the cities. Due to new technology and knowledge, many of these skyscrapers are even taller than today. At the same time, a lot of older buildings stay preserved, so that most towns and cities have kept an appearance that is somewhat balanced between old and new structures, just like today</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplemental Figure 3</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The psychodynamic aspects of leadership</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Abse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jessner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7312/grau91070-006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.7312/grau91070-006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Excellence and leadership in a democracy</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Graubard</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Holton</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="93" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social transitions and anomie among post-communist Bulgarian youth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ådnanes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1103308807072684</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1103308807072684" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">YOUNG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The authoritarian personality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Adorno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Frenkel-Brunswik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Levinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Sanford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Verso Books</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Out of control: How and why does perceived lack of control lead to ethnocentrism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Agroskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Religious racism. Islamophobia and antisemitism in Italian society</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alietti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Padovan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/rel4040584</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/rel4040584" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Religions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="584" to="602" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Altemeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The authoritarian specter</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The other &quot;Authoritarian Personality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Altemeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zanna</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="92" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Journal article reporting standards for quantitative research in psychology: The APA Publications and Communications Board task force report</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Appelbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mayo-Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nezu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Psychologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arendt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The origins of totalitarianism</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Houghton Mifflin Harcourt</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">244</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authoritarian reactions to terrorist threat: Who is being threatened, the Me or the We</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Asbrock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fritsche</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bechert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Quandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">ISSP data report: Attitudes towards the role of government</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>GESIS -Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Politics of resentment: right-wing radicalism in West Germany</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-G</forename><surname>Betz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/422304</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2307/422304" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BACON: Blocked adaptive computationally efficient outlier nominators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Billor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational Statistics &amp; Data Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anomie among European adolescents: Conceptual and empirical clarification of a multilevel sociological concept</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bjarnason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1573-7861.2008.01089.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1573-7861.2008.01089.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of national identity in East and West Germany: An empirical comparison of theories on the significance of authoritarianism, anomie, and general self-esteem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Blank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/0162-895X.00328</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/0162-895X.00328" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender inequality and gender differences in authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0146167212449871</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167212449871" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1301" to="1315" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction, control, and learned helplessness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Burger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.38.3.482</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.38.3.482" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="482" to="491" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Populist politics, communications media and large scale societal integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Calhoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/202117</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2307/202117" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Materialism as an attempt to cope with uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/mar.10016</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/mar.10016" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology and Marketing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diabolical dictators or capable commanders? An investigation of the differential effects of autocratic leadership on team performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H B</forename><surname>De Hoogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Greer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Den Hartog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.leaqua.2015.01.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.leaqua.2015.01.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Leadership Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="701" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Working-class authoritarianism: A re-examination of the Lipset thesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dekker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ester</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Political Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="415" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Threat and authoritarianism in the United States, 1978-1987</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Doty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Peterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Winter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="640" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authoritarianism and group identification: A new view of an old construct</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Duckitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/3791588</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2307/3791588" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of social threat on worldview and ideological attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Duckitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/0162-895X.00322</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/0162-895X.00322" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The march of modern fascism. A comparison of social dominance orientation and authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Duriez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Hiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0191-8869(01)00086-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0191-8869(01)00086-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Individual Differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1199" to="1213" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Suicide: A study in sociology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Durkheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Spaulding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antecedents of causal uncertainty and perceived control: A prospective study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Weary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Populism, persistent republicanism and declinism: An empirical analysis of populism as a thin ideology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elchardus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Spruyt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/gov.2014</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/gov.2014" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Government and Opposition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">G*Power 3: A flexible statistical power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Faul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Erdfelder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-G</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Buchner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3758/BF03193146</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3758/BF03193146" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavior Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the limitations of manipulation checks: An obstacle toward cumulative science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-P</forename><surname>Fayant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sigall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lemonnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Retsin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Alexopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5334/irsp.102</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5334/irsp.102" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Review of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pandemic threat and authoritarian attitudes in Europe: An empirical analysis of the exposure to COVID-19</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Filsinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Freitag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/14651165221082517</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/14651165221082517" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Union Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognition in harsh and unpredictable environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Frankenhuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Panchanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nettle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Man&apos;s search for meaning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Frankl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kushner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Winslade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>I. Lasch</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Beacon Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Trans.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intolerance of ambiguity as an emotional and perceptual personality variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Frenkel-Brunswik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1949">1949</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seeking structure in social organization: Compensatory control and the psychological advantages of hierarchy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Friesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Eibach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Galinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0035620</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0035620" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="590" to="609" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective reactions to threat: Implications for intergroup conflict and for solving societal crises</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fritsche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Issues and Policy Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Escape from freedom</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fromm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1941">1941</date>
			<publisher>Avon Books</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new look at urban alienation: The effect of neighborhood disorder on perceived powerlessness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Geis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2787110</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2787110" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Psychology Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">232</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der Sozialwissenschaften ALLBUS</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4232/1.10832</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4232/1.10832" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2011. 2006. 4500</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Köln</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>GESIS -Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften ; GESIS Datenarchiv</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social identities promote well-being because they satisfy global psychological needs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Greenaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cruwys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Haslam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="294" to="307" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Loss of Control Increases Belief in Precognition and Belief in Precognition Increases Control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Greenaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Louis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hornsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0071327</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0071327" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">71327</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived control qualifies the effects of threat on prejudice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Greenaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Louis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hornsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="422" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minority status decreases sense of control and increases interpretive processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Guinote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fiske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1521/soco.2006.24.2.169</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1521/soco.2006.24.2.169" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the pragmatics of communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Habermas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exposure to neoliberalism increases resentment of the elite via feelings of anomie and negative psychological reactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hartwich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/josi.12311</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/josi.12311" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are manipulation checks necessary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ellsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpsyg.2018.00998</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.00998" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to mediation, moderation, and conditional process analysis: A regression-based approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>First edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to mediation, moderation, and conditional process analysis: A regression-based approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical mediation analysis with a multicategorical independent variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Preacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Mathematical and Statistical Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Was treibt die Gesellschaft auseinander?: Bundesrepublik Deutschland: Auf dem Weg von der Konsens-zur Konfliktgesellschaft</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Heitmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Suhrkamp Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1 st edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The weirdest people in the world?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Henrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Heine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Norenzayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/S0140525X0999152X</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0140525X0999152X" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavioral and Brain Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of stigma in understanding ethnicity differences in authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between socioeconomic status, anomie, and authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Heydari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teymoori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nasiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Fardzadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">e-BANGI</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fear and uncertainty in the face of death: The role of life after death in group identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hohman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ejsp.818</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/ejsp.818" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="751" to="760" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social identity theory and self-categorization theory: A historical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hornsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social and Personality Psychology Compass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allgemeiner Autoritarismus-Kurzform. Zusammenstellung sozialwissenschaftlicher Items und Skalen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hübner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schürhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schwarzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.6102/zis119</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.6102/zis119" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ZIS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decade of system justification theory: Accumulated evidence of conscious and unconscious bolstering of the status quo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Banaji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nosek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="881" to="919" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Political conservatism as motivated social cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Glaser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kruglanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sulloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0033-2909.129.3.339</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.129.3.339" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors affecting social change: A social-psychological interpretation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1540-4560.1983.tb00173.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1540-4560.1983.tb00173.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Issues</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">God and the government: Testing a compensatory control mechanism for the support of external systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gaucher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Napier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Callan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Laurin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.95.1.18</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.95.1.18" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authoritarianism and its relationship with intuitive-experiential cognitive style and heuristic processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kemmelmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.paid.2009.08.012</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2009.08.012" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Individual Differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uncontrollability as irreducible uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kofta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sedek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5-6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What breeds conspiracy antisemitism? The role of political uncontrollability and uncertainty in the belief in Jewish conspiracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kofta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Soral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bilewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/pspa0000183</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/pspa0000183" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="900" to="918" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The uncertainty challenge: Escape it, embrace it</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kruglanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ellenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The psychology of insecurity</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="73" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The need for certainty as a psychological nexus for individuals and society</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kruglanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Orehek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Extremism and the psychology of uncertainty</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hogg</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Blaylock</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compensatory control and the appeal of a structured world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Landau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Whitson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0038703</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0038703" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="694" to="722" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Materialist and post-materialist concerns and the wish for a strong leader in 27 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E O</forename><surname>Lima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>De França</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Wohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Jasinskaja-Lahti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Costa-Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ariyanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Autin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Badea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Besta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Butera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fantini-Hauwel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Finchilescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gaertner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gollwitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Van Der Bles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5964/jspp.6213</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5964/jspp.6213" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social and Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authoritarianism, anomia, and prejudice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lutterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Middleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Forces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="492" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The psychology of the COVID-19 pandemic: A group-level perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Marmarosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Forsyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Burlingame</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/gdn0000142</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/gdn0000142" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Group Dynamics: Theory, Research, and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anomie, authoritarianism, prejudice, and socioeconomic status: An attempt at clarification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mcdill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2573215</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2573215" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Forces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social structure and anomie</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Merton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2084686</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2084686" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="672" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="1938">1938</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Societal threat to safety, compensatory control, and Right-Wing Authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mirisola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Roccato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Spagna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vieno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/pops.12048</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/pops.12048" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="795" to="812" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Threat to democracy: The appeal of authoritarianism in an age of uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Moghaddam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>American Psychological Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Full-cycle social psychology for theory and application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mortensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cialdini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social and Personality Psychology Compass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">It&apos;s (a) Shame: Why Poverty Leads to Support for Authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Neerdaels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tröster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Van Quaquebeke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="942" to="956" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Life events and substance use among adolescents: mediating effects of perceived loss of control and meaninglessness in life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Newcomb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Harlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">564</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social dominance orientation, right-wing authoritarianism, and their relation with alienation and spheres of control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A M</forename><surname>Nicol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.paid.2007.02.014</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2007.02.014" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Individual Differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="891" to="899" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The authoritarian-conservatism nexus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nilsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cobeha.2020.03.003</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cobeha.2020.03.003" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Behavioral Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="148" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cultural Backlash: Trump, Brexit, and authoritarian populism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Norris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Inglehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/9781108595841</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/9781108595841" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flight into security: A new approach and measure of the authoritarian personality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Oesterreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-9221.2005.00418.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9221.2005.00418.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sociology: A lost connection in social psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kesebir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Snyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="334" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design approaches to experimental mediation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pirlott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jesp.2015.09.012</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jesp.2015.09.012" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect size measures for mediation models: Quantitative strategies for communicating indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Preacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0022658</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0022658" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Threat-Compensation in Social Psychology: Is There a Core Motivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Proulx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1521/soco.2012.30.6.643</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1521/soco.2012.30.6.643" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="643" to="651" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Trust issues: Dealing with distrust in politics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Quilter-Pinner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Statham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Jennings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Valgarðsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The lasting effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on support for anti-democratic political systems: A six-month longitudinal study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Roccato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Colloca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cavazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2285" to="2295" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Age differences in right-wing authoritarianism and their relation to emotion recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ruffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kladnitski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Myftari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Halberstadt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/emo0000107</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/emo0000107" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Emotion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Economic threat as a determinant of conversion rates in authoritarian and nonauthoritarian churches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/h0033157</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/h0033157" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Threat as a factor in authoritarianism: An analysis of archival data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/h0035588</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/h0035588" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anomie, authoritarianism and ethnocentrism: Update of a classic theme and an empirical test</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scheepers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Felling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Politics &amp; the Individual</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Helplessness: On depression, development, and health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Seligman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>WH Freeman</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-determination: The tyranny of freedom</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0003-066X.55.1.79</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0003-066X.55.1.79" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Psychologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sidanius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pratto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Social dominance: An intergroup theory of social hierarchy and oppression</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Establishing a causal chain: Why experiments are often more effective than mediational analyses in examining psychological processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zanna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.89.6.845</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.89.6.845" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="851" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Our country needs a strong leader right now&quot;: Economic inequality enhances the wish for a strong leader</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sprong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mols</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Verkuyten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ariyanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Autin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Badea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Besta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Butera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Costa-Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fantini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Finchilescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gaertner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gollwitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Wohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0956797619875472</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797619875472" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1625" to="1637" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of seemingly unrelated regression equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dwivedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0304-4076(79)90061-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/0304-4076(79)90061-7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When we are worried, what are we thinking? Anxiety, lack of control, and conspiracy beliefs amidst the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Šrol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ballová Mikušková</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Čavojová</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/acp.3798</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/acp.3798" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Cognitive Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="720" to="729" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Integration and certain corollaries: An exploratory study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Srole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2088422</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2088422" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">709</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Stata Statistical Software: Release 15</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Statacorp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Llc</forename><surname>Statacorp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The authoritarian dynamic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stenner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/CBO9780511614712</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511614712" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relative validity of inferences about mediation as a function of research design characteristics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stone-Romero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rosopa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1094428107300342</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1094428107300342" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modernization, formal social control, and anomie: A 45-society multilevel analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Swader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0020715217736556</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0020715217736556" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Comparative Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="494" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a psychological analysis of anomie</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teymoori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1009" to="1023" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting the measurement of anomie</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teymoori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ariyanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Autin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Badea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Besta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Butera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Costa-Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fantini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Finchilescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gaertner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gollwitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Á</forename><surname>Gómez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>González</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0158370</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0158370" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">158370</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://stats.oarc.ucla.edu/stata/faq/how-can-i-do-mediation-analysis-with-a-categorical-iv-in-stata/" />
		<title level="m">How can I do mediation analysis with a categorical IV in Stata?</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Statistical Consulting Group</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2021b</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>UCLA</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>How can I analyze multiple mediators in Stata?</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The consequences of collective discontent: A new measure of zeitgeist predicts voting for extreme parties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Van Der Bles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Postmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lekander-Kanis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Otjes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="398" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Individual differences in causal uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Weary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.67.2.308</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.67.2.308" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="318" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The causal uncertainty model revisited</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Weary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tobin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of the uncertain self</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arkin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Oleson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Psychology Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="100" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bacon: An effective way to detect outliers in multivariate data using Stata (and Mata)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1536867X1001000302</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1536867X1001000302" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Stata Journal: Promoting Communications on Statistics and Stata</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b110">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acceptance of uncertainty as an indicator of effective leadership</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shullman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Consulting Psychology Journal: Practice and Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b111">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lacking control increases illusory pattern perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Whitson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Galinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5898</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b112">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How representative are student convenience samples? A study of literacy and numeracy skills in 32 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-J</forename><surname>Kyröläinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kuperman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0271191</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0271191" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">271191</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b113">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chapter 6 ostracism: A temporal need-threat model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0065-2601(08)00406-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0065-2601(08)00406-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="314" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b114">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The existential function of right-wing authoritarianism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Womick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Heintzelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Woody</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jopy.12457</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/jopy.12457" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1056" to="1073" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b115">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Religious fundamentalism, right-wing authoritarianism, and meaning in life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Womick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Woody</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jopy.12665</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/jopy.12665" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b116">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The apathy syndrome: How we are trained not to care about politics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zhelnina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/socpro/spz019References</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/socpro/spz019References" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Problems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b117">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bechert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Quandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">ISSP data report: Attitudes towards the role of government</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>GESIS -Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b118">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: Conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1173</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b119">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of factor analysis in the development and evaluation of personality scales</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Briggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cheek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-6494.1986.tb00391.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-6494.1986.tb00391.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b120">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antecedents of causal uncertainty and perceived control: A prospective study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Weary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Personality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b121">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seemingly unrelated regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fiebig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/9780470996249.ch6</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470996249.ch6" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A companion to theoretical econometrics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Baltagi</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="121" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b122">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der Sozialwissenschaften ALLBUS</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4232/1.10832</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4232/1.10832" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2011. 2006. 4500</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Köln</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>GESIS -Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften ; GESIS Datenarchiv</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b123">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to mediation, moderation, and conditional process analysis: A regression-based approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>First edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b124">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to mediation, moderation, and conditional process analysis: A regression-based approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Guilford Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b125">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical mediation analysis with a multicategorical independent variable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Preacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Mathematical and Statistical Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b126">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What breeds conspiracy antisemitism? The role of political uncontrollability and uncertainty in the belief in Jewish conspiracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kofta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Soral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bilewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/pspa0000183</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/pspa0000183" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="900" to="918" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b127">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect size measures for mediation models: Quantitative strategies for communicating indirect effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Preacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0022658</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0022658" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b128">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Our country needs a strong leader right now&quot;: Economic inequality enhances the wish for a strong leader</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sprong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mols</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Verkuyten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ariyanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Autin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Badea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Besta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Butera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Costa-Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fantini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Finchilescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gaertner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gollwitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Wohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0956797619875472</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797619875472" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1625" to="1637" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b129">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of seemingly unrelated regression equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dwivedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0304-4076(79)90061-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/0304-4076(79)90061-7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b130">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a psychological analysis of anomie</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teymoori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1009" to="1023" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b131">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting the measurement of anomie</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teymoori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ariyanto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Autin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Badea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Besta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Butera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Costa-Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fantini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Finchilescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gaertner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gollwitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Á</forename><surname>Gómez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>González</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0158370</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0158370" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">158370</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b132">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://stats.oarc.ucla.edu/stata/faq/how-can-i-do-mediation-analysis-with-a-categorical-iv-in-stata/" />
		<title level="m">How can I do mediation analysis with a categorical IV in Stata?</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Statistical Consulting Group</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>UCLA</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b133">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The causal uncertainty model revisited</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Weary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tobin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of the uncertain self</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arkin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Oleson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Psychology Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="100" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
