<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Societal inferences from the physical world</title>
				<funder ref="#_dpwFmJu #_r3nXqzh #_PED2dJC">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rodney</forename><surname>Tompkins</surname></persName>
							<email>rtompkins@ucsd.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Diego</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Julian</forename><surname>Jara-Ettinger</surname></persName>
							<email>julian.jara-ettinger@yale.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wu-Tsai Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Yale University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Adena</forename><surname>Schachner</surname></persName>
							<email>adschachner@ucsd.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Diego</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Moffett</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Societal inferences from the physical world</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">67C83160F01780CCF795AF68CC0029D5</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-23T06:20+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Moffett points to humans' use of physical markers to signal group identity as crucial to human society. We characterize the developmental and cognitive bases of this capacity, arguing that it is part of an early-emerging, intuitive socio-physical interface which allows the inanimate world to encode rich social meaning about individuals' identities, and the values of the society as a whole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main Text</head><p>Moffett proposes that a critical feature of human society is our ability to use physical markers as signals of shared group identity. We agree this is a notable feature of human cognition, and here argue that the use of physical markers to signal group identity is part of a broader human capacity to use the inanimate world as a rich source of social information. This reasoning, which we term the socio-physical interface, allows the inanimate world to encode social meaning, and is key to human social intelligence (Jara-Ettinger &amp; Schachner, submitted). This supports our ability to detect and signal societal membership by using "things we make as a kind of societal extended phenotype" <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Moffett, 2024)</ref>.</p><p>A key question in the target article is the extent to which the ability to use physical markers as signs of group identity is early-emerging and intuitive for humans. Developmental research provides evidence of this: Children attend to physical markers of group membership from early in life, demonstrating a mental theory of intuitive sociology <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Liberman et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Shutts &amp; Kalish, 2021)</ref>. Young children use group membership to predict others' external behaviors and internal mental states <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kinzler, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Shutts &amp; Kalish, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Tompkins et al., 2023)</ref>. Children also use physical attributes as markers of power structures, inferring who is 'in charge' and which group holds higher status <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Brey &amp; Shutts, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Dukler &amp; Liberman, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Shutts &amp; Kalish, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Humans intuitively use physical markers to make a wide variety of social inferences, and reasoning about societal identity from these markers may be understood as part of this broader reasoning capacity. To link physical cues with social meaning, we at times rely on perceptual processes, which support quick perception of objects' recent history, and detection of objects shaped by agents <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Chen &amp; Scholl, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Lopez-Brau et al., 2021)</ref>. Perceptual features also support inferences about group identity. For example, children can use attributes</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>like clothing color to track group identity, particularly if clothing color previously predicted cooperative behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Shutts &amp; Kalish, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>People also use high-level causal reasoning to infer social information from physical markers, using mental theories of physics and psychology <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Spelke, 2022)</ref>. The resulting integrated causal theory allows for rational inferences about others' behavior, mental states, traits, and potentially societal identity, from physical cues alone. From static physical objects (e.g., a block tower; a dresser with some drawers open and others closed), even young children can infer others' goals, levels of skill, and knowledge states in a way that is wellpredicted by Bayesian causal inference <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Gweon et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Lopez-Brau et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Pelz al., 2020)</ref>. From childhood, humans can engage in event reconstruction, inferring the particular past behaviors that shaped inanimate features <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Lopez-Brau et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Pesowski et al., 2020)</ref>. For example, people can reconstruct an agent's actions from cookie crumbs left behind, or a small object left to communicate that a spot is taken <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Lopez-Brau et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr">2023)</ref>. When viewing multiple objects, children and adults can use event reconstruction to infer when a design was copied, and thus trace social transmission of ideas <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Hurwitz et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Pesowski et al., 2020)</ref>. Engaging in this complex causal inference may be cognitively slow and computationally expensive. However, people create shortcuts: We store the results as simple associations, and avoid constant use of complex reasoning by substituting heuristics in future similar situations <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Lopez-Brau et al., 2023)</ref>. In this way, both simple heuristics and theory-based causal reasoning link the social and physical world in the human mind, creating a rich socio-physical interface.</p><p>Societal identities directly shape which objects people create or possess, by motivating particular choices (of culturally-valued goods), or by determining their knowledge (of culturally-specific technologies or styles). Thus, the socio-physical interface may also support early-emerging inferences about societal identities from physical markers through causal reasoning about how objects or design ideas were created or obtained.</p><p>To be diagnostic of societal identity, physical markers should be difficult-to-fake, honest signals of a person's socio-cultural past (their social connections and cultural exposure). For example, linguistic accents vary by group and are notoriously hard to modify, and serve as informative social cues from infancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kinzler, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>By this principle, objects that require specific, learned knowledge to create should be more diagnostic of one's social identity than other objects. Such design ideas are unlikely to be generated the same way twice independently, and therefore imply that learning via sociocultural contact has occurred. This can involve unique functional designs, as in complex, passed-down cultural knowledge of tool design <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Henrich, 2015)</ref>. It can also involve unique style: Things like art, music, cuisine, and dress should be particularly diagnostic of societal identity, because their styles are highly variable and learned <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Soley &amp; Spelke, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Children are sensitive to this: They can trace social transmission of design ideas person-to-person by detecting suspicious coincidences in the features of objects they create <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Pesowski et al., 2020)</ref>. Children also use knowledge of culturally-specific objects like food and musical instruments (and not general world knowledge) to infer others' social affiliations and cultural groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Öner &amp; Soley, 2023)</ref>. Similarly, infants and children use clothing as markers of group-specific social preferences and knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bian &amp; Baillargeon, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Weatherhead et al., 2022)</ref>.</p><p>Physical markers in urban design also provide information about societies at large, allowing for rich, inductive inferences. The placement of a religious building, library, or social gathering place at a prominent location may signal the relative value that society places on different activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Gehl, 2013)</ref>. People intuitively view physical markers as having social messages: This understanding motivates action to remove Confederate monuments in the American South <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Booth &amp; Kizzire, 2016)</ref>. These monuments in particular hold nuanced, tragic information about societal history. The number of lynchings of Black people in the historic record can be predicted by the number of Confederate memorials in that area <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Henderson et al., 2021)</ref>. People may infer endorsement, or at least tolerance, of nuanced political and moral views by the current society from its monuments. Interventions to change physical markers like monuments may powerfully change social values, by changing members' understanding of norms.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank <rs type="person">Michael Lopez-Brau</rs>, <rs type="person">Madison Pesowski</rs> and <rs type="person">Ethan Hurwitz</rs> for important conversations that helped develop these ideas.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><head>Funding</head><p>This material is based upon work supported by <rs type="funder">National Science Foundation</rs> Grants <rs type="grantNumber">DGE-2038238</rs> to RT, <rs type="grantNumber">BCS-2045778</rs> to JJE, and <rs type="grantNumber">BCS-1749551</rs> to AS.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_dpwFmJu">
					<idno type="grant-number">DGE-2038238</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_r3nXqzh">
					<idno type="grant-number">BCS-2045778</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PED2dJC">
					<idno type="grant-number">BCS-1749551</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When are similar individuals a group? Early reasoning about similarity and in-group support</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Baillargeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/09567976211055185</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/09567976211055185" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="752" to="764" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Booth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kizzire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.splcenter.org/whose-heritage" />
		<title level="m">Whose heritage? Public symbols of the Confederacy</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-05-30">2016. 30 May 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Children use nonverbal cues to make inferences about social power</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shutts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/cdev.12334</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/cdev.12334" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Child Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The perception of history: Seeing causal history in static shapes induces illusory motion perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0956797616628525</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797616628525" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="923" to="930" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Children use race to infer who is &quot;in charge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dukler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jecp.2022.105447</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jecp.2022.105447" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Child Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">221</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105447</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gehl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cities for People</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Island Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reverse-engineering the process: Adults&apos; and preschoolers&apos; ability to infer the difficulty of novel tasks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gweon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Asaba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bennett-Pierre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 39th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</title>
		<meeting>the 39th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Powers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Claibourn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Brown-Iannuzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Trawalter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2103519118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Henrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Secret of Our Success: How Culture is Driving Human Evolution, Domesticating Our Species, and Making Us Smarter</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting social transmission in the design of artifacts via inverse planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hurwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schachner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 41st Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</title>
		<meeting>the 41st Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jara-Ettinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schachner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/s8eka" />
		<title level="m">Traces of our past: The social representation of the physical world</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Order, order everywhere, and only an agent to think: The cognitive compulsion to infer intentional agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Keil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/mila.12074</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/mila.12074" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mind &amp; Language</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Language as a social cue</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kinzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-psych-010418-103034</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-psych-010418-103034" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="264" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The origins of social categorization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kinzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tics.2017.04.004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tics.2017.04.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends in Cognitive Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="556" to="568" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preverbal infants infer third-party social relationships based on language</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kinzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/cogs.12403</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/cogs.12403" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognitive Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="622" to="634" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">People can use the placement of objects to infer communicative goals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lopez-Brau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jara-Ettinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cognition.2023.105524</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cognition.2023.105524" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">239</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105524</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attentional prioritization for historical traces of agency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lopez-Brau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Colombatto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jara-Ettinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1167/jov.21.9.2748</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1167/jov.21.9.2748" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2748</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social inferences from physical evidence via Bayesian event reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lopez-Brau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jara-Ettinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/xge0001182</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/xge0001182" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Psychology: General</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2029" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is a society? Building an interdisciplinary perspective and why that&apos;s important</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Moffett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavioral and Brain Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Children use epistemic states flexibly to make diagnostic social inferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Öner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Soley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/dev0001653</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/dev0001653" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Developmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2277" to="2286" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The signature of all things: Children infer knowledge states from static images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pelz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jara-Ettinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 42nd Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</title>
		<meeting>the 42nd Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Children use inverse planning to detect social transmission in the design of artifacts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pesowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Quy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schachner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 42nd Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</title>
		<meeting>the 42nd Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expectations of intergroup empathy bias emerge by early childhood</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tompkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vasquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gerdin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dunham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/xge0001505</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/xge0001505" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Psychology: General</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shared cultural knowledge: Effects of music on young children&apos;s social preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Soley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Spelke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cognition.2015.09.017</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cognition.2015.09.017" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intuitive sociology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shutts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kalish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/bs.acdb.2021.05.004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/bs.acdb.2021.05.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in Child Development and Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Spelke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">What Babies Know</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wearing your knowledge on your sleeve: Young children&apos;s reasoning about clothing as a marker of group-specific knowledge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weatherhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nancekivell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cogdev.2022.101177</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cogdev.2022.101177" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognitive Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101177</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
