<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A reboot of Richard Owen&apos;s common archetype theory</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Fazale</forename><surname>Rana</surname></persName>
							<email>frana@reasons.org</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hugh</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Reasons to Believe</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91724</postCode>
									<settlement>Covina</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Reasons to Believe</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91724</postCode>
									<settlement>Covina</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A reboot of Richard Owen&apos;s common archetype theory</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">AF01279C5EB45FD93901BD4AEFAF7517</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:55+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>common design</term>
					<term>self-collapse</term>
					<term>common designer</term>
					<term>Richard Owen</term>
					<term>process structuralism</term>
					<term>quantum consciousness</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Developed a common design view of viruses and origins.</head><p>• Conducted the literature review for the fitness</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>In the mid-19th century, two prominent figures emerged, offering distinct explanations for species diversity: Richard Owen and Charles Darwin <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>. Owen, a distinguished natural scientist, engaged in scholarly debate with Darwin, whose groundbreaking work revolutionized evolutionary theory. Their contrasting views laid the foundation for a discourse that would shape biological thought for generations <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>.</p><p>Owen's concept of a "common archetype" challenged Darwin's theory of natural selection, suggesting that species similarities indicated shared design rather than common ancestry <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>. He argued that the repetition of a single vertebral element in vertebrates supported this idea, with each vertebral element adapting independently to functional needs or environmental pressures while maintaining a homotypic structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>. Owen also suggested that human cognitive traits, like the hippocampus minor, deviated from evolutionary predictions, challenging our descent from apes <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quantum Biology and Its Role in Evolution:</head><p>Quantum biology potentially offers a novel framework for understanding how life evolves not just through random mutations and natural selection, but through underlying organizing principles that may include quantum mechanics. For example, quantum coherence might influence mutation rates, genetic stability, and the broader evolutionary process, aligning with Owen's view of life as being guided by a deeper, organizing force.</p><p>Quantum Effects in Evolutionary Processes: If quantum states influence mutation rates or the stability of constants such as gravity or the fine-structure constant, we can begin to see how quantum biology might align with Owen's archetype theory. These quantum processes might help guide evolutionary outcomes in a way that transcends randomness and natural selection alone. However, this remains speculative and requires further testing to establish its validity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quantum Consciousness and Life's Design:</head><p>The possibility that quantum processes play a role in consciousness introduces the question of whether these processes reflect a purposeful design. Could the coherence and stability found in quantum systems point to an underlying intelligent design?</p><p>Integrating Quantum Biology with Intelligent Design: Just as quantum mechanics governs interactions at the subatomic level, intelligent design could offer a framework for how quantum processes are organized in a purposeful way. While quantum processes enable life to exist, they might also be the means by which life is structured, maintaining the integrity of Owen's archetypes through an intelligent, guiding force. However, the concept of intelligent design is often in conflict with the scientific community, particularly in evolutionary biology and physics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion: Bridging Quantum Biology and Owen's Archetypes</head><p>Quantum biology offers an intriguing framework for understanding how quantum processes shape biological systems. By integrating quantum consciousness and intelligent design, we propose a model that challenges traditional evolutionary perspectives and emphasizes a purposeful design underlying life's complexity. However, while quantum biology is grounded in empirical research, the inclusion of intelligent design as a guiding force remains speculative and requires further validation.</p><p>In quantum mechanics, the universal wave-function determines the possible states of particles in the universemuch like a guidebook outlining all potential paths. Similarly, Owen's archetype theory can be viewed as a "blueprint" for life, guiding the diversity of species across time. This analogy between the universal wave-function and Owen's archetype is crucial for bridging quantum mechanics with evolutionary biology. Just as the wavefunction organizes quantum possibilities into distinct outcomes, Owen's archetype suggests that life forms emerge according to preordained patterns that are consistent across species. Integrating quantum biology into this framework allows us to understand how these archetypal patterns might be realized at the molecular and genetic levels, further supporting the hypothesis of a purposeful, design-driven process underlying life's diversity. This perspective offers a novel way to reinterpret evolutionary mechanisms and provides a more comprehensive framework for understanding life's origins.</p><p>For example, contemporary debates in evolutionary science have prompted a shift towards recognizing the processes by which organisms develop as key factors in evolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>. This has led to a resurgence of process structuralism, a theory originally proposed by Richard Owen. Modern proponents of this theory argue for the existence of hidden natural forces-alongside traditional mechanisms like natural selection, mutations, gene exchange, and epigenetics-that influence biological development <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68]</ref>. Emerging data that challenge the concept of common descent raise important questions about the shared ancestry of living organisms and the adaptive order imposed by natural selection <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref>.</p><p>While traditional evolutionary models focus on gradual changes driven by natural selection, integrating quantum consciousness and process structuralism offers a more comprehensive framework that bridges biology, physics, and consciousness. This aligns with and extends Owen's archetype theory into new, scientifically robust dimensions. This prompts a reevaluation: Do all living organisms share a common ancestor or a common archetype/design? The Extended Modern Synthesis theory is based on two assumptions <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[48]</ref>: <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> mutations are a chance process, and (2) all living organisms share a common ancestor. Intelligent design, suggesting that life's complexity and the fine-tuning of the universe point to purposeful design, has sparked significant debate. Proponents argue for purposeful design, while critics maintain that evolutionary theory provides a sufficient explanation. In this context, external teleology (Plato's view) asserts that purpose is imposed on nature by an external mind, while internal teleology (Aristotle's view) suggests nature itself has inherent purpose <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[40]</ref>. This article integrates both perspectives, proposing that a universal designer may have guided evolutionary processes through a designed framework.</p><p>For example, when scientists describe mutations as "random," they refer to the unintentional nature of the processmutations do not "attempt" to meet an organism's needs at a given moment. Instead, environmental factors influence the rate, not the course, of mutations. Thus, mutations are considered random because no "conscious" intent is involved, suggesting there is no agent selecting adaptive combinations in evolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref>. This article also critiques several assumptions within common descent theory, including the endosymbiosis theory, the artifact hypothesis, and human evolution. While not addressing these models in depth, the article focuses on the role of a common ancestor in explaining evolutionary processes. For instance, Owen's theory did not explain why certain patterns were chosen for design, nor did it account for nested hierarchies between vertebrate species in detail <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b93">94]</ref>.</p><p>The primary objective of this article is to demonstrate that all extant organisms share a common design, traceable to a universal common designer, based on existing literature. First, we provide a brief review of Owen's concept of a common Platonic archetype and its potential connection to human consciousness and the self-collapsing wavefunction, synthesizing theories of quantum consciousness and process structuralism. Next, we argue that a direct design framework better supports this synthesis between the theories than a model of a designer who used a guided evolutionary process to develop life. We then introduce a separate creation model, followed by an adaptive model of species origins, illustrating how major species may have been separately designed and adapted to various environments. Finally, we outline methods for testing the model, including unique falsifiable predictions.</p><p>The rationale for our research approach is evident in this study, which revealed that 56.5% of students perceived evolution as atheistic, even when provided with the option to consider an agnostic perspective <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>. Notably, among the most religious students, those who viewed evolution as atheistic exhibited lower acceptance, discomfort in learning, and a heightened perception of conflict between their personal religious beliefs and evolution compared to those who considered evolution as agnostic <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>. The authors propose that if the observed associations in their study prove to be causally linked, college biology instructors could enhance acceptance of evolution by teaching students that it does not disprove the existence of a God or gods <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>.</p><p>Another rationale guiding our research approach pertains to the implications of Evolution's mechanisms, which generate biological innovations by repurposing existing designs and assembling them to form new ones. Consequently, a prevalent perspective within the scientific community perceives biological systems as inherently flawed <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>. This perception of fundamental flaws leads many scientists to prematurely conclude that biological systems lack purpose or function when initial investigations fail to unveil a clear rationale for their design <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>. Once this determination is made, the motivation to continue studying the system diminishes <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>.</p><p>Therefore, we contend that our enhanced version of Owen's evolution theory not only permits its inclusion in school curricula but also provides an additional avenue for educators to convey to students that evolution does not negate the existence of a God or gods, thereby fostering increased acceptance of evolution. Moreover, it offers a more robust framework for advancing scientific understanding, particularly when the rationale for the structure and function of a specific biological system remains elusive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Extended Common Archetype Theory</head><p>Richard Owen's concept of the universal common archetype posits that all organisms share underlying structural patterns, indicative of a fundamental design. When this theory is extended to incorporate insights from quantum mechanics, it offers a deeper, more robust framework for understanding the origins and complexity of life. Central to this expanded theory is the concept of the universal self-collapsing wave-function, a quantum mechanism that plays a critical role in shaping life forms. Through processes such as non-random mutations, horizontal gene transfer (HGT), and convergent co-option, this mechanism enables organisms to adapt, reproduce, and thrive across diverse environments while maintaining nested patterns of organization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Self-Collapse of the Wave-Function: A Quantum Foundation for Life</head><p>Wave-function: Quantum mechanics is a branch of science that explains how tiny particles, like electrons, behave. One strange concept in quantum mechanics is the idea of the wave-function (also called a quantum state), which can mathematically describe all possible outcomes of an event. Imagine you're flipping a coin-before it lands, it can be in a state of both heads and tails at once. The wave-function is like that 'in-between' state, showing all possibilities.</p><p>Wave-Function Collapse: When the coin finally lands, it 'chooses' heads or tails-this is like the collapse of the wave-function, where all possibilities become one definite outcome changing from an abstract mathematical object to a concrete state in the form of matter and energy.</p><p>Self-collapse in Owen's Theory: Now, in the case of living things, scientists are curious whether our consciousness might play a role in making the 'coin' land in a specific way. Could our thoughts or awareness influence how things at the tiny quantum level work? This is still a big mystery, but it's an idea that some scientists are exploring <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43]</ref>.</p><p>Visualizing the Concept: Imagine rolling a die with six faces. Normally, it lands on a random number, but in the quantum world, you could mentally choose the number, and the die would "collapse" to that number without physical contact. This illustrates how consciousness might influence wave-function collapse, affecting the quantum system's state.</p><p>Quantum Experiments and Consciousness: Interaction-free quantum experiments show that information can be obtained without physical interaction, suggesting that measurement is not just a physical process but a collapse of potential states into a single reality <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[45]</ref>. In this model, consciousness is an active force that shapes the quantum state and integrates teleological principles into physical systems.</p><p>Implications for Biological Systems: By influencing the wave-function in its own brain, consciousness could transcend physical limitations, enabling phenomena such as free moral judgment, decision-making, and the creation of stability in natural laws. This involvement suggests that life's development is not random but an intentional, guided process that actively shapes biological systems, such as gene expression and cellular functions.</p><p>Speculative Nature of Self-collapse: The concept of self-collapse, where the wave-function collapses without external observation, is intriguing but speculative. The role of consciousness in this process is still under investigation and not universally accepted, so it should be viewed as a promising idea requiring further experimental validation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary:</head><p>The wave-function collapse is a key quantum concept explaining how particles "choose" a specific state. Owen's theory extends this, suggesting that consciousness could influence this collapse from within the system itself. Although speculative, this theory opens exciting directions for future scientific inquiry and could significantly impact our understanding of biological complexity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Role of Consciousness</head><p>Consciousness has traditionally been viewed as a byproduct of brain activity. However, the extended common archetype theory suggests that consciousness itself may be a quantum phenomenon interacting with the wavefunction and influencing biological processes. This perspective posits that quantum mechanics governs how the mind shapes the world, with conscious thought playing an active role in collapsing quantum states. This idea resonates with Richard Owen's belief in an underlying force shaping life's diversity. While Owen did not explicitly link this force to consciousness, his framework of archetypes-universal blueprints shaping life's formsprovides a structural foundation that aligns with modern theories like Orch-OR. Unlike the conventional view of consciousness as an emergent property of the brain without causal power, this perspective suggests that consciousness is a fundamental force interacting with the quantum fabric of reality. While Penrose's Orch-OR theory proposes that consciousness results from the collapse of the quantum wave function, our theory shares this idea but differs in how we think this collapse happens and the role gravity plays in the process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Orch-OR and Gravity-Induced Self-Energy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>How Consciousness Works in Orch-OR:</head><p>Orch-OR suggests that conscious experiences happen when quantum states within microtubules (small structures inside cells) collapse in a coordinated way. This collapse is triggered by the energy of these quantum states within the fabric of space-time <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Role of Gravity:</head><p>Gravity plays a key role in the process. The energy associated with the superposition of states (where particles exist in multiple possible states) triggers the collapse, producing distinct conscious moments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quantum Coherence:</head><p>For consciousness to emerge, quantum coherence-where particles act in a coordinated, non-random way-must last long enough (milliseconds or more) and across large networks of neurons to allow for this quantum state collapse.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Owen's Theory and the Distinction</head><p>Consciousness in Owen's Theory:</p><p>Owen's extended theory doesn't try to explain consciousness through quantum effects. While quantum phenomena may influence biological processes, Owen viewed them as reflecting the deeper, universal design of lifearchetypes-rather than mechanisms of conscious thought.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>No Need for Gravity-Induced Collapse:</head><p>Owen's theory doesn't rely on specific mechanisms like gravity to explain how consciousness works. Instead, quantum effects like coherence and tunneling are seen as part of the biological design, independent of consciousness or gravity. This makes Owen's theory less vulnerable to criticisms that challenge quantum mind theories, since it is based on more traditional biological and structural principles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Criticisms and Responses:</head><p>1. Biological Implausibility Some critics argue that quantum effects in neurons are biologically unlikely because of factors like thermal noise and decoherence (when quantum states break down in warm, noisy environments).</p><p>• Does this Apply to Owen's Theory? No. Owen's theory doesn't require long-lasting quantum coherence in biological systems. Instead, short-lived quantum effects like coherence are enough to explain how biological systems work. This doesn't conflict with biological constraints like thermal noise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Lack of Empirical Evidence</head><p>Critics argue that there is a lack of direct evidence showing that quantum coherence or quantum processing in microtubules are related to consciousness.</p><p>• Does this Apply to Owen's Theory? No. While Orch-OR doesn't have direct evidence for its connection to consciousness, Owen's theory is supported by experiments showing quantum effects in biological systems <ref type="bibr">[103]</ref>. These effects support the idea that quantum phenomena may reflect archetypal principles, even if they are not directly related to consciousness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Alternative Explanations</head><p>Some critics suggest that traditional neurobiological theories can explain consciousness without needing quantum mechanics.</p><p>• Does this Apply to Owen's Theory? No. Traditional explanations don't account for the quantum effects seen in microtubules and other biological systems. Owen's archetypal principles offer a complementary layer of explanation that helps explain these effects, which conventional models can't fully address <ref type="bibr" target="#b91">[92]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Non-Local Causation and Implications for Universal Design</head><p>One of the key insights from quantum mechanics supporting Owen's extended theory is non-local causation, which suggests that quantum events can influence each other instantaneously, even across vast distances (i.e., simultaneous causation) <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">[88]</ref>. This non-locality is crucial because it implies that quantum events in one part of the universe could be influenced by consciousness elsewhere, even in biological systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">[86,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22]</ref>. For example, quantum entanglement shows that particles in one laboratory can affect particles in another, without physical connection between them, demonstrating that quantum systems, including biological ones, are interconnected and reflect a universal design <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b85">86,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Universal Wave-Function as the Quantum Blueprint for Owen's Archetype</head><p>This concept of non-locality connects to the universal wave-function, a quantum construct representing the vast range of possible quantum states or mathematical configurations of matter, including entire universes <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">[99]</ref>. Rather than existing at a specific place or time, the wave-function represents all possible outcomes of reality.</p><p>Building on this, the idea of the universal self-collapsing wave-function posits that the universe "decides" its own state, potentially influenced by consciousness. This collapse ensures that life-enabling constants, such as gravity and electromagnetic forces, remain stable to support life.</p><p>Within this speculative framework, quantum non-locality provides a conceptual tool:</p><p>Here is a visual representation of quantum non-locality, illustrating how non-local correlations connect distant particles. The image conceptualizes a global "decision-making" process, where these non-local connections lead to stable parameters and outcomes chosen by the universal wave-function. This diagram captures the interconnectedness and quantum coherence that spans across vast distances.</p><p>This can be imagined as a cosmic dice game. While there are many possible outcomes, only one materializes when the dice land-much like how the wave-function collapses into a stable configuration of physical constants, potentially guided by consciousness. These non-local connections could be what ensures the universe's collapse into life-supporting conditions.</p><p>This idea parallels Richard Owen's archetype theory, where all life forms share a common blueprint. Owen's archetype could be seen as analogous to the universal wave-function, with a structural pattern that underlies diverse life forms, much as the Many-Worlds Interpretation suggests that all possible outcomes occur in separate but real "worlds."</p><p>Although quantum non-locality is scientifically well-established <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">[88]</ref>, the proposed interplay between quantum theory and biological archetypes remains highly speculative, extending well beyond the scope of conventional physics. To advance this idea beyond a purely interpretive hypothesis, substantial theoretical and empirical support would be required. Still, the notion that a universal quantum blueprint might influence both fundamental cosmic constants and biological patterns presents an intriguing prospect for further exploration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Universal Self-Collapsing Wave-Function: The Quantum Counterpart to Owen's Archetype</head><p>For life to exist, certain fundamental constants-such as the strength of gravity and the fine-structure constantmust lie within extremely narrow ranges. Even slight deviations in these values would make life impossible, which aligns with Richard Owen's concept of a universal archetype that governs the design of biological forms. This finetuning suggests that life's emergence is not random, but rather part of a purposeful design. Studies have indicated that these dimensionless constants, determining the universe's physical laws and properties, are not arbitrary. Instead, they appear finely tuned to foster the emergence of life and consciousness, remaining stable throughout cosmic history <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">52]</ref>.</p><p>The universal self-collapsing wave-function (USCWF) offers a quantum-level explanation for maintaining these life-sustaining conditions. Serving as a quantum counterpart to Owen's archetype, the USCWF provides a deterministic mechanism that ensures the stability of fundamental constants. Unlike speculative theories such as String Theory, the USCWF model posits that the wave-function collapses in a predictable way. According to this perspective, consciousness may play an active role in guiding this collapse, reflecting Owen's idea of a purposeful organizing principle behind life's creation.</p><p>Recent research provides some support for aspects of this model, hinting that quantum processes in the brain-such as those involved in decision-making and perception-adhere to quantum principles <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38,</ref><ref type="bibr">102]</ref>. In one experimental scenario, evidence of quantum entanglement in the brain suggests that consciousness-related brain functions might influence quantum coherence <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref>. This implies that consciousness could actively shape quantum systems and, by extension, the conditions necessary for life <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>.</p><p>An analogy often used to illustrate the role of quantum coherence in the brain is that of a busy city:</p><p>In this metaphor, electrical signals in the brain act like cars moving through intersections, following defined patterns. Quantum consciousness proposes that hidden "traffic lights", or unseen quantum-level ordering principles, synchronize this neural traffic, making it more efficient and purposeful than it seems at the surface level. These quantum effects-like coherence-are thought to guide conscious thought and contribute to the stability of biological processes at the molecular level, much like hidden patterns within traffic management make city movement more coordinated.</p><p>Despite these intriguing hints, the precise mechanisms linking consciousness and quantum entanglement remain unclear and are not widely accepted within the scientific community. While the findings suggest the possibility of non-classical quantum operations in the brain, no definitive theory or conclusive evidence currently establishes a direct connection between consciousness and quantum phenomena. Quantum consciousness remains a frontier of inquiry, and future research will determine whether it stands up to empirical scrutiny or requires substantial revision.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implications for Life's Origins: A Teleological Model</head><p>The integration of quantum mechanics with Owen's archetype theory leads to a teleological model of life's origins. This model suggests that life and consciousness are not mere byproducts of physical systems but are rooted in the intentional design of the universe. By combining insights from quantum biology with Owen's theory of archetypes, this perspective proposes that consciousness actively participates in maintaining stable life-sustaining constants, such as gravity and dark energy, within ranges that permit life:</p><p>This teleological model reinforces the idea that the universe is purposeful, with consciousness as a driving force that shapes and sustains the physical constants essential for life. The synthesis of quantum mechanics, consciousness, and biological design offers a richer understanding of the universe's intentional design, complementing Owen's archetype theory with a quantum foundation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Predictions Supporting Owen's Universal Self-Collapsing Wave-Function</head><p>The confirmed predictions that directly support Owen's universal self-collapsing wave-function (USCWF) theory align with the idea that consciousness and quantum processes are intimately connected. The stability of universal constants, quantum coherence, and the collapse of the wave-function are all integral to biological and cognitive functions. Below is how these predictions connect with Owen's theory:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Fine-Structure Constant Stability</head><p>• Prediction: Studies suggest that any deviation in the fine-structure constant (which governs the strength of electromagnetic interactions) could disrupt the conditions necessary for life. • Empirical Support: Recent studies have refined the precision of the fine-structure constant, highlighting its critical role in maintaining the conditions for life [107].</p><p>• Connection to USCWF: This stability of universal constants directly supports the idea of a universal selfcollapsing wave-function (USCWF), where quantum processes must maintain coherence and fine-tune physical constants for life to exist. The USCWF model implies that the wave-function guiding the universe collapses to maintain constants like the fine-structure constant within narrow tolerances, which are essential for life.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Dark Energy and Life-Supporting Universes</head><p>• Prediction: Variations in dark energy could disrupt the formation of habitable planets and stars necessary for complex life.</p><p>• Empirical Support: Studies suggest that fluctuations in the expansion rate of the universe due to dark energy can alter conditions for complex life [104,105]. However, this particular model is still incomplete and remains an active area of research [106]. • Connection to USCWF: This supports the universal self-collapsing wave-function by demonstrating that</p><p>the quantum state of the universe must maintain certain fine-tuning (like the expansion rate) for life to exist. The wave-function must collapse in such a way as to sustain conditions that allow for life-supporting structures (e.g., stars, planets), which aligns with the idea that a self-collapsing wave-function stabilizes the conditions necessary for life.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Quantum Coherence in Microtubules</head><p>• Prediction: Orch-OR predicts that quantum coherence can be maintained within microtubules under biological conditions, enabling them to function as quantum processing elements. • Empirical Support: Experimental evidence of quantum vibrations in microtubule molecules suggests that quantum coherence is indeed preserved in living systems, aligning with the Orch-OR proposition <ref type="bibr">[117]</ref>.</p><p>• Connection to USCWF: The presence of stable quantum coherence across diverse species supports the notion of a universal self-collapsing wave-function (USCWF) that operates at fundamental biological levels. By providing a consistent quantum basis across evolutionary divergence, this coherence underpins a universal organizing principle. This harmonizes with Owen's framework, indicating that stable, lifesupporting quantum processes transcend species-specific adaptations, reinforcing the idea of a deep, archetypal pattern guiding biological complexity</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Quantum Vibrations in Microtubules</head><p>• Prediction: Orch-OR predicts that microtubules exhibit vibrational modes that support quantum processing. • Empirical Support: Experimental findings show that resonant vibrations in microtubules align with brain-relevant EEG frequencies (10-40 Hz), suggesting that quantum coherence underlies conscious processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b78">79]</ref>. • Connection to USCWF: This directly supports the USCWF model by illustrating how quantum coherence within microtubules (acting as quantum bits or qubits) enables consciousness to affect and be affected by quantum states. The coherence in microtubules contributes to maintaining stability at the quantum level, implying a self-collapsing wave-function that organizes quantum states to maintain biological and cognitive processes, facilitating decision-making and consciousness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Tubulin Dipole Oscillations</head><p>• Prediction: Orch-OR proposes that tubulin proteins in microtubules act as quantum bits (qubits) via dipole oscillations. • Empirical Support: Experimental findings indicate that tubulin dimers exhibit dynamic dipole behavior, consistent with the requirements for quantum processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">5,</ref><ref type="bibr">115,</ref><ref type="bibr">116</ref>].</p><p>• Connection to USCWF: The role of tubulin dipole oscillations in quantum computation aligns with the USCWF model, suggesting that consciousness modulates quantum behavior at the level of microtubules. The quantum self-collapse in these structures enables complex cognitive functions, such as decision-making and probabilistic reasoning, supporting the idea that consciousness plays a causal role in shaping quantum states at the biological level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of Predictions Supporting the Universal Self-Collapsing Wave-Function (USCWF)</head><p>1. Fine-Structure Constant Stability -Suggests that quantum processes must collapse the wave-function in a way that fine-tunes constants like the fine-structure constant, which are essential for life. 2. Dark Energy and Life-Supporting Universes -Supports the idea that quantum states, and their collapse, maintain conditions for life by stabilizing dark energy and the expansion of the universe. 3. Quantum Coherence in Microtubules: Quantum coherence can be maintained within microtubules under biological conditions, enabling them to function as quantum processing elements. 4. Quantum Vibrations in Microtubules -Demonstrates that quantum coherence in microtubules (in brain functions) plays a role in maintaining stable quantum states and guiding conscious processes. 5. Tubulin Dipole Oscillations -The quantum bits formed by tubulin oscillations show that consciousness can directly modulate quantum behavior, providing causal influence over cognitive functions.</p><p>These predictions collectively reinforce the idea of a universal self-collapsing wave-function that regulates and organizes quantum states in a way that supports consciousness and the stability of life-supporting conditions in the universe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The Direct Design Framework</head><p>The universal self-collapsing wave-function presents a robust framework connecting quantum mechanics, consciousness, and Owen's archetype. Its deterministic nature eliminates the need for a multiverse while offering a teleological explanation for the universe's fine-tuning. By integrating insights from quantum biology, genomics, and structural design, the direct design framework expands on Owen's theory to explain life's origins and adaptability. This section introduces two complementary models-the polarizing force model and the adaptive masks model-to illustrate how biological complexity emerges within this framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quantum Coherence and Its Role in the Models</head><p>In this section, we will explore how quantum mechanics, a field traditionally associated with the behavior of particles at the smallest scales, could potentially influence biological systems at the molecular level, such as in DNA replication and neural processes, through quantum coherence.</p><p>Quantum coherence plays a crucial role in both Owen's polarizing force and adaptive mask models, particularly in explaining how biological systems maintain foundational, invariant principles despite evolutionary divergence across species. The key links between these models and quantum coherence is the idea of a universal organizing principle that transcends species-specific evolutionary adaptations and is rooted in the fundamental laws of quantum mechanics, specifically electron tunneling and its effects on biochemical processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>. Moreover, the analogous nature of electron tunneling in biological systems resembles engineering principles found in artificial electronic devices, such as transistors and diodes <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>. Electron tunneling processes in biological systems are highly optimized, with transfer rates exceeding expectations based on classical tunneling theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Defining Quantum Coherence</head><p>Quantum coherence is when particles, like electrons, work together in a synchronized way, almost like a perfectly coordinated dance. Instead of being in one state or another, these particles can exist in multiple possibilities at once until they are measured.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simplified Summary:</head><p>Here is a diagram illustrating the concept of quantum coherence, where each musician plays their instrument in harmony with the others, creating beautiful music. In a similar way, quantum coherence is like the 'synchronization' of particles inside a living organism. Normally, particles like electrons behave like tiny, individual players. But when they achieve quantum coherence, they act together in a coordinated way, like the musicians playing in perfect harmony. Without this coherence, the 'music' of biological systems could fall out of tune, causing inefficiencies or errors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Example to Include:</head><p>In parts of our cells called microtubules (think of them like the cell's scaffold or skeleton), quantum coherence might help keep everything running smoothly, ensuring that cells can do their jobs efficiently by maintaining a form of 'harmony' at the quantum level. This highlights the stability of the "primal patterns" that Owen proposed, suggesting that certain biological structures are rooted in universal laws of nature rather than random or solely adaptive processes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Owen's Polarizing Force and Quantum Coherence</head><p>In Owen's theory, the polarizing force refers to a fundamental, guiding principle that organizes biological structures. This force is responsible for maintaining the basic blueprint of life, ensuring that despite environmental pressures or evolutionary changes, core biological patterns remain intact across generations <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>. Think of the polarizing force as a master blueprint that guides the design of biological forms.</p><p>Here is a visual metaphor illustrating the idea of an architect's foundational blueprint for a building, symbolizing the stability of biological patterns maintained by quantum coherence while life adapts over time. It shows the transition from blueprint to construction, highlighting both stability and adaptability. This quantum coherence in biological systems acts as a manifestation of this polarizing force.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary</head><p>In summary, quantum coherence helps particles work together in harmony, much like musicians in an orchestra, ensuring the stability of biological systems. The polarizing force maintains the integrity of life's design blueprint, while the universal self-collapsing wave-function ensures the universe's stability, allowing life to thrive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Owen's Adaptive masks and Quantum Coherence</head><p>In Owen's theory, adaptive masks refer to the idea that variations or modifications in the adaptive force (the secondary order shaped by environmental pressures) overlay the foundational, immutable "forms" (the polarizing force) that govern biological structures. This interaction allows organisms to respond and adapt to their specific environments <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>.</p><p>As evolutionary pressures shape the structure and functionality of biological systems, quantum coherence plays a key role in ensuring that adaptations occur without disrupting the underlying principles of life. Quantum coherence allows biological systems to retain fundamental quantum mechanical principles (such as electron transfer and biochemical reactions) while enabling these systems to adapt to environmental changes.</p><p>One example of this adaptability is seen in convergent evolution, where different species in similar environments evolve similar traits despite not sharing a recent common ancestor. The reason for this is that the quantum mechanical principles governing biochemical functions remain unchanged across species <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>. This allows species from different evolutionary lineages to develop similar solutions to common ecological challenges.</p><p>For instance, enzyme structures in different species may evolve differently in response to local environmental factors like temperature or pH. However, quantum coherence ensures that, despite these structural differences, the core biochemical processes-such as oxidation-reduction reactions driven by electron tunneling-remain fundamentally consistent. This allows organisms from diverse evolutionary lineages to function similarly in their environments, as the quantum mechanical principles governing these processes transcend evolutionary divergence <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Connection Between Quantum Mechanics and Owen's Models</head><p>Polarizing Force:</p><p>Quantum coherence supports the polarizing force by providing a constant, universal organizing principle that governs biochemical processes across species <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>. This coherence reflects the invariant form or primal pattern that Owen proposed is at the heart of biological systems. Just as quantum coherence ensures the stability of core biochemical processes, the polarizing force maintains the integrity of life's foundational patterns.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adaptive Masks:</head><p>Similarly, quantum coherence also plays a crucial role in how adaptive masks evolve. The core quantum principles, like electron tunneling, remain unchanged, but structural adaptations-such as the evolution of enzymes to better handle environmental conditions-reflect the dynamic interaction between quantum mechanical principles and environmental pressures <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>. This adaptability is key to how life diversifies across different ecological contexts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Convergence in Evolution:</head><p>Even when species exhibit structural differences, convergent evolution can occur as species develop similar traits in response to similar environmental pressures. This phenomenon highlights how quantum mechanical principles (like electron tunneling) persist across evolutionary paths, guiding biochemical processes across species. This dynamic interplay between immutable physical laws and adaptive responses underscores the evolutionary flexibility and stability within biological systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary:</head><p>In summary, quantum coherence serves as a bridge between the polarizing force and adaptive masks in Owen's models. It ensures the stability of underlying biological principles-such as electron tunneling-while allowing organisms to adapt and evolve in response to environmental pressures. This relationship demonstrates how physical constants, such as those governing quantum mechanics, are intricately woven into the evolutionary processes that shape life.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Predictions Supporting Owen's Polarizing Model</head><p>The polarizing model in Owen's theory suggests that there is a universal organizing principle or archetype that guides biological forms and processes. This model focuses on the stability and invariance of foundational principles, even as species evolve and diversify. Predictions that support this model emphasize universal consistency in biological systems, often through quantum principles or core biological processes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Anesthetics and Quantum Processes</head><p>• Prediction: Orch-OR suggests that anesthetics disrupt quantum coherence in microtubules, leading to the loss of consciousness. • Empirical Support: Studies confirm that anesthetics impact microtubule dynamics and disrupt quantum coherence <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr">114]</ref>. • Connection to Polarizing Model: The disruption of quantum coherence by anesthetics highlights how underlying organizing principles, like quantum coherence, maintain biological order. The stability of these principles in normal conditions and their disruption under specific circumstances suggests a guiding, universal archetype that governs biological function, supporting Owen's polarizing force.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Quantum Effects in Biological Systems</head><p>• Prediction: Biological systems exploit quantum effects for functions like signaling and control.</p><p>• Empirical Support: Evidence of superradiance in biological systems, like microtubules, suggests quantum effects influence cellular signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr">103]</ref>. • Connection to Polarizing Model: The consistent use of quantum effects across biological systems, including cellular signaling, points to fundamental organizing principles that guide biological processes in a coherent, predictable manner, regardless of evolutionary divergence. This aligns with Owen's polarizing model, where underlying forces organize life's complexity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Functional Junk DNA</head><p>• Prediction: Majority of the noncoding regions of the genome are recognized for their function in biological processes, such as transcription regulation and gene expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>. • Empirical Support: ENCODE's findings show over 80% of the genome is functional <ref type="bibr">[119,</ref><ref type="bibr">113]</ref>.</p><p>• Connection to Polarizing Model: The functional activity of what was once considered "junk DNA" suggests that there is an underlying organizing force that governs genome function, even in noncoding regions. This supports Owen's polarizing model, where fundamental patterns and organizing principles persist and guide biological complexity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Quantum Coherence in DNA</head><p>• Prediction: DNA operates as a quantum computer, utilizing quantum principles like entanglement and coherence to optimize genetic processes, such as information transmission and replication. • Empirical Support: Theoretical and experimental studies suggest that DNA's structure and function, including its ability to encode, decode, and transmit genetic information, rely on quantum effects like electron pair resonance and quantum entanglement in nitrogenous bases. These processes enhance the efficiency and precision of biological operations [120]. • Connection to Polarizing Model: The quantum coherence observed in DNA supports the idea of a purposeful design underlying life's complexity. DNA's operation as a quantum computer aligns with Owen's concept of a universal archetype, where life's processes are guided by an organizing quantum principle. This suggests that biological systems are not only shaped by evolutionary forces but are also optimized by quantum processes that reinforce a structured, designed framework for life.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Quantum Tunneling and Genetic Stability</head><p>• Prediction: Quantum effects, such as tunneling, play a crucial role in maintaining genetic stability and influencing mutation rates. • Empirical Support: The experiment modeling the misincorporation of noncomplementary DNA bases shows that quantum tunneling significantly increases the rate of proton transfer, influencing genetic error formation. The calculated rates of error are consistent with experimental observations in DNA, indicating that quantum tunneling is integral to transcription error frequency and genetic mutation <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">[83,</ref><ref type="bibr">129,</ref><ref type="bibr">130</ref>] . • Connection to Owen's Polarizing Force Model: The role of quantum tunneling in stabilizing genetic processes supports the idea that life operates according to an underlying organizing principle or archetype, consistent with Owen's polarizing force model. This model suggests that biological systems maintain core structures through inherent forces, ensuring the accuracy of processes like DNA replication and genetic transmission. The quantum effects observed in this experiment align with the notion of a guiding force, reinforcing the stability and resilience of genetic systems under design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Quantum Effects in Protein Folding</head><p>• Prediction: Quantum principles, such as quantum annealing, optimize biological processes like protein folding and design. • Empirical Support: Experiments with the D-Wave quantum annealer demonstrated its ability to efficiently identify optimal protein folding patterns and solve the protein design problem, achieving a 100% success rate in predicting sequences that fold into desired structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr">118]</ref>.</p><p>• Connection to Owen's Polarizing Force Model: The optimization of biological processes via quantum mechanisms supports Owen's polarizing force model, which posits an inherent organizing principle behind biological systems. Quantum annealing, by optimizing protein folding, reflects a quantum-guided process that maintains stability and efficiency in biological structures. This connection suggests that quantum effects play an active role in preserving and optimizing biological systems, reinforcing the idea of a universal design principle organizing life's complexity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Predictions Supporting Owen's Adaptive Force Model</head><p>The adaptive force model suggests that environmental pressures and evolutionary adaptation work within the framework of a universal archetype to shape life forms. This model emphasizes the adaptations that occur in response to ecological challenges and the non-random nature of these evolutionary processes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Optimization of Mutation Rates</head><p>• Prediction: Mutation rates are optimized to minimize harmful mutations and maximize organismal fitness.</p><p>• Empirical Support: Studies in organisms like E. coli show mutation rates are not random but optimized to preserve fitness [121, 122, 50].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Connection to Adaptive Force Model:</head><p>The non-random nature of mutations and their optimization in response to environmental conditions supports the adaptive force model. The model suggests that adaptive changes are not random but are guided by underlying principles (like quantum coherence) within the framework of universal design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Guided Mutations in Critical Regions</head><p>• Prediction: Mutations occur in critical genomic regions that enable adaptation to environmental pressures.</p><p>• Empirical Support: Studies of mitochondrial genomes across species show positively selected sites for mutations that enable adaptation <ref type="bibr">[123]</ref>. • Connection to Adaptive Force Model: The guidance of mutations in specific regions aligns with the adaptive force model, indicating that adaptive changes occur within a universal framework and are not random, but guided by principles that optimize survival in a changing environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Fine-Tuning and Quantum Coherence</head><p>• Prediction: Quantum principles like Grover's algorithm naturally optimize biological processes, such as DNA replication <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[59]</ref>. • Empirical Support: Experiments show that quantum effects improve the accuracy of biological processes, such as DNA replication <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Connection to Adaptive Force Model:</head><p>The fine-tuning of biological systems through quantum effects supports the idea that adaptive changes occur in response to underlying principles that optimize biological processes. This shows that adaptation happens within a framework of universal design, where quantum processes help to adapt systems for greater efficiency.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Quantum Effects in Biological Systems</head><p>• Prediction: Biological systems exploit quantum effects for functions like signaling and control.</p><p>• Empirical Support: Evidence of superradiant states in tryptophan networks in microtubules shows quantum effects play a role in cellular signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr">103]</ref>. • Connection to Adaptive Force Model: The adaptive utilization of quantum effects for biological functions like signaling supports the idea of adaptation occurring within a guiding framework of quantum coherence, as organisms adapt to their environments using quantum mechanisms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Convergence in Evolution</head><p>• Prediction: Convergent evolution occurs when unrelated species develop similar traits in response to similar environmental pressures.</p><p>• Empirical Support: Examples like the independent evolution of plants, protozoa, insects, fungi, and mammals, demonstrate convergent evolution [124]. • Connection to Adaptive Force Model: The occurrence of convergent evolution demonstrates that adaptive changes are guided by environmental pressures and underlying quantum principles, supporting the adaptive force model. This shows that adaptations are not random but purposeful within the larger framework of universal design.</p><p>This section highlights how quantum processes, such as quantum tunneling and coherence, can influence biological evolution by altering mutation rates and genetic stability. These processes suggest that evolution may not be solely driven by random mutations, but also by underlying quantum phenomena that guide the stability and adaptability of life. In essence, quantum biology proposes that life's diversity is shaped not just by natural selection and mutations, but by quantum-level processes that help stabilize and optimize genetic information across generations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of Predictions Supporting the Models</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supporting Owen's Polarizing</head><p>Model: 1. Anesthetics and Quantum Processes 2. Quantum Effects in Biological Systems 3. Functional Junk DNA 4. Quantum Coherence in DNA 5. Quantum Tunneling and Genetic Stability 6. Quantum Effects in Protein Folding These predictions emphasize the invariance and universality of organizing principles in biological systems, reflecting Owen's concept of a universal archetype or polarizing force that transcends evolutionary divergence. Supporting Owen's Adaptive Force Model: 1. Optimization of Mutation Rates 2. Guided Mutations in Critical Regions 3. Fine-Tuning and Quantum Coherence 4. Quantum Effects in Biological Systems</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Convergence in Evolution</head><p>These predictions highlight how evolutionary adaptations occur within the framework of a universal archetype, guided by non-random principles such as quantum coherence to optimize survival and function in response to environmental pressures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of the Direct Design Framework</head><p>By synthesizing Owen's archetype with insights from quantum biology and genomics, the Direct Design Framework offers a unified explanation for life's origins, complexity, and adaptability. It integrates polarizing and adaptive force models to describe how fine-tuned quantum principles drive biological innovation, challenging the sufficiency of unguided processes and emphasizing intentional design as the guiding force behind life's emergence and progression.</p><p>In contrast, guided evolutionary frameworks like theistic evolution struggle to explain key phenomena in the origin and diversification of life. For example, prebiotic chemistry lacks the self-replicating entities necessary for natural selection to operate, presenting an unresolved problem in the transition from non-life to life <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[93]</ref>. Without enzymes or biological machinery, molecules would have needed to form specific structures-such as functional proteins or nucleotide sequences-by random chance, which stretches plausibility, as it assumes the emergence of complex molecular machines from chance alone.</p><p>Additionally, phenomena like horizontal gene transfer (HGT) and polyphyletic viruses challenge evolutionary gradualism. Viruses, which lack a single evolutionary origin, complicate phylogenetic relationships by introducing foreign genes into host genomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>. This non-vertical inheritance suggests a mechanism beyond natural selection. In contrast, the Direct Design Framework accommodates these anomalies by proposing that processes like HGT and viral gene integration are intentional, adaptive strategies implemented by an overarching design <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>.</p><p>As a synthesis of the polarizing and adaptive force models, the Direct Design Framework predicts that many endogenous retroviruses (ERVs)-potentially more than 50%-will possess context-dependent or regulatory functions. This challenges the view of ERVs as "junk" DNA and supports the argument for purposeful design. Such findings would provide additional empirical support for the idea that life's complexity and adaptability are underpinned by intentional design.</p><p>However, it is important to note that the prediction regarding ERVs is speculative. While the hypothesis that ERVs serve regulatory functions presents a novel interpretation, it has not been conclusively demonstrated. Further investigation and empirical support are needed before it can be widely accepted as a scientific explanation. Moreover, we acknowledge that quantum biology is still a developing field and that more studies are needed to directly link quantum processes with the macro-level dynamics of evolutionary biology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objections to Design Inferences: Addressing Critiques of the Framework</head><p>While proponents argue that life exhibits features best explained by a direct design framework, critics, such as Coyne <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref>, emphasize that evolution does not produce perfectly designed organisms but creates adaptations constrained by ancestral history, often resulting in imperfections. Smith <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">[85]</ref> further suggests that flaws or inefficiencies in natural systems challenge the concept of a flawless Intelligent Designer (ID), casting doubt on the idea of an omniscient or benevolent common designer <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p><p>However, many perceived design flaws may stem from unwarranted assumptions rather than evidence of flawed creation. Upon closer examination, functional explanations often emerge, reflecting optimization within biological systems as scientific understanding advances. Numerous studies demonstrate that previously criticized designs serve essential roles, strengthening the case for a purposeful design framework rather than a random, unguided process <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref>[90][8][100][81][98][12][42][76][16][19][9][18][53][80][69][87][78][90][11][20][39]. Noncoding DNA and Its Functional Role One significant development in modern biology is the recognition of the function in noncoding regions of the genome, traditionally dismissed as "junk DNA." Research from the ENCODE project has shown that over 80% of the human genome exhibits biochemical activity, including roles in transcription regulation, DNA methylation, and enhancer-gene interactions [119]. This surpasses the 51% functional threshold proposed in Owen's extended theory, further suggesting the widespread utility of noncoding DNA [31]. Noncoding RNA and Pseudogene Functionality: Noncoding RNAs, including pseudogenes, play active roles in regulating protein synthesis and gene expression, challenging the random noise hypothesis and indicating functional significance in sequences once thought non-functional. Evidence, such as a 2017 report from the Second Aegean International Conference on Non-Coding RNAs, highlights the role of non-coding RNAs in cellular homeostasis and human disease [112]. Similarly, research from the RIKEN Center for Life Science Technologies, which identified over 19,000 functional long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs), further supports the functionality of these regions and confirms ENCODE's conclusions [113].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protein-Protein Interactions (PPIs) and Cellular Complexity</head><p>Research into PPIs underscores the necessity of precise biochemical regulation within cells. Studies from Harvard show that cellular systems meticulously regulate PPI concentrations, emphasizing a level of organization that points to intentional design rather than random processes <ref type="bibr">[126,</ref><ref type="bibr">127]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Critique of the Random Noise Hypothesis</head><p>The random noise hypothesis fails to account for the complexity observed in genomic function. For instance, nonfunctional protein-DNA interactions interfere with processes like transcription and replication. <ref type="bibr" target="#b124">Qian and Kussell (2016)</ref> demonstrated that genomes evolve mechanisms to minimize weak binding motifs, highlighting selective pressures that contradict the idea of randomness driving genomic complexity <ref type="bibr">[125]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Role of Perceived Imperfections in Design</head><p>Critics like Coyne and Smith argue that discovering function or purpose in design features weakens arguments against a purposeful framework based on perceived imperfections <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b84">85]</ref>. When features previously labeled suboptimal or vestigial fulfill critical roles, the argument against their intentionality becomes less compelling, suggesting that criticisms of design often reflect gaps in understanding rather than evidence against it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Integration of Polarizing Force and Adaptive Masks Models with Nested Patterns and Owen's Archetype</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Owen's Polarizing Force and Nested patterns</head><p>The polarizing force model complements Owen's archetype by proposing that all necessary instructions for life's development were fully optimized and front-loaded at the system's inception, such as in the genome of the first life forms. Over time, this system unfolded and diversified according to pre-designed rules or constraints.</p><p>This model suggests that nested hierarchies could naturally emerge from initial conditions combined with preprogrammed, evolutionary-like processes. For example:</p><p>• The Law of Entropy: Entropy, a universal law of thermodynamics, drives systems toward selforganizational order through energy dispersal, promoting hierarchical organization. This law applies to both animate and inanimate systems, where energy flows toward equilibrium or 'stationary states' <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. • RNA Viruses and Evolutionary Processes: RNA viruses, which likely preceded the first cells, exemplify pre-programmed evolutionary processes through mechanisms like convergent co-option and Horizontal Gene Transfer (HGT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>. HGT allows genetic material to be transferred between organisms outside parent-offspring relationships, enabling rapid adaptation. This accelerates evolutionary change by integrating innovations from different lineages into a single organism <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>. • Convergent Co-option: This process, akin to modularity in software engineering, involves organisms independently evolving similar traits by repurposing existing biological components <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">[82]</ref>. For example, endogenous viral elements (EVEs) in wasps integrate viral sequences into host genomes to enhance survival, much like gene therapy in human-engineered systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b95">97]</ref>. These patterns suggest that nested hierarchies in biological systems reflect intentional design, not random evolutionary processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref>.</p><p>Thus, predictable divergence patterns can emerge, where traits are shared across species due to common initial programming rather than independent evolutionary processes. This framework addresses objections to evolutionary models by showing how nested hierarchies could result from a single, pre-designed system responding to both environmental and internal pressures.</p><p>Moreover, it explains why nested hierarchies manifest not just within genomes but across species. By combining initial programming with diversification mechanisms, this design framework accounts for shared traits and hierarchical patterns, reinforcing Owen's polarizing force model in explaining complex biological systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Owen's Adaptive masks and Nested patterns</head><p>The adaptive force model complements nested patterns within Owen's archetype by explaining how quantum mechanisms guide molecular adaptations in a way that aligns with the hierarchical organization of life. This interplay ensures that core structures remain stable while specific traits adapt to environmental pressures, reflecting intentional design.</p><p>For instance, mutational hotspots flanked by stable DNA sequences enable adaptive changes without compromising critical functions. This balance mirrors the nested hierarchy observed in biological systems, where conserved structural forms (e.g., vertebrate body plans) serve as templates for ecological specialization.</p><p>Quantum coherence plays a central role in this framework by facilitating efficient biochemical processes like electron tunneling. At the molecular level, this supports precise adaptations, such as the optimization of protein structures for metabolic efficiency. These molecular adaptations cascade into higher-order patterns, sustaining complex systems like metabolic networks and neural architectures.</p><p>By integrating these processes, the adaptive force model explains how independently designed groups (as posited by the polarizing force model) achieve functional convergence. For example, the shared presence of regulatory elements driving echolocation in bats and dolphins illustrates how quantum-guided optimization enables similar traits to emerge across distinct taxa <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>. This nested functionality aligns with Owen's archetype, underscoring the intentionality embedded in biological design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Distinct Design Events in Vertebrate Evolution: The Separate Creation Model</head><p>The separate creation model posits that the development of vertebrate body plans and taxonomical groups results from non-local quantum processes and convergent co-option, diverging from the traditional common descent framework. Specifically, the model suggests that the non-local self-collapse of quantum wave-functions within microtubules (MTs) played a pivotal role in creating distinct taxonomical vertebrate groups from stem metazoans.</p><p>For instance, the model proposes that the non-computability of SC extending beyond mere quantum computation, relying on a larger scale infrastructure of efficiently functioning MTs capable of facilitating quantum-computational processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>.</p><p>Additionally, these expanded sets of MTs, shielded from decoherence, would enable higher levels of SC that created 4 Hox genes for each major vertebrate group. This diverges from the common descent model, which posits that Hox clusters were inherited from a common ancestor via only two rounds of gene duplication early in the vertebrate lineage. Then, this progression allowed the convergent co-option of stem metazoans to evolve into various taxonomical vertebrate groups of created kinds within the deep sea and clay minerals of the earth.</p><p>However, our model does not explain every aspect of evolutionary history through this process. Instead, it specifically addresses key events crucial to early evolution, thereby achieving proximal design objectives in the development of vertebrate body plans. Consequently, we do not anticipate this design bias to persist beyond the emergence of vertebrate created kinds. This parallels the behavior of human designers, who focus on specific goals when creating a design and then maintain it once those objectives are achieved. In essence, this encapsulates the concept of separate creation and serves as the primary distinction between the two models.</p><p>The direct design framework synthesizes this separate creation model's account of independent origins with the adaptive force model's explanation of molecular optimization. Together, they offer a comprehensive understanding of how nested patterns and functional convergence arise, highlighting the interplay between intentional creation and quantum-guided adaptations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Empirical Support for the Creation Model</head><p>Support for the separate creation model is bolstered by patterns observed in the fossil record, particularly the phenomena of stasis and sudden appearances. Fossil evidence often shows that species remain relatively unchanged for long periods (stasis) and are then suddenly replaced by new forms in the geological timeline (sudden appearances) <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">[91]</ref>.</p><p>For instance, the Permian-Triassic extinction event, which occurred around 252 million years ago, wiped out approximately 96% of marine species and about 70% of terrestrial species, making it the most severe extinction event in Earth's history <ref type="bibr">[108]</ref>. Contrary to earlier views of a prolonged recovery, recent discoveries, such as the Paris Biota in southeastern Idaho, suggest that some ecosystems rebounded rapidly in the early Triassic period, with new families and orders of life forms emerging within a few million years [108].</p><p>This challenges the gradualism expected by traditional Darwinian evolution <ref type="bibr">[109]</ref>. These patterns align with the predictions of common design or creation models, which suggest that life's history and diversity are shaped by discrete events of design or creation rather than the slow, smooth, and continuous changes that Lyell and Darwin had expected <ref type="bibr">[109]</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, the separate creation model is supported by numerous examples of convergent evolution, where unrelated species independently evolve similar traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">62]</ref>. While both models offer explanations for convergence, their predictions differ significantly at higher taxonomic levels, such as orders and families. Darwinian models typically treat these taxa as clades derived from shared ancestors, whereas Owen's theory identifies them as basic types or created kinds, arising independently through design <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">[94]</ref>.</p><p>For example, the red panda was historically grouped with the giant panda based on morphological similarities, such as their shared "false thumb" and dietary preferences. However, genetic analysis revealed that they are not closely related, supporting their classification as distinct families. This divergence between morphological and genetic evidence aligns with Owen's prediction of independent creation at the family or order level <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref>.</p><p>Another classic example is the centralized nervous systems found in all vertebrates and insects <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref>. While common descent models suggest a shared ancestor, evidence indicates that these systems emerged independently multiple times, supporting the notion of distinct design events. The separate creation model predicts more frequent convergence at higher taxonomic levels, reflecting intentional design solutions to shared environmental challenges, which contrasts with traditional descent models that predict convergence would be less frequent at higher taxonomic levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">[94]</ref>.</p><p>By addressing patterns of stasis, sudden appearances, and convergence, the separate creation model provides a robust framework for understanding life's diversity at higher taxonomic levels. The direct design framework complements this model, offering a more comprehensive explanation of the origins and complexity of life. Together, these models challenge traditional descent-based theories and reinforce the idea of purpose-driven creation.</p><p>Although the concept of adaptive masks in separate creation models remain highly speculative and controversial, its implications can be tested through rigorous scientific methods. The following section outlines the steps required to experimentally validate or challenge these ideas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary Table Suggestion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Testing Separate Creation Model</head><p>Richard Owen's and Charles Darwin's theories offer contrasting views on the diversity of life. Owen's theory emphasizes the discontinuities between vertebrate groups, proposing they are distinct created kinds, while Darwin's theory suggests a continuous lineage linking all organisms through common descent. Testing the separate creation model involves systematically identifying and analyzing these discontinuities, which poses challenges due to the limitations of traditional Linnaean classification and the assumptions of continuity inherent in evolutionary taxonomy <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[56]</ref>.</p><p>As we consider the empirical validation of our unified model, it's essential to examine the predictive power of the extended archetype theory. The key predictions emerging from this model-ranging from the fine-tuning of the universe's constants to the role of consciousness in guiding evolutionary processes-are ripe for investigation. The following section outlines a systematic approach to testing these predictions, drawing from both molecular and genetic data, and demonstrating how our model can be subjected to rigorous scientific scrutiny.</p><p>Current methodologies, such as phenetics and transformed cladistics, often generate tree-like diagrams (phenograms and cladograms) that assume continuity among life forms. To discern discontinuities, a comprehensive framework integrating morphological, molecular, and functional data across family-and order-level taxa is necessary. Such an approach bridges the gaps in traditional methods and provides a common ground for evaluating competing theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[56]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 1: Identifying Morpho-Molecular Dissimilarities and Fossil Gaps</head><p>The first step in testing the separate creation model involves analyzing morpho-molecular differences and gaps in the fossil record at the family and order levels.</p><p>• Baraminic Distance Correlation (BDC): This method categorizes organisms based on design features. A continuous chain of significant positive BDC values indicates shared membership within a basic type, while negative correlations or large gaps between groups suggest discontinuity <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[77]</ref>. • Classical Multidimensional Scaling (CMDS): CMDS visualizes similarities and dissimilarities between taxa. By comparing morphological features, this method identifies potential "basic types" based on shared design features <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[77]</ref>.</p><p>These tools are primarily helpful in lumping groups together. However, when it comes to identifying discontinuities, they are limited by subjectivity in defining basic types, incomplete fossil records, and transitional forms <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[77]</ref>. Supplementary approaches, such as k-mer signature analysis and comparative anatomical studies, can address these limitations <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Example:</head><p>For pandas, k-mer signature analysis revealed distinctions between red and giant pandas but failed to show discontinuity with certain outgroup taxa. However, it did not show discontinuity between pandas and certain outgroup taxa, suggesting no common ancestor with those taxa. Consequently, they are not presumed to be basic types but are considered separate families. Nonetheless, separate families do not inherently equate to basic types or "suspected" basic types.</p><p>To clarify, a basic type undergoes analysis thrice using the BDC and CMDS methods, while a suspected basic type is analyzed only once. These other analyses should help us overcome the challenges associated with these methods, which will be discussed in more detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 2: Identifying Functional Differences in Relation to Environmental Niches</head><p>If morpho-molecular dissimilarities suggest discontinuity, the next step is to assess functional differences among taxa in relation to their environments.</p><p>Comparative Anatomy or Physiology: By analyzing the structural and functional adaptations of taxa, researchers can distinguish between homologous traits (shared ancestry) and analogous traits (convergent evolution). This step addresses limitations in BDC and CMDS by focusing on functional distinctions tied to ecological roles <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref>.</p><p>This represents a pivotal second stage in the process of determining basic types, as it enables the differentiation between homologous and analogous phenotypic traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref>. Additionally, it offers a means to address any shortcomings or limitations inherent in the BDC and CMDS methods utilized for basic type determination <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[77]</ref>.</p><p>Case Example: For pandas, comparative anatomical analysis revealed structural and functional differences related to dietary and ecological niches, confirming their classification into distinct families <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 3: Testing Predictions of Genetic Convergence</head><p>Functional differences among taxa can inform predictions about the genetic mechanisms underlying convergence.</p><p>Comparative genomics provides a powerful tool to validate these predictions.</p><p>Testing Genetic Convergence: We expect to find at least one adaptive gene and one positively selected gene within each order and family taxa in vertebrate groups that are considered basic types <ref type="bibr" target="#b94">[96]</ref>. Predictions of adaptive and positively selected genes can be tested by identifying: a. Adaptive Genes: Demonstrated through functional assays to confer specific adaptive traits. b. Positively Selected Genes: Identified through population genetic analyses that detect signatures of positive selection.</p><p>To test the combined predictions of the separate creation and adaptive mask models, comparative genomic studies can assess how regulatory elements in unrelated taxa produce convergent traits. For instance, examining enhancergene interactions in echolocation across bats and dolphins could reveal whether adaptive quantum mechanisms underpin their independent origins. Such analyses must control for statistical rigor, including false discovery rates, and should cover diverse taxa within each group. If confirmed, we can confidently assert the origin of a particular group or groups from a created kind.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Example:</head><p>In pandas, predictions regarding the 3D structures of HOXA3 and HOXC10 genes, along with mutation effect assessments, were confirmed through comparative genomic analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>. Similar approaches can be applied to other taxa to test their origins as created kinds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional Phylogenetic Analyses</head><p>Traditional phylogenetic methods, such as cladograms and phenograms, often assume evolutionary continuity. However, these diagrams may not establish genuine ancestor-descendant relationships. The separate creation model advocates for supplementary phylogenomic analyses to evaluate whether taxonomic groups should be classified separately.</p><p>• Comparative Analyses: By comparing anatomically-based family trees with molecular phylogenetic trees, researchers can assess congruence or discordance. Significant conflicts may indicate the need to reclassify groups under a separate creation framework. • Experimental Setup: Representative taxa from birds, reptiles, mammals, and other groups are selected for detailed anatomical and genetic studies. Morphological features and DNA sequences are analyzed using robust statistical methods (e.g., bootstrap analysis, Bayesian inference) to evaluate evolutionary relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Example of Divergence:</head><p>The common descent model often lumps taxa into broad categories, such as reptiles and mammals, while the separate creation model predicts conflicts between anatomically-based and molecular-based family trees within these groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[58]</ref>. These conflicts could align with the model's prediction of discrete design events and stasis, as observed in the fossil record.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Testing the separate creation model requires a multi-faceted approach that integrates morphological, molecular, and functional data. By systematically identifying discontinuities, evaluating functional adaptations, and testing predictions of genetic convergence, this framework provides a robust alternative to traditional evolutionary assumptions. The insights gained not only challenge the paradigm of gradual evolutionary continuity but also highlight the intentional design of life's nested patterns. These patterns reflect a designer's objective to create systems that are highly functional, scalable, and adaptable, ensuring life's ability to thrive across diverse and changing environments. In the next section, we will explore how these nested patterns exemplify the principles of intelligent design, providing further evidence of their intentional origin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Testing Separate Creation Model Steps and Methods for Testing a Common Design Model for Nested Patterns</head><p>This methodology builds on the concept of a rational designer within a scientific framework, integrating Owen's theory with Charles Lyell's uniformitarian principle of causation <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">[94]</ref>. Proponents of the common design model argue that a universal common designer optimizes organisms for survival, reproduction, and adaptation, similar to principles in human engineering, while still adhering to natural laws. Support for this methodology comes from the observation that the likely natural origin and design of viruses (see refs. 255 and 87 <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>) mirror the artificial synthesis and design of viruses <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">[97]</ref>. These phenomena align with Owen's archetype, which posits an inherent structural blueprint underlying the diversity of life.</p><p>Owen emphasized a polarizing and adaptive force that drives life's organization according to universal laws of form. This force operates both before and after life's emergence, as exemplified by the law of entropy, which explains how energy dispersal fosters functional, self-organizing order and nested hierarchical complexity <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>This section outlines methods to test the predictions of a nested pattern framework in design. Below, we provide slightly modified definitions of previous evolutionary terms for animal taxa, adjusted to fit Owen's theory:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Species:</head><p>The term "species" refers to an ad hoc group of known animals, plants, or humans characterized by continuity without regard to discontinuity with other organisms【96】. Essentially, this group encompasses organisms linked by common descent, though not necessarily all of them. For example, think of a basic type as a tree, where one or more branches represent a species【96】. This definition reflects divergent evolution but diverges from Darwin's theory because it does not include interbreeding as a necessary condition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Basic Types:</head><p>The term "basic types" refers to the complete set of all known living and/or extinct animals, plants, or humans in a group or pair, formed after the designer created the original set of kinds capable of sexual reproduction【96】. This means that a basic type represents an entire related group that:</p><p>1. Shares continuity, meaning that each member is connected to at least one other member. 2. Is bounded by discontinuity, meaning it is distinct from other groups【96】.</p><p>Therefore, each natural group of related plants, animals, and humankind constitutes a basic type. Essentially, a basic type resembles a clade in evolution, with the distinction that the original kind does not have a common ancestor capable of sexual reproduction. Instead, stem metazoans and microbes are described as common design parts rather than common ancestors. This concept aligns with Owen's notion of fundamental forms in the natural world, referred to as Types, which are inherent and governed by the universal common archetype【21】.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Taxonomical Groups:</head><p>The term "taxonomical group" refers to a collection of known species delineated by discontinuity, without necessarily sharing common descent but exhibiting similar morphology, ecology, and function. This is akin to polyphyletic groups【96】. However, this term does not apply to humans. Richard Owen, for example, highlighted both the unity of mankind and the distinction between humans and higher apes. Through comparative studies of anthropoid apes, he classified humans into a distinct subclass named Archencephala【55】【63】. Owen cited specific cerebral features, such as the hippocampus minor, to underscore this classification【27】. Our model follows this description but suggests that the endorestiform nucleus is a unique cerebral feature present only in humans【60】.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Testing Alleged Design Flaws</head><p>The common design model anticipates that features initially perceived as flaws, such as the human heart's susceptibility to issues or the GULO gene deficiency, may contribute to enhanced efficiency in survival, reproduction, or adaptation under specific conditions. This prediction contrasts with traditional evolutionary perspectives, which view such features as inefficient remnants of natural selection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental Setup</head><p>• Organisms: Select species with alleged design flaws, such as humans with GULO gene deficiencies or heart issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[41]</ref>. • Data Collection: Measure survival rates, reproductive success, and adaptability under varying environmental conditions. • Statistical Tests: Use t-tests or ANOVA to compare metrics between organisms with and without the alleged design flaws. Confirm whether these traits contribute to efficiency in specific contexts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Example</head><p>Research could investigate whether heart issues in humans are linked to trade-offs optimizing other aspects of cardiovascular efficiency, or whether the GULO gene deficiency enhances other metabolic pathways.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Testing Alleged Harmful Design Features</head><p>The model predicts that features traditionally viewed as harmful-such as parasitism or pathogen design-may serve adaptive or population-regulating roles, contributing to overall survival and ecological stability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental Setup</head><p>• Populations: Focus on organisms with alleged harmful features, such as pathogens or parasitic adaptations (e.g., Toxoplasma gondii or tongue-eating louse). <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref> • Data Collection: Evaluate survival rates, reproductive success, and adaptability in populations with and without these features. • Statistical Tests: Employ chi-square tests or logistic regression to analyze differences between populations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Example</head><p>Mitochondrial and chloroplast DNA's role in apoptosis demonstrates a potential beneficial "harmful" feature, as apoptosis ensures timely cell death, essential for multicellularity. Cancer may similarly regulate population dynamics by reallocating resources to younger generations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Investigating Cognitive Qualities</head><p>Human cognitive features predicted by Owen's model, such as the presence of the endorestiform nucleus, are expected to demonstrate distinct functional advantages over those found in non-human nephesh species, which refer to refer to soulish animals endowed with mind, will, and emotions, capable of emotional bonds with one another and humans. Deviations from these predictions would challenge the model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental Setup</head><p>• Neuroanatomy: Compare the presence, volume, and function of the endorestiform nucleus in human and non-human nephesh brains, focusing first on animals that have been reported to bury their dead and exhibit religious practices. • Cognitive Metrics: Measure fine motor control and higher-order cognitive abilities associated with the endorestiform nucleus. • Statistical Tests: Correlation analysis or linear regression to examine the relationship between neuroanatomical features and cognitive performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Example</head><p>If the endorestiform nucleus is found only in humans or demonstrates unique characteristics compared to non-human nephesh brains, it would support Owen's theory. Conversely, its presence in non-human nephesh species without distinct differences would challenge the model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluating Nested Patterns</head><p>The nested patterns observed in biological systems are central to the common design model, reflecting modular principles akin to human-engineered systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref>. These patterns can be tested using comparative genomics, anatomical analysis, and phylogenetic studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental Setup</head><p>• Representative Taxa: Select species from diverse taxonomic groups (e.g., birds, mammals, reptiles).</p><p>• Data Collection: Gather morphological data (e.g., skeletal structures) and molecular data (e.g., mitochondrial and nuclear DNA). • Statistical Tests: Compare phylogenetic trees constructed from anatomical and molecular data using tools like MEGA or Bayesian inference.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Example</head><p>Discrepancies between phylogenies inferred from molecular and anatomical data-such as the grouping of reptiles and mammals-would align with predictions of episodic innovation and intentional design over gradual evolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[58]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Accounting for Perceived Design Flaws and Trade-Offs</head><p>The model acknowledges that design flaws and trade-offs-such as cancer as a byproduct of apoptosis-may not conflict with a common design framework. Instead, these features reflect inherent constraints of physical laws (e.g., the second law of thermodynamics) or adaptations to ensure ecological balance <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Thus, true disconfirmation would potentially come from failed design predictions on alleged design flaws assumed to have an function that optimizes organisms to survive, reproduce, and integrate into various environments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Example</head><p>Cancer may reflect a trade-off between DNA repair and cellular turnover, playing a population-regulating role akin to apoptosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[51]</ref>. These trade-offs are expected in a designed system constrained by universal physical laws.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Addressing Ethical and Philosophical Considerations</head><p>While testing predictions, the model considers that natural phenomena involving pain, suffering, or death may stem from decay, human moral failings, or necessary trade-offs, rather than malevolent design. Examples like natural disasters or disease reflect the consequences of free will and entropy rather than flaws in the design itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">75,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">51]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations and Future Directions</head><p>The interdisciplinary nature of testing this model necessitates collaboration across evolutionary biology, paleontology, ecology, and molecular biology. Challenges include:</p><p>• Terminology Differences: Harmonizing definitions across fields.</p><p>• Methodological Variability: Ensuring consistency in data collection and analysis.</p><p>• Criteria for Falsification: Establishing robust criteria to confirm or refute predictions.</p><p>Future research should focus on validating these methods through detailed experimental designs, statistical analyses, and criteria for falsification. Empirical findings that align with the model would strengthen its plausibility, while inconsistencies would prompt refinement or alternative explanations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Predictions from Orch-OR Theory Consistent with Extended Archetype</head><p>Although six confirmed predictions from Orch-OR theory support and align with Owen's extended theory, not all predictions from Orch-OR are directly relevant. Below, we highlight predictions from Orch-OR that are consistent with and relevant to Owen's theory but have not yet been confirmed. It is important to note that these predictions remain unconfirmed for several reasons: some of the experimental methods required to test these hypotheses are still in development, and in certain cases, the scientific community has yet to conduct the definitive studies needed to establish their validity. Nevertheless, confirming these predictions is crucial for providing direct and conclusive evidence for the quantum consciousness theory inherent in Owen's extended framework. Despite these challenges, the potential implications of these predictions for understanding consciousness and biological design make them worthy of further investigation:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Dynamic Microtubule Vibrations Correlate with Cellular Activity</head><p>• Orch-OR Prediction:</p><p>The Orch-OR model directly links consciousness to quantum processes in microtubules, suggesting that quantum coherence and superposition within microtubules are critical for brain function and consciousness. Vibrations at specific frequencies may help synchronize the quantum states within microtubules, contributing to coordinated cellular activity, which is crucial for the proper functioning of neurons and other cells in the body.</p><p>• Experimental Methods:  Vibration Frequency Measurement: Measure specific frequencies of microtubule vibrations in cells and investigate whether these vibrations correlate with changes in cellular activity (such as ion flux, membrane potential, or protein signaling).  Quantum Sensors and Ultrasound: Use quantum sensors to measure microtubules' quantum properties, and apply ultrasound or mechanical vibration to test if altering microtubules' vibrational states affects cellular activity.  Correlation Studies: Conduct studies to correlate microtubule vibration patterns with cellular processes such as signal transduction, synaptic plasticity, or gene expression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Synaptic Plasticity Correlates with Cytoskeletal Architecture/Activities</head><p>• Orch-OR Prediction:</p><p>Synaptic plasticity, the ability of synapses to strengthen or weaken over time, is critical for learning and memory. Orch-OR suggests that microtubules in the cytoskeleton play a crucial role in regulating synaptic function by facilitating quantum processes. Structural changes in synaptic connections may be influenced by quantum effects within the cytoskeleton.</p><p>• Experimental Methods:  Use super-resolution microscopy to visualize synaptic and cytoskeletal ultrastructure.  Stimulate synaptic activity and monitor synaptic strength while observing changes in the cytoskeleton.  Apply genetic or pharmacological manipulations to assess how microtubule dynamics influence synaptic plasticity and cognitive functions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Stable Microtubule Patterns Correlate with Memory</head><p>• Orch-OR Prediction:</p><p>Orch-OR predicts that microtubules encode memory through quantum processes. Though evidence is still inconclusive, the hypothesis suggests that stable patterns within microtubules could correlate with memory, acting as storage devices for quantum information. The connection between synaptic messengers like CaMKII and PkMz, which function through microtubules, indicates the cytoskeleton may play a more direct role in memory encoding.</p><p>• Experimental Methods:  Conduct animal model experiments to assess memory performance after manipulating microtubule stability.  Visualize microtubule patterns in neurons before and after memory-related tasks.  Use pharmacological interventions to assess the impact of microtubule dynamics on memory and cognition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">'EPR-like' Non-Local Correlation Between Separated Microtubules</head><p>• Orch-OR Prediction:</p><p>Orch-OR anticipates that quantum states within microtubules could exhibit non-local correlations, similar to quantum entanglement (EPR-like correlations), where changes in one part of a system affect distant parts instantaneously.</p><p>• Experimental Methods:  Isolate microtubules from individual neurons or brain tissue slices in a controlled environment.  Use quantum-sensitive detectors to measure quantum states and assess entanglement across microtubules.  Apply stimuli like laser excitation or magnetic field manipulation to test non-local correlation between microtubules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Quantum Correlations Between Microtubules in Different Neurons</head><p>• Orch-OR Prediction:</p><p>Orch-OR suggests that quantum correlations could occur between microtubules in different neurons, potentially influencing consciousness.</p><p>• Experimental Methods:  Employ quantum sensing and electrophysiology techniques to measure quantum coherence across microtubules in different neurons.  Investigate the functional role of gap junctions in facilitating these quantum correlations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Human Origins Model</head><p>In this section, we aim to draw correlations between Genesis 1 and contemporary scientific understanding, inspired by Richard Owen's methodology of using the Genesis narrative to bolster his theories and interpret science in light of scripture <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">55]</ref>. Our preference for Christianity as the framework arises from its perfect alignment with Owen's extended theory and its broader implications. Christianity, as depicted in the Bible, asserts a definitive beginning to the material cosmos, a concept that resonates with the Quran and Mormon writings (see Ch. 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). Furthermore, Christianity presents a unique perspective on the nature of God, emphasizing both divine and human aspects, setting it apart from all other monotheistic religions (see Ch. 7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p><p>However, we acknowledge and address potential criticisms and controversies surrounding the integration of biblical narratives with scientific explanations, particularly those within the scientific community. Hence, we refer readers to key literature to highlight the complexity of the subject <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>, including discussions on methodological differences between theological interpretation and scientific inquiry <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>. Emphasizing the importance of clear differentiation between established scientific facts and speculative theories, we stress the need for dialogue between theology and science <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>. Expanding our analysis, we explore how other major world religions interpret the origins and development of life, offering a more inclusive and comparative perspective <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">72]</ref>. Finally, we proactively address common criticisms or counterarguments from scientific and theological perspectives, offering a robust defense of the proposed synthesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>. This includes recognizing areas of agreement, tension, and potential mutual enrichment between science and theology, presenting our model as a starting point for further discussions <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">68,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>.</p><p>In constructing our scientific model, we integrate biblical texts with contemporary literature, ensuring alignment with both theological and scientific perspectives. Given the Bible's track record of anticipating and aligning with scientific discoveries, particularly regarding the origins and history of life <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">68,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>, this model holds promise for researchers and non-specialists alike. Additionally, our books delve deeper into demonstrating why our model aligns and contrasts with the consensus in the scientific community, especially concerning evolution and the age of the Earth <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>. The aim is to provide insights into natural history, with a particular focus on human origins.</p><p>Our progressive creation model elucidates the origins of various taxonomical groups of species and explores their survival and reproductive strategies under diverse environmental conditions throughout history. Additionally, it offers alternative explanations for key evolutionary events, such as the origin of viruses (day 1), eukaryotes (day 1), complex multicellular organisms (day 3 &amp; 5), vertebrate body plans (day 5), and human consciousness (day 6), corresponding to the respective 'days' in Genesis. In our books, we delve deeper into how specific scientific discoveries relate to the proposed timeline of events in Genesis and provide clear examples where possible, offering evidence for the claims we make <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">71]</ref>.</p><p>The progressive creation interpretation suggests that Genesis chapter 1 remains agnostic regarding the duration of the creation week, as the Hebrew word 'yôm,' translated as 'day' in English, encompasses various literal meanings, including a period of daylight, a 12-hour or 24-hour day, an epoch of time, or a period with unspecified duration <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">68]</ref>. Similarly, the Hebrew terms for evening and morning can denote the beginning and end of a period <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68]</ref>. According to this perspective, the primary aim of the creation account is to elucidate God's provision for humanity and his creation of humans as the preeminent spiritual beings on Earth. This approach offers a parsimonious interpretation of Genesis that harmonizes with other biblical creation passages and scientific data. For the purpose of our model, we adopt the interpretation that 'days' in Genesis signify periods of unspecified duration, drawing insights from scientific accounts to inform our understanding of each 'day' in Genesis. However, it's important to note that this is one among several interpretations within Christian theology <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">72,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b88">89]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Scientific account</head><p>In the early universe, and persisting to the present, self-collapse (SC) events primarily occur within electrically charged, polar environments such as water or various forms of matter. In these environments, quantum states rapidly entangle and undergo chemical reactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Hameroff 2017</ref>).</p><p>Around 4.7 to 4.2 billion years ago, pi electron resonance clouds within single-chain amphiphile molecules aggregated into geometric pi-stacks, forming viroids conducive to self-collapse (SC) events within Earth's deepsea hypothermal vents <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>. Over time, natural selection and convergent co-option led to the assembly of viroids into highly organized local domains containing key biomolecules characteristic of DNA/RNA viruses or molecules <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>. Subsequently, these assemblies evolved into various species of unicellular organisms involving the self-collapse of quantum wave functions within the microtubules of viruses throughout evolutionary history <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Day 1 Genesis account</head><p>1:1 In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth.</p><p>1:2 And the earth was formless and void, and darkness was over the surface of the deep; and the Spirit of God was moving over the surface of the waters.</p><p>Another plausible translation of Genesis 1:1 is "In the beginning, when God began to create heaven and earth." This same linguistic construction is found nearby in Genesis 5:1, and a similar one introduces the second creation story in Genesis 2:4. This suggests that the verse could also serve as the temporal setting for the description of pre-creation elements in Genesis 1:2, rather than indicating the absolute beginning of everything, including time <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, Genesis 1:2 clearly states that the frame of reference is "the surface of the waters" of the earth. This verse describes the initial conditions of primordial Earth: dark on its surface, covered with water, empty of life, and unfit for life (see Ch. 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). Most people have made the mistake of assuming the frame of reference of Genesis 1 is heaven or somewhere above the earth (see Ch. 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p><p>What does the text specifically say? The heavens (universe, solar system, sun, earth, etc.) were already created before the first "day" (see Ch. 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). With the frame of reference and the initial conditions for the six creation days thus established, a straightforward chronology of creation events unfolds (see Ch. 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p><p>In Genesis 1:2, God was "hovering or brooding" over the seas of the newly formed earth. The Hebrew word, rachaph, translated as "hovering or brooding" is used only twice in the Old Testament. The second reference is to an eagle caring for its young (Deuteronomy 32:11). Therefore, it seems likely that the use of the word rachaph in Genesis 1:2 may be referring to God creating the first life forms in the deep sea (see Ch. 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Scientific account</head><p>Through HGT, unicellular organisms underwent extensive regulatory switching and rewiring in their noncoding regulatory regions, leading to substantial innovation <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">50]</ref>.</p><p>Day 1 (ex.) Genesis account 1:3 Then God said, "Let there be light"; and there was light.</p><p>1:4 And God saw that the light was good; and God separated the light from the darkness.</p><p>1:5 And God called the light day, and the darkness He called night. And there was evening and there was morning, one day.</p><p>In Job 38 4-9 of the bible, it told us that at the earth's creation, it was covered with a dense layer of clouds and gases which would have made it dark at its surface. Genesis 1:2 says, "darkness was over the surface of the deep."</p><p>Next, God removed much of the cloud cover, when He stated, "Let there be light" (Genesis 1:3)</p><p>This was the light of the Sun (already created) which now "separated light from darkness" (Genesis 1:4). It is very clear from the text that the sun had already been created and the earth was rotating on its axis (see Ch. 4, <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>), since there was light (day) and darkness (night) (Genesis 1:5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Scientific account</head><p>Between 3.8 and 2.45 billion years ago, there was the initiation of a stable water cycle and the formation of continents through tectonic activity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Day 2 Genesis account</head><p>1:6 Then God said, "Let there be an expanse in the midst of the waters, and let it separate the waters from the waters."</p><p>1:7 And God made the expanse, and separated the waters which were below the expanse from the waters which were above the expanse; and it was so.</p><p>1:8 And God called the expanse heaven. And there was evening and there was morning, a second day.</p><p>1:9 Then God said, "Let the waters below the heavens be gathered into one place, and let the dry land appear";</p><p>and it was so.</p><p>1:10 And God called the dry land earth, and the gathering of the waters He called seas; and God saw that it was good.</p><p>The Hebrew words translated "expanse" and "sky" are rāqîa' and shāmayim (see Ch. 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). Both terms refer to the portion of Earth's atmosphere where clouds form and move (see Ch. 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). Some critics and skeptics of the Bible claim that the rāqîa' and shāmayim in verse 8 refer to the solid brass dome of ancient mythology (see Ch. 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p><p>They cite Job 37:18 as support for their view: "Can you join him <ref type="bibr">[God]</ref> in spreading out the skies, hard as a mirror of cast bronze?" (see Ch. 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). However, it should be noted that the word "as" indicates the use of a figure of speech. The picture continues in Job 37:21 (see Ch. 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p><p>In ancient times, no humanly crafted surface reflected light more effectively than a polished bronze mirror (see Ch. 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). The simile in Job 37 simply compares the Sun's brightness on a clear day to the painfully bright reflection of light from such a mirror (see Ch. 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Scientific account</head><p>As colonies of cells evolved into multicellular organisms 1 billion years ago (see Ch. 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>), different cells within the organism began to take on specialized roles and functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">50]</ref>. This specialization led to the divergence of transcription start sites and gene expression levels, which allowed for the development of more complex multicellular clades <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> starting with plant life 427-393 million years ago, such as brown algae, red algae, green algae, or vascular plants. (see Ch. 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Day 3 Genesis account</head><p>1:11 Then God said, "Let the earth sprout vegetation, plants yielding seed, and fruit trees bearing fruit after their kind, with seed in them, on the earth"; and it was so.</p><p>1:12 And the earth brought forth vegetation, plants yielding seed after their kind, and trees bearing fruit, with seed in them, after their kind; and God saw that it was good.</p><p>1:13 And there was evening and there was morning, a third day.</p><p>Plant life was created on the third day. The verse says quite clearly that the earth sprouted (or brought forth) vegetation and fruit trees bearing fruit. The English word translated "vegetation" on the third day comes from the Hebrew word deshe', (see Ch. 5, Ross 2014) which refers to small plants, such as grasses and herbs (see Ch. 5, <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p><p>The other word, ‛eśeb, translated "plants" is even more generic, referring to any kind of green plant (see Ch. 5, <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). So, the "day" encompasses the time from the formation of the first plants until the formation of fruit trees, as suggested in Genesis 2:5, since they take years to bear fruit (see Ch. 5, <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Scientific account</head><p>580 million years ago, oxygen concentrations became greater than 20 parts per million, which resulted in a decrease in aerosol production rate with increasing O2 concentration (see Ch. 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">71]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Day 4 Genesis account</head><p>1:14 Then God said, "Let there be lights in the expanse of the heavens to separate the day from the night, and let them be for signs, and for seasons, and for days and years;</p><p>1:15 and let them be for lights in the expanse of the heavens to give light on the earth "; and it was so.</p><p>1:16 And God made the two great lights, the greater light to govern the day, and the lesser light to govern the night; He made the stars also.</p><p>1:17 And God placed them in the expanse of the heavens to give light on the earth, 1:18 and to govern the day and the night, and to separate the light from the darkness; and God saw that it was good.</p><p>1:19 And there was evening and there was morning, a fourth day.</p><p>Next, the translucent cloud layer was removed, allowing the sun, moon, and stars to shine through (see Ch. 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). It's worth noting the peculiar construction in Genesis 1:14, which states, "Then God said, 'Let there be lights in the expanse of the heavens to separate the day from the night, and let them be for signs, and for seasons, and for days and years;'" The phrase "Let there be" presents an unconventional description of de novo creation (see also verse 1:3).</p><p>At this juncture, God lifted the translucent cloud cover from the planet, enabling the stars, moon, and Sun to become visible from the surface of the earth (the frame of reference for all of Genesis 1). The text then</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="13,72.00,84.87,360.00,360.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="15,72.00,72.00,360.00,360.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="16,72.00,205.75,468.00,256.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="32,72.00,98.92,468.00,222.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We would like to thank the RTB supporters from our scholars' community for their outstanding contributions. They provided a methodology for detecting created kinds and novel testable predictions, synthesized specific theories of quantum consciousness and process structuralism, and offered potential reasons why the designer might utilize nested patterns in creation. The authors also acknowledge the assistance of ChatGPT, an AI language model developed by <rs type="institution">OpenAI</rs>, for drafting and editing this manuscript and describing how all the predictions could be tested through specific experimental designs, statistical analyses, and criteria for falsification.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>reaffirms what God had previously accomplished in Genesis 1:1 concerning the creation of the sun, moon, and stars. The timeframe described spans events over days, seasons, and years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Scientific account</head><p>Between 575-545 million years ago marked the occurrence of the first Avalon explosion of animal life, succeeded by a second explosion producing simple, sessile, or minimally mobile organisms, such as stem metazoans (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). At the onset of the early Cambrian evolutionary explosion 540 million years ago, central nervous systems composed of approximately 300 neurons, found in tiny worms and urchins, theoretically possessed sufficient microtubules (MTs) for self-collapse (SC) to occur, thereby catalyzing the accelerated evolution of the Cambrian explosion <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">50]</ref>. This phenomenon would include marine invertebrates.</p><p>Further evolutionary progress necessitated the non-computability of SC extending beyond mere quantum computation, relying on a larger scale infrastructure of efficiently functioning MTs capable of facilitating quantum-computational processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>. Additionally, these expanded sets of MTs, shielded from decoherence, would enable higher levels of SC that created 4 Hox genes for each major vertebrate group. This progression allowed the convergent co-option of stem metazoans to evolve into various taxonomical vertebrate groups of created kinds within the deep sea and clay minerals of the earth, beginning with:</p><p>Jawless fish 485 mya 1:21 And God created the great sea monsters, and every living creature that moves, with which the waters swarmed after their kind, and every winged bird after its kind; and God saw that it was good.</p><p>1:22 And God blessed them, saying, "Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and let birds multiply on the earth."</p><p>1:23 And there was evening and there was morning, a fifth day.</p><p>Mayim Sherets ("Marine Creeping Things") -The Hebrew word Sherets is often translated creeping thing and is used with another Hebrew word Mayim meaning waters, thus effectively referring to small marine life (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). Genesis 1:20 seems to be telling us that much of the production of small marine life is brought forth by "the waters," as opposed to continuous direct intervention by God <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[55]</ref>. Therefore, one would not perceive a contradiction between the biblical record and observable instances of naturalistic speciation <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[55]</ref>.</p><p>However, the extent of speciation allowable according to the biblical account remains a topic of debate. Leviticus 11:10 specifies that marine creeping things are those lacking fins and scales in the seas and rivers.</p><p>Mayim Chay ("Marine Life") -Chay is often translated "life", whereas Mayim refers to waters, thus Marine Life (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). It appears to be a major category for fish and larger marine life. It is the 4th creation mentioned in Genesis 1 and was created on the 5th day (Genesis Gadowl Tanniyn ("Huge Dragons") -Two Hebrew words are used here, Gadowl meaning "Huge" and Tanniyn, a word of uncertain origin usually translated "Dragon" by the KJV (21 times) and otherwise translated "Serpent" (3 times), "Whale" (3 times), or "Sea Monster (1 time). In Genesis 1 the two words are translated "Great Whales". It is the 3rd creation mentioned in Genesis 1 and was created on the 5th day (Genesis To be clear, these sea monsters or mammals are referred to generically while the land animals in day 6 are given more detailed descriptions (see Ch. 6, Ross 2014). For example, the Hebrew word tannin seems to mean "great reptile" <ref type="bibr">(Youngblood 1999</ref>) and therefore, represents a large category of creatures, rather than one specific land or water dwelling species <ref type="bibr">(Youngblood 1999)</ref>.</p><p>'Owph ("Flying Creatures") -This Hebrew word is often translated "fowl" by the KJV but simply refers to flying creatures. They are the second creation mentioned in Genesis 1 and were made on the 5th day (Genesis 1:20-30 Genesis account 1:24 Then God said, "Let the earth bring forth living creatures after their kind: cattle and creeping things and beasts of the earth after their kind"; and it was so.</p><p>1:25 And God made the beasts of the earth after their kind, and the cattle after their kind, and everything that creeps on the ground after its kind; and God saw that it was good.</p><p>Bara is not used in Genesis 1:25 (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>) because the different kinds of land mammals described in Genesis 1:24-25 are not the first land mammals that God made (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). Rather, Genesis 1:24-25 describes three subcategories of land mammals, the subcategories that would prove crucial for enabling human beings to launch and sustain civilization (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). A much longer description of the features and roles in serving human beings for many of these animals is described in Job 38:39-39:30. God created the three subcategories of land mammals mentioned in Genesis 1:24-25 long after he created the first land mammals.</p><p>Hence, the different kinds of land mammals described in Genesis 1:24-25 are not brand new.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Scientific account</head><p>Between 150,000 to 100,000 years ago, a non-computable conscious process emerged directly from nonlocal self-collapse (SC) events at the quantum level within neurons, following the development of the vertebrate body plan for the first human within the clay minerals of the earth <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>. This process differs from the emergence of animal consciousness, which is often attributed to connections between neurons forming artificial neural networks (ANNs). ANNs serve as simplified models inspired by biological neural networks present in human and animal brains <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref>. Comprising interconnected artificial neurons, ANNs process information and can be trained to perform various tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref>.</p><p>Then, after taxonomical groups and a human pair were created, conserved structural features, such as the precise positioning of amino acid residues and metal cofactors, along with specific protein folding patterns, facilitated electron delocalization and quantum tunneling <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>. Over evolutionary time, non-random mutations, insertions, deletions, and HGT led to variations in the amino acid sequences of proteins involved in electron transfer reactions through quantum tunneling. Subsequent changes in protein resulted in corresponding alterations in protein structures, where even minor modifications in amino acid sequences could impact protein folding, stability, and interactions with other molecules <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[57]</ref>. These structural changes influenced the efficiency and specificity of electron transfer within the protein, with modifications enhancing electron transfer rates in one context potentially reducing specificity or stability in another context.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Day 6 (ex.) Genesis account</head><p>1:26 Then God said, "Let Us make man in Our image, according to Our likeness; and let them rule over the fish of the sea and over the birds of the sky and over the cattle and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creeps on the earth."</p><p>1:27 And God created man in His own image, in the image of God He created him; male and female He created them.</p><p>1:28 God blessed them and said to them, "Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the earth and subdue it; rule over the fish of the sea and the birds of the air and every creature that crawls upon the earth.</p><p>As to what in man constituted the "Our image", the reformed theologians commonly held it to have consisted of (see Ch. 7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>):</p><p>(1) in the spirituality of his being, as an intelligent and free agent</p><p>(2) in the moral integrity and holiness of his nature</p><p>(3) in his dominion over the creatures A second portrayal of God is suggested in John 1:1, which parallels Genesis 1:1: "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God." The Greek meaning of "the Word" mentioned in John 1:1 is "something said; by implication, a topic, also reasoning or motive; by extension, a computation; specially, the Divine Expression" <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>.</p><p>In Genesis 1:28, we get a glimpse of God's intentions for humans and animals, as they are blessed to "be fruitful and multiply and fill the earth and subdue it." However, it's important to note that this blessing applies specifically to birds, mammals, and select species of reptiles, such as crocodiles and small lizards, as they are considered nephesh (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>) and were created on the "fifth" day (Genesis 1:20-21). "Swarms of living creatures," where "creatures" is the Hebrew word nephesh, refer to soulish animals endowed with mind, will, and emotions, capable of emotional bonds with one another and humans (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p><p>contrast, all other animals are not nephesh, either because they are not mentioned in the text or not designated as nephesh (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>). Consequently, we would anticipate God's intervention to ensure the survival of these groups throughout the history of life. This perspective offers insight into the extinction of trilobites and dinosaurs, as they are either not mentioned in the text or not considered nephesh animals (see Ch. 6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>).</p><p>For a comprehensive model of human history, please refer to "Who Was Adam: A Creation Model Approach to the Origin of Humanity" <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref> and consult this source <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[46]</ref> to understand how our human origins model compares with other theories of human origin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">Conclusions and Summary</head><p>After evaluating the presented evidence, our research tentatively concludes that all existing organisms share a common design originating from a universal common designer. This conclusion offers insights into key aspects of biological and cosmological phenomena:</p><p>The remarkable precision of the cosmological constant, the constancy of the fine-structure constant, and the absence of variation in fine-tuning constants suggest a finely crafted cosmos.</p><p>Parallels observed between quantum systems and human cognitive processes, along with evidence of design principles across different domains of life, hint at a deeper connection between reality and the human mind.</p><p>While these findings are compelling, alternative scientific explanations remain viable:</p><p>• Cognitive Science and Evolutionary Biology provide naturalistic accounts for these patterns.</p><p>• Future discoveries could potentially align with string theory, offering additional explanations for finetuning and the universal wave-function.</p><p>Despite these alternatives, Richard Owen's extended theory stands out as a robust framework, reintroducing external teleology into biology. It challenges the prevailing teleonomic view by proposing a purposeful organization underlying life's complexity and evolutionary trajectory. This framework fosters new inquiries into biological and cosmological phenomena and offers a reconciliatory approach between scientific understanding and religious faith.</p><p>By bridging these domains, it promotes harmonious dialogue and broader acceptance of evolutionary theory within a design-oriented perspective.</p><p>However, several limitations must be addressed to refine and expand this framework:</p><p>1. Religious Inclusivity: While the conclusion implies that Christianity provides the most coherent explanation of God reality, not all readers share this perspective. Engaging with diverse religious and philosophical viewpoints through collaborative gatherings or interdisciplinary forums could enrich the discussion. 2. Interdisciplinary Challenges: Integrating quantum physics, consciousness studies, and process structuralism into a unified model presents significant obstacles, including: a. Terminological differences. b. Methodological variability. c. Differing standards of evidence. d. Foundational assumptions across disciplines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposed Strategies for Overcoming Challenges</head><p>To address these challenges and foster further development of this framework, the following strategies are recommended:</p><p>• Interdisciplinary Training: Equip researchers with the tools to navigate multiple fields effectively.</p><p>• Collaborative Research Projects: Facilitate partnerships across disciplines to explore shared questions and hypotheses. • Communication Platforms: Develop forums and conferences to encourage dialogue among experts from diverse fields. • Interdisciplinary Journals: Promote publication venues that prioritize cross-disciplinary research, ensuring rigorous peer review and the dissemination of integrated insights.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Final Thoughts</head><p>By exploring the interplay of fine-tuning, biological design, and human consciousness, this research offers a compelling narrative that redefines traditional boundaries between science, philosophy, and religion. Owen's extended theory and the concept of a universal common designer provide a meaningful lens through which to view life's complexity and purpose. Moving forward, continued interdisciplinary collaboration will be essential to test, refine, and expand this framework, fostering a deeper understanding of the natural world and its profound implications for humanity.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural hierarchy emerges from energy dispersal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Annila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kuismanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">19038306</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-11-06">2009. 2008 November 6</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Corruption kills</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ambraseys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bilham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">469</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colloquium paper: Footprints of nonsentient design inside the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Avise</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8969" to="8976" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Darwin&apos;s greatest discovery: Design without designer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ayala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8567" to="8573" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anesthetic Alterations of Collective Terahertz Oscillations in Tubulin Correlate with Clinical Potency: Implications for Anesthetic Action and Post-Operative Cognitive Dysfunction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Craddock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kurian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Preto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41598-017-09992-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-09992-7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9877</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accepting evolution means You can&apos;t believe in God&apos;: Atheistic perceptions of evolution among college biology students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CBE Life Sci. Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The RNA world hypothesis: The worst theory of the early evolution of life (except for all the others)(a)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bernhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Direct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biofilms in the large bowel suggest an apparent function of the human vermiform appendix</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bollinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Barbas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">17936308</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">249</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="826" to="831" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-09-07">2007. 2007 September 7</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondrial genomes are retained by selective constraints on protein targeting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Björkholm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Harish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hagström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ernst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G E</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10154" to="10161" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accounting for vertebrate limbs: From Owen&apos;s homology to novelty in Evo-Devo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Brigandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophy and Theory in Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uterine selection of human embryos at implantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brosens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3894</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polydnaviruses of parasitic wasps: Domestication of viruses to act as gene delivery vectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Strand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Insects</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overcoming challenges and dogmas to understand the functions of pseudogenes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cheetham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Faulkner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Why Evolution Is True</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Coyne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Viking Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression of multiple horizontally acquired genes is a hallmark of both vertebrate and invertebrate genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Crisp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Boschetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Perry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tunnacliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Micklem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nociceptive sensitization reduces predation risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dickson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hanlon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Walters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1121" to="1125" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tail of two pandas-Whole genome k-mer signature analysis of the red panda (Ailurus fulgens) and the Giant panda (Ailuropoda melanoleuca)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cserhati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unconventional care: Offspring abandonment and filial cannibalism can function as forms of parental care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Davenport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bonsall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Klug</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual selection targets cetacean pelvic bones</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">25186496</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC4213350</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3296" to="3306" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-10-20">2014. 2014 October 20</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological feedbacks between the Pleistocene megafauna extinction and climate: The first human-induced global warming?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Doughty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Field</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophys. Res. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15703</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Types: A persistent structuralist challenge to Darwinian pan-selectionism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Denton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BIO-Complexity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reply to comment on: &apos;experimental indications of non-classical brain function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kerskens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pérez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/2399-6528/acc636Google</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1088/2399-6528/acc636GoogleScholar" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Phys Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2023. 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>journal of physics communications 6 105001)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural selection and convergent evolution of the HOX gene family in Carnivora</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Ecol. Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1107034</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental indications of non-classical brain functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kerskens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pérez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1088/2399-6528/ac94beGoogle</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1088/2399-6528/ac94beGoogleScholar" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Phys Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ancient horizontal gene transfer and the last common ancestors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fournier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Andam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gogarten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">70</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing regulatory networks in bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Freyre-Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Trevino-Quintanilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hippocampus minor, calcar avis, and the Huxley-Owen debate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Binder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurosurgery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The quantum origin of life: How the brain evolved to feel good in On Human Nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hameroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="353" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consciousness, cognition and the neuronal cytoskeleton -A new paradigm needed in neuroscience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hameroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Mol. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">869935</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Updated fundamental constant constraints from planck 2018 data and possible relations to the Hubble tension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chluba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">493</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3255" to="3263" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Junk DNA: Evidence for evolution or design?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.equip.org/articles/junk-dna-evidence-for-evolution-or-design/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Christian Research Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimizing Caribbean tsunami risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hillebrandt-Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">341</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="966" to="968" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modularity, reuse, and hierarchy: Measuring complexity by measuring structure and organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hornby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Complexity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the atmosphere of neoproterozoic earth: The effect of O2 on haze formation and composition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hörst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3847/1538-4357/aabd7d</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi:10.3847/1538-4357/aabd7d" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">858</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electronic energy migration in microtubules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kalra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACS Cent. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="352" to="361" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental indications of non-classical brain functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kerskens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">López</forename><surname>Pérez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Horizontal transfer beyond genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Koonin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15865" to="15866" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wave-like patterns in parameter space interpreted as evidence for macroscopic effects resulting from quantum or quantum-like processes in the brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kurtev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18938</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Retinal glial cells enhance human vision acuity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Labin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Ribak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">20482021</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">158102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010-04-16">2010. 2010 April 16</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Teleology in Keywords in Evolutionary Biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lennox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>E.F. Keller, E.A. Lloyd</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Errors: A Panorama of Our Glitches, from Pointless Bones to Broken Genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lents</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular biology. &apos;dead&apos; enzymes show signs of life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leslie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">340</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The finer scale of consciousness: Quantum theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Transl. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">585</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Understanding Genesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lisle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Master Books</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Green Forest, Arkansas</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The experimental demonstration of high efficiency interaction-free measurement for quantum counterfactual-like communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10875</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing contemporary evangelical models regarding human origins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Luskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Religions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">748</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extent of functionality in the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mattick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">HUGO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolutionary chance mutation: A defense of the modern synthesis&apos; consensus view</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Merlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convergent Evolution: Limited Forms Most Beautiful</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mcghee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Vienna Series in Theoretical Biology)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular and Natural Viral Engineering in Cognition-Based Evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W B</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. Integr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2196145</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular survival over genomic perfection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nik-Zainal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="802" to="803" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constraints on spatial variations in the fine-structure constant from Planck</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>O'bryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Smidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Bernardis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cooray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">798</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A three-headed plantaris muscle: Evidence that the plantaris is not a vestigial muscle?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ł</forename><surname>Olewnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zielinska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Karauda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tubbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Polguj</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surg. Radiol. Anat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1189" to="1193" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Live visualizations of single isolated tubulin protein self-assembly via tunneling current: effect of electromagnetic pumping during spontaneous growth of microtubule</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sahu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fujita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/srep07303</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/srep07303" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7303</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On parthenogenesis, or the successive production of procreating individuals from a single ovum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1849">1849</date>
			<publisher>John Van Voorst</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A paradigm shift in our view of species drives current trends in biological classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Padial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>De La Riva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="731" to="751" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural engineering principles of electron tunnelling in biological oxidation-reduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">402</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenomic conflict coincides with rapid morphological innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Parins-Fukuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stull</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum algorithms and the genetic code</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pramana J. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="381" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human Brainstem: Cytoarchitecture, Chemoarchitecture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Paxinos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Myeloarchitecture</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental proof of nonlocal wavefunction collapse for a single particle using homodyne measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fuwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zwierz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ncomms7665</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms7665" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6665</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Tangled Tree: A Radical New History of Life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Quammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Simon &amp; Schuster</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1st ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biology without Darwin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Quick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="588" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Who Was Adam: A Creation Model Approach to the Origin of Man</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>RTB Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Covina</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd expanded ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grover Search as a Naturally Occurring Phenomenon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Roget</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Arrighi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Di</forename><surname>Molfetta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">180501</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Scientific Evidences of Organic Evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Romanes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biblical perspectives as a guide to research on Life&apos;s origin and history</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Religions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">547</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Black holes as evidence of God&apos;s care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Religions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">201</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">More than a Theory (Reasons to Believe): Revealing a Testable Model for Creation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Baker</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Grand Rapids</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Navigating Genesis: A Scientist&apos;s Journey through Genesis 1-11</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Covina, California</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Rescuing Inerrancy: A Scientific Defense</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>RTB Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rubicondior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Malevolent Designer: Why Nature&apos;s God Is Not Good (Unintelligent Design)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence of a false thumb in a fossil carnivore clarifies the evolution of pandas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Salesa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Antón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Peigné</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morales</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="382" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global Late Quaternary megafauna extinctions linked to humans, not climate change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sandom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Faurby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sandel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Svenning</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutually opposing forces during locomotion can eliminate the tradeoff between maneuverability and stability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sefati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18798" to="18803" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using creation science to demonstrate evolution 2: Morphological continuity within Dinosauria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Senter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Evol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2197" to="2216" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perfect use of imperfection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rammensee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">404</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="709" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic water channel controlling remarkable properties of a single brain microtubule: correlating single protein to its supramolecular assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sahu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Aswani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hirata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fujita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosens Bioelectron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell types promoting goosebumps form a niche to regulate hair follicle stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">182</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predator control of ecosystem nutrient dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schmitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hawlena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Trussell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">20602626</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ecol. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1199" to="1209" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-species transmission of an ancient endogenous retrovirus and convergent co-option of its envelope gene in two mammalian orders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kozak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Boso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">36240227</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC9604959</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1010458</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum tunnelling effects in the guanine-thymine wobble misincorporation via tautomerism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Slocombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Winokan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Al-Khalili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sacchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can intelligent design become respectable?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Natl Cent. Sci. Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Intelligent Design Creationism and Its Critics: Philosophical, Theological, and Scientific Perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>Robert</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interaction-Free Effects Between Distant Atoms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Aharonov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Elitzur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10701-017-0127-y</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10701-017-0127-y" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Found Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of pelvic canal shape and rotational birth in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Stansfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D S</forename><surname>Grunstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pouca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mitteroecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">224</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relativistic bell test within quantum reference frames</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Streiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Giacomini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Č</forename><surname>Brukner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">230403</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Four Views on Creation, Evolution, and Intelligent Design (Counterpoints: Bible and Theology)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stump</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Zondervan</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Grand Rapids</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Despite slow catalysis and confused substrate specificity, all ribulose bisphosphate carboxylases may be nearly perfectly optimized</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G B</forename><surname>Tcherkez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Farquhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7246" to="7251" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The million-year wait for macroevolutionary bursts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Uyeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pienaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15908" to="15913" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What if consciousness is not an emergent property of the brain? Observational and empirical challenges to materialistic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wahbeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Radin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cannard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Delorme</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">955594</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The algorithmic origins of life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C W</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. R. Soc. Interface</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20120869</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond reasonable doubt: Evolution from DNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T J</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Penny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">69924</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A list and bibliography of identified baramins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Creation Theology and Science Series B: Life Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthetic chromosomes, genomes, viruses, and cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Venter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Glass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hutchison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vashee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cell.2022.06.046/</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2022.06.046/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2708" to="2724" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global human mandibular variation reflects differences in agricultural and huntergatherer subsistence strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Von Cramon-Taubadel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">22106280</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC3241821</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U. S. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19546" to="19551" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-11-21">2011. 2011 November 21</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct measurement of nonlocal quantum states without approximation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">杨</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">杨</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">龚</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">祝</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chinese Phys. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Case of coexisting, ipsilateral nonrecurrent and recurrent inferior laryngeal nerves</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Laryngol. Otol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Youngblood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Theological wordbook of the Old Testament</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">976</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>electronic ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Archer</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Waltke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">2528 ‫תנן‬</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chicago</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Moody Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">102</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human Perception as a Phenomenon of Quantization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Aerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Arguëlles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/e24091207</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/e24091207103" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Entropy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1207</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultraviolet Superradiance from Mega-Networks of Tryptophan in Biological Architectures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Babcock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Montes-Cabrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Oberhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chergui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Celardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kurian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/acs.jpcb.3c07936</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jpcb.3c07936104" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The journal of physical chemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4035" to="4046" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>B</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cosmic Explosions, Life in the Universe, and the Cosmological Constant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Piran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jimenez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cuesta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Verde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevLett.116.081301</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">26967406</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys Rev Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81301</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-02-23">2016. 2016 Feb 23</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lethal Radiation from Nearby Supernovae Helps Explain the Small Cosmological Constant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tomonori</forename><surname>Totani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1089/ast.2018.1895</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gamma-ray bursts: not so much deadlier than we thought</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brian C</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dimitra</forename><surname>Atri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adrian</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Melott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/mnras/staa3364</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/staa3364107" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">500</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1970" to="1973" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determination of the fine-structure constant with an accuracy of 81 parts per trillion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Morel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cladé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41586-020-2964-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2964-7108" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">588</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unexpected Early Triassic marine ecosystem and the rise of the Modern evolutionary fauna</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brayard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/sciadv.1602159</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1602159</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Happy accidents?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/17737110</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">397</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="665" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convergent evolution of bilaterian nerve cords</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Martín-Durán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Børve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature25030</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature25030111" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b110">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contingency and entrenchment in protein evolution under purifying selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mccandlish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Plotkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b111">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Canonical mRNA is the exception, rather than the rule</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Conn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s13059-017-1268-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-017-1268-1113" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b112">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An atlas of human long non-coding RNAs with accurate 5′ ends</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ramilowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Harshbarger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature21374</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature21374114" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">543</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b113">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microtubule-stabilizer epothilone b delays anesthetic-induced unconsciousness in rats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Timuçin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">eNeuro</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">115</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024. 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ENEURO</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b114">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct modulation of microtubule stability contributes to anthracene general anesthesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Emerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Weiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Psonis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Taratula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fiamengo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Chem Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5398" to="5116" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b115">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epothilone D improves microtubule density, axonal integrity, and cognition in a transgenic mouse model of tauopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brunden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Potuzak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M L</forename><surname>Hogan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Trojanowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">117</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b116">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizing and Disorganizing Resonances of Microtubules, Stem Cells, and Proteins Calculated by a Quantum Equation of Coherence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Geesink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schmieke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Modern Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b117">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using quantum annealing to design lattice proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Irbäck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Knuthson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mohanty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Peterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.013162</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b118">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expanded encyclopaedias of DNA elements in the human and mouse genomes [published correction appears in</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">ENCODE Project Consortium</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Purcaro</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">ENCODE Project Consortium</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41586-021-04226-3</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1038/s41586-020-2493-4 120</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">605</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="699" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2022 May. 7909. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Nature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b119">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA as a perfect quantum computer based on the quantum physics principles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Riera Aroche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ortiz García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Martínez Arellano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Leal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41598-024-62539-5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-62539-5121" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11636</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b120">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence of non-random mutation rates suggests an evolutionary risk management strategy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Martincorena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Seshasayee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Luscombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">485</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">122</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b121">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-random mutation: the evolution of targeted hypermutation and hypomutation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Martincorena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Luscombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioessays</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b122">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution: are the monkeys&apos; typewriters rigged</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Garvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gharrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Royal Society of Open Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140172" to="140124" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b123">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The origins of multicellular organisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Niklas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution &amp; development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">125</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b124">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide motif statistics are shaped by DNA binding proteins over evolutionary time scales</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kussell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review X</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41009" to="041126" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b125">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topology of protein interaction network shapes protein abundances and strengths of their functional and nonspecific interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Maslov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Shakhnovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.0702766104</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0702766104128" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14952" to="14957" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2011. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Robust protein protein interactions in crowded cellular environments Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b126">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein Design by Integrating Machine Learning and Quantum-Encoded Optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Panizza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hauke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Micheletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Faccioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PRX Life</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b127">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electronic and Nuclear Quantum Effects on Proton Transfer Reactions of Guanine-Thymine (G-T) Mispairs Using Combined Quantum Mechanical/Molecular Mechanical and Machine Learning Potentials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Giese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>York</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/molecules29112703</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules29112703130" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecules</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2703</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<pubPlace>Basel, Switzerland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b128">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum and classical effects in DNA point mutations: Watson-Crick tautomerism in AT and GC base pairs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Slocombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Al-Khalili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sacchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1039/d0cp05781a</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">33533770</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics : PCCP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4141" to="4150" />
			<date type="published" when="2021-02">2021 Feb</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
