<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Celestial Body Language Implied In The Planet Earth Upside Down</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Henghua</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Testing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jiangsu Guojian Testing Technology Co</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>214135</postCode>
									<settlement>Ltd. Wuxi</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Testing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jiangsu Guojian Testing Technology Co</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>214135</postCode>
									<settlement>Ltd. Wuxi</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Celestial Body Language Implied In The Planet Earth Upside Down</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2DD074EDB1937800C4CDDB8B9FDB90C7</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Golden Law of the competition of expanding Vs. shrinking is implied in the celestial body language of the Moon and the planet Earth. The evolving of the Pacific Ocean shifting from the fast-expanding state to the mini-shrinking state of micro speed in the world map upside down (South Pole up and North Pole down) matches with the waxing and waning in the phase of the Moon exactly. As the master leading role of the planet Earth absolutely, the evolving process of the Pacific Ocean matching with the phase of the Moon may be concluded as following clue, Birth ➨ fast-expanding ➨ glorious maximum point ➨ mini-shrinking ➨ aging ➨ fade away forever on Earth.</p><p>It is just the birth of the Pacific Ocean about 66 Ma ago and its competing with the (ancient) Atlantic Ocean (including the Indian and Arctic Ocean) for the expanding or shrinking state that triggered the full blooming of the residual ancient plates flower nowadays based on the unique super continental bud which symbolizing the golden time and the glorious period in the evolving history of the planet Earth that human being is experiencing. However, the Golden Law of the competition of expanding Vs. shrinking is also performed by human individual from generation to generation of decades, and even the beautiful flowers as well from year to year in mini time scale.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>It seems that a convenient channel has been opened to approach the truth of the evolving of the oceans and the ancient plates of the planet Earth based on the world map upside down (South Pole up and North Pole down) with the Northwestern Pacific Ocean lying in the middle.</p><p>Since the evolving behavior of the Pacific Ocean matches with the waxing and waning of the phase of the Moon in a degree beyond imagination. Although it might be a pity thing that the waxing process (fast-expanding) and the full Moon (glorious maximum point) of the Pacific Ocean had passed away for tens of millions of years and it is in the process of waning (mini-shrinking) by micro step, it had been catalyzed the incredible full blooming of residual ancient plates flower nowadays based on the unique super continental bud about 66 Ma ago.</p><p>With the Golden Law of the competition of expanding Vs. shrinking implied in the celestial body language of it, the Moon is more than a natural satellite surrounding the planet Earth from night to night and rising up to a beautiful scene to be cheered by human race. In fact, the Moon is a miraculous mirror reflecting what happened long long ago and what is happening at present and even what would happen in the near and faraway future on Earth, Especially focusing on the birth and fast-expanding shifted to mini-shrinking of the Pacific Ocean in which the largest ancient plate (ancient Jiazhou plate) lies as the central core of the ancient plates group broke up from the unique supercontinent about 66 Ma ago.</p><p>Chinese saying that "A stone from another mountain can attack a jade" which mean we could learn more efficiently about the evolving of the planet Earth from its natural satellite--the Moon. Furthermore, even to reveal the evolving mystery of the planet Earth which has been puzzling the geoscience circle all the way for centuries.   3.0 the body language hinted in the phase of the Moon.</p><p>In the phase of the Moon, it sounds reasonable that the bright part is always focused or emphasized by human being. That is the power of conventional inertia thinking of human race. Whether the waxing or waning process, both of them is just the description of the varying of the brightness in the Moon. So much so that the golden full Moon is often highlighted by some talented people. It is shown by Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> as following, However, due to the constant area of the Moon face locked towards the Earth, the phase of the Moon is actually the competition between the bright part and the shadow part. In other words, during the waxing process, the bright part is expanding gradually and the shadow part is shrinking correspondingly. When the bright part gets to the maximum extreme point of expanding, it would get to the reverse side--shrinking, while the shadow part shifts to expanding. That is the essence of waxing and waning process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.0">the phase of the Pacific Ocean matching with that of the Moon and accompanied</head><p>with the assembling of the full blooming of the ancient plates flower.</p><p>In the world map upside down (South Pole up and North Pole down), the red triangle area just shows the largest ancient plate (the ancient Jiazhou plate) sank to the ocean floor about 66 Ma ago at the equatorial area and had been drifting towards higher latitude of the North Hemisphere accompanied with rotating anticlockwise passively until nowadays it is located at the Northwestern Pacific Ocean floor. However, it is magic that the surface of the largest ancient plate was decorated with geological age distribution of clam shell shape by the upwelling of mantle magma around it.</p><p>Just like a baby in the baby carriage eager for running on the ground and touching everything and expanding his or her circle of activities. When it was born on the largest ancient plate (red triangle area) in the middle of the unique supercontinent at the equatorial area about 66 Ma ago, the Pacific Ocean trigged the fast-expanding of itself on the surface of planet Earth, and which forced the Ancient Atlantic Ocean to be shrinking correspondingly. About 40 Ma ago, the newborn Pacific Ocean came to its extreme maximum point of fast-expanding and had to turn to the reverse side--mini-shrinking， due to the newborn Atlantic Ocean What is more miraculous of the planet Earth is that the evolving of the residual ancient plates by reassembling from the beginning of about 66 Ma ago just matches the full blooming process of the flower bud. No doubt, the full blooming of the ancient plates flower nowadays just implies that it is the unique golden time in the evolving history of the planet Earth. Different from the waxing and waning of the flowers each year, the ancient plates flower would exist for single once and its whole process would last for 166 Ma or so. Also, different from the phase of the Moon happens 12 or 13 times per year, the phase of the Pacific Ocean would exist for single once on the planet Earth. About 100 Ma in the future, the Pacific Ocean would be shrinking to the largest ancient plate (red triangle area, the ancient Jiazhou plate) located at the North Pole and would be aging her end life there. Just like an old man or woman sitting in a wheelchair which would lead to sharp shrinking of his or her circle of activities. Obviously, the competition of the (ancient) Atlantic Ocean (including the Indian Ocean and the Arctic Ocean) and the Pacific Ocean is separated by the Pacific Ring of Fire which is formed by the left whirl arm of American ancient plate and the right whirl arm of Asian ancient plate and its extending island chain to the end of New Zealand. If neglect the residual ancient plates and islands on the surface of the Earth, only consider the competition of the (ancient) Atlantic Ocean and the Pacific Ocean, due to the constant area of the Earth's surface from -66 Ma to +100 Ma, that would be a complete evolving of the phase of the Moon.  is shortened to one month, it would match with the variation trend of the phase of the Moon exactly; if its lifespan is shortened to 80~100 years, it would match with the rhythm of human individuals beyond imagination; if its lifespan is shortened to several weeks, it would match with the beautiful scene of blooming of flowers marvelously.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.0">the human individual's life matching with the phase of the</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>"Comparative celestial bodyology" would catalyze and shorten the process to reveal the evolving mystery of the planet Earth.</p><p>It is a famous western saying that "All roads lead to Rome". "Comparative celestial bodyology" would provide a good choice to approach the evolving truth of the Earth through the celestial body language. The waxing and waning process in the phase of the Moon is a natural and reasonable case applied on the planet Earth, especially on the Pacific Ocean, even human individuals and flowers.</p><p>3. "Comparative celestial bodyology" would be booming to be applied in the research of geoscience in the future.</p><p>Given the live case applied in celestial body language of the intimate relationship between the Moon and the planet Earth, the "comparative celestial bodyology" would act as the waxing crescent in the field of geoscience and get its booming welcome like the full Moon in the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Would the supercontinent cycle exist as popular expected?</head><p>The supercontinent cycle might be only existing ideally in computer forever and would never exist on Earth since the Pacific Ocean is alone and feels lonely in the universe. The life of the Pacific Ocean would be existing single once on Earth just like that of the human individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">What is the dinosaur family distinguish from the human race?</head><p>Undoubtedly, the dinosaur family was the overlord of the super continental bud about 66</p><p>Ma ago, while the human race is the crystallization of full blooming of the residual ancient plates flower nowadays. Without the broke up of the supercontinent and sudden extinction of the dinosaur family 66 Ma ago, it would not lead to the full blooming of the residual ancient plates flower nowadays and booming globalization of human being.</p><p>6. What is it symbolizing for the Pacific Ring of Fire as well-known?</p><p>It is the direct body language of the Northwestern Pacific Ocean forced to be mini-shrinking in the state of rotating passively anticlockwise while drifting towards the high latitude of the North Hemisphere until the North Pole in the rhythm of micro pace as slow as a snail moves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7.</head><p>What way should it be more high-efficiency for us to communicate with the celestial bodies in the universe, such as the Moon and the planet Earth and the other members of the solar system, even the whole solar system and the spiral galaxy and the Black Hole?</p><p>Like the communication between the human individuals, the body language often dominates the expressing of the true intention of one person. Therefore, how to catch the profound meaning of the celestial body language should be an indispensable choice in researching of all kinds of celestial bodies in the universe, especially the planet Earth on which human race could establish the base camp during the period of Anthropocene solely.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 1 as following,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. The state of a full blooming flower hinted by the ancient plates in the world map upside down with the Northwestern Pacific Ocean in the middle.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,89.85,77.77,420.40,144.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>2. 0</head><label>0</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The flower bud on the surface of ancient Atlantic Ocean hinted by the unique supercontinent 66 Ma ago in the world map upside down.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,89.85,491.66,420.40,212.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. the body language hinted in the phase of the Moon.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,99.05,189.49,401.93,261.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 4. The phase of the Pacific Ocean matching with that of the Moon and flowers.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,89.85,384.31,420.40,215.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>5. 0</head><label>0</label><figDesc>fig. 5. the body language competition between the phase of the Pacific Ocean and that of the (ancient)Atlantic Ocean (including the Indian Ocean and the Arctic Ocean).</figDesc><graphic coords="6,89.85,246.70,420.40,300.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Moon and blooming of flowers. It is common sense that the human individual's life may match with the phase of Moon and blooming of flowers. The first half of individual's life would exist as fast-expanding while the afternoon of his life may suffer in the process of shrinking. It is always considered to be the blooming of flower season when an individual of human is in his teenage. That is to say, the enough energy fermented by the individual may trigger the process of fast-expanding and wandering around the world without any hesitation. It is shown by Figure 7 as following,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. the human individual's life matching with the phase of the Moon and blooming of flowers. 8.0 the Golden Law of the celestial body language implied in the phase of the Moon. What implied in the phase of the Moon is the Golden Law of competition of expanding Vs. shrinking. In simple words, things would turn to the reverse side of it once reaching the extreme point of evolving. The phase of the Moon is actually the mirror reflection of what is happening between the evolving of the Atlantic Ocean (including the Indian Ocean and the Arctic Ocean) and the Pacific Ocean.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,89.85,392.13,420.40,200.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="7,111.05,573.65,377.93,137.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The jigsaw recovery of the Earth&apos;s unique supercontinent 66 million years ago. ESS Open Archive</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Henghua</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.22541/essoar.168500251.13364603/v1</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-05-25">May 25, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Discovery of the Cross &quot;十&quot; Shape Ocean-Plate Whirlpool of Double Whirl Arms of the Planet Earth. Preprints 2023</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.20944/preprints202312.1236.v1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202312.1236.v1" />
		<imprint>
			<date>2023121236</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tin isotopes indicative of liquid-vapour equilibration and separation in the Moon-forming disk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fitoussi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bourdon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41561-019-0433-4</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-019-0433-4" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Geosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="711" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exotic clasts in Chang&apos;e-5 regolith indicative of unexplored terrane on the Moon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41550-022-01840-7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41550-022-01840-7" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Astron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moon-forming impactor as a source of Earth&apos;s basal mantle anomalies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Desch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41586-023-06589-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06589-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">623</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A soft X-ray image of the Moon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schmitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Snowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Aschenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/349583a0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/349583a0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">349</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New Integrals of Motion and the Orbital History of the Moon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Goudas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/218726a0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/218726a0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">218</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="726" to="728" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cometary collisions on the Moon and Mercury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Srnka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/284022a0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/284022a0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lunar Periodicity in Reproduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/109237a0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/109237a0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="1922">1922</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
