<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting National Nostalgia: Make America Moral Again!</title>
				<funder ref="#_BhCzgQf">
					<orgName type="full">Air Force Office of Scientific Research</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">AFOSR</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Farzan</forename><surname>Karimi-Malekabadi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>California</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alireza</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ziabari</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern California</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Morteza</forename><surname>Dehghani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>California</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern California</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Karimi-Malekabadi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3620 McClintock Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>90089</postCode>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting National Nostalgia: Make America Moral Again!</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FFA18A9A8A33C7141C462FAAB4648A04</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:56+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>national nostalgia</term>
					<term>moral decline</term>
					<term>self-discontinuity</term>
					<term>political rhetoric</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Data and Code Availability. The data and analysis code supporting the findings of this study are openly available at the Open Science Framework (OSF): https://osf.io/b742y.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Revisiting National Nostalgia: Make America Moral Again! Humans have long relied on cooperation for survival. From foraging to defense, most tasks are inefficient or impossible to accomplish without cooperation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Henrich &amp; Muthukrishna, 2021)</ref>. Cooperation endures across generations only when people perceive their groups as stable and enduring, which is known as collective self-continuity, the sense that "we" remain the same entity over time despite shifting social, political, and economic conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Brewer &amp; Gardner, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Sani et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Sedikides et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Smeekes &amp; Verkuyten, 2014)</ref>. When continuity feels threatened, groups risk fragmentation and reduced cooperation <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Smeekes &amp; Verkuyten, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>One psychological response to such threats is collective nostalgia, a longing for the group's past <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Sedikides &amp; Wildschut, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Smeekes et al., 2023)</ref>. Collective nostalgia can restore a sense of temporal stability and cooperation, yet like other mechanisms that heighten the salience of collective identity, collective nostalgia is a double-edged sword: it can strengthen solidarity among ingroup members while sharpening intergroup boundaries and fostering exclusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Wildschut et al., 2014)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Smeekes, 2019b</ref> has cataloged several triggers of collective nostalgia (e.g., perceived collective discontinuity, relative deprivation) and documented its consequences (ingroup protection, outgroup rejection). However, no existing theory has yet identified which aspects of group identity make discontinuity most psychologically destabilizing, leaving the underlying mechanism underdeveloped.</p><p>We try to address this gap with the Moral Nostalgia Hypothesis (MNH), which proposes that shared moral values, more than group cues or material concerns, anchor the collective self. In this sense, collective nostalgia is recruited as a moral emotion to safeguard collective self-continuity. MNH frames moral identity threats as the most powerful triggers of collective nostalgia. Drawing on research on the essential moral self, which shows that moral traits are central to self-continuity such that moral loss implies self-loss <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Strohminger &amp; Nichols, 2014)</ref>, even moderate changes to a person's moral identity lead others to perceive them as fundamentally different. We extend these insights to the group level. If moral values define "who I am" as an individual, they can also serve as the foundation of "who we are" as a group. Thus, shared moral decline should uniquely threaten a group's sense of self. Building on past evidence on collective self-continuity and nostalgia <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Sedikides &amp; Wildschut, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Smeekes et al., 2023)</ref>, MNH suggests that nostalgia functions as an affective mechanism that reestablishes a morally coherent image of the collective. In this view, nostalgia is not merely sentimentality or partisan rhetoric, but a moralized emotion that is recruited to regulate cooperation by orienting groups toward a morally imagined past.</p><p>If collective nostalgia is morally relevant, then, drawing on MNH, we derive two corollaries specifying its mechanism: who is most susceptible at a dispositional level and when it is most likely to arise at a situational level. First, regarding Trait-sensitivity (who is most susceptible, dispositional), if moral traits are central to personal identity (moral loss ∼ self-loss) and groups are incorporated into the self-concept <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Brewer &amp; Gardner, 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Strohminger &amp; Nichols, 2014)</ref>, then individuals who chronically endorse moral values should be especially prone to collective nostalgia, even in the absence of an immediate threat. Their strong moral commitment heightens motivation to preserve the group's moral image <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Aquino &amp; Reed II, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lasaleta et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Skitka et al., 2005)</ref>. Second, regarding Threat-selectivity (when nostalgia is most likely to arise, situational), among threats to collective self-continuity, perceived moral decline should be the most powerful trigger. Moral deterioration suggests that "we are no longer the same us," whereas economic or material decline undermines welfare without directly challenging the group's moral essence <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Sedikides &amp; Wildschut, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Smeekes et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Strohminger &amp; Nichols, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>To empirically test MNH, we focus on national nostalgia, where the group is one's country. National identity is a universally salient form of group membership, rich with historical narratives, and deeply tied to contemporary political behavior, making it both theoretically meaningful and methodologically practical for studying collective nostalgia.</p><p>With only one exception (e.g., organizational nostalgia; <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Leunissen et al., 2024)</ref>), most research on collective nostalgia has centered on nations, and the literature often uses the terms collective nostalgia and national nostalgia interchangeably <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Smeekes et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Wildschut et al., 2014)</ref>. To evaluate MNH's distinctiveness, we directly compare moral values and perceived moral decline against alternative explanations, including political ideology and national identification, thereby specifying morality as the key identity content underlying national nostalgia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Present Research</head><p>We derive two specific predictions from MNH and test them across four studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Trait-sensitivity Prediction</head><p>Endorsement of moral values is the strongest predictor of national nostalgia, above and beyond political ideology, national identification, personal nostalgia, and several key control variables. This prediction is tested in Studies 1 and 2. Specifically, Study 1 examines trait-sensitivity prediction in a U.S. sample. This foundational test is necessary to establish morality as an independent explanatory factor in national nostalgia. We operationalize moral values using Moral Foundations Theory (MFT; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Atari et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Graham et al., 2013)</ref>), a socio-cultural framework that defines morality across six domains: care (sensitivity to others' suffering), equality (fairness and in-kind reciprocity), proportionality (rewards and punishments based on merit), loyalty (group obligations), authority (respect for hierarchy and tradition), and purity (values related to chastity).</p><p>Next, Study 2 replicates and extends this test across 19 countries to evaluate whether the morality-national nostalgia link is robust across diverse cultural and economic contexts.</p><p>Because the salience of specific moral foundations varies across cultures, this study examines whether the link between morality and national nostalgia is universal or instead bounded by cultural context. Controlling for economic indicators (e.g., GDP, inequality, unemployment) and cultural variables (e.g., individualism, cultural distance to the U.S.) ensures that the observed effects are not artifacts of structural context.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Threat-selectivity Prediction</head><p>Perceived decline in shared moral values predicts national nostalgia more strongly than perceived economic decline (controlling for political ideology and national identification). This prediction is tested in Studies 3 and 4. Specifically, in Study 3, using a U.S. sample, we directly compare perceived moral decline with perceived economic decline to predict national nostalgia, while controlling for political ideology, national identification, and moral values themselves. Study 3 isolates the relative contribution of moral versus non-moral threats. Lastly, Study 4 takes a historical approach, analyzing two centuries of American and Chinese texts to examine whether concerns about moral decline and national nostalgic expression co-fluctuate over time. The very notion of moral decline is inherently temporal, presupposing that present standards are worse than those of the past.</p><p>While Study 3 captures this perception through self-report, such measures are bound to contemporary frames of reference. Historical text analysis provides an ecologically valid test of the hypothesis by treating language as a cultural archive, allowing us to examine whether moral decline and nostalgia reliably co-occur across generations <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Chen et al., 2024)</ref>. Including both American (COHA) and Chinese (People's Daily) corpora assesses whether the link holds across two traditions with distinct moral frameworks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 1</head><p>The primary goal of Study 1 is to determine if moral values predict national nostalgia in the American context. The analysis controls for a range of related variables, including personal nostalgia, the general tendency to live in the past or future, memory vividness, conservatism, national identification, and age.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>Participants were recruited through Prolific (N = 622), with the sample stratified by political orientation and gender. They first completed the Moral Foundations Questionnaire-2 to assess moral values <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Atari et al., 2023)</ref>, followed by control measures, the National Nostalgia Scale <ref type="bibr">(Smeekes, 2019a)</ref>, and demographic questions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Moral Foundation Questionnaire-2 (MFQ-2). We assessed moral values using the Moral Foundation Questionnaire-2 (MFQ-2), which measures six domains: Care, Equality, Proportionality, Loyalty, Authority, and Purity <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Atari et al., 2023)</ref>. Participants rated 36 items on a 5-point scale from 1 (Does not describe me at all) to 5 (Describes me extremely well). A sample item for each foundation is, respectively: "It pains me when I see someone ignoring the needs of another human being." (Care); "I believe that everyone should be given the same quantity of resources in life." (Equality); "I think people who are more hard-working should end up with more money." (Proportionality); "Everyone should love their own community." (Loyalty); "I think having a strong leader is good for society." (Authority); "I admire people who keep their virginity until marriage." (Purity). In the present sample, the Cronbach's α coefficients for the subscales were strong: Care (α = .89), Equality (α = .87), Proportionality (α = .78), Loyalty (α = .85), Authority (α = .87), and Purity (α = .86).</p><p>National Nostalgia. To assess national nostalgia, we used four items (α = .86) adapted from <ref type="bibr">(Smeekes, 2019a)</ref>. Participants responded on a 7-point scale ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree). Example items include: "I get nostalgic when I think back to my country in past times," "I experience nostalgic feelings when I hear my country's music of the past," "I often long for the old days of my country," and "I often think back about the good old days." We averaged the four items to form a composite score (M = 4.87, SD = 1.54).</p><p>Personal Nostalgia. We measured personal nostalgia using the Southampton Nostalgia Scale <ref type="bibr">(Routledge et al., 2011)</ref>. Participants responded to items (e.g., "How often do you experience nostalgia?", "How prone are you to feeling nostalgic?") on a 5-point scale ranging from 1 (Does not describe me at all) to 5 (Describes me extremely well). We averaged the five items to form a composite score, where higher scores reflect greater nostalgia proneness (α = .91; M = 3.96, SD = 1.45).</p><p>Past Orientation. To assess past orientation, we used a single-item created for this study, which asks: "If you were to live in a different time, would you prefer to live in the future or the past?" Responses were coded such that 0 corresponds to Future and 1 corresponds to Past (M = 0.66, SD = 0.47).</p><p>Past Vividness. We measured past vividness with a single item developed for this study, which asks: "Which time (the past vs. the future) can you more vividly imagine in your mind?" Responses were coded such that 1 = Distant future, 2 = Near future, 3 = Recent past, and 4 = Distant past (M = 3.21, SD = 0.84).</p><p>Conservatism. We measured conservatism with a single item on a 6-point scale ranging from 1 (Left/Progressive) to 6 (Right/Conservative). Participants' average score was M = 3.44, SD = 1.62.</p><p>National Identification. To measure national identification, we asked participants to rate their agreement with the statement "I identify with my country" on a 7-point scale ranging from 1 (Strongly disagree) to 7 (Strongly agree). We averaged responses to form a composite score (M = 5.16, SD = 1.59).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and Discussion</head><p>To isolate the unique contribution of moral values in predicting national nostalgia, we ran two sequential multiple regression models in R (R Core Team, 2021). The first model (Model 1), which included only the control variables, was statistically significant, F (6, 448) = 70.52, p &lt; .001, and accounted for 48.6% of the variance in national nostalgia</p><p>The second model (Model 2) extended Model 1 by including the six moral values as additional predictors and was also statistically significant, F (12, 442) = 47.95, p &lt; .001. This new model accounted for 56.6% of the total variance , explaining an additional 8% of the variance in national nostalgia (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>).  Consistent with prior work portraying nostalgia as predominantly conservative and hierarchical in nature <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Smeekes et al., 2021)</ref>, we found that conservatives were generally more nostalgic. However, the effects of authority and equality were not moderated by conservatism, indicating that these moral commitments contribute to nostalgic sentiment across the ideological spectrum, suggesting a broadly moral rather than purely partisan basis for national nostalgia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A comparison of the models reveals that the inclusion of moral values in</head><p>Because Study 1 focused on a single national context, it remains unclear whether the association between moral values and national nostalgia generalizes across societies that differ in cultural and economic conditions. Study 2 therefore extends the test of the trait-sensitivity corollary across 19 diverse societies while examining potential macro-level moderators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 2</head><p>Building on Study 1, which established a link between moral values and national nostalgia in the United States, Study 2 examines the cross-cultural generalizability of this finding. We test whether moral foundations consistently predict national nostalgia across 19 diverse nations (N = 3,902), deliberately selected based on cultural distance metrics <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Muthukrishna et al., 2020)</ref> to ensure broad variation in cultural and economic contexts.</p><p>Participants completed the same primary measures as Study 1: MFQ-2 and the National Nostalgia Scale. Our analysis controlled for the same individual-level factors (including personal nostalgia, ideology, and age) and also introduced key national-level variables, such as the Human Development Index (HDI), the Gini Index (a measure of income inequality), GDP, and the Misery Index.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>Our cross-cultural investigation involved 3,902 participants, recruited from nationally stratified samples across 19 countries to reflect national demographics of gender, education, and age. The selected countries-Argentina, Belgium, Chile, Colombia, Egypt, France, Ireland, Japan, Kenya, Mexico, Morocco, New Zealand, Nigeria, Peru, Russia, Saudi Arabia, South Africa, Switzerland, and the United Arab Emirates, were chosen to represent a broad spectrum of cultural distances <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Muthukrishna et al., 2020)</ref>. Data collection was managed by Qualtrics Panels, resulting in cohorts of 205-207 participants per nation. Prior to administration, all study materials were translated into Spanish, French, Arabic, Japanese, and Russian using the standard back-translation procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Brislin, 1970)</ref>, with independent bilingual researchers verifying the translations to ensure accuracy and resolve any discrepancies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>In addition to the individual-level variables examined in Study 1, our analysis incorporated the following society-level covariates: GDP. We incorporated Gross Domestic Product (GDP) to assess each country's economic performance. GDP, which measures the total value of all goods and services produced within a nation's borders in a specific period (typically one year), is a common proxy for a nation's economic prosperity and standard of living. The GDP data used in this study were collected from the World Bank Data website 1 Notably, all GDP figures were log-transformed prior to analysis to normalize their distribution.</p><p>Gini Index. We incorporated the Gini coefficient to measure country-level income inequality. The Gini coefficient, a statistical measure that quantifies the degree of income distribution inequality within a country, ranges from 0 to 100. A score of 0 represents perfect equality (where everyone has the same income), whereas a score of 100 represents perfect inequality (where one person has all the income). The Gini coefficient data used in 1 https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GDP.MKTP.CD.</p><p>this study were obtained from the World Bank's Data website 2 . Misery Index. We utilized the Misery Index to assess the overall level of economic distress in each country. The Misery Index, an economic indicator designed to measure financial hardship, is calculated by combining a nation's unemployment rate with its inflation rate. The data for this measure were obtained from Statista 3 . Individualism. To account for cultural differences in social values, we included a measure of country-level individualism. This dimension contrasts individualistic cultures, which emphasize personal rights, autonomy, and self-reliance, with collectivistic cultures, where preference is given to group harmony, cooperation, and integration into the social structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Oyserman, 2017)</ref>. The country-level individualism indices used in this study were obtained from Hofstede <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Hofstede, 2013)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human Development Index (HDI). We included the Human Development</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and Discussion</head><p>Similar to the first study, we ran two models: Model 1, which excluded moral values, and Model 2, which included moral values. To account for the nested nature of our data, we used multilevel models using "lme4" R package <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bates et al., 2015)</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref> illustrates the variations in national nostalgia across 19 nations.</p><p>Model 1 accounted for 43% of the variance in national nostalgia when considering 2 https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SI.POV.GINI  only the fixed effects, and 44% when including both fixed and random effects. Model 2 extended Model 1 by including moral values as additional predictors (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">3</ref>). The overall multi-level model accounted for 50% of the variance based on fixed effects and 51% when accounting for both fixed and random effects. The addition of these fixed effects successfully captured the variance attributable to country-level differences, leaving very little unexplained variance at the country level: only about 2% of the variance in Model 1 (country-level variance = 0.024, residual variance = 1.18) and 1.6% in Model 2 (country-level variance = 0.017, residual variance = 1.04).  unexplained variance remained at the country level, suggesting that the psychological link between moral identity and nostalgic longing is remarkably stable, despite significant cultural, political, and economic differences. At the same time, macro-indicators such as the Misery Index and individualism influenced overall levels of nostalgia but did not alter the person-level moral pattern. These findings demonstrate that moral identity content travels well across societies and that cross-national differences in nostalgia largely reflect structural conditions rather than a change in the underlying moral mechanism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 3</head><p>Building on Studies 1 and 2, which supported the trait-sensitivity prediction of the Moral Nostalgia Hypothesis by showing that people who chronically endorse certain moral values are more prone to national nostalgia, Study 3 tests MNH's second key claim: threat-selectivity. According to this prediction, nostalgia should not only stem from stable moral commitments but also be activated when people perceive that their nation's moral fabric is eroding. We therefore examined whether perceived moral decline predicts national nostalgia above and beyond stable moral values and other dispositional factors (personal nostalgia, ideology, national identification, temporal orientation, and age). To test MNH's specificity, we contrasted moral decline with perceived economic decline, asking whether nostalgia responds more strongly to moral threat than to material hardship.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dataset and Procedure</head><p>A total of 400 U.S. participants were recruited through Prolific using stratified sampling to ensure variation in political orientation, age, and gender. Participants completed measures assessing their moral values (MFQ-2), perceptions of moral decline, perceptions of economic decline, and national nostalgia. Control variables included personal nostalgia proneness, political ideology, national identification, past orientation, and age. As in Studies 1 and 2, all items were scored so that higher values reflected stronger endorsement or greater perception of decline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Perceived Moral Decline. To assess perceived moral decline, we created six items corresponding to the six moral foundations (Care, Equality, Proportionality, Loyalty, Authority, and Purity). Participants rated the extent to which each moral value is less respected in today's society compared to the past. Example items included: "It seems like people today care less about helping others and showing compassion compared to the past" (Care decline), "Society used to value treating everyone equally, but nowadays it seems more divided and unfair" (Equality decline), and "In the past, people valued chastity and modesty more than they do today" (Purity decline). Each item was conceptually aligned with its respective MFQ-2 foundation to ensure consistency with the moral values measured in earlier studies. Participants responded on a 7-point scale ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree) and they reported moderate to high levels of Other Measures. All other variables, including national and personal nostalgia, moral foundations (MFQ-2), political ideology, national identification, past orientation, and age, were assessed using the same instruments and response formats as in Studies 1 and 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and Discussion</head><p>We regressed national nostalgia on perceived moral decline scores, moral foundations, and all control variables. The overall model was statistically significant, F (17, 379) = 61.20, p &lt; .001, explaining 73.3% of the variance in national nostalgia (R 2 = .733, adjusted R 2 = .721). Among the six perceived moral declines, three emerged as significant predictors: perceived equality decline (b = 0.149, p &lt; .001), perceived proportionality decline (b = 0.131, p &lt; .001), and perceived purity decline (b = 0.078, p = .040). However, the effects of current moral values (MFQ-2) were largely non-significant, with the exception of authority (b = 0.389, p &lt; .001).</p><p>Perceived economic decline was a weaker predictor (b = 0.059, p = .10) and only marginally significant. Personal nostalgia (b = 0.354, p &lt; .001), temporal orientation (b = 0.413, p &lt; .001), and conservatism (b = 0.139, p &lt; .01) also predicted national nostalgia.</p><p>These findings are consistent with the MNH, which proposes that national nostalgia is most strongly activated when people perceive moral, rather than economic, values to be under threat. The results refine our understanding of national nostalgia as shaped by both enduring dispositions and situational perceptions of societal change, and they contribute to broader theories of collective memory and moral motivation. The authority endorsement predicted nostalgia even in the absence of perceived authority decline, suggesting that some values may function as chronic dispositions: valuing order and tradition can evoke a longing for the past, even in the absence of an explicit threat to these values. However, the strong influence of perceived declines in equality and proportionality highlights the threat-selectivity mechanism; national nostalgia intensifies when people sense that fairness has been eroded. This distinction suggests that not all moral concerns are associated with nostalgia in the same way: values such as authority can sustain a baseline of longing, whereas fairness-related values activate nostalgia primarily in response to perceived threats.</p><p>The consistent role of equality across Studies 1-3 further suggests that fairness concerns may operate as a unifying moral driver, potentially resonating across ideological divides. Together, these findings imply that collective longing for the past is not solely a conservative impulse to restore hierarchy but can also reflect aspirations to recover moral fairness and cohesion in times of perceived societal change. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 4</head><p>In Study 4, we examined whether discourse about moral decline and national nostalgia co-occur historically in public language. Whereas previous studies established an individual-level link between moral concerns and national nostalgia, these findings relied on self-reports that can be influenced by memory biases, motivated reasoning, and current political attitudes <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Mastroianni &amp; Gilbert, 2023)</ref>. Moreover, moral decline is not an objective marker, but a socially constructed and historically variable perception that shifts in response to broader cultural contexts. To address these limitations and test whether the MNH generalizes beyond individual assessments, we analyzed large-scale historical language data. If national nostalgia is, in part, a response to moral concerns, then historical fluctuations in discourse about moral decline should systematically align with expressions of longing for the national past.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corpus</head><p>We analyzed historical English and Chinese texts using a combination of natural language processing and time series modeling. For English, we used the Corpus of Historical American English (COHA), which contains over 400 million words spanning from the 1810s to 2010s across diverse genres, including fiction, journalism, academic prose, and spoken dialogue. For Chinese, we used the People's Daily corpus, a comprehensive and longitudinal textual archive of the official newspaper of the Chinese Communist Party, which has been published daily since 1946. As one of the most authoritative sources of public discourse in modern Chinese history, the corpus offers insight into how moral and national narratives have been shaped by, and have reflected, state ideology, sociopolitical shifts, and cultural transformation. It includes millions of articles across politics, economy, society, and culture, making it a rich resource for tracing moral and nostalgic discourse in a highly centralized media environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Language Analysis</head><p>To extract construct-relevant signals from these corpora, we used the Contextualized Construct Representation (CCR) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Chen et al., 2024)</ref>. CCR quantifies the presence of psychological constructs in text using sentence embeddings derived from validated scale items. We operationalized both moral decline and national nostalgia using the same face-valid survey items employed in Study 3. CCR computes cosine similarities between item embeddings and sentences in the target corpus, aggregating across time to produce annual construct prevalence scores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preprocessing and Analysis.</head><p>For both corpora, we first generated yearly time series of average CCR scores for national nostalgia and moral decline. We applied autoregressive integrated moving average (ARIMA) modeling using the auto.arima function <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Hyndman &amp; Khandakar, 2008)</ref> to identify optimal (p, d, q) parameters for each series based on the corrected Akaike Information Criterion (AICc). Differencing (d) was applied as needed to achieve stationarity, and residual diagnostics (Ljung-Box tests at lags 10, 15, and 20) confirmed adequate whiteness. Residuals from these fitted models were then used in cross-correlation analyses to test contemporaneous and lagged associations between moral decline and national nostalgia. Statistical significance was evaluated against the ±1.96/ √ N confidence band with Bonferroni-corrected p values. To obtain robust 95% confidence intervals and test cross-corpus differences, we implemented a restandardized block bootstrap (block size = 5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and Discussion</head><p>In the English-language COHA corpus, cross-correlation analysis revealed a significant contemporaneous association between residualized national nostalgia and moral decline scores, peaking at lag 0 with r = .368, p = 2.83 × 10 -7 (Bonferroni p = 1.16 × 10 -5 ). The effect exceeded the ±1.96/ √ N confidence band (±0.146; N =180), and the Fisher z-based 95% confidence interval was <ref type="bibr">[0.234, 0.488]</ref>. This indicates that moral decline and national nostalgia discourse moved closely together over historical time in U.S. English (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">5</ref>).</p><p>We observed a similar pattern in the People's Daily Chinese corpus, where residual cross-correlation likewise peaked at lag 0 with r = .577, p = 2.60 × 10 -6 (Bonferroni p = 1.07 × 10 -4 ). This value exceeded the ±1.96/ √ N confidence band (±0.267; N =54), with a corresponding 95% confidence interval of [0.366, 0.732]. These results again suggest strong synchrony between moral decline and national nostalgia discourse (see Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>). The cross-corpus synchrony observed in both U.S. and Chinese texts supports the idea that when societies express concerns about declining morality, they concurrently evoke nostalgic ideals of a better national past. Although the association was numerically stronger in the Chinese corpus (r = .58 vs. r = .37), this difference was not statistically significant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 6</head><p>Cross-correlation between national nostalgia and moral decline discourse in the People's Daily corpus (Chinese). The residual cross-correlation peaked at lag 0 (r = .58, p &lt; .001), reflecting strong synchrony in state-controlled discourse.</p><p>Overall, the findings indicate that public moral and nostalgic discourse rise and fall together over historical time, suggesting that the relationship between moral threat and national longing generalizes across distinct cultural and political contexts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General Discussion</head><p>In remark captures more than nostalgia for a bygone political style; it invokes a moral vision of hierarchy, discipline, and deference to authority.</p><p>Our findings show this is no isolated flourish. Across 20 cultural contexts and roughly 4,924 participants, authority values consistently emerged as the strongest predictor of national nostalgia, even after accounting for ideology, national identification, personal nostalgia, and economic conditions, a broad "return to order" rhetoric. Yet authority's influence appears dispositional rather than reactive: in Study 3, perceived declines in authority did not significantly predict nostalgia.</p><p>However, fairness-related values functioned primarily as reactive triggers. Perceived declines in equality and proportionality, rather than mere endorsement of these values, were among the strongest situational predictors of nostalgia, echoing the populist narrative that "the system is rigged.". At the macro level, higher Gini coefficients and Misery Index scores correlated with stronger national nostalgia, suggesting that inequality and economic hardship create fertile conditions for longing for the past <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Eatwell &amp; Goodwin, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Norris &amp; Inglehart, 2016</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2019</ref>). Yet when participants were asked directly about economic decline, its predictive power vanished once moral decline was taken into account. This pattern implies that structural economic upheavals, fading powers, rising competitors, and widespread economic volatility are psychologically reframed as moral failures of fairness rather than as purely material losses <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Judis, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Mudde &amp; Kaltwasser, 2017)</ref>.</p><p>This dynamic resonates with the broader geopolitical context. The post-Cold War order has eroded: once-dominant powers fade as new ones rise, and multipolarity and uncertainty define the current international landscape <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Ikenberry, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Mearsheimer, 2019)</ref>. Rising income inequality over recent decades, documented by the World Inequality Report 2022<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">6</ref> , has further intensified perceptions of unfairness, making earlier eras seem comparatively more equitable. Such structural upheavals amplify anxieties about who "we" are as a nation and whether resources are distributed justly <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Norris &amp; Inglehart, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Populist movements across diverse contexts-including Trumpism in the United States, Brexit in the United Kingdom, Marine Le Pen's National Rally in France, Viktor Orbán's Fidesz in Hungary, Jair Bolsonaro's presidency in Brazil, and Giorgia Meloni's Brothers of Italy-tap into these sentiments, wielding nostalgic rhetoric such as "Make America Great</p><p>Again" <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Eatwell &amp; Goodwin, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Mudde &amp; Kaltwasser, 2017)</ref>. By framing contemporary challenges as moral decline rather than mere economic hardship, these movements transform national nostalgia into a powerful mobilizing force.</p><p>At the same time, the robust and stable association between authority values and national nostalgia underscores a trait-level pathway: even in the absence of perceived decline, those who prioritize hierarchy and tradition are predisposed to view the past as morally superior. Together, these findings suggest that material distress and structural shifts prepare the ground, but moral concerns, especially fairness and authority, provide the emotional spark.</p><p>Our historical analysis reveals that moral-decline discourse and nostalgic rhetoric consistently co-fluctuate over time, indicating a dynamic interplay between moral concerns and collective memory. While these data do not establish a causal direction, they open a promising avenue for future work. Experimental and longitudinal designs could clarify whether perceptions of moral decline cause nostalgia, whether nostalgia itself moralizes the past, or whether both processes reinforce one another. By spanning 20 cultures and combining surveys and text analyses, our evidence provides a robust foundation for MNH;</p><p>the next potential step is to test its scope beyond national identity to explore other moral dimensions that might similarly mobilize nostalgic longing.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Model 2 partially accounted for the effects of national identification, conservatism, and equality. Specifically, the coefficient for national identification dropped from b = 0.320 (SE = 0.046; t = 6.90, p &lt; .001) in Model 1 to b = 0.185 (SE = 0.051; t = 3.61, p &lt; .001) in Model 2. Similarly, the coefficient for conservatism dropped from b = 0.135 (SE = 0.044; t = 3.05, p = .003) in Model 1 to b = 0.106 (SE = 0.047; t = 2.24, p = .026) in Model 2. Finally, equality emerged as a significant predictor in Model 2 (b = 0.125, SE = 0.045; t = 2.76, p = .006). These reductions in coefficients suggest that the moral values included in Model 2 partially account for the effects of national identification and conservatism on national nostalgia. Regarding the effects of group-based moral values, equality (b = 0.125, SE = 0.045, t = 2.76, p = .006) and authority (b = 0.256, SE = 0.063, t = 4.08, p &lt; .001) were significant predictors of national nostalgia in Model 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 Standardized regression coefficients from Study 1 predicting national nostalgia. Orange and green dots represent coefficients from Models 1 and 2, respectively. Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,72.00,318.58,468.01,280.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Index (HDI) to provide a broad assessment of national well-being and quality of life. The HDI, a composite statistic from the United Nations, evaluates a country's overall development by incorporating three key dimensions: life expectancy, education (based on mean and expected years of schooling), and per capita income. The data for this index were obtained from the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) Human Development Reports 4 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>3</head><label></label><figDesc>https://www.statista.com/statistics/227162/most-miserable-countries-in-the-world/ 4 https://hdr.undp.org/data-center/human-development-index</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 Country-level means of National nostalgia across 19 nations; darker shading indicates higher scores. Countries with no data are shown in gray.</figDesc><graphic coords="13,72.00,75.19,467.97,233.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Focusing</head><label></label><figDesc>on Model 2, we found a positive relationship between national nostalgia and conservatism (b = 0.106, SE = 0.047, t = 2.24, p = .026), national identification (b = 0.140, SE = 0.015, t = 9.34, p &lt; .001), personal nostalgia (b = 0.336, SE = 0.013, t = 25.67, p &lt; .001), MI (b = 0.009, SE = 0.002, t = 3.93, p = .003), authority (b = 0.298, SE = 0.041, t = 7.35, p &lt; .001), loyalty (b = 0.158, SE = 0.037, t = 4.27, p &lt; .001), and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3 Standardized regression coefficients from Study 2 predicting national nostalgia. Orange and green dots represent coefficients from Models 1 and 2, respectively. Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,72.00,75.19,468.01,280.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>perceived decline: Care (M = 4.63, SD = 1.72), Equality (M = 3.98, SD = 2.02), Proportionality (M = 4.65, SD = 1.56), Loyalty (M = 4.91, SD = 1.59), Authority (M = 5.46, SD = 1.33), and Purity (M = 5.65, SD = 1.45). Perceived Economic Decline. Perceived economic decline was measured with two items to capture both collective and personal perspectives on economic loss. The first item was: "I believe my country's economic strength has diminished compared to what it was in the past." The second item was: "My financial situation was better in the past." Participants responded to both on the same 7-point scale (1 = strongly disagree, 7 = strongly agree). Perceived economic decline was M = 4.65 (SD = 1.46).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4 Standardized regression coefficients from Study 3 examining predictors of national nostalgia. Significant predictors include perceived declines in Purity, Proportionality, and Equality. Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</figDesc><graphic coords="18,72.00,199.05,468.01,280.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5Cross-correlation between national nostalgia and moral decline discourse in the COHA corpus (English). The residual cross-correlation peaked at lag 0 (r = .37, p &lt; .001), indicating strong contemporaneous coupling.</figDesc><graphic coords="21,130.50,75.18,350.99,240.03" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="22,130.50,75.19,351.00,248.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>February 2016, during a rally in Las Vegas, protesters interrupted Donald Trump's speech. After security escorted them out, Trump told the crowd, "In the good old days, this doesn't happen because they used to treat them very, very rough. And when they protested once, they would not do it again so easily. I love the old days. You know what they used to do to guys like that when they were in a place like this? They'd be</figDesc><table /><note><p>carried out on a stretcher." 5 Featured prominently in DuVernay's documentary 13th, the 5 The Washington Post, March 2016; DuVernay's 13th (2016).</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://wir2022.wid.world/</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>This research was supported by the <rs type="funder">Air Force Office of Scientific Research (AFOSR)</rs> under Grant No. <rs type="grantNumber">A9550-23-1-0463</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_BhCzgQf">
					<idno type="grant-number">A9550-23-1-0463</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The self-importance of moral identity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Aquino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1423</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morality beyond the weird: How the nomological network of morality varies across cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Atari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koleva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dehghani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Lme4: Linear mixed-effects models using eigen and s4. r package version 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mächler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bolker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2015. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who is this&quot; we&quot;? levels of collective identity and self representations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Back-translation for cross-cultural research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brislin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of cross-cultural psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Surveying the dead minds: Historical-psychological text analysis with contextualized construct representation (ccr) for classical chinese</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Atari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2403.00509</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">National populism: The revolt against liberal democracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Eatwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Penguin UK.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moral foundations theory: The pragmatic validity of moral pluralism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koleva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Motyl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Iyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wojcik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ditto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="130" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The origins and psychology of human cooperation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Henrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Muthukrishna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual review of psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hofstede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">National cultural dimensions. Recuperado el</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">22</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic time series forecasting: The forecast package for r</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hyndman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Khandakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of statistical software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The end of liberal international order</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ikenberry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International affairs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The populist explosion: How the great recession transformed american and european politics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Judis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Columbia Global Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nostalgia increases punitiveness by intensifying moral concern</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lasaleta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wildschut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sedikides</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11425</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational nostalgia: The construct, the scale and its implications for organizational functioning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leunissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Dijke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wildschut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sedikides</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="816" to="838" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The illusion of moral decline</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mastroianni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">618</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7966</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="782" to="789" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bound to fail: The rise and fall of the liberal international order</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mearsheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International security</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Populism: A very short introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mudde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kaltwasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond western, educated, industrial, rich, and democratic (weird) psychology: Measuring and mapping scales of cultural and psychological distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Muthukrishna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Henrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Curtin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gedranovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcinerney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Thue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="678" to="701" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trump, brexit, and the rise of populism: Economic have-nots and cultural backlash</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Norris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Inglehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Harvard JFK School of Government Faculty Working Papers Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Norris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Inglehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cultural backlash: Trump, brexit, and authoritarian populism</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Culture three ways: Culture and subcultures within countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Oyserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual review of psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="463" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The past makes the present meaningful: Nostalgia as an existential resource</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Arndt</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">R Core Team.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wildschut</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">R Core Team.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sedikides</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">R Core Team.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">R Core Team.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Juhl</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">R Core Team.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vingerhoets</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">R Core Team.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schlotz</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">R Core Team.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">R Core Team.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.R-project.org/Routledge" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">R Foundation for Statistical Computing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2021. 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">638</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived collective continuity and social well-being: Exploring the connections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-continuity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sedikides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wildschut</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="361" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The sociality of personal and collective nostalgia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sedikides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wildschut</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Review of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moral conviction: Another contributor to attitude strength or something more</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Skitka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Bauman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Sargis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">895</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Longing for the good old days of &apos;our country&apos;: Understanding the triggers, functions and consequences of national nostalgia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smeekes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Longing for the good old days of &apos;our country&apos;: Understanding the triggers, functions and consequences of national nostalgia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smeekes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">History and collective memory from the margins: A global perspective</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Nova Science Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019-10">2019b, October</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="77" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective nostalgia: Triggers and consequences for collective action intentions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smeekes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sedikides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wildschut</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective self-continuity, group identification and in-group defense</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smeekes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Verkuyten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="984" to="994" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceived group continuity, collective self-continuity, and in-group identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smeekes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Verkuyten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Self and Identity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="663" to="680" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Longing for the &quot;good old days&quot; of our country: National nostalgia as a new master-frame of populist radical right parties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smeekes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wildschut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sedikides</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Theoretical Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The essential moral self</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Strohminger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nichols</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective nostalgia: A group-level emotion that confers unique benefits on the group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wildschut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bruder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Van Tilburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sedikides</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">844</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
