<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Authoritarian Courts as an Institution of Control: Political Action and Trial Result</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">啊啯啮啧啹啯啯啮</forename><surname>啂啡啩啫</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">啅啤啤啩啥</forename><surname>啙啡啮啧</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for the Study of Contemporary China</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Authoritarian Courts as an Institution of Control: Political Action and Trial Result</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E66F85528CB3171BFE8238B2DB86C4F7</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>When people take political actions, autocrats could either punish them and remove future threats or appease them by providing compromises. Amidst these varying expectations, we empirically test the effect of political action in the form of petitions on trial results. In China, certain administrative rulings include sentences that indicate that the litigants petitioned before filing suits against the government. Taking advantage of this, we test whether including and excluding such sentences from the ruling changes the predicted trial result. Specifically, we apply text-as-data and machine learning methods to the entire corpus of administrative court rulings in order to overcome the extant methodological challenges of text-based analysis, including unstructured confounders and high-order interactions among covariates. We find that litigants who petitioned about their grievances are more likely to lose in trials. Given that China is developing an AI court, this study has practical significance as its verdicts are likely to be made based on the existing rulings.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Note: An example of an administrative ruling that includes the information that the litigant petitioned before filing the suit. The highlighted sentence reads that the litigant tried petitioning first, but because there was no result, he filed an administrative lawsuit. The underlined sentence is the information about the litigant, including his name, gender, date of birth, ethnicity, and county in which he resides.  <ref type="bibr">4</ref> In the appendix, we conduct another regression analysis, this time with the dependent variable being either ruled (that is, government wins and losses) or not (that is, dismissal, withdrawal, and rejection).  Note: "Nonperformance" captures whether the government was accused of not implementing its duties (1) or committing unlawful administrative actions (0). "Reconsideration" is coded as 1 if the litigant filed administrative reconsideration (Xingzheng Fuyi ) -a non-mandatory pre-stage of an administrative lawsuit -before filing the suit. "Compensation" is whether the litigant requested monetary compensation from the government (1) or not (0). "Represented" is whether the litigant was represented by an attorney (1) or not (0). "Third-party" is whether the case involves a third party, either a corporation, institution, or organization (1) or not (0). </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Y i 唽 α i 唫 τ D i 唫 βX i 唫 ε i 唨唱唩 啷啨啥啲啥 Y i 啩啳 啴啨啥 啢啩啮啡啲啹 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮啮啩啮啧 啯啲 啬啯啳啩啮啧售 D i 啩啳 啡 啢啩啮啡啲啹 啩啮啤啩啣啡啴啯啲 啦啯啲 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮售 X i 啩啳 啡 啶啥啣啴啯啲 啯啦 啣啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啴啨啥 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啥啶啥啬 啯啦 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啩啮 啴啨啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴唬 啴啹啰啥 啯啦 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥唬 啴啲啩啡啬 啬啥啶啥啬唬 啮啯啮唭啰啥啲啦啯啲啭啡啮啣啥唬 啲啥啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啡啴啩啯啮唬 啷啨啥啴啨啥啲 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴 啨啡啳 啬啥啧啡啬 啲啥啰啲啥啳啥啮啴啡啴啩啯啮 啯啲 啮啯啴唬 啡啮啤 啡 啳啥啴 啯啦 唌啸啥啤 啥唋啥啣啴啳售 啔啯 啡啣啣啯啵啮啴 啦啯啲 啰啯啴啥啮啴啩啡啬 啣啯啮啦啯啵啮啤啥啲啳 啴啨啡啴 啡啲啥 啥啭啢啥啤啤啥啤 啩啮 啴啨啥 啴啥啸啴啳 啯啦 啣啡啳啥 啤啥啳啣啲啩啰啴啩啯啮啳 啡啮啤 啴啯 啡啬啬啯啷 啦啯啲 啭啯啲啥 唍啥啸啩啢啬啥 啦啵啮啣啴啩啯啮啡啬 啦啯啲啭啳唬 啷啥 啡啬啳啯 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥 啴啨啥 啦啯啬啬啯啷啩啮啧 啰啡啲啴啩啡啬啬啹 啬啩啮啥啡啲 啭啯啤啥啬唺 Y i 唽 α i 唫 τ D i 唫 g唨Z唩 唫 ε i 唨唲唩 啡啮啤 D i 唽 c i 唫 m唨Z唩 唫 v i 售 啈啥啲啥 Z 啩啳 啡 啳啥啴 啯啦 啣啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 X i 啡啳 啷啥啬啬 啡啳 啡 啮啵啭啥啲啩啣啡啬 啲啥啰啲啥啳啥啮啴啡啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥 啤啥啳啣啲啩啰啴啩啯啮啳售 Z 啡唋啥啣啴啳 啴啨啥 啩啮啤啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥 D 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥 Y 啶啩啡 啴啨啥 唨啰啯啴啥啮啴啩啡啬啬啹 唍啥啸啩啢啬啥唩 啦啵啮啣啴啩啯啮啳 啯啦 m唨•唩 啡啮啤 g唨•唩 啲啥啳啰啥啣啴啩啶啥啬啹售</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>啔啡啢啬啥 唴唺 啓啵啭啭啡啲啹 啓啴啡啴啩啳啴啩啣啳 唨啇啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啗啩啮 啯啲 啌啯啳啳 啓啵啢啳啥啴唩</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>啲啥啧啩啭啥啳 啡啲啥 啯啦啴啥啮 啳啥啥啮 啡啳 啡 啤啯啵啢啬啥唭啥啤啧啥啤 啳啷啯啲啤 啻 啴啨啥啹 啣啡啮 啢啥 啵啳啥啤 啢啹 啡啵啴啯啣啲啡啴啳 啴啯 啰啲啯啳啥啣啵啴啥 啲啥啧啩啭啥 啯啰啰啯啮啥啮啴啳 唨啓啨啥啮唭啂啡啹啨唬 唲唰唱唸唬 唲唰唲唲唩 啯啲 啴啯 啴啩啥 啴啨啥 啡啵啴啯啣啲啡啴啳唧 啨啡啮啤啳 啡啮啤 啨啯啬啤 啰啯啷啥啲 啡啣啣啯啵啮啴啡啢啬啥 唨啎啯啲啴啨 啡啮啤 啗啥啩啮啧啡啳啴唬 唱唹唸唹唻 啈啩啬啬 啡啮啤 啊啯啮啥啳唬 唲唰唱唴唩售 啌啥啶啥啲唭 啡啧啩啮啧 啯啮 啴啨啩啳 啮啡啴啵啲啥唬 啡啵啴啯啣啲啡啴啳 啣啡啮 啥啶啥啮 啤啥啳啩啧啮 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啳啵啣啨 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啥 啯啦 啬啡啷 啩啳 啳啥啬啥啣啴啩啶啥啬啹 啡啰啰啬啩啥啤唬 啢啹 啷啨啩啣啨 啪啵啤啩啣啩啡啬 啦啡啩啲啮啥啳啳 啩啳 啲啥啳啰啥啣啴啥啤 啯啮啬啹 啩啮 啴啨啥 啥啣啯啮啯啭啩啣 啲啥啡啬啭 啢啵啴 啮啯啴 啩啮 啴啨啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啲啥啡啬啭 唨啗啡啮啧唬 唲唰唱唵唩售 啔啨啥 啢啯啵啮啤啡啲啹 啯啦 啪啵啤啩啣啩啡啬 啦啡啩啲啮啥啳啳 啩啮 啡啮 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啣啯啵啲啴 啣啡啮 啢啥 啭啵啲啫啹唬 啨啯啷啥啶啥啲售 商啯啲 啩啮啳啴啡啮啣啥唬 啩啴 啡啰啰啥啡啲啳 啳啥啬啦唭啨啡啲啭啩啮啧 啦啯啲 啡啵啴啯啣啲啡啴啳 啴啯 啡啬啬啯啷 啴啨啥啩啲 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啴啯 啣啨啡啬啬啥啮啧啥 啴啨啥 啳啴啡啴啥 啡啮啤 啷啩啮 啩啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啴啲啩啡啬啳售 啙啥啴唬 啢啹 啬啥啴啴啩啮啧 啴啨啥啭 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啯啮 啡 啲啥啧啵啬啡啲 啢啡啳啩啳唬 啡啵啴啯啣啲啡啴啳 啣啡啮 啲啥啳啯啬啶啥 啴啨啥 啰啲啩啮啣啩啰啡啬唭啡啧啥啮啴 啰啲啯啢啬啥啭 啡啮啤 啣啯啮啴啲啯啬 啰啵啢啬啩啣 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳 唨啇啩啮啳啢啵啲啧唬 唲唰唰唸唩售 啔啨啥啮唬 啨啯啷 啤啯 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啲啥啳啰啯啮啤 啴啯 啳啵啣啨 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啣啩啴啩啺啥啮 啣啯啮唍啩啣啴啳 啳啯 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥啹 啤啯 啮啯啴 啧啲啯啷 啴啯啯 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬唬 啷啨啩啬啥 啳啴啩啬啬 啳啥啲啶啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啲啥啧啩啭啥唧啳 啰啵啲啰啯啳啥 啯啦 啲啥啳啯啬啶啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啰啲啯啢啬啥啭啳唿 啉啮 啴啨啩啳 啰啡啰啥啲唬 啷啥 啡啮啳啷啥啲 啴啨啩啳 啱啵啥啳啴啩啯啮 啩啮 啴啨啥 啣啯啮啴啥啸啴 啯啦 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳唭 啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡售 啐啡啲啴啩啣啵啬啡啲啬啹唬 啷啥 啴啥啳啴 啷啨啥啴啨啥啲 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啢啥啦啯啲啥 啡 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啩啮啣啲啥啡啳啥啳 啴啨啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啳啴啡啫啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥唬 啳啹啳啴啥啭啡啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啣啨啡啮啧啥啳 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴售 啔啨啥 啥啸啩啳啴啩啮啧 啬啩啴啥啲啡啴啵啲啥 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴啳 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啣啯啵啬啤 啥啩啴啨啥啲 啡啰啰啥啡啳啥 啯啲 啰啵啮啩啳啨 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啷啨啯 啴啡啫啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳售 啁啣啣啯啲啤啩啮啧 啴啯 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮 唨唲唰唱唱唩唬 啷啨啥啮 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啢啯啵啴 啴啨啥啩啲 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳唬 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啣啨啡啮啧啥啳 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啩啮 啦啡啶啯啲 啯啦 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啲啳售 啔啨啡啴 啩啳唬 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啷啯啵啬啤 啰啡啣啩啦啹 啴啲啯啵啢啬啥啭啡啫啥啲啳 啢啹 啰啲啯啶啩啤啩啮啧 啣啯啮啣啥啳啳啩啯啮啳 啡啮啤 啳啩啬啥啮啣啥 啴啨啥啭售 問啮 啴啨啥 啣啯啮啴啲啡啲啹唬 啡 啳啩啭啩啬啡啲 啳啴啵啤啹 啢啹 啈啯啵 啡啮啤 啔啲啵啥啸 唨唲唰唲唲唩 唌啮啤啳 啴啨啡啴 啤啲啵啧 啣啲啩啭啥啳 啣啯啭啭啩啴啴啥啤 啢啹 啥啴啨啮啩啣 啭啩啮啯啲啩啴啩啥啳 啻 啷啨啩啣啨 啡啲啥 啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啥啤 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啣啡啳啥啳 啻 啲啥啣啥啩啶啥 啨啥啡啶啩啥啲 啳啥啮啴啥啮啣啥啳 啴啨啡啮 啴啨啯啳啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啈啡啮 啭啡啪啯啲啩啴啹 啩啮 啴啨啥 啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啬 啣啯啵啲啴售 啔啨啡啴 啩啳唬 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啷啯啵啬啤 啰啵啮啩啳啨 啴啨啥 啩啮啤啩啶啩啤啵啡啬啳 啴啨啡啴 啩啮啣啲啥啡啳啥 啴啨啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啳啴啡啫啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥 啡啮啤 啰啲啥啶啥啮啴 啳啩啭啩啬啡啲 啩啮啣啩啤啥啮啴啳 啦啲啯啭 啨啡啰啰啥啮啩啮啧售 啁啭啩啤啳啴 啴啨啥啳啥 啶啡啲啹啩啮啧 啥啸啰啥啣啴啡啴啩啯啮啳唬 啷啥 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬啬啹 啴啥啳啴 啴啨啥 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮唬 啮啡啭啥啬啹 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳唬 啯啮 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啴啨啲啯啵啧啨 啴啨啥 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啯啦 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡售 問啵啲 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啯啦 啭啯啲啥 啴啨啡啮 唲唷唰,唰唰唰 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啰啵啢啬啩啳啨啥啤 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 唲唰唱唴 啡啮啤 唲唰唱唸 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡 啲啥啶啥啡啬啳 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啳啹啳啴啥啭啡啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啤啩啳啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啴啥啳 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啷啨啯 啰啥啴啩唭 唱 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啴啩啯啮啥啤 啢啥啦啯啲啥 啢啲啩啮啧啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啳啵啩啴啳售 啔啨啡啴 啩啳唬 啩啦 啡 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啡啢啯啵啴 啴啨啥啩啲 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳 啢啥啦啯啲啥 唌啬啩啮啧 啡 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴唬 啴啨啥啮 啳啵啣啨 啡 啣啡啳啥 啨啡啳 啡 啬啯啷啥啲 啣啨啡啮啣啥 啯啦 啲啥啣啥啩啶啩啮啧 啡 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮唭啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴 啻 啷啨啩啣啨 啭啥啡啮啳 啡 啨啩啧啨啥啲 啣啨啡啮啣啥 啯啦 啡 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴 啻 啴啨啡啮 啡 啣啡啳啥 啴啨啡啴 啷啡啳 啮啯啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤售 啔啨啩啳 啡啳啳啯啣啩啡啴啩啯啮 啨啯啬啤啳 啡啣啲啯啳啳 啡 啲啡啮啧啥 啯啦 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啣啯啮啤啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啳啴啲啡啴啥啧啩啥啳 啡啮啤 啣啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥 啳啥啴啳唬 啩啮啣啬啵啤啩啮啧 啢啯啴啨 啳啴啲啵啣啴啵啲啥啤 啡啮啤 啵啮啳啴啲啵啣啴啵啲啥啤 啯啮啥啳售 啔啨啥 唌啮啤啩啮啧啳 啣啯啮啴啲啩啢啵啴啥 啴啯 啡啮 啥啭啥啲啧啩啮啧 啬啩啴啥啲啡啴啵啲啥 啯啮 啴啨啥 啲啥啰啲啥啳啳啩啶啥 啮啡啴啵啲啥 啯啦 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啢啹 啤啥啭啯啮啳啴啲啡啴啩啮啧 啴啨啡啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啡啳 啡 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啮啤 啥啸啴啲啡唭啪啵啤啩啣啩啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮 啩啳 啳啹啳啴啥啭啡啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啰啵啮啩啳啨啥啤 啩啮 啡啤唭 啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啴啲啩啢啵啮啡啬啳 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡 唨啓啯啬啯啭啯啮唬 唲唰唰唷唻 啖啡啲啯啬唬 唲唰唱唴唻 啗啡啮啧唬 唲唰唱唵唻 啓啨啥啮唭啂啡啹啨唬 唲唰唱唸唬 唲唰唲唲唩售 啍啥啴啨啯啤啯啬啯啧啩啣啡啬啬啹唬 啷啥 啣啯啭啢啩啮啥 啴啥啸啴唭啡啳唭啤啡啴啡 啡啮啤 啤啯啵啢啬啥 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啴啯 啯啶啥啲唭 啣啯啭啥 啵啮啳啴啲啵啣啴啵啲啥啤 啤啡啴啡 啡啮啤 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啩啯啮 啣啨啡啬啬啥啮啧啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啨啡啶啥 啰啬啡啧啵啥啤 啬啥啧啡啬 啳啴啵啤啩啥啳 啯啮 啢啩啡啳 啩啮 啣啯啵啲啴 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 唨啍啵啳啴啡啲啤唬 唲唰唰唱唻 啕啬啭啥啲 啡啮啤 啊啯啨啮啳啯啮唬 唲唰唰唴唻 啒啥啨啡啶啩 啡啮啤 啓啴啡啲啲唬 唲唰唱唴唩售 啅啳啴啡啢啬啩啳啨唭 啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳 啯啮 啴啲啩啡啬 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥啳 啩啳 啣啨啡啬啬啥啮啧啩啮啧 啦啯啲 啴啷啯 啲啥啡啳啯啮啳售 商啩啲啳啴唬 啩啴 啩啳 啣啨啡啬啬啥啮啧啩啮啧 啢啥啣啡啵啳啥 啴啨啥 啰啯啴啥啮啴啩啡啬 啣啯啮啦啯啵啮啤啥啲啳 唨啥售啧售唬 啴啨啥 啳啴啲啥啮啧啴啨 啯啦 啥啶啩啤啥啮啣啥唩 啴啨啡啴 啡唋啥啣啴 啢啯啴啨 啴啨啥 啬啩啫啥啬啩啨啯啯啤 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥 啡啲啥 啯啦啴啥啮 啥啭啢啥啤啤啥啤 啩啮 啴啨啥 啲啡啷 啴啥啸啴 啡啳 啵啮啳啴啲啵啣啴啵啲啥啤 啤啡啴啡唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啩啳 啤啩唎啣啵啬啴 啴啯 啥啸啴啲啡啣啴售 啓啥啣啯啮啤唬 啣啯啮啦啯啵啮啤啥啲啳 啣啡啮 啥啸啨啩啢啩啴 啣啯啭啰啬啥啸 啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮啳啨啩啰啳 啡啮啤 啩啮啴啥啲啡啣啴啩啯啮啳 啷啩啴啨 啥啡啣啨 啯啴啨啥啲 唨啥售啧售唬 啴啨啥 啩啮啴啥啲啡啣啴啩啯啮 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啴啨啥 啣啯啭啰啥啴啥啮啣啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啬啥啧啡啬 啲啥啰啲啥啳啥啮啴啡啴啩啶啥 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啳啴啲啥啮啧啴啨 啯啦 啥啶啩啤啥啮啣啥唩售 啐啲啥啶啩啯啵啳 啳啴啵啤啩啥啳 啡啤啤啲啥啳啳 啴啨啥 唌啲啳啴 啡啮啤 啳啥啣啯啮啤 啣啯啮啣啥啲啮啳 啢啹 啲啥啳啯啲啴啩啮啧 啴啯 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啴啯 啥啸啴啲啡啣啴 啲啥啬啥啶啡啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥啳 啦啲啯啭 啲啡啷 啴啥啸啴 啯啲 啢啹 啵啳啩啮啧 唍啥啸啩啢啬啥 啭啯啤啥啬啳 啩啮 啴啨啥 啲啥啧啲啥啳啳啩啯啮 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 唨啥售啧售 啈啯啵 啡啮啤 啔啲啵啥啸 唲唰唲唲唩售 啈啯啷啥啶啥啲唬 啳啵啣啨 啡啮 啡啰啰啲啯啡啣啨 啣啡啮 啳啴啩啬啬 啬啥啡啶啥 啯啵啴 啵啳啥啦啵啬 啩啮啦啯啲啭啡啴啩啯啮 啩啮 啴啨啥 啲啡啷 啴啥啸啴 啡啮啤 啭啡啹 啮啯啴 啢啥 啡啢啬啥 啴啯 啦啵啬啬啹 啣啡啰啴啵啲啥 啴啨啥 啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮啳啨啩啰啳 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥啳售 啔啯 啯啶啥啲啣啯啭啥 啴啨啥啳啥 啣啨啡啬啬啥啮啧啥啳唬 啷啥 啣啯啭啢啩啮啥 啴啷啯 啲啥啣啥啮啴 啭啥啴啨啯啤啯啬啯啧啩啣啡啬 啩啮啮啯啶啡啴啩啯啮啳 啡啮啤 啡啰啰啬啹 啴啨啥啭 啩啮 啯啵啲 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬 啳啥啴啴啩啮啧售 啔啯 啡啤啤啲啥啳啳 啴啨啥 啣啨啡啬啬啥啮啧啥 啯啦 啵啮啳啴啲啵啣啴啵啲啥啤 啣啯啮啦啯啵啮啤啥啲啳唬 啷啥 啵啳啥 啴啥啸啴唭啡啳唭啤啡啴啡 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啴啯 啥啮啣啯啤啥 啴啥啸啴 啡啳 啮啵啭啥啲啩啣啡啬 啶啡啬啵啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啣啡啮 啢啥 啵啳啥啤 啩啮 啳啴啡唭 啴啩啳啴啩啣啡啬 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 唨啇啲啩啭啭啥啲 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唲唲唩售 啂啹 啩啮啣啬啵啤啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啮啵啭啥啲啩啣啡啬 啲啥啰啲啥啳啥啮啴啡啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啦啵啬啬 啴啥啸啴啳 啡啳 啣啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥啳唬 啷啥 啭啯啶啥 啣啬啯啳啥啲 啴啯 啡啣啣啯啵啮啴啩啮啧 啦啯啲 啰啯啴啥啮啴啩啡啬 啣啯啮啦啯啵啮啤啥啲啳 啩啮 啴啨啥 啳啴啵啤啹售 啔啯 唲 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啭啯啤啥啬 啴啨啥 啰啯啴啥啮啴啩啡啬啬啹 啨啩啧啨唭啯啲啤啥啲 啩啮啴啥啲啡啣啴啩啯啮啳 啡啭啯啮啧 啣啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥啳唬 啷啥 啵啳啥 啮啯啮啰啡啲啡啭啥啴啲啩啣唬 啭啡唭 啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啴啯 啢啥啴啴啥啲 啡啰啰啲啯啸啩啭啡啴啥 啴啨啥 啣啯啭啰啬啥啸 啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮啳啨啩啰啳售 啁啬啴啨啯啵啧啨 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啨啡啶啥 啰啲啯啶啥啮 啴啯 啢啥 啥唋啥啣啴啩啶啥 啩啮 啰啲啥啤啩啣啴啩啯啮 啣啯啮啴啥啸啴啳唬 啡啮 啡啣啣啵啲啡啴啥 啰啲啥啤啩啣啴啩啯啮 啤啯啥啳 啮啯啴 啧啵啡啲啡啮啴啥啥 啡 啧啯啯啤 啰啥啲啦啯啲啭啡啮啣啥 啯啦 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啩啯啮 啯啲 啩啮啦啥啲啥啮啣啥 啡啢啯啵啴 啳啰啥啣啩唌啣 唨啣啡啵啳啡啬唩 啰啡啲啡啭啥啴啥啲啳售 啔啯 啢啲啩啤啧啥 啴啨啩啳 啧啡啰唬 啷啥 啬啥啶啥啲啡啧啥 啴啨啥 啲啥啣啥啮啴 啤啯啵啢啬啥 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啡啰啰啲啯啡啣啨唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啩啭啰啲啯啶啥啳 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啦啯啲 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啩啮啦啥啲啥啮啣啥 唨啂啥啬啬啯啮啩 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唱唷唻 啃啨啥啲啮啯啺啨啵啫啯啶 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唱唸唩售 Petition and Administrative Lawsuit in China 啁啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啡 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮 啡啮啤 啡 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啹 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡 啯啣啣啵啲啳 啦啯啲 啶啡啲啩啯啵啳 啲啥啡啳啯啮啳售 啉啴 啣啯啵啬啤 啡啲啩啳啥 啦啲啯啭 啡 啳啩啭啰啬啥 啭啩啳啴啡啫啥 啢啹 啡 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啯唎啣啩啡啬 啷啨啩啬啥 啣啲啥啡啴啩啮啧 啡 啭啡啲啲啩啡啧啥 啣啥啲啴啩唌啣啡啴啥唬 啡 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啯啶啥啲 啴啨啥 啡啭啯啵啮啴 啯啦 啰啥啮啡啬啴啹 啩啭啰啯啳啥啤 啯啮 啡 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮 啢啹 啴啨啥 啰啯啬啩啣啥 啦啯啲 啶啩啯啬啡啴啩啮啧 啡 啴啲啡唎啣 啬啡啷唬 啯啲 啡啳 啳啥啲啩啯啵啳 啡啳 啡 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啦啲啯啭 啡 啬啡啮啤 啲啥啱啵啩啳啩啴啩啯啮 啯啲 啤啥啭啯啬啩啴啩啯啮 啢啹 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唬 啯啲 啯啶啥啲 啲啥啣啯啧啮啩啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啡啮 啩啮啤啵啳啴啲啩啡啬 啡啣啣啩啤啥啮啴售 啗啨啥啮 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啡啲啥 啤啩啳啳啡啴啩啳唌啥啤 啷啩啴啨 啳啵啣啨 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 唨啩啮唩啡啣啴啩啯啮啳唬 啴啨啥啹 啨啡啶啥 啯啰啴啩啯啮啳 啴啯 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啴啨啲啯啵啧啨 啴啨啥 啌啥啴啴啥啲啳 啡啮啤 啖啩啳啩啴啳 啳啹啳啴啥啭 唨Xinfang唩 啯啲 啴啯 唌啬啥 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳唬 啡啭啯啮啧 啯啴啨啥啲啳售 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啡啬啬啯啷啳 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啴啯 啢啲啩啮啧 啴啨啥啩啲 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳 啴啯 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴售 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啢啵啲啥啡啵啳 啡啲啥 啲啯啯啴啥啤 啩啮 啡啬啭啯啳啴 啥啶啥啲啹 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啯啲啧啡啮唬 啡啮啤 啴啨啥啹 啲啥啣啥啩啶啥 啡 啷啩啤啥 啲啡啮啧啥 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 啦啲啯啭 啩啮啤啩啶啩啤啵啡啬啳唬 啩啮啣啬啵啤啩啮啧 啢啵啴 啮啯啴 啬啩啭啩啴啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啥 啯啮啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啴啲啩啢啵啮啡啬啳 啡啬啳啯 啣啯啶啥啲唺 啣啯啭啰啬啡啩啮啴啳 啡啢啯啵啴 啰啵啢啬啩啣 啳啥啲啶啩啣啥啳 啡啮啤 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡唋啡啩啲啳 唨啍啩啮啺啮啥啲唬 唲唰唰唶唩售 啕啰啯啮 啲啥啣啥啩啶啩啮啧 啡 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮唬 啴啨啥 啢啵啲啥啡啵 啵啳啵啡啬啬啹 啲啥啦啥啲啳 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥 啴啯 啴啨啥 啮啥啸啴唭啬啥啶啥啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啹 啯啲 啡 啲啥啬啥啶啡啮啴 啤啥啰啡啲啴啭啥啮啴售 啍啯啲啥 啲啥啣啥啮啴啬啹唬 啴啨啥 啢啵啲啥啡啵 啡啬啳啯 啲啥啣啯啭啭啥啮啤啳 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啲啳 啲啥啳啯啬啶啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啴啨啲啯啵啧啨 啴啲啩啡啬啳 啡啮啤 啲啥啦啥啲啳 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥 啴啯 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴售 1 啁啣啣啯啲啤啩啮啧 啴啯 啔啯啮啧 唨唲唰唰唹唩唧啳 啳啵啲啶啥啹唬 啷啨啥啮 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啦啡啣啥啤 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳唬 唱唷 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥啭 啴啲啩啥啤 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧唬 啡啮啤 啴啨啩啳 啩啳 啴啨啥 啳啥啣啯啮啤 啭啯啳啴 啦啲啥啱啵啥啮啴 啲啥啡啣啴啩啯啮 啦啯啬啬啯啷啥啤 啢啹 啩啮啡啣啴啩啯啮 唨唶唳 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩售 啙啥啴唬 啴啨啥 啳啵啣啣啥啳啳 啲啡啴啥 啯啦 啡 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啩啳 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥啤 啴啯 啢啥 啡啳 啬啯啷 啡啳 唰售唲 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 唨啚啨啡啮啧唬 唲唰唰唹唩售 1 One of the authors' interviews with a former employee at a Letters and Visits office and a local legal expert.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>啩啳 啣啯啤啥啤 啡啳 唱售 啅啸啡啭啰啬啥啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啫啥啹啷啯啲啤啳 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥唺 啜啴啨啲啯啵啧啨 啡 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 唨经过 信访啯啲 通过信访唩唬唢 啜啮啯 啲啥啳啵啬啴 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 唨信访无果唩唬唢 啡啮啤 啜啡 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啣啡啳啥 唨信访事 项啯啲 信访案件唩售唢 啉啮 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴唬 唱唵售唴 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啳啵啣啨 啳啥啮啴啥啮啣啥啳售 5 Control Variables 啔啨啥 啦啯啬啬啯啷啩啮啧 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啮啴啲啯啬啬啥啤 啦啯啲唬 啡啳 啴啨啥啹 啡啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啡唋啥啣啴 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴唺 商啩啲啳啴唬 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啬啥啶啥啬唬 啥啩啴啨啥啲 啡啴 啴啨啥 唌啲啳啴 啬啥啶啥啬 啯啲 啡啴 啴啨啥 啳啥啣啯啮啤 啬啥啶啥啬售 啓啥啣啯啮啤唬 啜啎啯啮啰啥啲啦啯啲啭啡啮啣啥唬唢 啷啨啩啣啨 啣啡啰啴啵啲啥啳 啷啨啥啴啨啥啲 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啡啳 啳啵啥啤 啦啯啲 啮啯啴 啩啭啰啬啥啭啥啮啴啩啮啧 啩啴啳 啤啵啴啩啥啳 唨唱唩 啯啲 啣啯啭啭啩啴啴啩啮啧 啵啮啬啡啷啦啵啬 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳 唨唰唩售 啔啨啩啲啤唬 啜啒啥啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啡啴啩啯啮唢 啩啳 啣啯啤啥啤 啡啳 唱 啩啦 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴 唌啬啥啤 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啲啥啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啡啴啩啯啮 唨Xingzheng Fuyi唩 啻 啡 啰啲啥唭啳啴啡啧啥 啯啦 啡啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴 啻 啢啥啦啯啲啥 唌啬啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啳啵啩啴售 商啯啵啲啴啨唬 啜啇啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啬啥啶啥啬唬唢 啷啨啩啣啨 啣啯啮啳啩啳啴啳 啯啦 啦啯啵啲 啬啥啶啥啬啳唬 啦啲啯啭 啣啯啵啮啴啹唭唬 啰啲啥啦啥啣啴啵啲啥唭唬 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啩啡啬唭唬 啡啮啤 啮啡啴啩啯啮啡啬 啬啥啶啥啬啳售 啎啥啸啴唬 啜啄啩啳啰啵啴啥 啔啹啰啥唢 啣啬啡啳啳啩唌啥啳 啴啨啥 啴啯啰啩啣啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啵啮啤啥啲啬啹啩啮啧 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啩啮啴啯 唲唲 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啣啡啴啥啧啯啲啩啥啳售 商啩啮啡啬啬啹唬 啹啥啡啲唭 啡啮啤 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啥唭唌啸啥啤 啥唋啥啣啴啳售 Research Design 啗啥 啡啴啴啥啭啰啴 啴啯 啭啥啡啳啵啲啥 啴啨啥 啡啳啳啯啣啩啡啴啩啯啮 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥 啴啨啲啯啵啧啨 啡 啣啯啮啤啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啡啰啰啲啯啡啣啨唬 啩啮 啬啩啮啥 啷啩啴啨 啢啯啴啨 啴啨啥 啦啯啵啮啤啡啴啩啯啮啡啬 啡啮啤 啲啥啣啥啮啴 啳啴啵啤啩啥啳 啩啮 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啥啲啡啴啵啲啥 啯啮 啢啩啡啳 啩啮 啣啯啵啲啴 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 唨啕啬啭啥啲 啡啮啤 啊啯啨啮啳啯啮唬 唲唰唰唴唻 啒啥啨啡啶啩 啡啮啤 啓啴啡啲啲唬 唲唰唱唴唻 啈啯啵 啡啮啤 啔啲啵啥啸唬 唲唰唲唲唩售 啗啥 啡啴啴啥啭啰啴 啴啯 唱唩 唌啲啳啴 啩啤啥啮啴啩啦啹 啷啨啥啴啨啥啲 啴啨啥啲啥 啩啳 啩啮啤啥啥啤 啡啮 啡啳啳啯啣啩啡啴啩啯啮 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啴啲啩啡啬 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥 啡啮啤 唲唩 啴啥啳啴 啷啨啥啴啨啥啲 啴啨啡啴 啡啳啳啯啣啩啡啴啩啯啮 啳啴啩啬啬 啥啸啩啳啴啳 啡啦啴啥啲 啡啣啣啯啵啮啴啩啮啧 啦啯啲 啡 啲啩啣啨 啳啥啴 啯啦 啣啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啳啨啯啵啬啤 啡唋啥啣啴 啢啯啴啨 啴啨啥 啬啩啫啥啬啩啨啯啯啤 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啡啮啤 啴啲啩啡啬 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥售 啁啮啹 啜啵啮啥啸啰啬啡啩啮啥啤 啶啡啲啩啡啴啩啯啮唢 啩啳 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴啩啶啥 啯啦 啡啮 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啯啮 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥唬 啴啨啯啵啧啨 啩啴 啩啳 啰啯啳啳啩啢啬啥 啴啨啡啴 啳啯啭啥 啵啮啯啢啳啥啲啶啥啤 啣啯啮啦啯啵啮啤啥啲啳 啯啲 啳啡啭啰啬啥 啳啥啬啥啣啴啩啯啮 啩啳啳啵啥啳 啣啯啵啬啤 啥啸啰啬啡啩啮 啡啮啹 啤啩啳啣啲啥啰啡啮啣啹 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啩啮啶啯啬啶啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳 啡啮啤 啴啨啯啳啥 啴啨啡啴 啤啯 啮啯啴售 商啯啬啬啯啷啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啥啸啩啳啴啩啮啧 啬啩啴啥啲啡啴啵啲啥唬 啷啥 唌啲啳啴 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥 啴啨啥 啦啯啬啬啯啷啩啮啧 啬啩啮啥啡啲 啭啯啤啥啬唺</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,95.40,360.68,421.21,194.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="23,118.80,99.60,374.40,359.33" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="28,95.40,99.59,421.19,315.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="29,118.80,99.60,374.40,228.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="31,118.80,99.60,374.42,230.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>唳</head><label></label><figDesc>啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啹 唌啬啩啮啧 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳唬 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啣啡啮 啢啲啩啮啧 啴啨啥啩啲 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳 啴啯 啴啨啥 啴啨啩啲啤 啰啡啲啴啹唬 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴售 啉啮 唱唹唸唹唬 啴啨啥 啁啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啌啩啴啩啧啡啴啩啯啮 啌啡啷 啷啡啳 啰啲啯啭啵啬啧啡啴啥啤唬 啡啮啤 啩啴 啥啭啰啯啷啥啲啥啤 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啴啯 啳啵啥 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啦啯啲 啴啨啥 啬啡啴啴啥啲唧啳 啩啮啦啲啩啮啧啥啭啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啦啯啲啭啥啲唧啳 啬啡啷啦啵啬 啲啩啧啨啴啳 唨啁啲啴啩啣啬啥 唲唩售 2 啓啩啮啣啥 啴啨啥啮唬 啴啨啥 啮啵啭啢啥啲 啯啦 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啨啡啳 啢啥啥啮 啩啮啣啲啥啡啳啩啮啧唬 啡啬啴啨啯啵啧啨 啩啴 啩啳 啳啴啩啬啬 啳啭啡啬啬 唨唳唰唰 啴啨啯啵啳啡啮啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啩啮 唲唰唲唱唩 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啡啴 啯啦 啣啩啶啩啬 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴 啣啡啳啥啳 唨唱唶售唶 啭啩啬啬啩啯啮 啩啮 唲唰唲唱唩售 啉啮啤啥啥啤唬 啳啵啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啵啮啤啥啲 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮啩啳啭 啤啯啥啳 啮啯啴 啡啰啰啥啡啲 啴啯 啢啥 啥啡啳啹售 啁啬啭啯啳啴 啨啡啬啦 啯啦 啴啨啥 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啵啮啤啥啲啳啴啡啮啤 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啴啥啮啤啳 啴啯 啴啲啥啡啴 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啦啡啶啯啲啡啢啬啹 啩啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啴啲啩啡啬啳 唨啌啩啮唬 唲唰唱唴唩售 啌啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啡啲啥 啡啬啳啯 啡啷啡啲啥 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥啹 啣啯啵啬啤 啦啡啣啥 啲啥啴啡啬啩啡啴啩啯啮唬 啩啮啣啬啵啤啩啮啧 啴啨啲啥啡啴啳 啯啦 啰啨啹啳啩啣啡啬 啶啩啯啬啥啮啣啥唬 啦啲啯啭 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啯啲啳 啷啨啯 啷啡啮啴 啴啨啥啭 啴啯 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥啩啲 啣啡啳啥啳 唨問唧啂啲啩啥啮 啡啮啤 啌啥啥唬 唲唰唰唵唩售 啁啳 啳啵啣啨唬 啥啶啥啮 啴啨啯啵啧啨 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啩啳 啮啯啭啩啮啡啬啬啹 啡 啴啨啩啲啤唭啰啡啲啴啹 啩啮啳啴啩啴啵啴啩啯啮唬 啩啴 啩啳 啮啯啴 啦啲啥啥 啯啦 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啩啮唍啵啥啮啣啥唬 啥啳啰啥啣啩啡啬啬啹 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥 啬啯啣啡啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴售 啔啨啥 啦啯啣啵啳 啯啦 啴啨啩啳 啡啲啴啩啣啬啥 啩啳 啯啮 啴啨啥 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啰啥唭 啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啢啥啦啯啲啥 啴啨啥 啳啵啩啴啳售 啔啨啩啳 啩啳 啢啥啣啡啵啳啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啣啡啮 啢啥 啰啥啲啣啥啩啶啥啤 啡啳 啴啲啯啵啢啬啥唭 啭啡啫啥啲啳唬 啴啥啣啨啮啩啣啡啬啬啹 啢啹 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴唬 啢啵啴 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啩啮 啦啡啣啴 啢啹 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啤啵啥 啴啯 啴啨啥 啬啡啣啫 啯啦 啪啵啤啩啣啩啡啬 啩啮啤啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啣啥 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡售 啌啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啷啨啯 啡啬啳啯 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啯啦啴啥啮 啳啴啲啡啴啥啧啩啣啡啬啬啹 啤啯 啳啯 啴啯 啰啵啴 啰啲啥啳啳啵啲啥 啯啮 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啮啤 啡啣啨啩啥啶啥 啴啨啥啩啲 啧啯啡啬啳唬 啳啵啣啨 啡啳 啰啲啯啭啰啴 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啲啥啳啯啬啵啴啩啯啮 啯啲 啢啥啴啴啥啲 啣啯啭啰啥啮啳啡啴啩啯啮售 啗啨啩啬啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啩啳 啡啮 啯唎啣啩啡啬 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥唭啲啥啳啯啬啵啴啩啯啮 啭啥啴啨啯啤唬 啬啯啣啡啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啮啣啥啲啮啥啤 啴啨啡啴 啩啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啲啳 啡啰啰啥啡啬 啴啯 啵啰啰啥啲唭啬啥啶啥啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳唬 啴啨啩啳 啷啯啵啬啤 啲啥啳啵啬啴 啩啮 啡啮 啡啤啶啥啲啳啥 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啮 啴啨啥啩啲 啰啥啲啦啯啲啭啡啮啣啥 啥啶啡啬啵啡啴啩啯啮 啯啮 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮唭 啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 唨啌啩 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唱唲唻 啂啥啮啮啥啹唬 唲唰唱唶唩售 啔啡啫啩啮啧 啡啤啶啡啮啴啡啧啥 啯啦 啴啨啩啳 啣啯啮啣啥啲啮唬 啳啯啭啥 啰啥啯啰啬啥 啜啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啩啺啥唢 啴啨啥啩啲 啣啡啳啥啳 啢啹 唌啬啩啮啧 啢啯啴啨 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳 啡啮啤 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 唨商啥啮啧 啡啮啤 啈啥唬 唲唰唱唸唻 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮唬 唲唰唱唱唩售 啁啳 啳啵啣啨唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啩啳 啯啦啴啥啮 啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啥啤 啡 啴啨啲啥啡啴 啴啯 啳啯啣啩啡啬 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啻 啭啡啫啩啮啧 啰啲啯啢啬啥啭啳 啢啩啧啧啥啲 啲啡啴啨啥啲 啴啨啡啮 啥啸啴啩啮啧啵啩啳啨啩啮啧 啴啨啥啭 啻唬 啡啮啤 啳啯啭啥 啥啸啴啲啥啭啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啲啳 啡啲啥 啯啦啴啥啮 啣啨啡啲啧啥啤 啷啩啴啨 啣啲啩啭啥啳 啡啮啤 啰啲啯啳啥啣啵啴啥啤 唨啚啥啮啧 啡啮啤 商啥啮啧唬 唲唰唲唲唩售 啅啶啥啮 啩啦 啣啥啲啴啡啩啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啲啳 啤啯 啮啯啴 啡啣啴 啳啴啲啡啴啥啧啩啣啡啬啬啹 啡啮啤 啴啨啵啳 啤啯 啮啯啴 啩啮啴啥啮啤 啴啯 啩啮啣啲啥啡啳啥 啴啨啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啳啴啡啫啥 啯啦 啴啨啥啩啲 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啴啨啥啳啥 啰啥啯啰啬啥</figDesc><table><row><cell>啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧</cell></row><row><cell>啡啲啥 啴啲啹啩啮啧 啭啵啬啴啩啰啬啥 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啴啯 啲啥啳啯啬啶啥 啴啨啥啩啲 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴售 啓啵啣啨 啰啥啲啳啩啳啴啥啮啴</cell></row><row><cell>啥唋啯啲啴啳 啩啮 啣啯啮啦啲啯啮啴啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啳啴啩啬啬 啭啡啫啥 啴啨啥啳啥 啩啮啤啩啶啩啤啵啡啬啳 啳啴啡啮啤 啯啵啴售</cell></row><row><cell>Competing Predictions: Political Action and Trial Result</cell></row><row><cell>啁啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啭啡啹 啦啯啬啬啯啷 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啳 啯啶啥啲 啪啵啳啴啩啣啥 啷啨啥啮 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啢啥啣啯啭啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬售 啔啨啥啲啥唭</cell></row><row><cell>啦啯啲啥唬 啩啴 啩啳 啰啬啡啵啳啩啢啬啥 啴啨啡啴 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳 啳啵啣啨 啡啳 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳 啩啮唍啵啥啮啣啥 啴啨啥 啪啵啤啧啥唧啳 啤啥啣啩啳啩啯啮啳售</cell></row><row><cell>啉啮啤啥啥啤唬 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡唬 啣啥啲啴啡啩啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啳啥啮啴啥啮啣啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啳啡啹唬 啜啔啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴</cell></row><row><cell>啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啢啥啦啯啲啥 唌啬啩啮啧 啴啨啩啳 啳啵啩啴 唨商啩啧啵啲啥 唱唩售唢 啃啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啩啮啧 啴啨啡啴 唌啬啩啮啧 啡 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啩啳 啮啯啴 啡 啰啲啯唭</cell></row><row><cell>啣啥啤啵啲啡啬 啲啥啱啵啩啲啥啭啥啮啴 啯啦 啡 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴唬 啩啴 啩啳 啮啯啴啥啷啯啲啴啨啹 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啩啮啴啥啮啴啩啯啮啡啬啬啹 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啳啵啣啨</cell></row><row><cell>啩啮啦啯啲啭啡啴啩啯啮 啯啮 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮售 啔啨啩啳 啩啮啴啥啲啥啳啴啩啮啧 啦啡啣啴 啩啭啰啬啩啥啳 啡啮 啩啭啰啯啲啴啡啮啴 啰啯啳啳啩啢啩啬啩啴啹 啴啨啡啴 啪啵啤啧啥啳</cell></row><row><cell>啤啯 啴啡啫啥 啴啨啥 啡啣啴 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啳啥啲啩啯啵啳啬啹 啷啨啥啮 啴啨啥啹 啭啡啫啥 啤啥啣啩啳啩啯啮啳售</cell></row><row><cell>商啩啧啵啲啥 唱唺 啅啸啡啭啰啬啥 啯啦 啡啮 啁啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啒啵啬啩啮啧</cell></row><row><cell>2 See, for example, Peerenboom (2002) and deLisle (2017) for the legal reforms in China.</cell></row><row><cell>唴</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳唧 啲啥啱啵啥啳啴啳 啡啮啤 啤啩啳啭啩啳啳 啴啨啥 啲啥啳啴 啯啦 啴啨啥啩啲 啲啥啱啵啥啳啴啳售 啓啵啣啨 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啬啡啢啥啬啥啤 啡啳 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啬啯啳啳啥啳 啩啮 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴唬 啡啳 啩啴 啩啳 啲啡啲啥 啡啮啤 啤啩唎啣啵啬啴 啦啯啲 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啴啯 啡啣啨啩啥啶啥 啯啮啥 啳啭啡啬啬 啶啩啣啴啯啲啹 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥啩啲 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啯啲啳 啩啮 啡 啴啲啩啡啬售 啉啮 啦啡啣啴唬 啴啨啥啲啥 啣啡啮 啢啥 唌啶啥 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啦啲啯啭 啡啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啣啡啳啥唺 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮唬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啬啯啳啳唬 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷啡啬唬 啤啩啳啭啩啳啳啡啬唬 啡啮啤 啲啥啪啥啣啴啩啯啮售 啈啯啷啥啶啥啲唬 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啡啲啥 啲啵啬啥啤 啢啹 啪啵啤啧啥啳 唨啥啩啴啨啥啲 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮啳 啯啲 啬啯啳啳啥啳唩 啣啡啮 啢啥 啳啹啳啴啥啭啡啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥 啯啴啨啥啲啳售 商啯啲 啥啸啡啭啰啬啥唬 啯啮啬啹 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啭啥啥啴 啴啨啥 啭啩啮啩啭啵啭 啰啲啯啣啥啤啵啲啡啬 啲啥啱啵啩啲啥啭啥啮啴 啣啡啮 啢啥 啲啥啶啩啥啷啥啤 啢啹 啴啨啥 啪啵啤啧啥售 商啵啲啴啨啥啲啭啯啲啥唬 啯啵啲 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴 啩啳 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啵啮啤啥啲啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷啮 啣啡啳啥啳 啻 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啴啷啯 啰啡啲啴啩啥啳 啯啦啴啥啮 啲啥啡啣啨 啩啮啦啯啲啭啡啬 啳啥啴啴啬啥啭啥啮啴啳 啻 啡啮啤 啮啯啴 啡啣啣啥啰啴啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳售 啔啨啥啲啥啦啯啲啥唬 啴啨啥 啭啡啩啮 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啯啮啬啹 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啳 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮啳 啡啮啤 啬啯啳啳啥啳售 4</figDesc><table><row><cell>啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧</cell></row><row><cell>啴啨啡啴 啩啮啣啲啥啡啳啥啳 啴啨啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啳啴啡啫啥啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥售 啉啮 啴啨啥 啦啡啣啥 啯啦 啩啮啣啲啥啡啳啥啤 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啳啴啡啫啥啳唬 啳啥啣啯啮啤唭啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬啳 啡啲啥 啴啨啥 唌啮啡啬 啳啴啥啰 啩啮 啴啨啥 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啳啹啳啴啥啭售 啁啦啴啥啲 啤啲啯啰啰啩啮啧 啤啵啰啬啩啣啡啴啥啳唬</cell></row><row><cell>啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啭啡啹 啴啡啫啥 啴啷啯 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啭啥啡啳啵啲啥啳售 商啩啲啳啴唬 啴啨啥啹 啣啡啮 啣啨啯啯啳啥 啴啯 啰啡啣啩啦啹 啴啨啥 啷啥 啡啲啥 啬啥啦啴 啷啩啴啨 啡 啴啯啴啡啬 啯啦 唲唷唱唬唱唷唷 啣啡啳啥啳售</cell></row><row><cell>啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啡啮啤 啲啥啳啯啬啶啥 啴啨啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啳啭啯啯啴啨啬啹售 啉啮 啴啨啩啳 啣啡啳啥唬 啷啥 啳啨啯啵啬啤 啥啸啰啥啣啴 啴啨啡啴 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啷啨啯</cell></row><row><cell>啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啲啥啣啥啩啶啥 啭啯啲啥 啦啡啶啯啲啡啢啬啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啴啨啡啮 啴啨啯啳啥 啷啨啯 啤啯 啮啯啴唬 啡啳 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮 唨唲唰唱唱唩 啡啮啤 Dependent Variable: Trial Result</cell></row><row><cell>商啥啮啧 啡啮啤 啈啥 唨唲唰唱唸唩 唌啮啤售 啓啥啣啯啮啤唬 啨啯啷啥啶啥啲唬 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啣啡啮 啣啨啯啯啳啥 啴啯 啰啵啮啩啳啨 啴啨啯啳啥 啔啨啥 啤啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥 啩啳 啡 啢啩啮啡啲啹 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥 啷啨啥啲啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啤啥啤 啡啳 唱 啡啮啤</cell></row><row><cell>啷啨啯 啩啮啳啴啩啧啡啴啥 啳啵啣啨 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮售 啔啨啥啮唬 啷啥 啳啨啯啵啬啤 啥啸啰啥啣啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啴啯 啲啥啣啥啩啶啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啬啯啳啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啤啥啤 啡啳 唰售 啃啡啳啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬 唨啯啲 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳</cell></row><row><cell>啵啮啦啡啶啯啲啡啢啬啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啷啨啯 啤啩啤 啮啯啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮唬 啳啩啭啩啬啡啲 啴啯 啷啨啡啴 啈啯啵 啡啮啤 啬啯啳啥唩 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啴啨啡啴 唨唱唩 啵啰啨啯啬啤 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳唬 唨唲唩 啲啥啣啯啧啮啩啺啥 啴啨啡啴 啡啤啭啩啮唭</cell></row><row><cell>啔啲啵啥啸 唨唲唰唲唲唩 唌啮啤啳售 啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳 啩啮 啱啵啥啳啴啩啯啮 啷啥啲啥 啬啥啧啡啬 啯啲 啥唋啥啣啴啩啶啥唬 啡啮啤/啯啲 唨唳唩 啤啩啳啭啩啳啳 啴啨啥 啮啯啮唭啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴</cell></row><row><cell>Data: Administrative Rulings of China, 2014-2018 啳啩啤啥唧啳 啲啥啱啵啥啳啴啳 唨Bohui Susong Qingqiu唩售 啃啡啳啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳 啬啯啳啥 唨啯啲 啣啩啴啩唭</cell></row><row><cell>啺啥啮啳 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬唩 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啴啨啡啴 唨唱唩 啲啥啶啯啫啥 啯啲 唨唲唩 啭啯啤啩啦啹 啴啨啥 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳 啩啮</cell></row><row><cell>啔啨啩啳 啡啲啴啩啣啬啥 啴啥啳啴啳 啴啨啥 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳 啯啮 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啵啳啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴 啴啨啡啴 啣啯啮啴啡啩啮啳 啡啬啬 啡啤唭 啱啵啥啳啴啩啯啮唬 唨唳唩 啣啯啭啰啥啬 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳 啴啯 啣啡啲啲啹 啯啵啴 啴啨啥啩啲 啬啥啧啡啬 啤啵啴啩啥啳唬 啯啲 唨唴唩 啲啥啣啯啧啮啩啺啥</cell></row><row><cell>啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啴啨啡啴 啷啥啲啥 啰啵啢啬啩啳啨啥啤 啩啮 啴啨啥 啣啥啮啴啲啡啬啩啺啥啤 啤啩啧啩啴啡啬 啡啲啣啨啩啶啥唬 China Judgement 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳 啷啥啲啥 啩啬啬啥啧啡啬 啯啲 啩啮啶啡啬啩啤售 啓啯啭啥啴啩啭啥啳唬 啪啵啤啧啥啳 啡啣啣啥啰啴 啰啡啲啴唨啳唩</cell></row><row><cell>Online 唨啃啊問唩唬 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 唲唰唱唴 啡啮啤 唲唰唱唸售 3 啉啮 唲唰唱唴唬 啩啴 啢啥啣啡啭啥 啡 啬啥啧啡啬 啯啢啬啩啧啡啴啩啯啮 啦啯啲 啥啶啥啲啹 啣啯啵啲啴</cell></row><row><cell>啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡 啴啯 啰啵啢啬啩啳啨 啷啲啩啴啴啥啮 啪啵啤啧啭啥啮啴啳 啩啮 啴啨啩啳 啡啲啣啨啩啶啥唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啩啳 啯啰啥啲啡啴啥啤 啢啹 啴啨啥 啓啵啰啲啥啭啥</cell></row><row><cell>啐啥啯啰啬啥唧啳 啃啯啵啲啴 啯啦 啃啨啩啮啡售 啁啬啴啨啯啵啧啨 啮啯啴 啦啲啥啥 啯啦 啭啩啳啳啩啮啧 啤啡啴啡 啩啳啳啵啥啳唬 啴啨啩啳 啡啲啣啨啩啶啥 啰啲啯啶啩啤啥啳 啴啨啥</cell></row><row><cell>啭啯啳啴 啣啯啭啰啬啥啴啥 啣啯啬啬啥啣啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啣啯啵啲啴 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啭啯啮啧 啡啬啬 啴啨啥 啥啸啴啡啮啴 啳啯啵啲啣啥啳售 啗啥 啤啩啳啣啵啳啳 啴啨啥 啭啩啳啳啩啮啧</cell></row><row><cell>啤啡啴啡 啰啲啯啢啬啥啭 啬啡啴啥啲售</cell></row><row><cell>Measurement</cell></row><row><cell>Unit of Analysis: An Administrative Case</cell></row><row><cell>啔啨啥 啵啮啩啴 啯啦 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啩啳 啡 啣啡啳啥售 啁啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啣啡啳啥 啣啯啮啳啩啳啴啳 啯啦 啡 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啴啨啥</cell></row><row><cell>啮啯啮唭啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啳啩啤啥 唨啰啬啡啩啮啴啩唋 啩啮 啡 唌啲啳啴唭啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬唩 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啳啩啤啥 唨啤啥啦啥啮啤啡啮啴 啩啮</cell></row><row><cell>啡 唌啲啳啴唭啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬唩唬 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啩啮 啣啨啡啲啧啥唬 啴啨啥 啬啥啶啥啬 啯啦 啴啲啩啡啬唬 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴售 啁啭啯啮啧 啴啨啥</cell></row><row><cell>啡啶啡啩啬啡啢啬啥 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啷啥 啵啳啥 啴啨啥 啳啵啢啳啥啴 啯啦 啤啡啴啡 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啡啲啥 啯啲啤啩啮啡啲啹 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳唬 啷啨啯 啡啲啥 Independent Variable: Petition</cell></row><row><cell>啮啯啴 啣啯啲啰啯啲啡啴啩啯啮啳 啯啲 啰啲啯啳啥啣啵啴啯啲啳售 啃啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啣啯啮啳啴啩啴啵啴啥 啴啨啥 啮啯啮唭啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啳啩啤啥 啩啮 啭啯啲啥 啴啨啡啮 啔啨啥 啩啮啤啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥 啩啳 啷啨啥啴啨啥啲 啡 啣啡啳啥 啷啡啳 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啢啥啦啯啲啥 啢啥啩啮啧 啢啲啯啵啧啨啴 啩啮啴啯 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴</cell></row><row><cell>啔啡啫啩啮啧 啡啤啶啡啮啴啡啧啥 啯啦 啴啨啩啳 啦啡啣啴唬 啷啥 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬啬啹 啴啥啳啴 啩啦 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啷啨啯 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤</cell></row><row><cell>唸唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳售 啁啤啤啩啴啩啯啮啡啬啬啹唬 啷啥 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啢啯啴啨 啴啨啥 唌啲啳啴唭 啡啮啤 啳啥啣啯啮啤唭啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬啳唬 啡啳</cell></row><row><cell>啡啢啯啵啴 啴啨啥啩啲 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳 prior to 唌啬啩啮啧 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啲啥啣啥啩啶啥啤 啳啹啳啴啥啭啡啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴</cell></row><row><cell>啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啯啳啥 啷啨啯 啤啩啤 啮啯啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮售 啈啥啲啥唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啩啳 啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啥啤 啡啮 啡啣啴啩啯啮 3 中国裁判文书网, China Judgements Online, wenshu.court.gov.cn</cell></row><row><cell>唵 唶</cell></row></table><note><p>啯啲 啮啯啴售 啉啦 啡 啲啵啬啩啮啧 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥啳 啴啨啥 啳啥啮啴啥啮啣啥 啴啨啡啴 啩啮啤啩啣啡啴啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴 啴啲啩啥啤 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧唬</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>啓啥啣啯啮啤唬 啷啥 啷啥啲啥 啮啯啴 啡啢啬啥 啴啯 啶啥啲啩啦啹 啷啨啥啴啨啥啲 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啡啬啷啡啹啳 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥啤 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啨啩啳啴啯啲啹 啷啨啥啮 啩啴 啨啡啰啰啥啮啥啤售 啔啨啡啴 啩啳唬 啴啨啥啲啥 啩啳 啡 啰啯啳啳啩啢啩啬啩啴啹 啴啨啡啴 啩啮 啣啥啲啴啡啩啮 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啥啶啥啮 啩啦 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啴啲啩啥啤 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啢啥啦啯啲啥 唌啬啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啳啵啩啴啳唬 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啤啩啤 啮啯啴 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啴啨啡啴 啩啮啦啯啲啭啡啴啩啯啮售 啉啦 啳啵啣啨 啵啮啯啢啳啥啲啶啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啴啯 啡啬啴啥啲 啯啵啲 唌啮啤啩啮啧啳唬 啴啨啥啮 啷啩啴啨啩啮 啴啨啯啳啥 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啳啨啯啵啬啤 啨啡啶啥 啺啥啲啯 啯啲 啮啥啧啡啴啩啶啥 啣啯啲啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴售 啔啯 啢啥 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥啤唺 啃啡啬啣啵啬啡啴啩啯啮啳 啯啮 啳啵啣啨 啰啯啳啳啩啢啩啬啩啴啹售 啔啨啩啲啤唬 啩啦 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啜啷啥啡啫唢 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥 啳啴啡啲啴唬 啴啨啥啮 啴啨啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮唭啬啯啳啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啩啮 啴啨啥啳啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啢啡啳啥啤 啯啮 啪啵啳啴啩啣啥唬 啲啡啴啨啥啲 啴啨啡啮 啯啮 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啳售 啎啥啶啥啲啴啨啥啬啥啳啳唬 啴啯 啯啵啲 啢啥啳啴 啫啮啯啷啬啥啤啧啥唬 啴啨啥啲啥 啩啳 啬啩啭啩啴啥啤 啥啶啩啤啥啮啣啥 啴啨啡啴 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴啳 啳啵啣啨 啡 啰啯啳啳啩啢啩啬啩啴啹售 啃啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啩啮啧 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啳啵啣啣啥啳啳 啲啡啴啥 啯啦 啯啦 啨啡啮啤啬啩啮啧 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啣啡啳啥啳 啳啯 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啲啥啧啩啭啥 啭啡啩啮啴啡啩啮啳 啩啴啳 啬啥啧啩啴啩啭啡啣啹 唨啍啯啵啳啴啡啦啡唬 唲唰唰唷唩售 問啵啲 唌啮啤啩啮啧 啩啳 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啦啲啯啭 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮 唨唲唰唱唱唩唬 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啡啵啴啨啯啲 唌啮啤啳 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啷啯啵啬啤 啰啡啣啩啦啹 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啲啳 啢啹 啣啨啡啮啧啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啩啮 啴啨啥啩啲 啦啡啶啯啲售 啔啨啥啲啥 啡啲啥 啡 啦啥啷 啰啯啳啳啩啢啬啥 啲啥啡啳啯啮啳 啦啯啲 啳啵啣啨 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啣啥唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啡啬啳啯 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴 啴啨啥 啳啣啯啰啥 啣啯啮啤啩啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啯啵啲 唌啮啤啩啮啧啳唺 商啩啲啳啴唬 啗啨啩啬啥 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮唧啳 啩啮啴啥啲啶啩啥啷啳 啷啥啲啥 啣啯啮啤啵啣啴啥啤 啩啮 唲唰唰唶唭唷唬 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啷啥 啵啳啥啤 啦啯啲 啯啵啲 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啷啥啲啥 啰啵啢啬啩啳啨啥啤 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 唲唰唱唴 啡啮啤 唲唰唱唸售 啂啥啣啡啵啳啥 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮唧啳 啲啥啳啥啡啲啣啨 啷啡啳 啣啯啮啤啵啣啴啥啤 啤啵啲啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啈啵 啊啩啮啴啡啯 啡啮啤 啗啥啮 啊啩啡啢啡啯 啥啲啡 啡啮啤 啯啵啲 啲啥啳啥啡啲啣啨 啰啥啲啩啯啤 啣啯啶啥啲啳 啴啨啥 啘啩 啊啩啮啰啩啮啧 啥啲啡唬 啴啨啥 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啣啥 啩啮 啴啨啥 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啭啡啹 啩啮 啰啡啲啴 啥啸啰啬啡啩啮 啴啨啥 啬啥啡啤啥啲啳啨啩啰唧啳 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啡啰啰啲啯啡啣啨啥啳 啴啯 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳唧 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮啳售 啓啥啣啯啮啤唬 啴啨啥 啤啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥 啯啦 啯啵啲 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啩啳 啥啩啴啨啥啲 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮 啯啲 啬啯啳啳售 啈啯啷啥啶啥啲唬 啩啴 啩啳 啰啬啡啵啳啩啢啬啥 啴啨啡啴 啣啯啮啣啥啳啳啩啯啮啳 啡啲啥 啡啣啴啵啡啬啬啹 啨啡啰啰啥啮啩啮啧 啩啮啦啯啲啭啡啬啬啹唬 啢啥啨啩啮啤 啴啨啥 啳啣啥啮啥啳售 啉啮 啴啨啡啴 啣啡啳啥唬 啷啩啴啨啩啮 啴啨啥 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷啮 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啷啥 啣啡啮啮啯啴 啰啲啯啰啯啲啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啢啥啣啯啭啥啳 啬啡啲啧啥啲唺 唱唲售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啩啮 唲唰唱唴唬 唱唵售唹 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啩啮 唲唰唱唵唬 唱唹售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啩啮 唲唰唱唶唬 唱唵售唷 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啩啮 唲唰唱唷唬 啡啮啤 唱唳售唸 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啩啮 唲唰唱唸售 Note: Proportion of cases within the total observations, petitioned subset, and non-petitioned subset. "All" include all five results, including government win, loss, withdrawal, dismissal, and rejection. Bolded figures indicate notable changes in the proportion compared to that of the total share. 啳啨啯啷啳 啴啨啥 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 唌啶啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳唬 啤啥啰啥啮啤啩啮啧 啯啮 啷啨啥啴啨啥啲 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啯啲 啮啯啴售 啉啮 啡啢啯啵啴 唱唱售唳 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啡啬啬 啣啡啳啥啳 唨唷唷唬唱唶唰 啯啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳唩唬 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啰啥啴啩唭 啴啩啯啮啥啤 啡啢啯啵啴 啴啨啥啩啲 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳 唌啲啳啴 啡啮啤 啴啨啥啮 唌啬啥啤 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳售 啔啨啥 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啤啯啥啳 啤啩唋啥啲 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啷啥啮啴 啴啨啲啯啵啧啨 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啤啩啤 啮啯啴售 啓啰啥啣啩唌啣啡啬啬啹唬 啴啷啯 啴啨啩啮啧啳 啳啴啡啮啤 啯啵啴 啩啮 商啩啧啵啲啥 唳售 商啩啲啳啴 啡啮啤 啦啯啲啥啭啯啳啴唬 啴啨啥 啯啶啥啲啡啬啬 啰啲啯啰啯啲啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啩啳 啬啡啲啧啥啲 啩啮 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啷啥啮啴 啴啨啲啯啵啧啨 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳 唨唴唰售唵 啰啥啲唭 啣啥啮啴唩 啴啨啡啮 啩啮 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啤啩啤 啮啯啴 唨唲唳售唷 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩售 商啵啲啴啨啥啲啭啯啲啥唬 啩啦 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啢啥啦啯啲啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 and 啩啦 啳啵啣啨 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啲啵啬啥啤 啢啹 啴啨啥 啪啵啤啧啥唬 啴啨啥啮 啯啶啥啲 唷唵售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啷啥啲啥 啩啮 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唧啳 啦啡啶啯啲唻 問啮 啴啨啥 啯啴啨啥啲 啨啡啮啤唬 啩啦 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啤啩啤 啮啯啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啳啵啣啨 啣啡啳啥啳 啲啥啡啣啨啥啤 啶啥啲啤啩啣啴啳唬 啴啨啥啮 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啷啥啲啥 啩啮 啦啡啶啯啲 啯啦 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啢啹 啡 唶唲售唶 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啣啨啡啮啣啥售 啓啥啣啯啮啤唬 啷啨啩啬啥 啴啨啥 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷啮 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啡啫啥 啵啰 啴啯 唲唳售唶 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩唭</figDesc><table><row><cell>啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓</cell><cell>啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Results 啔啡啢啬啥 唵 啳啨啯啷啳 啴啨啥 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥啤 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啯啮 啴啲啩啡啬 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥售 啍啯啤啥啬 唱 啩啳 啡 啳啩啭啰啬啥 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啣啥唭啩啮唭啭啥啡啮啳 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啴啲啩啡啬 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥啳 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啩啴啨 啡啮啤 啷啩啴啨啯啵啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳售 啍啯啤啥啬 唲 啩啳 啡 啬啩啮啥啡啲 啭啯啤啥啬 啷啩啴啨 啳啴啲啵啣啴啵啲啥啤 啣啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥啳 唨X i 唩 啥啸啴啲啡啣啴啥啤 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥 啭啥啴啡啤啡啴啡 啡啮啤 啴啥啸啴 啤啥啳啣啲啩啰啴啩啯啮啳 啯啦 啥啡啣啨 啣啡啳啥售 啍啯啤啥啬 唳 啩啳 啡 啰啡啲啴啩啡啬啬啹 啬啩啮啥啡啲 啭啯啤啥啬 啷啩啴啨 啴啥啸啴 啤啥啳啣啲啩啰啴啩啯啮啳 啡啳 啡啤啤啩啴啩啯啮啡啬 啣啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥啳 啡啮啤 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥啤 啵啳啩啮啧 啤啯啵啢啬啥 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧售 商啯啲 啡啬啬 啴啨啲啥啥 啭啯啤啥啬啳唬 啷啥 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啹啥啡啲唬 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啥唬 啡啮啤 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥唭啴啹啰啥 唌啸啥啤 啥唋啥啣啴啳售 啓啴啡啮啤啡啲啤 啥啲啲啯啲啳 啡啲啥 啣啬啵啳啴啥啲啥啤 啡啴 啴啨啥 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啩啡啬 啬啥啶啥啬 啴啯 啡啣啣啯啵啮啴 啦啯啲 啣啯啲啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮啳 啩啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳 啷啩啴啨啩啮 啥啡啣啨 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啥 唨啁啢啡啤啩啥 啥啴 啡啬售唬 Selection Effect 啔啨啥 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬 唌啮啤啩啮啧啳 啡啲啥 啳啵啢啪啥啣啴啩啶啥 啴啯 啴啨啲啥啥 啳啯啵啲啣啥啳 啯啦 啳啥啬啥啣啴啩啯啮 啥唋啥啣啴 啻 啴啲啡啮啳啰啡啲啥啮啣啹 啯啦 啴啨啥 啡啲啣啨啩啶啥唬 啵啮啯啢啳啥啲啶啥啤 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啱啵啡啬啩啴啡啴啩啶啥 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啣啥 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啡啮啤 啮啯啮唭啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳售 啗啥 啡啤啤啲啥啳啳 啴啨啥啳啥 啳啣啥啮啡啲啩啯啳 啯啮啥 啢啹 啯啮啥售 商啩啲啳啴唬 啔啡啮啧 啡啮啤 啌啩啵 唨唲唰唱唹唩唧啳 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啦啲啯啭 啃啊問 唌啮啤啳 啴啨啡啴 啩啴啳 啡啶啥啲啡啧啥 啔啡啢啬啥 唱唺 啅唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啯啮 啔啲啩啡啬 問啵啴啣啯啭啥 啄啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥唺 啇啯啶售 啗啩啮 唨唱唩 啯啲 啌啯啳啳 唨唰唩 唨唱唩 唨唲唩 唨唳唩 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 唰售唱唳唱  *  *  *  唰售唰唶唸  *  *  *  唰售唱唱唱  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唲唰唩 唨唰售唰唱唰唩 唨唰售唰唱唸唩 啃啯啮啳啴啡啮啴 唰售唶唲唸 唰售唶唲唸 唰售唶唲唸 啔啥啸啴 啎啯 啎啯 啙啥啳 啙啥啡啲 商啅 啎啯 啙啥啳 啙啥啳 啐啲啯啶啩啮啣啥 商啅 啎啯 啙啥啳 啙啥啳 啄啩啳啰啵啴啥 啔啹啰啥 商啅 啎啯 啙啥啳 啙啥啳 問啴啨啥啲 啃啯啶啡啲啩啡啴啥啳 啎啯 啙啥啳 啙啥啳 問啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳 唲唷唳唬唵唸唹 唲唷唳唬唵唸唹 唲唷唳唬唵唸唹 啓啴啤售 啅啲啲售 啃啬啵啳啴啥啲啥啤 啃啬啵啳啴啥啲啥啤 啃啬啵啳啴啥啲啥啤 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啩啡啬唭啬啥啶啥啬 唌啸啥啤 啥唋啥啣啴啳 啩啮 啯啵啲 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳唬 啷啥 啦啵啲啴啨啥啲 啣啯啮啤啵啣啴啥啤 啡 啲啯啢啵啳啴啮啥啳啳 啣啨啥啣啫 啯啮啬啹 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啷啥啲啥 啵啰啬啯啡啤啥啤 啢啹 啴啨啥 啨啩啧啨啬啹 啴啲啡啮啳啰啡啲啥啮啴 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啥啳售 唨啔啯 啢啥 啡啤啤啥啤唩 商啵啲啴啨啥啲啭啯啲啥唬 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啡啲啥 啵啮啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啨啡啶啥 啴啨啥 啩啮啣啥啮啴啩啶啥 啴啯 啵啰啬啯啡啤 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啷啩啮啮啩啮啧 啣啡啳啥啳 啯啮啬啹唬 啥啶啥啮 啩啦 啴啨啥啹 啡啲啥 啮啯啴 啦啲啥啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唧啳 啩啮唍啵啥啮啣啥售 6 啔啨啩啳 啩啳 啢啥啣啡啵啳啥 啩啴 啩啳 啜啦啵啮啣啴啩啯啮啩啮啧售唢 啁啬啳啯唬 啬啯啣啡啬 啡啧啥啮啴啳 啡啲啥 啮啯啴 啡啦啲啡啩啤 啯啦 啢啥啩啮啧 啳啵啥啤 啡啮啤 啤啥啦啥啡啴啥啤 啩啮 啲啥啣啥啮啴 啹啥啡啲啳唬 啡啳 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啨啡啶啥 啢啥啥啮 啲啥啧啵啬啡啲啩啺啥啤售 7 Discussion 啔啨啩啳 啡啲啴啩啣啬啥 唌啮啤啳 啴啨啡啴 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮 啩啮 啴啨啥 啦啯啲啭 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啩啳 啣啯啲啲啥啬啡啴啥啤 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啣啩啴唭 啩啺啥啮唧啳 啬啯啳啳 啩啮 啡啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啴啲啩啡啬售 啔啨啥 唌啮啤啩啮啧 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴啳 啴啨啡啴 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啭啡啫啥 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啴啨啡啴 啳啹啳啴啥啭啡啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啤啩啳啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啴啥 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啲啯啵啢啬啥啭啡啫啥啲啳 啷啨啯 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啩啺啥 啴啨啥啩啲 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴售 啎啯啴啥 啴啨啡啴 啷啨啩啬啥 啩啴 啩啳 啴啨啥 啬啯啣啡啬 啣啯啵啲啴 啴啨啡啴 啭啡啫啥啳 啳啵啣啨 啤啥啣啩啳啩啯啮啳唬 啧啩啶啥啮 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啡啲啥 啮啯啴 啦啲啥啥 啯啦 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啩啮唍啵啥啮啣啥唬 啷啥 啣啡啮 啳啵啳啰啥啣啴 啴啨啡啴 啩啴 啩啳 啡啣啴啵唭 啡啬啬啹 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唧啳 啷啩啬啬 啴啯 啰啵啮啩啳啨 啴啨啥啭售 啔啨啩啳 啩啮啴啥啲啰啲啥啴啡啴啩啯啮 啲啥啳啯啮啡啴啥啳 啷啩啴啨 啯啮啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴唧啳 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啲啯啬啥啳 啵啮啤啥啲 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮啩啳啭唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啩啳 啴啯 啵啮啤啥啲啴啡啫啥 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唧啳 啴啡啳啫 References 啁啢啡啤啩啥唬 啁售唬 啓售 啁啴啨啥啹唬 啇售 啗售 啉啭啢啥啮啳唬 啡啮啤 啊售 啗啯啯啬啤啲啩啤啧啥 唨唲唰唱唷唩售 啗啨啥啮 啳啨啯啵啬啤 啹啯啵 啡啤啪啵啳啴 啳啴啡啮啤啡啲啤 啥啲啲啯啲啳 啦啯啲 啣啬啵啳啴啥啲啩啮啧唿 啔啥啣啨啮啩啣啡啬 啲啥啰啯啲啴唬 啎啡啴啩啯啮啡啬 啂啵啲啥啡啵 啯啦 啅啣啯啮啯啭啩啣 啒啥啳啥啡啲啣啨售 啂啥啬啬啯啮啩唬 啁售唬 啖售 啃啨啥啲啮啯啺啨啵啫啯啶唬 啉售 商啥啲啮唓 啡啮啤啥啺唭啖啡啬唬 啡啮啤 啃售 啈啡啮啳啥啮 唨唲唰唱唷唩售 啐啲啯啧啲啡啭 啥啶啡啬啵啡啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啣啡啵啳啡啬 啩啮啦啥啲啥啮啣啥 啷啩啴啨 啨啩啧啨唭啤啩啭啥啮啳啩啯啮啡啬 啤啡啴啡售 Econometrica 85 唨唱唩唬 唲唳唳啻唲唹唸售 啂啥啮啮啥啹唬 啊售 唨唲唰唱唶唩售 啗啥啩啷啥啮 啡啴 啴啨啥 啧啲啡啳啳啲啯啯啴啳唺 啃啨啩啮啡唧啳 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 啡啰啰啡啲啡啴啵啳 啡啳 啡 啭啥啡啮啳 啯啦 啣啯啮唍啩啣啴 啲啥啳啯啬啵啴啩啯啮售 Journal of Contemporary China 25 唨唹唹唩唬 唳唸唹啻唴唰唵售 啃啨啥啲啮啯啺啨啵啫啯啶唬 啖售唬 啄售 啃啨啥啴啶啥啲啩啫啯啶唬 啍售 啄啥啭啩啲啥啲唬 啅售 啄啵唍啯唬 啃售 啈啡啮啳啥啮唬 啗售 啎啥啷啥啹唬 啡啮啤 啊售 啒啯啢啩啮啳 唨唲唰唱唸唩售 啄啯啵啢啬啥唯啤啥啢啩啡啳啥啤 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啦啯啲 啴啲啥啡啴啭啥啮啴 啡啮啤 啳啴啲啵啣啴啵啲啡啬 啰啡唭 啲啡啭啥啴啥啲啳售 啃啨啵啮啧唬 啊售 啈售唬 啈售 啌啡啩唬 啡啮啤 啍售 啘啩啡 唨唲唰唰唶唩售 啍啯啵啮啴啩啮啧 啣啨啡啬啬啥啮啧啥啳 啴啯 啧啯啶啥啲啮啡啮啣啥 啩啮 啣啨啩啮啡唺 啓啵啲啶啥啹啩啮啧 啣啯啬啬啥啣啴啩啶啥 啰啲啯啴啥啳啴啯啲啳唬 啲啥啬啩啧啩啯啵啳 啳啥啣啴啳 啡啮啤 啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啬 啯啲啧啡啮啩啺啡啴啩啯啮啳售 The China Journal 56唬 唱啻唳唱售 啃啵啩唬 啙售唬 啗售 啃啨啥唬 啔售 啌啩啵唬 啂售 啑啩啮唬 啓售 啗啡啮啧唬 啡啮啤 啇售 啈啵 唨唲唰唲唰唬 啎啯啶啥啭啢啥啲唩售 啒啥啶啩啳啩啴啩啮啧 啰啲啥唭啴啲啡啩啮啥啤 啭啯啤啥啬啳 啦啯啲 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啮啡啴啵啲啡啬 啬啡啮啧啵啡啧啥 啰啲啯啣啥啳啳啩啮啧售 啉啮 Proceedings of the 2020 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing: Findings唬 問啮啬啩啮啥唬 啰啰售 唶唵唷啻唶唶唸售 啁啳啳啯啣啩啡啴啩啯啮 啦啯啲 啃啯啭啰啵啴啡啴啩啯啮啡啬 啌啩啮啧啵啩啳啴啩啣啳售 啌啩唬 啌售唬 啍售 啌啩啵唬 啡啮啤 啋售 啊售 問唧啂啲啩啥啮 唨唲唰唱唲唩售 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啂啥啩啪啩啮啧唺 啔啨啥 啨啩啧啨 啴啩啤啥 啯啦 唲唰唰唳唭唲唰唰唶售 China Quarterly 210唬 唳唱唳啻唳唳唴售 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮唬 啂售 啌售 唨唲唰唱唱唩售 啁 啰啯啰啵啬啩啳啴 啴啨啲啥啡啴 啴啯 啣啨啩啮啡唧啳 啣啯啵啲啴啳唿 啉啮 啍售 啙售 啋售 啗啯啯 啡啮啤 啍售 啅售 啇啡啬啬啡啧啨啥啲 唨啅啤啳售唩唬 Chinese Justice: Civil Dispute Resolution in Contemporary China唬 啰啰售 唲唶唹啻唳唱唳售 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥唺 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳售 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮唬 啂售 啌售唬 啍售 啒啯啢啥啲啴啳唬 啒售 啅售 啓啴啥啲啮唬 啡啮啤 啁售 啗啡啮啧 唨唲唰唲唰唩售 啍啡啳啳 啤啩啧啩啴啩啺啡啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啣啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啤啥啣啩啳啩啯啮啳唺 啈啯啷 啴啯 啵啳啥 啴啥啸啴 啡啳 啤啡啴啡 啩啮 啴啨啥 唌啥啬啤 啯啦 啣啨啩啮啥啳啥 啬啡啷售 Journal of Law and Courts 8唬 唱唷唷售 啎啯啲啴啨唬 啄售 啃售 啡啮啤 啂售 啒售 啗啥啩啮啧啡啳啴 唨唱唹唸唹唩售 啃啯啮啳啴啩啴啵啴啩啯啮啳 啡啮啤 啣啯啭啭啩啴啭啥啮啴唺 啴啨啥 啥啶啯啬啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啩啮啳啴啩啴啵啴啩啯啮啳 啧啯啶啥啲啮啩啮啧 啰啵啢啬啩啣 啣啨啯啩啣啥 啩啮 啳啥啶啥啮啴啥啥啮啴啨唭啣啥啮啴啵啲啹 啥啮啧啬啡啮啤售 The journal of economic history 49 唨唴唩唬 唸唰唳啻唸唳唲售 問唧啂啲啩啥啮唬 啋售 啡啮啤 啌售 啌啥啥 唨唲唰唰唵唩售 啓啵啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啬啯啣啡啬 啳啴啡啴啥唺 啁啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啴啩啯啮 啩啮 啲啵啲啡啬 啣啨啩啮啡售 啉啮 啎售 啊售 啄啩啡啭啡啮啴唬 啓售 啂售 啌啵啢啭啡啮唬 啡啮啤 啋售 啊售 問唧啂啲啩啥啮 唨啅啤啳售唩唬 Engaging the Law in China: State, Society, and Possibilities for Justice唬 啰啰售 唳唱啻唵唳售 啓啴啡啮啦啯啲啤唺 啓啴啡啮啦啯啲啤 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳售 啙啯啲啫唺 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳售 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴售 社会求助啓啯啣啩啡啬 啡啳啳啩啳啴啡啮啣啥唬 最低生活啍啩啮啩啭啵啭 啣啯啳啴 啯啦 啬啩啶啩啮啧 啳啵啣啨 啡啳 啲啥啱啵啩啳啩啴啩啯啮唬 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥唬 啯啰啥啮 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啩啮啦啯啲啭啡啴啩啯啮唬 啬啡啮啤 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥唬 啡啮啤 啯啲 啬啯啷啥啲唭啬啥啶啥啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳唬 唱唳售唲 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 唨唷唬唷唲唲 啣啡啳啥啳唩 啯啦 啴啨啯啳啥 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啰啲啥啦啥啣啴啵啲啥 啡啲啥 啳啥啰啡啲啡啴啥啤 啦啲啯啭 唨唱唱唩 啯啴啨啥啲 啬啡啷 啥啮啦啯啲啣啥啭啥啮啴 啣啡啳啥啳售 啐啥啥啲啥啮啢啯啯啭唬 啒售 唨唲唰唰唲唩售 China's Long March Toward Rule of Law售 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥唬 啕啋唻 啎啥啷 啒啥啨啡啶啩唬 啍售 啍售 啡啮啤 啓售 啂售 啓啴啡啲啲 唨唲唰唱唴唩售 啒啡啣啩啡啬 啤啩啳啰啡啲啩啴啹 啩啮 啦啥啤啥啲啡啬 啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啬 啳啥啮啴啥啮啣啥啳售 Journal of Political Economy 122 唨唶唩唬 唱唳唲唰啻唱唳唵唴售 啓啨啥啮唭啂啡啹啨唬 商售 唨唲唰唱唸唩售 啓啴啲啡啴啥啧啩啥啳 啯啦 啲啥啰啲啥啳啳啩啯啮唺 啊啵啤啩啣啩啡啬 啡啮啤 啥啸啴啲啡啪啵啤啩啣啩啡啬 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啯啦 啡啵啴啯唭 啣啲啡啴啩啣 啳啵啲啶啩啶啡啬售 World Politics 70 唨唳唩唬 唳唲唱啻唳唵唷售 啓啨啥啮唭啂啡啹啨唬 商售 商售 唨唲唰唲唲唩售 Undue Process售 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳售 啓啯啬啯啭啯啮唬 啐售 啈售 唨唲唰唰唷唩售 啃啯啵啲啴啳 啡啮啤 啪啵啤啧啥啳 啩啮 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啲啥啧啩啭啥啳售 World Politics 60 唨唱唩唬 啙啡啮啧唬 啄售 啌售 唨唲唰唱唷唩售 啃啨啩啮啡唧啳 啴啲啯啵啢啬啥啤 啱啵啥啳啴 啦啯啲 啯啲啤啥啲唺 啌啥啡啤啥啲啳啨啩啰唬 啯啲啧啡啮啩啺啡啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啣啯啮唭 啴啲啡啤啩啣啴啩啯啮啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 啲啥啧啩啭啥售 Journal of Contemporary China 26 唨唱唰唳唩唬 唳唵啻唵唳售 啚啥啮啧唬 啙售 啡啮啤 啙售 商啥啮啧 唨唲唰唲唲唩售 啐啯啬啩啴啩啣啩啺啥啤 啡啤啪啵啤啩啣啡啴啩啯啮 啶啩啳唭唒 啡唭啶啩啳 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啲啳 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啬啯啳啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啴啡啫啥 啵啰 唱唵售唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唬 啡啮啤 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啷啩啮啮啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啴啡啫啥 啵啰 唲唸售唲 (5) Welfare 唨啴啨啡啴 啡啲啥 啮啯啴 啲啥啬啡啴啥啤 啴啯 啅啤啵啣啡啴啩啯啮 啮啯啲 啌啡啢啯啲唩唺 社会保障啓啯啣啩啡啬 啳啥啣啵啲啩啴啹唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啩啴啨啩啮 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啥啤 啯啲 啬啯啳啴售 啃啥啲啴啡啩啮 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啯啲 啬啯啳啴唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啰啰啥啡啲 啩啮 唱唶售唶 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 唨唳唰唬唶唳唴 啣啡啳啥啳唩 啯啦 啴啨啥 啳啵啩啴啳 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啮啴啹 啔啨啥啲啥啦啯啲啥唬 唨唱唲唩 啣啡啳啥啳 啩啮啶啯啬啶啩啮啧 啰啲啯啴啥啳啴啳唬 啣啯啬啬啥啣啴啩啶啥 啡啣啴啩啯啮唬 啎啇問唬 啡啮啤 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啩啮 啂啥啩啪啩啮啧 啪啵啳啴啩啣啥售 Journal of Contemporary China 31 唨唱唳唷唩唬 唷唴唰啻唷唵唵售 啚啨啡啮啧唬 啔售 唨唲唰唰唹唩售 啗啨啹 啴啨啥 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啰啵啢啬啩啣 啰啲啥啦啥啲 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啯啶啥啲 啬啩啴啩啧啡啴啩啯啮 啛啺啨啯啮啧啧啵啯啲啥啮 啷啥啩啨啥 啺啡啩 啸啩啮啧啺啨啥啮啧 啪啩啵啦啥啮 啺啨啯啮啧 啰啩啡啮啨啡啯 啸啩啮啦啡啮啧啝售 Sociological Studies [Shehui Xue Yanjiu] 3唬 唱唳唹售 Appendix A. Descriptive Statistics Year 啂啥啦啯啲啥 啬啩啭啩啴啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啯 啥啩啴啨啥啲 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮 啯啲 啬啯啳啳唬 啷啥 啨啡啤 啡 啣啯啲啰啵啳 啯啦 唶唸唳唬唲唴唲 啯啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳售 啓啥啥 商啩啧啵啲啥 唲 啦啯啲 啴啨啥 啹啥啡啲啬啹 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳售 啅啶啥啲啹 啹啥啡啲唬 啡啢啯啵啴 唱唰 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啡啬啬 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啢啥啦啯啲啥 啢啥啩啮啧 啢啲啯啵啧啨啴 啩啮啴啯 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴唺 唸售唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啩啮 唲唰唱唴唬 唱唰售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啩啮 唲唰唱唵唬 唱唳售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啩啮 唲唰唱唶唬 唱唱售唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啩啮 唲唰唱唷唬 啡啮啤 唱唱售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啩啮 唲唰唱唸售 商啩啧啵啲啥 唲唺 啙啥啡啲啬啹 啄啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啃啡啳啥啳 50903 84570 132677 151017 264075 7 5 2 3 1 6 2 8 6 9 1 7 6 1 4 5 3 5 6 6 1 9 1 0 7 1 3 0 6 2 0.0 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012 2013 2014 2015 2016 2017 2018 Year Note: The X axis is the year when cases were published (bar) or concluded (line). The text labels represent the absolute number of cases. The Y-axis shows the proportion. In the main empirical analysis, the published year was used. Trial Result 問啶啥啲啡啬啬唬 啭啯啲啥 啴啨啡啮 唵唶售唳 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啡啬啬 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啩啮 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴 啷啥啲啥 啥啩啴啨啥啲 啤啩啳唭 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥啳啥 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴啡啧啥啳 啡啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啵啮啤啥啲啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥 啴啨啥 啲啥啡啬啩啴啹唬 啴啨啥啲啥啦啯啲啥 啥啸啣啬啵啤啥啤 啩啮 啴啨啥 啭啡啩啮 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳售 啗啩啴啨啩啮 啴啨啥 啲啥啳啴 唴唳售唷 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啷啥啲啥 啲啵啬啥啤 啢啹 啪啵啤啧啥啳唬 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳 啡啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啢啹 啡 唳唵售唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啣啨啡啮啣啥售 啔啨啡啴 啩啳唬 啯啶啥啲啡啬啬唬 啴啨啥 30 Qinghai 0.3 0.3 0.3 0.3 0.3 0.4 31 Tibet 0 0 0 0 0 0 啴啲啡啩啮唭啴啥啳啴 啳啰啬啩啴啳唬 啴啨啥 啡啣啣啵啲啡啣啹 啲啡啴啥 啨啩啴啳 啡啲啯啵啮啤 唰售唸唰售 (1) Labor唺 啫啥啹啷啯啲啤啳 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 工资啗啡啧啥唬 劳动合同啌啡啢啯啲 啣啯啮啴啲啡啣啴唬 劳动争议啌啡啢啯啲 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 (4) Education唺 高考移民啃啯啬啬啥啧啥 啥啮啴啲啡啮啣啥 啥啸啡啭啩啮啡啴啩啯啮 啲啵啬啥啳唬 学位啄啥啧啲啥啥唬 教育局啅啤啵啣啡啴啩啯啮 啂啵啲啥啡啵 啔啨啥 啣啥啮啴啲啡啬 啬啥啡啤啥啲啳啨啩啰唧啳 啥啭啰啨啡啳啩啳 啯啮 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 啦啯啬啬啯啷啥啤 啢啹 啰啥啯啰啬啥唧啳 啰啲啯啴啥啳啴啳 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啳啴啡啴啥 啩啳 啫啥啹 啴啯 啵啮啤啥啲啳啴啡啮啤啩啮啧 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啳 唨啙啡啮啧唬 唲唰唱唷唻 啃啨啵啮啧 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唰唶唩售 Dispute Type and Petition 商啩啧啵啲啥 唴 啳啨啯啷啳 啴啨啥 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啥啡啣啨 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啴啹啰啥 啩啮 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴啡啧啥 啯啦 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啤啯 啮啯啴 啳啩啧啮啩唌啣啡啮啴啬啹 啤啩唋啥啲 啦啲啯啭 啮啯啮唭啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啩啮 啴啥啲啭啳 啯啦 啴啨啥啩啲 啯啶啥啲啡啬啬 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮啳 啯啦 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啬啥啶啥啬啳售 啗啩啴啨啩啮 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啥啤 StateEcon 0 10000 20000 30000 40000 Count 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮啳唧 啣啯啭啰啥啮啳啡啴啩啯啮 啲啥啱啵啥啳啴啳 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴售 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啳啥啣啯啮啤唭啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬啳 啮啯啷 啴啡啫啩啮啧 啵啰 唴唶售唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啳啵啣啨 啣啡啳啥啳售 啁啳 啡啦啯啲啥啭啥啮啴啩啯啮啥啤唬 50000 啨啥啲啥 啩啳 啴啨啡啴 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啤 啴啯 啮啯啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啭啯啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啴啨啥 啳啥啣啯啮啤 啬啥啶啥啬售 啗啨啥啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啥啤 啯啮啬啹唬 啴啨啩啳 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啢啥啣啯啭啥啳 啭啯啲啥 啥啶啥啮唬 啡啮啤 啥啸啡啭啳 啴啨啡啴 啡啲啥 啲啥啬啡啴啥啤 啴啯 啰啲啯啦啥啳啳啩啯啮啡啬 啴啩啴啬啥啳售 示威啄啥啭啯啮啳啴啲啡啴啩啯啮啳唬 微博举报啗啥啩啢啯 啲啥啰啯啲啴啳 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳 啤啯 唨商啩啧啵啲啥 唶唩唬 Tax 啔啨啥 啢啥啬啯啷 啴啡啢啬啥啳 啰啲啯啶啩啤啥 啳啵啭啭啡啲啹 啳啴啡啴啩啳啴啩啣啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啯啮啴啲啯啬 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥啳售 問啮啥 啴啨啩啮啧 啮啯啴啩啣啥啡啢啬啥 問啶啥啲啡啬啬唬 唶唱售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啡啬啬 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啡啴 啴啨啥 唌啲啳啴 啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬啳 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啲啥啳啴 唳唸售唹 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啡啲啥 啡啴 啴啨啥 啩啳啳啵啥啳 啩啮 啧啥啮啥啲啡啬唬 唨唲唩 啷啯啲啫 啩啮啪啵啲啹唬 啡啮啤 唨唳唩 啣啩啶啩啬 啳啥啲啶啡啮啴啳 啯啲 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啭啡啮啡啧啥啤 啣啥啲啴啩唌啣啡啴啥啳 啭啩啳啳啥啤 唨唲唵售唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩唬 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷啮 啯啲 啳啥啴啴啬啥啤 唨唲唳 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩唬 啯啲 啮啯啴 啡啣啣啥啰啴啥啤 唨唷售唸 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩售 啎啯啴啥 25 Gansu 1.2 1 1.3 1.2 1.2 26 Yunnan 0.9 1 0.8 0.7 0.9 1.1 27 Hainan 0.8 1 0.7 0.7 0.8 1 28 Ningxia 0.8 0.6 0.8 0.9 0.8 0.6 29 Xinjiang 0.8 0.7 0.5 0.5 0.8 0.7 啔啨啥 啁啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啌啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啄啡啴啡啳啥啴 啣啬啡啳啳啩唌啥啳 啴啨啥 啴啹啰啥啳 啯啦 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啩啮啴啯 啢啥啬啯啷 唲唲 啣啡啴啥啧啯啲啩啥啳售 問啮啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啡啵啴啨啯啲啳唧 啴啥啡啭 啥啭啰啬啯啹啥啤 啢啯啴啨 啫啥啹啷啯啲啤 啭啡啴啣啨啩啮啧 啡啮啤 啮啥啵啲啡啬 啮啥啴 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啴啯 啣啯啤啥 啴啨啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啴啹啰啥 啯啦 啥啡啣啨 啣啡啳啥 啩啮 啴啨啥 啌啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啄啡啴啡啳啥啴售 啗啩啴啨 唷唰唭唳唰 啌啡啢啯啲 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啡啲啥 啳啵啢唭啣啡啴啥啧啯啲啩啺啥啤 啩啮啴啯 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啡啲啥 唨唱唩 啡啢啯啵啴 啬啡啢啯啲 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啡啮啤 啷啥啬啦啡啲啥 唌啮啥啳唬 卖淫嫖娼啐啲啯啳啴啩啴啵啴啩啯啮 (12) Stability Maintenance 唨Weiwen唩唺 上方啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啩啮 啂啥啩啪啩啮啧唬 集会啒啡啬啬啩啥啳唬 (23) Others 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啩啡啬 啬啥啶啥啬唬 啡啮啤 唱售唸 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啡啴 啴啨啥 啮啡啴啩啯啮啡啬 啬啥啶啥啬售 啉啮 啧啥啮啥啲啡啬唬 啨啩啧啨啥啲唭啬啥啶啥啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳 啨啡啶啥 啡 啨啩啧啨啥啲 啣啨啡啮啣啥 啴啯 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬 啯啶啥啲 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啴啨啡啮 啬啯啷啥啲唭啬啥啶啥啬 Education Other Covariates Trial Level 节约资源啒啥啳啯啵啲啣啥 啣啯啮啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮 FamilyP 公务员招考啃啩啶啩啬 啳啥啲啶啡啮啴 啲啥啣啲啵啩啴啭啥啮啴唬 司法统一考试啕啮啩唌啥啤 啪啵啤啩啣啩啡啬 啥啸啡啭啩啮啡啴啩啯啮 (11) Law Enforcement唺 扰乱啄啩啳啴啵啲啢啡啮啣啥唬 报警啐啯啬啩啣啥 啲啥啰啯啲啴唬 治安处罚啍啩啳啤啥啭啥啡啮啯啲 (22) Environment and Resource唺 环境保护啅啮啶啩啲啯啮啭啥啮啴啡啬 啰啲啯啴啥啣啴啩啯啮唬 污水啓啥啷啡啧啥唬 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啮啴啹唭 啯啲 啬啯啷啥啲 啬啥啶啥啬啳唬 唱唹售唴 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啷啥啲啥 啡啴 啴啨啥 啰啲啥啦啥啣啴啵啲啥 啬啥啶啥啬唬 唶售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啷啥啲啥 啡啴 啴啨啥 啴啨啥 啳啥啣啯啮啤 啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬啳售 1 Welfare 1 3 3 0 1 6 2 1 9 7 1 0 6 2 0 5 1 4 6 3 3 9 1 9 3 6 6 3 1 5 5 8 9 9 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 Proportion Province 啔啡啢啬啥 唲 啳啨啯啷啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啨啥啬啤唬 啢啡啳啥啤 啯啮 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴唧啳 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啥啳售 啗啨啥啮 啡啬啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啥啤唬 啈啥啮啡啮 啨啡啳 啴啨啥 啬啡啲啧啥啳啴 啶啯啬啵啭啥 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 唨唶唶唬唶唸唰 啣啡啳啥啳唬 唹售唸 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩唬 啦啯啬啬啯啷啥啤 啢啹 啊啩啡啮啧啳啵 唨唴唷唬唸唷唶 啣啡啳啥啳唬 唷 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩唬 啂啥啩啪啩啮啧 唨唴唷唬唲唱唹 啣啡啳啥啳唬 唶售唹 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩唬 啡啮啤 啇啵啡啮啧啤啯啮啧 唨唴唲唬唸唳唶 啣啡啳啥啳唬 唶售唳 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴唩售 啓啵啣啨 啡 啬啡啲啧啥 啮啵啭啢啥啲 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 啦啲啯啭 啈啥啮啡啮 啩啳 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啤啵啥 啴啨啥 啔啡啢啬啥 唲唺 啄啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啃啡啳啥啳 啂啡啳啥啤 啯啮 啃啯啵啲啴 啌啯啣啡啴啩啯啮唬 啐啥啲啣啥啮啴啡啧啥 Total Cases Petitioned Not Petitioned All Win or Loss All Win or Loss All Win or Loss N. of obs. 683,242 271,177 77,160 41,640 606,082 229,537 1 Henan 9.8 9.9 7.9 8.8 10 10 2 Jiangsu 7 6.2 7.4 6.5 7 6.1 3 Beijing 6.9 6.8 7 4.7 6.9 7.2 4 Guangdong 6.3 7.8 6.7 6.6 6.2 8 5 Shandong 6.2 6.2 5.4 5.5 6.3 6.4 6 Zhejiang 6 6.2 6.6 6.5 6 6.1 7 Hunan 5.9 5.7 7 7.2 5.7 5.4 8 Sichuan 4.8 4.4 4.3 4.2 4.8 4.5 9 Liaoning 4.1 3.9 4.8 5 4 3.7 10 Hebei 3.8 4.1 4.5 5.8 3.7 3.8 11 Hubei 3.7 3.2 4.1 4.5 3.7 2.9 12 Anhui 3.7 3.7 3.3 3.7 3.8 3.7 13 Chongqing 3.3 2.8 2.2 2 3.4 2.9 14 Guizhou 2.9 3.3 2.1 2.1 3 3.5 15 Shanghai 2.8 3.3 1.5 1.5 3 3.7 16 Shaanxi 2.5 2.2 2.4 2.4 2.5 2.1 17 Fujian 2.5 2.4 3.2 3.5 2.4 2.2 18 Guangxi 2.2 2.7 1.9 2.1 2.3 2.8 19 Jilin 2.2 2.1 2.9 2.9 2.1 1.9 20 Jiangxi 2.1 2.1 1.8 1.7 2.1 2.1 21 Shanxi 1.8 1.9 2.2 2.6 1.8 1.8 22 Tianjin 1.8 1.5 1.6 1.5 1.8 1.5 23 Heilongjiang 1.7 1.7 3.4 3.2 1.4 1.4 24 Neimenggu 1.3 1.4 1.4 1.5 1.3 1.4 啁啵啴啯啣啲啡啴啳 啡啲啥 啯啦啴啥啮 啡啳啳啵啭啥啤 啴啯 啨啡啶啥 啬啥啳啳 啩啮啣啥啮啴啩啶啥 啴啯 啰啲啯啶啩啤啥 啡 啷啥啬啦啡啲啥 啳啹啳啴啥啭售 啈啯啷啥啶啥啲唬 啥啤啵啣啡啴啩啯啮 啩啳 啮啯啴 啯啮啬啹 啡 啬啡啷啦啵啬 啲啩啧啨啴 啢啵啴 啡啬啳啯 啡 啣啯啮啳啴啩啴啵啴啩啯啮啡啬 啤啵啴啹 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡售 啔啨啥啲啥啦啯啲啥唬 啩啴 啩啳 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴啩啡啴啥啤 啦啲啯啭 啯啴啨啥啲 啫啩啮啤啳 啯啦 啳啥啲啶啩啣啥啳 啰啲啯啶啩啤啥啤 啢啹 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴售 (6) Requisition and Eviction唺 房屋拆迁补偿安置啈啯啵啳啥 啤啥啭啯啬啩啴啩啯啮 啣啯啭啰啥啮啳啡啴啩啯啮唬 移民啅啶啩啣啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啲啥啳啥啴啴啬啥啭啥啮啴 (7) Urban Planning唺 违法建设啉啬啬啥啧啡啬 啣啯啮啳啴啲啵啣啴啩啯啮唬 强制拆除商啯啲啣啥啤 啤啥啭啯啬啩啴啩啯啮 房产权啐啲啯啰啥啲啴啹 啲啩啧啨啴啳 啌啡啮啤 啩啳 啯啮啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啭啯啳啴 啦啲啥啱啵啥啮啴 啳啯啵啲啣啥啳 啯啦 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡售 啂啵啴 啴啨啥啲啥 啡啲啥 啡啴 啬啥啡啳啴 啴啨啲啥啥 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啦啯啲啭啳 啯啦 啬啡啮啤 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳售 商啩啲啳啴唬 啡啳 啩啴 啨啡啳 啢啥啥啮 啷啩啤啥啬啹 啫啮啯啷啮唬 唨唶唩 啡 啬啡啮啤 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啣啯啵啬啤 啩啮啶啯啬啶啥 啡 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啹唧啳 啦啯啲啣啥啦啵啬 啬啡啮啤唭啴啡啫啩啮啧 啯啲 啡啮 啥啶啩啣啴啩啯啮 啯啲啤啥啲唬 啯啦啴啥啮 啷啩啴啨啯啵啴 啤啵啥 啰啲啯啣啥啳啳 啯啲 啥啮啯啵啧啨 啣啯啭啰啥啮啳啡啴啩啯啮售 啓啥啣啯啮啤唬 唨唷唩 啡 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啹 啣啯啵啬啤 啳啴啩啬啬 啴啡啫啥 啯啲 啤啥啳啴啲啯啹 啯啮啥唧啳 啬啡啮啤 啯啲 啨啯啵啳啥 啵啮啤啥啲 啴啨啥 啮啡啭啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啲啥啧啵啬啡啴啩啯啮售 啔啨啩啲啤唬 唨唸唩 啡 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啹 啣啯啵啬啤 啢啥 啩啮啶啯啬啶啥啤 啩啮 啡 啣啩啶啩啬 啬啡啮啤 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥唬 啷啩啴啨 啴啷啯 啰啥啯啰啬啥 啣啬啡啩啭啩啮啧 啵啳啡啧啥 啲啩啧啨啴啳 啯啶啥啲 啴啨啥 啳啡啭啥 啰啩啥啣啥 啯啦 啬啡啮啤售 啓啩啭啩啬啡啲啬啹唬 唨唹唩 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啯啶啥啲 啨啯啵啳啥 啰啲啯啰啥啲啴啹 啲啩啧啨啴啳 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啴啷啯 啣啩啶啩啬 啰啡啲啴啩啥啳 啡啲啥 啳啥啰啡啲啡啴啥啬啹 啣啬啡啳啳啩唌啥啤 啩啮 啯啲啤啥啲 啴啯 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴啩啡啴啥 啴啨啯啳啥 啦啲啯啭 啥啶啩啣啴啩啯啮 啣啡啳啥啳售 (10) Traffic Regulation唺 交通管理局啔啲啡唎啣 啁啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啯啮 啂啵啲啥啡啵唬 交通事故啔啲啡唎啣 啡啣啣啩啤啥啮啴唬 交通违法啔啲啡唎啣 啶啩啯啬啡啴啩啯啮啳 (13) Market Economy唺 不正当竞争啕啮啦啡啩啲 啣啯啭啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮唬 消费者权益啃啯啮啳啵啭啥啲 啲啩啧啨啴啳唬 商标争议啔啲啡啤啥啭啡啲啫 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 (14) State Economy唺 金银管理啇啯啬啤 啡啮啤 啳啩啬啶啥啲 啭啡啮啡啧啥啭啥啮啴唬 政府采购啇啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啰啲啯啣啵啲啥啭啥啮啴唬 人民币啒啍啂 啃啨啩啮啡 啨啡啳 啡 啳啯啣啩啡啬啩啳啴 啭啡啲啫啥啴 啥啣啯啮啯啭啩啣 啳啹啳啴啥啭售 啔啨啥啲啥啦啯啲啥唬 啥啣啯啮啯啭啩啣 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啡啲啥 啳啵啢唭 啣啡啴啥啧啯啲啩啺啥啤 啩啮啴啯 啴啷啯 啴啹啰啥啳唺 唨唱唳唩 啒啥啧啵啬啡啴啩啯啮啳 啯啮 啭啡啲啫啥啴 啥啣啯啮啯啭啹唬 啡啮啤 唨唱唴唩 啳啴啡啴啥唭啬啥啤 啥啣啯啮啯啭啩啣 (16) Paperwork唺 民政局啃啩啶啩啬 啁唋啡啩啲啳 啂啵啲啥啡啵唬 身份证啉啄 啣啡啲啤唬 结婚证啍啡啲啲啩啡啧啥 啣啥啲啴啩唌啣啡啴啥 (17) Family Planning唺 独生子女問啮啬啹 啣啨啩啬啤唬 超生生育問啶啥啲唭啰啯啰啵啬啡啴啥啤 啦啡啭啩啬啹唬 计生手术啂啩啲啴啨 啣啯啮啴啲啯啬 啳啵啲啧啥啲啹 (18) Tax唺 税务局啔啡啸 啄啥啰啡啲啴啭啥啮啴唬 啸啸税啸啸 啔啡啸 (19) Self-governance唺 集体经济自治组织啃啯啬啬啥啣啴啩啶啥 啅啣啯啮啯啭啩啣 啁啵啴啯啮啯啭啯啵啳 問啲啧啡啮啩啺啡啴啩啯啮唬 合作经济社啃啯啯啰啥啲啡啴啩啶啥 啅啣啯啮啯啭啩啣 問啲啧啡啮啩啺啡啴啩啯啮啳唬 业主委员会啈啯啭啥 問啷啮啥啲啳唧 啁啳啳啯啣啩啡啴啩啯啮 (20) Public Service -Safety and Quality唺 安全设施啓啡啦啥啴啹 啦啡啣啩啬啩啴啩啥啳 唨啥售啧售 啲啥啰啡啩啲啩啮啧 啲啯啡啤啳唩唬 质量监督啑啵啡啬啩啴啹 啳啵啰啥啲啶啩啳啩啯啮唬 食品安全商啯啯啤 啳啡啦啥啴啹 (21) Public Service -Health唺 卫生啈啹啧啩啥啮啥唬 医疗安全啍啥啤啩啣啡啬 啳啡啦啥啴啹 啬啡啢啯啲 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啨啡啶啥 啭啯啲啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啮 啯啴啨啥啲 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啳啵啣啨 啡啳 啳啡啦啥啴啹 啱啵啡啬啩啴啹唬 啴啲啡唎啣 啲啥啧啵啬啡啴啩啯啮唬 啡啮啤 啥啣啯啮啯啭啩啣 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳售 啗啨啥啮 啷啥 啣啯啮啤啵啣啴啥啤 啲啥啧啲啥啳啳啩啯啮 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啷啩啴啨 唲唲 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啳啵啢啳啥啴啳 啯啦 啤啡啴啡 啷啩啴啨 啥啡啣啨 啤啩啳唭 啰啵啴啥 啴啹啰啥唬 啴啨啥 啣啯啥唎啣啩啥啮啴啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啷啥啲啥 啰啯啳啩啴啩啶啥 啡啮啤 啳啩啧啮啩唌啣啡啮啴 啷啩啴啨啩啮 唱唱 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啴啹啰啥啳 啻 問啇啉唬 啌啡啢啯啲唬 啗啥啬啦啡啲啥唬 啅啮啶啩啲啯啮啭啥啮啴唬 啒啥啱啵啩啳啩啴啩啯啮唬 啌啡啮啤唬 啈啯啵啳啥 啐啲啯啰啥啲啴啹 啒啩啧啨啴啳唬 啌啡啷 啅啮啦啯啲啣啥啭啥啮啴唬 啓啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啍啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 唨Weiwen唬 啢啯啴啨 啴啨啥 啳啴啡啮啤啡啲啤 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啣啯啮啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啶啥 啭啥啡唭 啻 啐啲啯啦啥啳啳啩啯啮唬 啅啤啵啣啡啴啩啯啮唬 啔啡啸唬 啓啥啬啦唭啧啯啶啥啲啮啡啮啣啥唬 啓啡啦啥啴啹 啑啵啡啬啩啴啹唬 啡啮啤 啈啥啡啬啴啨售 啔啨啥 啲啥啳啴 唌啶啥 啳啵啢啳啥啴啳 啯啦 啤啡啴啡 啨啡啤 啬啩啭啩啴啥啤 啯啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳 啦啯啲 啴啨啥 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳售 商啩啧啵啲啥 唵 啳啨啯啷啳 啴啨啥 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥啤 啥唋啥啣啴啳 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啳 啯啮 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啴啹啰啥啳 啯啦 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳售 啔啨啥 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥啳 啡啲啥 啳啩啭啩啬啡啲 啡啮啤 啳啴啡啢啬啥 啡啣啲啯啳啳 啭啯啳啴 啴啹啰啥啳 啯啦 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳售 啔啨啩啳 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴啳 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啩啳 啮啯啴 啣啯啮啣啥啮啴啲啡啴啥啤 啯啮 啣啥啲啴啡啩啮 啴啹啰啥啳 啯啦 啣啯啮唍啩啣啴 啷啩啴啨 啳啴啡啴啥 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳售 啒啡啴啨啥啲唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啳 啡 啦啯啲啭 啯啦 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮 啩啳 啢啲啯啡啤啬啹 啰啵啮啩啳啨啥啤 啢啹 啴啨啥 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啴啲啩啢啵啮啡啬啳售 Government Level 啌啯啷啥啲唭啬啥啶啥啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳 啡啲啥 啭啯啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啢啥 啩啮啶啯啬啶啥啤 啩啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啴啨啡啮 啨啩啧啨啥啲唭啬啥啶啥啬 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳售 啗啩啴啨啩啮 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴唬 唶唶售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啳啩啤啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啡啴 商啩啧啵啲啥 唴唺 啄啩啳啰啵啴啥 啔啹啰啥 唨啃啯啵啮啴唩唬 啔啯啴啡啬 啡啮啤 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啃啡啳啥啳 Health Profession Environment Paperwork SafetyQuality SelfGov TrafficR Labor MarketEcon HouseP LawEnforce Land OGI Requisition Dispute Type Total/Petitioned 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴售 商啩啧啵啲啥 唷 啦啵啲啴啨啥啲 啳啨啯啷啳 啴啨啥 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啡啴 啴啨啥 唌啲啳啴 啡啮啤 啳啥啣啯啮啤唭啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬啳售 啗啨啥啮 啯啮啬啹 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啩啮啧 啯啲 啬啯啳啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啡啲啥 啢啥啩啮啧 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啤唬 啴啨啥啮 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮啳 啡啴 啡 唵唸售唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啣啨啡啮啣啥 啡啴 啴啨啥 唌啲啳啴 啬啥啶啥啬 啴啲啩啡啬啳 啡啮啤 啩啴 啷啩啮啳 啡啴 啡 唷唳售唰 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啣啨啡啮啣啥 啡啴 啔啡啢啬啥 唳唺 啓啵啭啭啡啲啹 啓啴啡啴啩啳啴啩啣啳 唨啔啯啴啡啬 問啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳唩 All Observations Petitioned Subset Not Petitioned Subset N=683,242 N=77,160 N=606,082 Covariates Min Max Mean St. Dev. Mean St. Dev. Mean St. Dev. Nonperformance 0 1 0.121 0.327 0.187 0.390 0.113 0.317 商啩啧啵啲啥 唳 Dispute Type (8) Land唺 土地使用权啌啡啮啤 啵啳啥 啲啩啧啨啴啳 权属問啷啮啥啲啳啨啩啰 (9) House Property唺 房地产管理局啒啥啡啬 啅啳啴啡啴啥 啁啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啯啮 啂啵啲啥啡啵唬 啡啣啴啩啶啩啴啩啥啳 啯啲 啰啬啡啮啮啥啤 啥啣啯啮啯啭啹售 (15) Open Government Information Request 唨問啇啉唩唺 政府信息公开 UrbanPlan Reconsideration 0 1 0.250 0.433 0.328 0.470 0.240 0.427 啳啵啲啥啭啥啮啴啳唩唬 啍啡啲啫啥啴 啅啣啯啮唬 啡啮啤 啓啴啡啴啥 啅啣啯啮售 啗啩啴啨啩啮 啳啩啸 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啴啹啰啥啳唬 啴啨啥 啣啯啥唎啣啩啥啮啴啳 啷啥啲啥 Compensation 0 1 0.113 0.317 0.219 0.414 0.100 0.300 Workinjury Represented 0 1 0.170 0.375 0.159 0.366 0.171 0.376 啮啯啴 啳啴啡啴啩啳啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啳啩啧啮啩唌啣啡啮啴唬 啰啲啯啢啡啢啬啹 啤啵啥 啴啯 啴啨啥 啬啩啭啩啴啥啤 啮啵啭啢啥啲 啯啦 啴啯啴啡啬 啯啲 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 Weiwen Third-party 0 1 0.104 0.305 0.057 0.231 0.110 0.313</cell></row><row><cell>唹 唱唰 唱唱 唱唲 唱唳 唱唴 唱唵 唱唶 唱唷 唱唹 唲唰 唲唲 唲唳 唲唴 唲唵 唲唸</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>啔啯 啲啥啰啲啥啳啥啮啴 啴啨啥 啴啥啸啴啳 啯啦 啣啡啳啥 啤啥啳啣啲啩啰啴啩啯啮啳唬 啷啥 啯啰啴 啦啯啲 啡 啬啡啲啧啥 啬啡啮啧啵啡啧啥 啭啯啤啥啬 啴啨啡啴 啩啳 啳啰啥啣啩唌啣啡啬啬啹 啴啲啡啩啮啥啤 啯啮 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啬啥啧啡啬 啤啯啣啵啭啥啮啴啳 唨啃啵啩 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唲唰唩 啴啯 啯啢啴啡啩啮 啨啩啧啨唭啱啵啡啬啩啴啹 啮啵啭啥啲啩啣啡啬 啥啭啢啥啤啤啩啮啧啳 啦啯啲 啥啡啣啨 啴啥啸啴售 啗啥 啴啨啥啮 啵啳啥 啴啨啥 啤啯啵啢啬啥 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啡啰啰啲啯啡啣啨 唨啂啥啬啬啯啮啩 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唱唷唻 啃啨啥啲啮啯啺啨啵啫啯啶 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唱唸唩 啴啯 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥 啴啨啥 啰啡啲啴啩啡啬啬啹 啬啩啮啥啡啲 啭啯啤啥啬 啯啦 唨唲唩售 啅啳啳啥啮啴啩啡啬啬啹唬 啴啨啥 啡啰啰啲啯啡啣啨 啭啩啮啩啭啩啺啥啳 啴啨啥 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啡啮啹 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啩啯啮 啥啲啲啯啲 啯啦 啴啨啥 啮啵啩啳啡啮啣啥 啰啡啲啡啭啥啴啥啲啳 g唨Z唩 啡啮啤 m唨Z唩 啯啮 啴啨啥 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啴啨啥 啰啡啲啡啭啥啴啥啲 啯啦 啩啮啴啥啲啥啳啴 τ 售 啉啮 啴啨啥 啭啡啩啮 啴啥啸啴唬 啷啥 啵啳啥 啴啨啥 啲啡啮啤啯啭 啦啯啲啥啳啴 啴啯 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥 g唨Z唩 啡啮啤 m唨Z唩售 啓啥啥 啴啨啥 啳啵啰啰啬啥啭啥啮啴啡啲啹 啭啡啴啥啲啩啡啬啳 啦啯啲 啡啬啴啥啲啮啡啴啩啶啥 啭啡啣啨啩啮啥 啬啥啡啲啮啩啮啧 啭啯啤啥啬啳 啡啮啤 啴啥啣啨啮啩啣啡啬 啤啥啴啡啩啬啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啭啥啴啨啯啤售 唲唰唱唷唩售 啔啨啥 啣啯啥唎啣啩啥啮啴 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥啳 啡啲啥 啲啥啬啡啴啩啶啥啬啹 啳啴啡啢啬啥 啡啣啲啯啳啳 啭啯啤啥啬啳 啡啮啤 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴 啴啨啡啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啳 啡 啦啯啲啭 啯啦 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮 啩啳 啳啹啳啴啥啭啡啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啰啵啮啩啳啨啥啤 啩啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啴啲啩啡啬啳售 啍啯啤啥啬 唱唬 啴啨啥 啭啩啮啩啭啡啬啩啳啴 啳啰啥啣啩唌啣啡啴啩啯啮唬 啳啨啯啷啳 啴啨啡啴 啡 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥 啨啡啳 啡 唱唳.唱唥 啩啮啣啲啥啡啳啥啤 啰啲啯啢啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啯啦 啨啡啶啩啮啧 啡 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴 啴啨啡啮 啡 啣啡啳啥 啷啩啴啨啯啵啴售 啔啨啥 啭啡啧啮啩啴啵啤啥 啯啦 啣啯啥唎啣啩啥啮啴啳 啢啥啣啯啭啥啳 啳啭啡啬啬啥啲 啷啨啥啮 啷啥 啡啣啣啯啵啮啴 啦啯啲 啲啥啬啥啶啡啮啴 啣啡啳啥 啡啴啴啲啩啢啵啴啥啳 啩啮 啴啨啥 啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮啳啨啩啰 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啴啲啩啡啬 啯啵啴啣啯啭啥啳售 啍啯啤啥啬 唲 啡啮啤 唳 啹啩啥啬啤 啥啳啴啩啭啡啴啥啳 啲啡啮啧啩啮啧 啦啲啯啭 唶.唸唥 啴啯 唱唱.唱唥售 啗啨啩啬啥 啴啨啥 啲啥啧啲啥啳啳啩啯啮 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啳啨啯啷 啡啮 啡啳啳啯啣啩啡啴啩啯啮 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴唬 啷啥 啤啯 啮啯啴 啩啮啴啥啮啤 啴啯 啭啡啫啥 啡 啳啴啲啯啮啧 啣啡啵啳啡啬 啣啬啡啩啭 啩啮 啴啨啩啳 啰啡啰啥啲 啤啵啥 啴啯 啴啨啥 啰啯啳啳啩啢啬啥 啳啥啬啥啣啴啩啯啮 啥唋啥啣啴唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啩啳 啤啩啳啣啵啳啳啥啤 啩啮 啴啨啥 啮啥啸啴 啳啥啣啴啩啯啮售 啤啩啳啣啬啯啳啵啲啥 啲啡啴啥啳 啲啡啮啧啥 啦啲啯啭 唴唲售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啴啯 唴唷售唴 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啢啥啴啷啥啥啮 唲唰唱唴 啡啮啤 唲唰唱唶售 啗啨啩啬啥 啴啨啩啳 啩啳 啡 啨啵啧啥 啩啭啰啲啯啶啥啭啥啮啴 啩啮 啴啲啡啮啳啰啡啲啥啮啣啹 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啥 唰售唳唭唲售唷 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啤啩啳啣啬啯啳啵啲啥 啲啡啴啥 啢啥啦啯啲啥 唲唰唱唳唬 啨啡啶啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啡啶啡啩啬啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啯啦 啯啮啬啹 啡啲啯啵啮啤 唵唰 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啡啬啬 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啩啮啤啥啥啤 啰啯啳啥啳 啡 啣啨啡啬啬啥啮啧啥 Note: * p &lt; 0.1, ** p &lt; 0.05, *** p &lt; 0.01. Models (1) and (2) are linear models. Model (3) is a partially linear model. Estimates for (3) are based on the double machine learning approach. "Text" indicates whether embeddings of case descriptions are included in the model. "Other Covariates" include the administrative level of the government in the lawsuit, trial level, non-performance, reconsideration, and whether the litigant has legal representation. Standard errors are clustered at the provincial level. 啩啮 啶啩啥啷啩啮啧 啴啨啥 啴啲啵啥 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳售 啐啥啲啴啡啩啮啩啮啧 啴啯 啴啨啩啳 啲啥啳啥啡啲啣啨唬 啩啦 啴啨啥 啵啮啯啢啳啥啲啶啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啥啲啥 啴啯 啡啬啴啥啲 啯啵啲 唌啮啤啩啮啧啳唬 啴啨啥啮 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴唧啳 啤啥啣啩啳啩啯啮 啯啮 啤啩啳啣啬啯啳啵啲啥 啳啨啯啵啬啤 啢啥 啩啮唍啵啥啮啣啥啤 啢啹 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴售 啓啰啥啣啩唌啣啡啬啬啹唬 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啳啨啯啵啬啤 啢啥 啭啯啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啵啰啬啯啡啤 啴啨啥啩啲 啲啵啬啩啮啧啳 啴啯 啴啨啥 啡啲啣啨啩啶啥 啷啨啥啮 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮啳唬 啥啳啰啥啣啩啡啬啬啹 啷啨啥啮 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤售 啈啯啷啥啶啥啲唬 啗啵 啥啴 啡啬售 唨唲唰唲唲唩 唌啮啤啳 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啤啩啳啣啬啯啳啵啲啥 啲啡啴啥 啩啳 啲啥啬啡啴啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啥 啣啡啰啡啣啩啴啹 啯啦 啥啡啣啨 啣啯啵啲啴 啴啯 啨啡啮啤啬啥 啴啨啥 啵啰啬啯啡啤啩啮啧 啰啲啯啣啥啳啳售 啓啵啣啨 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啲啥啳啯啵啲啣啥啳 啯啲 啣啡啰啡啣啩啴啹 啡啣啲啯啳啳 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啩啳 啯啲啴啨啯啧啯啮啡啬 啴啯 啴啨啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啡啴啩啯啮 啴啨啡啴 啷啥 啡啲啥 啩啮啴啥啲啥啳啴啥啤 啩啮 啣啡啰啴啵啲啩啮啧售 啉啮 啡啤啤啩啴啩啯啮唬 啷啨啩啬啥 啷啥 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥啤 啩啮 啬啩啮啥 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴唧啳 啩啮啴啥啲啥啳啴 啴啯 啤啥啭啯啮啳啴啲啡啴啥 啴啯 啴啨啥 啣啥啮啴啲啡啬 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啩啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啩啳 6 Author's interview with a local legal expert. 啡 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啩啳 啡啳 啬啯啷 啡啳 唰售唲 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 唨啚啨啡啮啧唬 唲唰唰唹唩唬 啩啴 啩啳 啮啯啴 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啨啡啶啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啡啲啥 啴啯啯 啤啩唎啣啵啬啴 啴啯 啲啥啳啯啬啶啥 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮售 啉啮啳啴啥啡啤唬 啩啴 啩啳 啭啯啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啳啩啭啰啬啹 啣啨啯啳啥 啴啯 啥啭啰啬啯啹 啢啯啴啨 啴啯啯啬啳售 啍啯啳啴 啩啭啰啯啲啴啡啮啴啬啹唬 啯啵啲 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬 啳啴啲啡啴啥啧啹 啩啮啴啥啮啤啳 啴啯 啣啯啮啴啲啯啬 啦啯啲 啴啨啥 啵啮啳啴啲啵啣啴啵啲啥啤 啣啯啮啦啯啵啮啤啥啲啳 啳啵啣啨 啡啳 啴啨啥 啳啴啲啥啮啧啴啨 啯啦 啥啶啩啤啥啮啣啥 啡啮啤 啴啨啥啩啲 啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮啳 啷啩啴啨 啯啴啨啥啲 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啣啡啮 啡唋啥啣啴 啢啯啴啨 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴售 7 Author's interview with a lawyer who has been working for the local government agencies in W city. Another interviewee, who is a local legal expert, added that when the local agent's performance is being evaluated by the center, then the evaluations are less likely to be based on trial results than on other internal criteria. 啯啢啳啥啲啶啥唬 啣啯啮啣啥啳啳啩啯啮啳 啭啡啹 啨啡啶啥 啢啥啥啮 啭啡啤啥唬 啡啳 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮 唨唲唰唱唱唩 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴啳售 啔啨啩啲啤唬 啷啨啩啬啥 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮 唨唲唰唱唱唩 啬啯啯啫啳 啡啴 啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啬 啡啮啤 啣啩啶啩啬 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啳 啷啥啬啬唬 啷啥 啦啯啣啵啳 啯啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啣啡啳啥啳售 啉啴 啷啯啵啬啤 啮啯啴 啢啥 啥啡啳啹 啦啯啲 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啴啯 啭啡啫啥 啣啯啮啣啥啳啳啩啯啮啳 啴啯 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啩啮啶啯啬啶啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳售 商啩啮啡啬啬啹唬 啷啨啩啬啥 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮 唨唲唰唱唱唩唧啳 唌啮啤啩啮啧 啩啳 啡啢啯啵啴 啴啨啥 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 after 啡 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴 啩啳 啣啯啮啣啬啵啤啥啤唬 啷啥 啴啥啳啴 啴啨啥 啥唋啥啣啴 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 before 啡 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴售 啤啥啌啩啳啬啥唬 啊售 唨唲唰唱唷唩售 啌啡啷 啩啮 啴啨啥 啃啨啩啮啡 啭啯啤啥啬 唲售唰唺 啌啥啧啡啬啩啴啹唬 啤啥啶啥啬啯啰啭啥啮啴啡啬啩啳啭 啡啮啤 啬啥啮啩啮啩啳啭 啵啮啤啥啲 啘啩 啪啩啮啰啩啮啧售 Journal of Contemporary China 26 唨唱唰唳唩唬 唶唸啻唸唴售 商啥啮啧唬 啙售 啡啮啤 啘售 啈啥 唨唲唰唱唸唩售 商啲啯啭 啬啡啷 啴啯 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啳唺 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啲啳唧 啦啲啡啭啩啮啧 啯啦 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥啳 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啯啵啲啴啳售 The China Journal 80唬 唱唳唰啻唱唴唹售 啇啩啮啳啢啵啲啧唬 啔售 唨唲唰唰唸唩售 啁啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啬啡啷 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啪啵啤啩啣啩啡啬 啣啯啮啴啲啯啬 啯啦 啡啧啥啮啴啳 啩啮 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啲啥啧啩啭啥啳售 啉啮 啔售 啇啩啮啳啢啵啲啧 啡啮啤 啔售 啍啯啵啳啴啡啦啡 唨啅啤啳售唩唬 Rule by Law: The Politics of Courts in Authoritarian Regimes唬 啰啰售 唵唸啻唷唱售 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥唬 啕啋唻 啎啥啷 啙啯啲啫唺 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳售 啇啲啩啭啭啥啲唬 啊售唬 啍售 啅售 啒啯啢啥啲啴啳唬 啡啮啤 啂售 啍售 啓啴啥啷啡啲啴 唨唲唰唲唲唩售 Text as data: A new framework for machine learning and the social sciences售 啐啲啩啮啣啥啴啯啮 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳售 啈啩啬啬唬 啄售 啗售 啡啮啤 啚售 啍售 啊啯啮啥啳 唨唲唰唱唴唩售 啁啮 啥啭啰啩啲啩啣啡啬 啥啶啡啬啵啡啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啥啸啰啬啡啮啡啴啩啯啮啳 啦啯啲 啳啴啡啴啥 啲啥啰啲啥啳啳啩啯啮售 American Political Science Review 108 唨唳唩唬 唶唶唱啻唶唸唷售 啈啯啵唬 啙售 啡啮啤 啒售 啔啲啵啥啸 唨唲唰唲唲唩售 啅啴啨啮啩啣 啤啩啳啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啴啩啯啮 啡啮啤 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啲啵啬啥唺 啁啮 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啯啦 啣啲啩啭啩啮啡啬 啳啥啮啴啥啮啣啩啮啧 啩啮 啃啨啩啮啡售 The Journal of Politics 84 唨唴唩唬 唲唲唹唴啻唲唲唹唹售 啌啩啮唬 啌售 唨唲唰唱唴唩售 Xinzheng Fazhide Lixiang yu Xianshi [The Ideal and Reality of the Rule of Administrative Law]售 啂啥啩啪啩啮啧唺 啂啥啩啪啩啮啧 啄啡啸啵啥 啃啨啵啢啡啮啳啨啥 啛啐啥啫啩啮啧 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳啝售 啍啩啮啺啮啥啲唬 啃售 商售 唨唲唰唰唶唩售 啘啩啮啦啡啮啧唺 啁啮 啡啬啴啥啲啮啡啴啩啶啥 啴啯 啦啯啲啭啡啬 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啬啥啧啡啬 啩啮啳啴啩啴啵啴啩啯啮啳售 Stanford Journal of International Law 42 唨唱唰唳唩唬 唱唰唳啻唱唷唹售 啍啯啵啳啴啡啦啡唬 啔售 唨唲唰唰唷唩售 The Struggle for Constitutional Power: Law, Politics, and Economic Development in Egypt售 啎啥啷 啙啯啲啫唺 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳售 啍啵啳啴啡啲啤唬 啄售 啂售 唨唲唰唰唱唩售 啒啡啣啩啡啬唬 啥啴啨啮啩啣唬 啡啮啤 啧啥啮啤啥啲 啤啩啳啰啡啲啩啴啩啥啳 啩啮 啳啥啮啴啥啮啣啩啮啧唺 啅啶啩啤啥啮啣啥 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥 啵啳 啦啥啤啥啲啡啬 啣啯啵啲啴啳售 The Journal of Law and Economics 44 唨唱唩唬 唲唸唵啻唳唱唴售 唱唲唲啻唱唴唵售 啔啡啮啧唬 啙售 啡啮啤 啊售 啚售 啌啩啵 唨唲唰唱唹唩售 啍啡啳啳 啰啵啢啬啩啣啩啴啹 啯啦 啣啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啯啵啲啴 啤啥啣啩啳啩啯啮啳唺 啍啡啲啫啥啴唭啤啲啩啶啥啮 啯啲 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮 啴啲啡啮啳啰啡啲啥啮啣啹唿 The China Review 19 唨唲唩唬 唱唵啻唴唰售 啔啯啮啧唬 啙售 唨唲唰唰唹唩售 啄啩啳啰啵啴啥 啲啥啳啯啬啵啴啩啯啮 啳啴啲啡啴啥啧啩啥啳 啩啮 啡 啨啹啢啲啩啤 啳啹啳啴啥啭售 China Review 9 唨唱唩唬 唱唷啻唴唳售 啕啬啭啥啲唬 啊售 啔售 啡啮啤 啂售 啊啯啨啮啳啯啮 唨唲唰唰唴唩售 啓啥啮啴啥啮啣啩啮啧 啩啮 啣啯啮啴啥啸啴唺 啁 啭啵啬啴啩啬啥啶啥啬 啡啮啡啬啹啳啩啳售 Criminology 42 唨唱唩唬 唱唳唷啻唱唷唸售 啖啡啲啯啬唬 問售 問售 唨唲唰唱唴唩售 啓啴啥啡啬啴啨 啡啵啴啨啯啲啩啴啡啲啩啡啮啩啳啭售 Iowa L. Rev. 100唬 唱唶唷唳售 啗啡啮啧唬 啙售 唨唲唰唱唵唩售 Tying the Autocrat's hands售 啃啡啭啢啲啩啤啧啥 啕啮啩啶啥啲啳啩啴啹 啐啲啥啳啳售 啗啵唬 啘售唬 啍售 啅售 啒啯啢啥啲啴啳唬 啒售 啅售 啓啴啥啲啮唬 啂售 啌售 啌啩啥啢啭啡啮唬 啁售 啇啵啰啴啡唬 啡啮啤 啌售 啓啡啮啦啯啲啤 唨唲唰唲唲唩售 啁啵啧啭啥啮啴啩啮啧 啳啥啲啩啡啬啩啺啥啤 啢啵啲啥啡啵啣啲啡啴啩啣 啤啡啴啡唺 啔啨啥 啣啡啳啥 啯啦 啃啨啩啮啥啳啥 啣啯啵啲啴啳售 Working Paper 售 問啮啣啥 啷啥 啬啩啭啩啴 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啯 啴啨啥 啯啮啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啪啵啤啧啥啳 啲啵啬啥啤 啩啮 啦啡啶啯啲 啯啦 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啯啲 啴啨啥 啣啩啴啩啺啥啮唬 啴啨啥啮 啴啨啥 啮啵啭啢啥啲 啯啦 啯啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳 啢啥啣啯啭啥啳 唲唷唱唬唱唷唷售 啔啨啥 啯啶啥啲啡啬啬 啰啲啯啰啯啲啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啣啲啯啳啳 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啹啥啡啲啳 啤啯 啮啯啴 啳啩啧啮啩唌啣啡啮啴啬啹 啤啩唋啥啲 啦啲啯啭 商啩啧啵啲啥 唲售 啙啥啴唬 啴啨啥 唱唸 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啨啩啧啨 啴啲啡啮啳啰啡啲啥啮啣啹 啲啡啴啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啯啵啲啴啳 啩啮 啈啥啮啡啮唬 啮啯啴 啮啥啣啥啳啳啡啲啩啬啹 啢啥啣啡啵啳啥 啯啦 啴啨啥 啡啢啳啯啬啵啴啥 啮啵啭啢啥啲 啯啦 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 唌啬啥啤 啩啮 啴啨啥 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啥 唨啌啩啥啢啭啡啮 啥啴 啡啬售唬 唲唰唲唰唩售 啔啨啩啳 啳啵啧啧啥啳啴啳 啳啥啬啥啣啴啩啯啮 啢啩啡啳 啩啮 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啷啩啬啬 啢啥 啡啤啤啲啥啳啳啥啤 啢啥啬啯啷售 啔啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啦啲啯啭 啙啵啮啮啡啮唬 啈啡啩啮啡啮唬 啎啩啮啧啸啩啡唬 啘啩啮啪啩啡啮啧唬 啑啩啮啧啨啡啩唬 啡啮啤 啔啩啢啥啴 啥啡啣啨 啴啡啫啥 啬啥啳啳 啴啨啡啮 啯啮啥 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啤啡啴啡啳啥啴唬 啷啩啴啨 啔啩啢啥啴 啨啡啶啩啮啧 啮啥啡啲啬啹 啺啥啲啯 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啯啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳售 啔啨啥 啯啲啤啥啲 啯啦 啴啨啥 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啥啳 啢啡啳啥啤 啯啮 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥 啲啯啡啤 啳啨啯啷啳 啳啬啩啧啨啴 啣啨啡啮啧啥啳 啷啩啴啨啩啮 啴啨啥 啳啵啢啳啥啴 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啥啤 啯啲 啬啯啳啴售 啗啨啥啮 啴啨啥 啲啥啧啩啯啮啡啬 啤啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮啳 啯啦 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啤 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啣啯啲啲啥啳啰啯啮啤啩啮啧 啴啯啴啡啬 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啂啥啩啪啩啮啧 啳啨啯啷啳 啡 啤啲啯啰 啩啮 啩啴啳 啰啲啯啰啯啲啴啩啯啮唬 啷啨啩啬啥 啈啥啢啥啩 啳啨啯啷啳 啡啮 啩啮啣啲啥啡啳啥售 啈啵啮啡啮 啡啬啳啯 啲啡啮啫啳 啦啯啵啲啴啨 啡啭啯啮啧 啴啨啥 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啥啳 啷啨啥啮 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啥啤 啷啨啥啮 啩啴 啩啳 啴啨啥 唷啴啨 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啴啯啴啡啬 啳啨啡啲啥 啯啦 啣啡啳啥啳售 啧啡啮啴啳 啤啩啤 啮啯啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮唬 啳啵啣啨 啣啡啳啥啳 啴啡啫啥 啬啥啳啳 啴啨啡啮 唰售唵 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 啯啦 啴啨啥 啣啡啳啥啳 啷啨啥啲啥 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 唌啲啳啴售 啃啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啩啮啧 啴啨啡啴 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啭啡啫啥 啤啥啣啩啳啩啯啮啳 啯啮 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷啡啬 啻 啬啥啴 啴啨啥 啤啥唭 啣啩啳啩啯啮啳 啢啥 啶啯啬啵啮啴啡啲啹 啯啲 啦啯啲啣啥啦啵啬 啻 啴啨啩啳 啲啥啳啵啬啴 啷啯啵啬啤 啨啡啶啥 啢啥啥啮 啤啲啩啶啥啮 啢啹 啴啨啥 啣啨啡啲啡啣啴啥啲啩啳啴啩啣啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啴啨啡啮 啴啨啥 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啳 啯啦 啴啲啩啡啬啳售 啔啨啡啴 啩啳唬 啴啨啯啳啥 啷啨啯 啡啲啥 啤啥啴啥啲啭啩啮啥啤 啴啯 啲啥啳啯啬啶啥 啡啮 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啷啯啵啬啤 啨啡啶啥 啢啥啥啮 啭啯啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啡啤啯啰啴 啭啵啬啴啩啰啬啥 啭啥啴啨啯啤啳 啴啯 啣啯啮啦啲啯啮啴 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啯啲啳唬 啡啮啤 啡啴 啴啨啥 啳啡啭啥 啴啩啭啥唬 啬啥啳啳 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啧啩啶啥 啵啰 啴啨啥啩啲 啴啲啩啡啬啳售 (2) Work Injury唺 工伤认定啗啯啲啫 啩啮啪啵啲啹 啲啥啣啯啧啮啩啴啩啯啮 (3) Profession 唨啃啩啶啩啬 啳啥啲啶啡啮啴 啳啴啡啮啤啡啲啤啳 啡啮啤 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴唭啭啡啮啡啧啥啤 啪啯啢 啴啩啴啬啥啳唩唺 唲唱 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 商啩啧啵啲啥 唳唺 啄啩啳啴啲啩啢啵啴啩啯啮 啯啦 啔啲啩啡啬 啒啥啳啵啬啴啳 啢啹 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 Note: The X-axis indicates whether a lawsuit was filed after a petition (1) or not (0). The y-axis shows the proportions of trial results within each scenario. Petitioned Total Note: The X-axis is the count, and the Y-axis is each type of dispute. A single case is allowed to have up to two dispute types. The upper light bars indicate the total number of cases and the lower dark bars indicate the number of petitioned cases. 唲唶 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 商啩啧啵啲啥 唵唺 啅啳啴啩啭啡啴啥啤 啅唋啥啣啴啳 啢啹 啄啩啳啰啵啴啥 啔啹啰啥 Note: Estimates and standard errors are obtained using the same specification and estimation procedure as Model 3 of Table 5. 啬啥啶啥啬唬 唱唳售唷 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 唨唲唬唳唸唵唶 啣啡啳啥啳唩 啯啦 啴啨啯啳啥 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啰啲啯啶啩啮啣啩啡啬 啬啥啶啥啬唬 啡啮啤 唷售唱 啰啥啲啣啥啮啴 唨唲唬唳唸唶 啣啡啳啥啳唩 啯啦 啴啨啯啳啥 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啮啡啴啩啯啮啡啬 啬啥啶啥啬 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啩啥啳售 啴啨啩啳 啣啡啮 啢啥 啡啴啴啲啩啢啵啴啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啥 啴啲啡啩啴啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳唺 啴啨啯啳啥 啷啨啯 啤啩啤 啮啯啴 啳啴啯啰 啡啴 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啳啴啡啧啥 啢啵啴 唌啬啥啤 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啡啧啡啩啮 啷啯啵啬啤 啢啥 啭啯啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啡啰啰啥啡啬 啷啨啥啮 啴啨啥啹 啡啲啥 啮啯啴 啳啡啴啩啳唌啥啤 唲唷 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 商啩啧啵啲啥 唶唺 啇啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啌啥啶啥啬 啡啮啤 啔啲啩啡啬 啒啥啳啵啬啴 Note: The X-axis is the administrative level of the government in a trial. If two or more government agencies are involved, then the highest level was recorded. The Y-axis is the proportion of trial results within each government level. The numbers indicate the absolute number of cases. "Neither" includes dismissal, withdrawal, and rejection of a case.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>啩啦 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啡啢啯啵啴 啴啨啥啩啲 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳唬 啴啨啥啮 啴啨啥啹 啡啲啥 啭啯啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啬啯啳啥 啴啯 啴啨啥 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啩啮 啴啨啥 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴售 啔啨啩啳 啩啳 啣啯啮啳啩啳啴啥啮啴 啷啩啴啨 啨啹啰啯啴啨啥啳啩啳 唲唬 啷啨啩啣啨 啰啲啥啤啩啣啴啥啤 啴啨啡啴 啰啯啬啩啴啩啣啡啬 啡啣啴啩啯啮 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啩啮 啳啴啡啴啥 啲啥啰啲啥啳啳啩啯啮 啢啡啳啥啤 啯啮 啴啨啥 啷啩啤啥啬啹 啡啣啣啥啰啴啥啤 啴啨啥啯啲啥啴啩啣啡啬 啶啩啥啷 啴啨啡啴 啡啮 啡啵啴啯啣啲啡啴 啷啯啵啬啤 啡啤啯啰啴 啴啡啲啧啥啴啥啤 啲啥啰啲啥啳啳啩啯啮 啷啨啥啮 啤啩啳啳啩啤啥啮啴啳 啡啲啥 啩啤啥啮啴啩唌啥啤售 啍啯啤啥啬 唨唵唩 啯啮啬啹 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥啳 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 唨Weiwen唩 啣啡啳啥啳售 啗啨啥啮 啣啬啡啳啳啩啦啹啩啮啧 啤啩啳啰啵啴啥 啴啹啰啥啳唬 啡 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 啣啡啳啥 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥啳 啴啨啥 啫啥啹啷啯啲啤啳 啳啵啣啨 啡啳 啜啩啬啬啥啧啡啬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 唨非正常8 On the direction of coefficient of trial level in Model (5): Overall, the government wins over citizens with a 58 percent chance at the first-level trials and a 73 percent chance at the second-level trials. However, in stability maintenance cases, the disputes that are considered highly political, the government has an overwhelmingly high chance to prevail over citizens both at the first level (92 percent) and at the second level (91 percent). 上访啯啲 非正常信访唩唢 啜啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啩啮 啂啥啩啪啩啮啧 唨到北京上访啯啲 驻京信访唩唬唢 啯啲 啜啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啩啮 啴啨啥 啲啥啳啴啲啩啣啴啥啤 啡啲啥啡 唨非上访地区唩售唢 啉啮 啳啵啣啨 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啡啲啥 唌啬啩啮啧 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啡啧啡啩啮啳啴 啴啨啥 啬啡啷 啥啮啦啯啲啣啥啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啹 啴啨啡啴 啩啭啰啯啳啥啤 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啰啥啮啡啬啴啩啥啳 啯啮 啴啨啥啭 啦啯啲 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啻 啴啨啥 啵啮啤啥啲啬啹啩啮啧 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啬啥啤 啴啨啥啳啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳 啴啯 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啲啥 啮啯啴 啲啥啬啡啴啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啥 啬啡啷 啥啮啦啯啲啣啥啭啥啮啴 啡啧啥啮啣啹售 啂啥啣啡啵啳啥 啴啨啥 啫啥啹啷啯啲啤啳 啵啳啥啤 啦啯啲 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 啡啮啤 啦啯啲 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啡啲啥 啳啩啭啩啬啡啲 唨啹啥啴唬 啴啨啥啲啥 啡啲啥 啮啯 啯啶啥啲啬啡啰啰啩啮啧 啫啥啹啷啯啲啤啳售 啁啬啳啯唬 啴啯 啡啶啯啩啤 啣啯啮唍啩啣啴唬 啴啨啥 啫啥啹啷啯啲啤啳 啣啯啮啳啩啳啴 啯啦 啴啷啯 啯啲 啭啯啲啥 啷啯啲啤啳唬 啮啯啴 啡 啳啩啮啧啬啥 啷啯啲啤 啳啵啣啨 啡啳 啜信 访唢 啡啬啯啮啥唩唬 啡 啣啯啮啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啶啥 啡啰啰啲啯啡啣啨 啷啡啳 啴啡啫啥啮 啷啨啥啮 啣啯啤啩啮啧 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啷啩啴啨啩啮 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 啣啡啳啥啳售 啔啨啡啴 啩啳唬 啷啩啴啨啩啮 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 啣啡啳啥啳唬 啩啦 啴啨啥啲啥 啩啳 啩啮啦啯啲啭啡啴啩啯啮 啯啮 啴啨啥 啵啮啤啥啲啬啹啩啮啧 啡啤啭啩啮啩啳啴啲啡啴啩啶啥 啧啲啩啥啶啡啮啣啥啳 啴啨啡啴 啬啥啤 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴 啴啯 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮唬 啴啨啥啮 啳啵啣啨 啣啡啳啥啳 啨啡啶啥 啜唰唢 啩啮 啴啨啥啩啲 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啣啯啬啵啭啮啳售 啗啩啴啨 啴啨啩啳 啣啯啮啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啶啥 啡啰啰啲啯啡啣啨唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啳啴啩啬啬 啳啨啯啷啳 啡 啰啯啳啩啴啩啶啥 啡啮啤 啳啩啧啮啩唌啣啡啮啴 啣啯啲啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴售 Appendix C. Ruled or Not 啉啮 啴啨啥 啭啡啩啮 啡啲啴啩啣啬啥唬 啷啥 啤啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥 啷啡啳 啥啩啴啨啥啲 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啷啩啮 唨唱唩 啯啲 啬啯啳啳 唨唰唩售 啉啮 啴啨啩啳 啳啥啣啴啩啯啮唬 啷啥 啴啲啥啡啴 啴啨啥 啤啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴啬啹售 啎啯啷唬 啥啩啴啨啥啲 啧啯啶啥啲啮啭啥啮啴 啰啲啥啶啡啩啬啩啮啧 啯啲 啬啯啳啩啮啧 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啡啲啥 啣啯啤啥啤 啡啳 唱唬 啡啮啤 啴啨啥 啯啴啨啥啲 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啻 啤啩啳啭啩啳啳啡啬唬 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷啡啬唬 啡啮啤 啲啥啪啥啣啴啩啯啮 啻 啷啥啲啥 啣啯啤啥啤 啡啳 唰售 啔啡啢啬啥 唶 啳啨啯啷啳 啴啨啡啴 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳 啡啲啥 啭啯啲啥 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啢啥 啲啵啬啥啤 啢啹 啴啨啥 啪啵啤啧啥 啣啯啭啰啡啲啥啤 啴啯 啮啯啮唭啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啣啡啳啥啳售 啁啧啡啩啮唬 啴啨啥啳啥 啲啥啳啵啬啴啳 啡啲啥 啩啮 啰啡啲啴 啡啴啴啲啩啢啵啴啥啤 啴啯 啴啨啥 啴啲啡啩啴啳 啯啦 啴啨啥 啬啩啴啩啧啡啮啴啳唺 啴啨啯啳啥 啷啨啯 啤啩啤 啮啯啴 啳啴啯啰 啡啴 啴啨啥 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮 啳啴啡啧啥 啢啵啴 唌啬啥啤 啬啡啷啳啵啩啴啳 啡啧啡啩啮 啷啯啵啬啤 啢啥 啬啥啳啳 啬啩啫啥啬啹 啴啯 啷啩啴啨啤啲啡啷 啦啲啯啭 啴啨啥啩啲 啣啡啳啥啳售</figDesc><table><row><cell>啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓 啒啅商啅啒啅啎啃啅啓</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧 啂啡啩啫 啡啮啤 啙啡啮啧</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">商啩啧啵啲啥 唷唺 啔啲啩啡啬 啌啥啶啥啬 啡啮啤 啔啲啩啡啬 啒啥啳啵啬啴</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="9">啔啡啢啬啥 唵唺 啌啩啮啥啡啲 啒啥啧啲啥啳啳啩啯啮 啁啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啷啩啴啨 啒啯啢啵啳啴 啓啴啡啮啤啡啲啤 啅啲啲啯啲啳 唨唱唩</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="9">啔啡啢啬啥 唶唺 啌啩啮啥啡啲 啒啥啧啲啥啳啳啩啯啮 啁啮啡啬啹啳啩啳 啷啩啴啨 啒啯啢啵啳啴 啓啴啡啮啤啡啲啤 啅啲啲啯啲啳 唨唲唩</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="7">啄啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥唺 啇啯啶售 啗啩啮 唨唱唩 啯啲 啌啯啳啳 唨唰唩</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唱唩</cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唲唩</cell><cell cols="3">唨唳唩 啄啥啰啥啮啤啥啮啴 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥唺</cell><cell>唨唴唩</cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唵唩</cell></row><row><cell>啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤</cell><cell cols="2">唰售唱唲唵  *  *  *</cell><cell cols="6">唰售唱唳唴  *  *  *  唱唺 啇啯啶售 啗啩啮 啯啲 啌啯啳啳唬 唰唺 問啴啨啥啲 啒啥啳啵啬啴啳 唰售唱唴唵  *  *  *  唰售唰唶唶  *  *  *</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell>唨唱唩</cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell>唨唲唩</cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell>唨唳唩</cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唳唩</cell><cell>唨唴唩</cell></row><row><cell>啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤 啐啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啥啤</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">唰售唱唶唱  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell cols="2">唰售唱唶唴  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell cols="2">唰售唱唳唷  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell cols="3">唰售唰唹唳  *  *  *  唰售唰唴唰  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell></row><row><cell>唨啃啯啮啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啶啥唩</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唵唩</cell></row><row><cell>啔啲啩啡啬 啌啥啶啥啬 啔啲啩啡啬 啌啥啶啥啬</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">唰售唱唳唱  *  *  *  唰售唱唰唱  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唱唩</cell><cell cols="3">唰售唱唱唸  *  *  *  唰售唰唹唸  *  *  *  -唰售唰唱唹  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唱唩</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唴唩</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">啎啯啮唭啰啥啲啦啯啲啭啡啮啣啥 啎啯啮唭啰啥啲啦啯啲啭啡啮啣啥</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="6">-唰售唱唴唳  *  *  *  唰售唰唷唹  *  *  *  -唰售唱唳唱  *  *  *  唰售唰唶唵  *  *  *  -唰售唲唶唵  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唲唩 唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唳唩</cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唳唩</cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唲唸唩</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">啒啥啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啡啴啩啯啮 啒啥啣啯啮啳啩啤啥啲啡啴啩啯啮</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">唰售唰唹唹  *  *  *  唰售唲唸唰  *  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唱唩</cell><cell cols="3">唰售唰唷唳  *  *  *  唰售唲唵唱  *  *  *  唰售唰唱唱  *  *  唨唰售唰唰唱唩</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唲唩</cell><cell></cell><cell>唨唰售唰唰唵唩</cell></row><row><cell>啙啥啡啲 商啅</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell></cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell></cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell></cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell></row><row><cell>啙啥啡啲 商啅 啐啲啯啶啩啮啣啥 商啅</cell><cell></cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">啐啲啯啶啩啮啣啥 商啅 啇啯啶售 啌啥啶啥啬啳 商啅</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">啇啯啶售 啌啥啶啥啬啳 商啅 啄啩啳啰啵啴啥 啔啹啰啥 商啅</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啎啯</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell><cell>啙啥啳</cell></row><row><cell cols="11">All Observations 啎啯 唶唲唱唬唵唸唷 唶唲唰唬唲唶唹 N=271,177 Max 啎啯 Mean St. Dev. 唲唷唱唬唱唷唷 唲唷唰唬唸唰唱 唰售唰唱唱 唰售唰唲唶 唰售唰唰唹 唰售唰唳唸 唰售唰唱唱 唰售唰唲唶 1 0.144 0.351 1 0.384 0.486 唰售唴唷唶 唰售唴唶唹 唲唬唴唲唰售唹唳唷  *  *  *  Min 問啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳 啄啩啳啰啵啴啥 啔啹啰啥 商啅 Covariates 問啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳 啒 2 啁啤啪啵啳啴啥啤 啒 2 啁啤啪啵啳啴啥啤 啒 2 Nonperformance 0 Reconsideration 0 啒啥啳啩啤啵啡啬 啓售 啅售 商 啓啴啡啴啩啳啴啩啣 唳唰唹售唵唲唷  *  *  *  唷唰唱售唹唲唱  *  *  *  Petitioned Subset 啎啯 啙啥啳 唵唸唷唬唴唶唴 Not Petitioned Subset 啎唯啁 唵唸唷唬唴唶唴 N=41,640 N=229,537 Mean St. Dev. Mean 唲唶唶唬唳唱唹 唲唶唶唬唳唱唹 唱唶唬唳唴唶 唰售唱唰唱 唰售唱唶唳 唰售唰唹唷 唰售唱唵唱 唰售唰唴唰 唰售唱唰唱 唰售唱唶唳 St. Dev. 0.190 0.392 0.135 0.342 0.389 0.488 0.383 唰售唴唵唴 唰售唴唴唰 唰售唲唷唵 唷唴唳售唴唴唹  *  *  *  啒啥啳啩啤啵啡啬 啓售 啅售 唰售唴唹唳 唰售唴唹唰 唰售唴唷唲 唰售唴唵唶 唱唷售唸唷唹  *  *  *  商 啓啴啡啴啩啳啴啩啣 唶唬唷唶唸售唱唳唰  *  *  *  唴唶唵售唱唱唳  *  *  *  唱唬唶唱唷售唳唷唴  *  *  *  唱唬唷唸唲售唱唸唳  *  *  *  0.486 Compensation 0 1 0.132 0.339 0.245 0.430 0.112 0.315 啤啦 唱唻 唲唷唱唬唱唷唵 唳唵唻 唲唷唰唬唷唶唵 唴唱唻 唲唶唶唬唲唷唷 唶唴唻 唲唶唶唬唲唵唴 唴唰唻 唱唶唬唳唰唵 啤啦 唱唻 唶唲唱唬唵唸唵 唳唵唻 唶唲唰唬唲唳唳 唴唱唻 唵唸唷唬唴唲唲 唶唴唻 唵唸唷唬唳唹唹</cell></row><row><cell>Represented Note: Note:</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0.169</cell><cell cols="2">0.375</cell><cell>0.161</cell><cell cols="4">0.367  *  啰&lt;唰售唱唻  *  *  啰&lt;唰售唰唵唻  *  *  *  啰&lt;唰售唰唱 0.170 0.376</cell></row><row><cell>Third-party</cell><cell>0</cell><cell cols="9">1 啍啯啤啥啬 唨唵唩 啯啮啬啹 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥啳 啳啴啡啢啩啬啩啴啹 啭啡啩啮啴啥啮啡啮啣啥 唨Weiwen唩 啣啡啳啥啳 0.120 0.325 0.061 0.239 0.130 0.337</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">See the note from Table 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">唲唹 唳唰 唳唱 唳唲 唳唳</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>Note: The X-axis is the trial result. the Y-axis shows the proportion of each trial result within the firstand second-level trials.</p>Appendix B. Full Linear Regression Analysis</p>8 啔啡啢啬啥 唵 啳啨啯啷啳 啴啨啥 啬啩啮啥啡啲 啲啥啧啲啥啳啳啩啯啮 啲啥啳啵啬啴 啷啩啴啨 啲啯啢啵啳啴 啳啴啡啮啤啡啲啤 啥啲啲啯啲啳售 啍啯啤啥啬啳 唨唱唩 啴啨啲啯啵啧啨 唨唴唩 啩啮啣啬啵啤啥 啡啬啬 啯啢啳啥啲啶啡啴啩啯啮啳 啷啩啴啨 啤啩唋啥啲啥啮啴 啣啯啮啴啲啯啬 啶啡啲啩啡啢啬啥啳 啡啮啤 唌啸啥啤 啥唋啥啣啴啳售 啁啣啲啯啳啳 啴啨啥啳啥 啭啯啤啥啬啳唬 啰啥啴啩啴啩啯啮啩啮啧 啣啯啮啳啴啡啮啴啬啹 啳啨啯啷啳 啡 啰啯啳啩啴啩啶啥 啡啮啤 啳啴啡啴啩啳啴啩啣啡啬啬啹 啳啩啧啮啩唌啣啡啮啴 啣啯啲啲啥啬啡啴啩啯啮 啷啩啴啨 啴啨啥 啴啲啩啡啬 啲啥啳啵啬啴售 啔啨啡啴 啩啳唬 * 啰&lt;唰售唱唻 * * 啰&lt;唰售唰唵唻 * * * 啰&lt;唰售唰唱 唳唴</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Note that the actual percentage of petitioned cases is likely to be higher than 15.4 percent, as some rulings may not include the information on petitioning even when it happened. Nevertheless, we still assume that the cases where the rulings do mention petition take the act of petitioning seriously, thereby different from other cases. We further address the selection effect later in this paper.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
