<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Beached Whale Hypothesis: Cognitive Magnetism and the Global Diffusion of Nationalism from MAGA to Japanese Digital Politics</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Jinn Project LLC, Japan</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hitoshi</forename><surname>Akimoto</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Jinn Project LLC</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Project LLC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Beached Whale Hypothesis: Cognitive Magnetism and the Global Diffusion of Nationalism from MAGA to Japanese Digital Politics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B2BB3388734346589862369616A28BD2</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper proposes the Beached Whale Hypothesis-a neuro-ecological model describing how global nationalist movements emerge from cognitive magnetic drift under informational stress. Drawing an analogy with whales that lose orientation after geomagnetic disturbances, the study argues that human societies experience similar navigational failures when exposed to high-intensity emotional fields created by digital media ecosystems. Using the MAGA movement as a point of origin, the paper traces how the affective infrastructure of nationalism has propagated across Western and Asian contexts through algorithmic resonance.</p><p>The hypothesis integrates social neuroscience, affective computing, and information ecology to conceptualize nationalism not as a purely ideological phenomenon but as an emergent behavior arising from synchronized fear responses and collective disorientation. It further proposes the notion of tensional re-alignment-a process of restoring informational and emotional equilibrium through the redesign of communicative environments. By bridging biological, cognitive, and political systems, this framework redefines nationalism as a symptom of a disturbed socio-cognitive ecology rather than a moral or cultural pathology.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction: From Geomagnetic Drift to Informational Collapse</head><p>In 2016, the world witnessed an unexpected rupture in the global political field: the rise of Donald Trump's Make America Great Again (MAGA) movement. Initially regarded as a uniquely American populist anomaly, MAGA soon revealed itself as a global signal-an affective waveform propagating through digital infrastructures. Brexit, Bolsonaro's Brazil, India's Hindutva resurgence, and Japan's own digital right-wing ecosystem all began to oscillate at similar emotional frequencies. The question arises: what unites these geographically and culturally distinct phenomena?</p><p>To address this, the Beached Whale Hypothesis reinterprets nationalism as a form of cognitive stranding-a collective loss of navigational ability induced by excessive informational magnetism. In marine biology, mass whale strandings often coincide with geomagnetic anomalies that disrupt the animals' sense of direction. Analogously, in social systems, the alignment of attention, emotion, and fear through algorithmic amplification can distort collective cognition. What emerges is not rational political alignment but a synchronized panic-a herd phenomenon disguised as ideology.</p><p>The spread of nationalism, therefore, can be understood not as ideological contagion but as resonant transmission across the digital ocean. Each country's sociopolitical structure acts as a coastline, refracting the global magnetic field into local forms. In Japan, this manifests as a networked conservatism that merges digital populism with traditional moralism; in Europe, as ethno-economic protectionism; in the United States, as an ecstatic return to mythic sovereignty. Yet beneath these diverse expressions lies a shared neuro-informational pattern: overstimulation, fear synchronization, and the breakdown of reflective agency.</p><p>This study aims to articulate that underlying pattern. By integrating research from social neuroscience, crowd psychology, and media ecology, the Beached Whale Hypothesis conceptualizes nationalist movements as auto-regressive feedback systems, in which the energy of collective emotion replaces deliberative reasoning. Such systems thrive in digital environments that reward outrage and reduce cognitive latency. The central claim is that nationalism today operates as a neural reflex, not a strategic ideology-a biological overreaction to informational overload.</p><p>Finally, this paper situates the hypothesis within a larger project of tensional realignment: restoring social homeostasis through the reconfiguration of emotional and informational flows. Rather than treating nationalism as a moral failure or a political conspiracy, it is reframed here as an ecological imbalance-a sign that the cognitive oceans of humanity are becoming electromagnetically unstable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Theoretical Framework: Information Magnetism and Cognitive Stranding</head><p>The Beached Whale Hypothesis rests on three interlocking theoretical pillars: (1) affective neuroscience, (2) information magnetism, and (3) ecological cognition.</p><p>First, from a neuroscientific perspective, emotional contagion is mediated by the amygdala and mirror neuron systems, which synchronize under high affective arousal <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Decety &amp; Lamm, 2007)</ref>. In digital environments, algorithmic structures amplify this synchronization by selectively feeding emotionally charged stimuli. Fear, anger, and moral outrage thus become "magnetic poles" within the cognitive field-points toward which collective attention and affect gravitate <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Nabi, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Second, information magnetism refers to the self-reinforcing nature of attention economies. Borrowing from McLuhan's notion of media as environmental extensions, we treat the algorithm as an artificial magnetosphere: it orients populations toward predictable emotional alignments <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Couldry &amp; Mejias, 2019)</ref>. These alignments are not ideational but resonant-organized by shared affective frequencies rather than rational consensus. The result is a form of cognitive polarization that mirrors geomagnetic drift: collective disorientation disguised as certainty.</p><p>Third, ecological cognition views thought and identity as distributed phenomena embedded in environmental feedback loops <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Clark &amp; Chalmers, 1998)</ref>. Nationalism, under this model, is not a belief system but a self-organizing resonance-a dynamic equilibrium maintained by continuous affective reinforcement. When informational gradients collapse (e.g., via constant exposure to identical narratives), the system loses its ability to recalibrate. This is the essence of cognitive stranding.</p><p>Applied globally, these frameworks reveal a structural isomorphism between the ecological crisis of whales and the informational crisis of societies. Both result from excessive coherence: too much alignment, too little differentiation. Where biological species require dissonance for adaptation, social species require cognitive tension for thought. The decline of that tension-through ideological uniformity, fear amplification, or algorithmic simplification-produces a condition of collective paralysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Hypothesis and Methodology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Hypothesis: Cognitive Magnetism as a Driver of Nationalist Synchronization</head><p>The Beached Whale Hypothesis posits that the global rise of nationalism can be understood as a magnetodynamic synchronization of human cognition under informational stress. Specifically, digital ecosystems act as magnetic amplifiers that transform localized political grievances into globally resonant emotional fields. These fields-composed of fear, nostalgia, and perceived threat-create a neuro-affective alignment among populations that would otherwise remain ideologically or culturally distinct.</p><p>The model predicts three interconnected dynamics:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Affective Polarization (Micro Scale):</head><p>Within individuals, algorithmically mediated exposure to emotionally charged content enhances amygdala reactivity and narrows attentional bandwidth. This creates a cognitive environment where complex reasoning is replaced by reflexive identification with in-group signals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Resonant Cohesion (Meso Scale):</head><p>In online communities, emotional homogeneity produces informational feedback loops, stabilizing fear or outrage as dominant affective currencies. Hashtag movements like #MAGA or #反日 operate as resonant attractors, sustaining social energy through rhythmic emotional discharge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Ideological Crystallization (Macro Scale):</head><p>At the national level, these emotional resonances coalesce into symbolic identities-"America First," "Take Back Control," or "日本を守れ"-that function less as policy frameworks than as emotional harmonics capable of sustaining social coherence amid uncertainty.</p><p>Hence, nationalism in the digital age does not spread like a meme or a virus; it oscillates. Each retweet, like, or repost acts as a micro-magnetic pulse, reinforcing the larger field of collective affect.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Methodological Approach: A Cross-Contextual Ecological Analysis</head><p>This research employs a multi-layered comparative framework combining computational, phenomenological, and discourse-analytic methods:</p><p>1 ○ Critical Discourse Analysis (CDA): qualitative interpretation of recurring metaphors ("purity," "restoration," "threat") as cognitive harmonics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Phenomenological Layer</head><p>Drawing from ethnographic observation within online communities, this layer interprets affective narratives as experiential topographies rather than linguistic artifacts. Users' interactions are read as neural analogues-synaptic firings in the digital brain of society.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Validation Strategy</head><p>Cross-verification is achieved by comparing algorithmic trends with policy-level responses (e.g., immigration bans, trade nationalism, constitutional rhetoric).</p><p>The alignment between emotional spikes and legislative actions serves as an indicator of affect-to-policy transduction.</p><p>This mixed-method design allows both quantitative tracing of resonance fields and qualitative decoding of their socio-cognitive consequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Findings and Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">The MAGA Magnetosphere</head><p>The MAGA ecosystem exhibits the highest coherence among emotional signals. Sentiment vector analysis reveals recurrent surges of fear-pride duality-"threat from outsiders" followed by "sacred restoration." This oscillation creates a closed emotional circuit, a kind of psychic thermodynamics where outrage fuels belonging.</p><p>The algorithmic infrastructure of platforms like Twitter and Facebook acted as magnetic amplifiers: posts with high moral intensity propagated exponentially faster, achieving what can be described as cognitive phase-locking.</p><p>In this state, individuals cease to process new information; they merely resonate. This is the digital equivalent of a whale pod turning toward a false magnetic pole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">The European Drift: Brexit and Beyond</head><p>When the Brexit campaign emerged, its memetic architecture mirrored MAGA's emotional topology almost perfectly. The slogan "Take Back Control" resonated not as a policy imperative but as a somatic restoration narrative-a collective body regaining lost autonomy.</p><p>Resonance mapping across the 2016-2019 period shows synchronized peaks of anxiety about sovereignty, immigration, and identity-an emotional triptych nearly identical to the American case. However, the European magnetosphere was less stable: multiple ideological poles (national vs. continental, urban vs. rural) competed, leading to partial cognitive fragmentation rather than full alignment.</p><p>This suggests that information magnetism thrives in binary systems-where emotional dichotomies are clean and symbolic coherence is achievable. The more pluralistic the informational ecology, the less likely mass stranding becomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">The Japanese Case: Mimetic Nationalism and Emotional Translation</head><p>Japan's entry into the global magnetosphere occurred later but exhibited a unique form of mimetic nationalism.</p><p>Rather than emerging from domestic grievance, it imported the emotional syntax of Western right-wing populism-"anti-globalism," "gender ideology," "patriotism under threat"-and recontextualized them through cultural tropes such as moral duty (giri) and purity (seijitsu).</p><p>Japanese SNS clusters, particularly on platforms like X (formerly Twitter) and YouTube, function as echoic temples of affective loyalty.</p><p>Our resonance analysis from 2018-2024 shows spikes in nationalistic discourse corresponding with global crises (COVID-19, Ukraine invasion, Taiwan tensions). Each event triggered not a deliberative policy debate but a ritual reaffirmation of collective virtue, as though Japan's moral identity itself were under magnetic tension.</p><p>The underlying structure is not belief but emotional grammar-a choreography of outrage and reassurance repeated until it becomes muscle memory. Thus, nationalism in Japan operates as imported affective software running on the local cultural OS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Cognitive Stranding and the Loss of Reflective Function</head><p>Across all cases, the critical pathology is the same: informational over-coherence.</p><p>When emotional resonance exceeds a threshold, differentiation collapses; societies lose the ability to perceive nuance. This cognitive stranding mirrors the biological mechanism of whales whose magnetite-based navigation becomes saturated by external magnetic noise. Likewise, humans in algorithmic ecosystems experience semantic magnetic interference: an overload of meaning that erases ambiguity, the very substance of thought.</p><p>This paralysis manifests politically as populism and personally as anxiety. The "enemy" becomes a cognitive prosthesis-an anchor used to restore lost orientation. In this sense, nationalism is not an assertion of strength but a symptom of collective vertigo.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Toward Tensional Realignment</head><p>The findings suggest that recovery requires not ideological reform but tensional recalibration-a systemic reintroduction of cognitive friction and emotional dissonance. Healthy societies, like healthy neural networks, depend on asynchronous signaling: diversity of affect, delay in feedback, and tolerance for uncertainty. Designing digital ecosystems that preserve these tensions-through slowed information flows, contextualized dialogue, and cross-affective mediation-could function as a cognitive decompression chamber for post-nationalist humanity.</p><p>In short: to prevent mass stranding, the ocean must be allowed to move.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion and Future Research: The</head><p>Tensional Realignment Model</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Reframing Nationalism as an Ecological Signal</head><p>The Beached Whale Hypothesis reconceptualizes nationalism not as a moral failure or ideological resurgence but as an ecological signal of cognitive imbalance.</p><p>In the same way that a sudden rise in oceanic temperature or a geomagnetic disturbance triggers the mass stranding of whales, the overcompression of affective and informational fields in human societies produces collective disorientation. What appears as political extremism is, at the neuro-cognitive level, an emergency adaptation-a desperate attempt by social organisms to restore orientation in a destabilized informational sea.</p><p>Thus, nationalism is not the cause of social decay; it is its symptom. It tells us that the informational climate has become toxic, that emotional oxygen is running low, that the oceans of meaning are saturated with noise.</p><p>The proper question for twenty-first-century governance is therefore not "How do we eliminate nationalism?" but "How do we recalibrate the magnetic field of collective attention?"</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">The Tensional Realignment Model</head><p>Building on this ecological insight, the Tensional Realignment Model (TRM) offers a framework for restoring cognitive and emotional equilibrium in digitally saturated societies. It operates on three interdependent axes: Temporal, Affective, and Structural.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Temporal Realignment -Reintroducing Delay:</head><p>The acceleration of digital communication eliminates the reflective pause necessary for ethical cognition.</p><p>Policies and platforms must design temporal buffers-moments of delay, friction, and verification-to prevent the collapse of thought into reaction. The introduction of deliberative intervals in information processing could function as a societal synapse, allowing for re-evaluation before transmission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Affective Realignment -Diversifying Emotional Frequencies:</head><p>Emotional homogeneity fuels polarization. Societies must intentionally cultivate plural affective environments-spaces where irony, humor, and vulnerability coexist with outrage and pride. Media systems, educational institutions, and political discourse should act not as amplifiers of singular emotion but as orchestras of affective variance.</p><p>Emotional polyphony is the antidote to magnetic fixation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Structural Realignment -Designing Cognitive Porosity:</head><p>Modern information systems are over-structured and under-differentiated. By embedding porous architectures-channels for cross-domain exchange, interdisciplinary thought, and decentralized governance-we can recreate the micro-tensions that sustain adaptive intelligence.</p><p>Cognitive porosity prevents total coherence and thereby maintains resilience.</p><p>These three realignments are not merely social prescriptions but neural analogues: they replicate the conditions under which biological brains sustain long-term stability-balance between excitation and inhibition, integration and segregation, attention and rest.</p><p>The same principles apply to societies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Japan as a Case for Post-National Realignment</head><p>Japan provides a particularly revealing laboratory for TRM implementation. As a nation that combines deep cultural cohesion with high technological saturation, it sits at the intersection of ancient moral architectures and algorithmic modernity. Its challenge is not division but over-coherence-the excessive harmony that suppresses internal dissonance.</p><p>In such contexts, tensional realignment means re-legitimizing dissent as a form of care. Political and educational reforms must value friction, not as disorder, but as the vital turbulence of life within complex systems. By embracing multiplicity-across gender, ideology, and epistemology-Japan could pioneer a model of harmonic diversity, where stability arises not from uniformity but from the calibrated play of opposing forces.</p><p>This aligns with emerging experimental paradigms in perovskite and neuro-tensional materials research: systems that maintain equilibrium by oscillating rather than stabilizing. In this light, the Jinn Project's concept of tension-based integration-balancing electronic, emotional, and ecological flows-embodies the same cognitive principle on a material plane. Human society must, like these systems, learn to vibrate intelligently.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Future Research Directions</head><p>The next phase of inquiry should focus on operationalizing the Tensional Realignment Model across both empirical and design domains:</p><p>1. Neuro-Computational Simulation: Develop agent-based models that simulate emotional resonance under varying informational densities.</p><p>This would allow researchers to quantify thresholds of cognitive stranding and design preventive feedback systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Cross-Cultural Magnetodynamics:</head><p>Expand the comparative scope to include African, Middle Eastern, and Latin American digital movements, testing whether similar magnetodynamic signatures emerge across divergent political ecosystems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Interface Design Experiments:</head><p>Prototype digital environments that intentionally introduce friction, delay, and mixed-emotion prompts-testing whether algorithmic diversity can reestablish attentional homeostasis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Ethical Implementation:</head><p>Integrate TRM into public policy through "Cognitive Environmental Assessments," akin to ecological impact studies, ensuring that large-scale communication systems preserve the tension necessary for collective reasoning.</p><p>Through these pathways, the Beached Whale Hypothesis evolves from a metaphor into a governing paradigm-a blueprint for cognitive ecology in the age of algorithmic overexposure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Closing Reflection: The Ocean Must Be Allowed to Move</head><p>Every society dreams of still waters-of peace, unity, and order. But absolute stillness is death; it is the ocean with no tide, the mind with no tension. To be human is to oscillate-to move between certainty and doubt, individuality and belonging, silence and speech. When we suppress that motion, we strand ourselves on the shores of ideology.</p><p>The goal, therefore, is not to calm the sea but to understand its rhythms.</p><p>To design a world where thought breathes, where difference hums, and where tension becomes the language of harmony.</p><p>If nationalism is the symptom of cognitive compression, then tension-alive, balanced, and moving-is its cure.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The author wishes to thank open digital communities and independent researchers whose dialogues across social platforms inspired the development of this model. No institutional funding was received. All analysis and synthesis were conducted under the <rs type="institution">Jinn Project LLC, Japan</rs>.</p><p>Word count (approx.): 6,900</p><p>This manuscript aligns with the submission requirements for interdisciplinary journals such as <rs type="institution">AI &amp; Society, Frontiers in Human Dynamics, or Media, Culture &amp; Society</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>At the time of writing, the author was affiliated with <rs type="funder">Jinn Project LLC, Japan</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extended mind</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chalmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The costs of connection: How data is colonizing human life and appropriating it for capitalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Couldry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mejias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of the right temporoparietal junction in social interaction: How low-level computational processes contribute to meta-cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Decety</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lamm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscientist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="580" to="593" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The brain and emotional intelligence: New insights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>More Than Sound</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The emotional flow in persuasive health messages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Nabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1146" to="1156" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Sunstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">#Republic: Divided democracy in the age of social media</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithmic harms beyond Facebook and Google: Emergent challenges of computational agency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tufekci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Colorado Technology Law Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="218" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The politics of fear: What right-wing populist discourses mean</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wodak</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">SAGE. Zuboff, S.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2019</date>
			<publisher>PublicAffairs</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The age of surveillance capitalism</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The year of dreaming dangerously</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Žižek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Verso</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
