<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Global Perspectives from the Development Engagement Lab&apos;s Database</title>
				<funder ref="#_tggnYSP">
					<orgName type="full">Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_fdjRWtt">
					<orgName type="full">Gates Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">German Institute</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-10-01">October 1, 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Felipe</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">London School of Economics and Political Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Soomin</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Birmingham</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Birmingham</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University College London</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Paolo</forename><surname>Morini</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">King&apos;s College London</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Global Perspectives from the Development Engagement Lab&apos;s Database</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-10-01">October 1, 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">12E42E7FE6C5180494185834154E8070</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Public support is crucial for shaping effective development and foreign aid policies. The Development Engagement Lab (DEL) has conducted comprehensive surveys in France, Germany, Great Britain, and the U.S. to track and analyse public attitudes on foreign aid and engagement with sustainable development. This data descriptor presents multiple datasets curated by DEL, identifying shifts in public opinion and behaviour, alongside underlying mechanisms explaining these attitudes and actions. DEL's data comprises nationally representative panel data (2019 -2023), repeated cross-sections (2019 -2024), and several foreign aid subject-specific datasets. DEL has made available 87 datasets totalling 246,352 observations from 129,128 unique respondents. We have developed an R package, DELdata, to facilitate the use and dissemination of these datasets. DEL data will enable scholars and policymakers to produce valuable insights that will generate a better understanding of how citizens think about, and engage with, global poverty and sustainable development.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Backgroud and summary</head><p>Public support is essential for the quantity and quality of foreign aid spending, development policy, programming, and international cooperation. Although foreign aid is financed by the public purse through taxpayer contributions, and is subject to government approval and oversight, aid is spent in support of non-tax-paying citizens of other countries. This tension has been recognised by both policymakers and academics <ref type="bibr">(Mosley, 1985</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">, Baum and Potter, 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">, Heinrich and Kobayashi, 2020</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">, Kiratli, 2020)</ref>, who have long-argued that public support allows political elites to operate more effectively within a contested political space.</p><p>Direct action from the public, including through donations, activism, or volunteering, also supports and legitimises the work of international development NGOs, who can advocate for further government efforts or who can deliver aid and support to developing countries directly as well <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Darnton and</ref><ref type="bibr">Kirk, 2011, Micklewright and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Wright, 2005)</ref>.</p><p>As we approach the 2030 Sustainable Development Goals deadline, citizens' understanding of, and engagement with, development efforts will be a critical part of advancing and addressing global issues such as ending extreme poverty to achieving gender equality worldwide. Contemporary global and national events such as soaring inflation, refugee crises, and international conflict are shaping people's attitudes towards helping distant strangers in different ways. On the one hand, we witness increases in charitable donations in some countries <ref type="bibr">(Charities Aid Foundation, 2023</ref>); and at the same time, we have also seen public support for development cooperation falling significantly <ref type="bibr">(Development Compass, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>The Development Engagement Lab (DEL) Database is the first publicly available, comprehensive source of longitudinal and cross-sectional data on key donor countries' attitudes and engagement with global poverty. We collected these data through a series of dedicated surveys and experiments described below. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> A key feature of DEL data is the multidimensional measures of key indicators, for example, measuring the general concept of support for development as a set of attitudinal indicators ranging from 'concern about levels of poverty in poor countries' to 'support for current levels or increases in aid expenditures', and to 'support for giving aid in the national interest or for altruistic reasons'.</p><p>Beyond public attitudes, the data also allow for exploring and understanding public engagement with global poverty and development through respondents' self-reported behaviours. The data include ten key indicators capturing actions the public take to tackle global poverty, lobby government, or support international NGOs. This battery is used to segment respondents into six groups -Negatively Engaged, Totally Disengaged, Marginally Engaged, Transactionally Engaged, Purposively Engaged, and Fully Engaged <ref type="bibr">(Hudson et al., 2020)</ref>. This audience segmentation helps us understand the characteristics of individuals We expect researchers in the fields of public opinion, foreign aid, and sustainable development will be able to take advantage of the granularity and richness of DEL data to shed new light on citizen's preferences, attitudes, and behaviours towards global challenges and development cooperation-related issues. One of the advantages of DEL's data is the large sample sizes and its panel structure. The richness of the data allows for sufficiently-powered sub-group analysis of certain segments of the population and to monitor change over time, as well as allowing researchers to leverage the temporal structure of the data using dynamic and latent class models. This is helpful not only for researchers to understand what drives changes in public opinion and engagement, as well as development NGOs and charities who need deep insights to target key audiences and drive change.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>The DEL project (2019-2024) is a collaboration between University College London and the University of Birmingham funded by the Gates Foundation (1199734). DEL's is an independent reseach organisation charged with generating data, robust research, and evidence and insights on how donor publics engage with global poverty, sustainable development and international cooperation. To achieve this goal, our team developed three approaches to gather evidence on these topics: 1) track both short-and long-term changes in attitudes and behaviours over time, 2) identify the factors driving changes in public attitudes and behaviours within different groups and across countries, and 3) assess people's preferences, perceptions, beliefs, and expectations to long-standing global challenges, and investigating public preferences to tackle these through personal actions or through the work of governments and other non-governmental organisations.</p><p>Over the course of the DEL project, we conducted 87 online surveys in France, Germany, Great Britain<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">foot_1</ref> and the United States, collecting 246,352 observations from 129,128 unique respondents. Table <ref type="table">1</ref> provides additional information on the data collection for three types Panel. To capture long-term changes in attitudes and behaviour over time as well as key mediators, we developed a panel survey including 47 fixed questions and a varying number of context-specific questions. We collected panel survey data once a year between 2019 and 2023 in each of the four countries, yielding 20 panel datasets. The fixed questions section includes an extensive battery of items aimed at eliciting, among many issues, individuals' support for aid, charitable donations to international NGOs, perceptions of the costs and benefits of aid, attitudes towards migration, and questions on economic outlook and trust.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">2</ref> in the appendix provides a full breakdown of all the questions in the Panel. The year-specific questions section contains a bespoke battery of items responsively developed in collaboration with the project's stakeholders -over 40 international development NGOs and government ministries -in collaboration with our research team. For instance, in the 2023 survey, we embedded a conjoint experiment to get a more nuanced understanding of which dimensions of aid projects (including purpose and region, to name a few) matter more for public support of aid projects <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">4</ref> In 2021, we explored in-depth the features of NGOs make respondents more likely to donate (including the size of the NGOs, location of the headquarters, and issue worked on). The results of this conjoint experiment are shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Size Headquarters Region Programming 0 . 4 0 0 . 4 5 0 . 5 0 0 . 5 5 0 . 6 0 Large NGO/charity Small NGO/charity Headquarters in the UK Headquarters in a poor country Eastern Europe/Central Asia Sub-Saharan Africa Middle East and North Africa South Asia/Southeast Asia Latin America Water, sanitation and hygiene Women and girls Education Health A range of issues Marginal means Significant Not significant Note: This figure shows the marginal means of all levels within each attribute of a forced-choice conjoint experiment included in Wave 3 in Great Britain. Respondents were presented with two profiles of NGOs. Exact wording of the question and response options are in the appendix.</p><p>Each year, we collected nationally representative samples using YouGov's Plc online panels. The sample sizes ranged from at least 6,000 observations in France, Germany, and the United States to at least 8,000 in Great Britain. We systematically collected all Panel waves between September through October/November of each year. In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">5</ref> in the appendix, we summarise the data collection dates, sample size, and retention rates of the data. All surveys include survey weights to yield nationally representative samples. Table <ref type="table">10</ref> in the appendix provides a visual metric of the depth of the topics covered in each country and wave.</p><p>Panel is an unbalanced panel where, on average, across all countries, the retention of the original first wave respondents gradually decreases from 70% in second wave to 39%</p><p>in the fifth and final wave in 2023. Samples were topped up with new respondents to keep sample sizes consistent in size over the waves. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">7</ref> in the appendix shows the aggregate retention rate pooling all countries together. Looking at each country individually, we find similar retention rates, except for Great Britain, where dropout rates are considerably lower than the other three countries. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">5</ref> This level of attrition falls within the expected dropout rates in longitudinal studies that range from 30 to 70% Lugtig (2014), <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Gustavson et al. (2012)</ref>. Table <ref type="table">11</ref> in the Appendix summarises some key demographics included in Panel.</p><p>Tracker. In addition to the annual longitudinal panel survey, we collected two smaller repeated cross-sectional samples each year capturing key attitudinal and behavioural indicators. These data aim to identify and highlight higher frequency changes in public engagement, especially around key events and changes in the political, economic, and social landscapes. Tracker data were collected through a reduced 20-question survey drawn from the larger Panel instrument, implemented in all four countries from 2019 until 2024 (10 waves). <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">6</ref> This means for these 20 items we effectively have three data points per year. Sample sizes for German, French, and American Tracker surveys are at least 1,000 responses, with larger samples of 2,000 respondents available for some samples in Great Britain. Table <ref type="table">3</ref> in the appendix summarises details of these samples, including collection dates and sample sizes. levels of development aid expenditure.</p><p>Table 12 in the Appendix summarises some key demographics included in Tracker. 66 64 60 46 70 68 59 47 65 65 54 45 67 66 61 44 69 67 53 44 68 67 54 53 66 64 57 53 68 67 56 53 66 61 54 56 65 59 59 50 62 58 54 48 65 58 54 51 60 55 56 51 58 47 57 52 50 60 Sandbox. Sandboxes are the responsive component of the DEL project. Sandboxes are deep dives into specific topics of interest connected to the main question of public engagement with sustainable development, identified and developed in collaboration with project stakeholders across the four DEL countries. Throughout the DEL project, we conducted 27 surveys examining topics ranging from citizens' beliefs and responses to the Syrian refugee crisis to global gender (in)equality. The frequency of Sandboxes varied from year to year and country, driven by research priorities. For example, we conducted 9 Sandboxes in France and 5 in the U.S. Most Sandboxes have a minimum and typical sample size of 2,000 responses,</p><p>but for specific studies, this is much larger, up to 5,591 for a U.S. sample. Table <ref type="table">4</ref> in the appendix provides information on the data collection dates, sample sizes of these surveys, and themes covered.</p><p>In these deep dives, we frequently used experimental designs to investigate citizens' attitudes towards addressing humanitarian crises, war/conflict or tackling global challenges.</p><p>For example, in 2022, we studied how citizens in Great Britain were engaging with the conflict in Ukraine, seeking to understand, among other key questions, whether respondents were willing to reallocate financial aid and donations from humanitarian crises in Africa and the Middle East to support Ukraine. In 2021, we looked at U.S. citizens' engagement with security as a key question for international cooperation, including public support for withdrawing their military forces from Afghanistan, and whether the public deemed the primary role of foreign aid spending as an important instrument to promote global stability.</p><p>In Table <ref type="table">8</ref> in the appendix we provide further information on the topics covered in these surveys.</p><p>We also frequently used Sandboxes to test the effectiveness of different messages and forms of communication with the public, to create evidence informing charities', NGOs' and governments' campaigning, education, engagement efforts. In these surveys, we investigated the the role of different "frames" and "narratives" and how they impacted on support for development actors or policies. For example, in 2023, across all four DEL countries, we tested how public attitudes varied using different ways of framing gender equality.</p><p>Another recurring theme across Sandboxes is the role of imagery in campaigning efforts.</p><p>In light of the rapid growth of digital photography, the internet, and social media, images and video content have become one of the primary sources through which citizens consume political information <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Banducci and Karp, 2016</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">, Bennett and Iyengar, 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">, Entman, 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">, Hindman, 2018)</ref>. In Sandboxes conducted in 2021 and 2023, we investigated the role of images and videos as a medium to encourage citizen engagement with aid appeals and impact on charitable donations.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">foot_6</ref> </p><p>Pre-Harmonisation and Survey Design. To ensure cross-linguistic comparability, the survey questionnaires were initially developed in (British) English. The harmonisation involved translation by qualified professionals. In Germany, translations are handled initially by YouGov Plc's translators, followed by verification by DEL's local German consultant team for linguistic, semantic, and technical accuracy. In the case of France, DEL's French con-sultants took the lead in the translation, with YouGov Plc providing an additional check.</p><p>Finally, for the U.S. surveys, the DEL team adapted the questionnaire to match American terminology and writing conventions.</p><p>We have followed several practices to improve the quality of data collected through online surveys. We simplified the wording and length of the surveys to reduce survey fatigue<ref type="foot" target="#foot_7">foot_7</ref> .</p><p>We randomised item order within question batteries, including when asking respondents to rank different options, and we systematically aimed to ease cognitively demanding question batteries by limiting the number of items and response options. We actively avoided including double-barrelled, vague, or all-or-nothing types of questions <ref type="bibr">(Stantcheva, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>For unipolar and bipolar items, we consistently used a small but sufficient number of categories, still obtaining sufficient variation in respondents' answers <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Dillman et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Cross survey contamination between Trackers and Panels was also low, as out of 40,605 respondents that answered Trackers across the four countries, only 8,561 were also included in the Panels. We provide further detail about the different quality controls we underwent in the technical validation section of this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Records</head><p>DEL data comprises an unprecedented collection of datasets for France, Germany, Great</p><p>Britain and the United States, four major development aid donors from 2019 until 2023<ref type="foot" target="#foot_8">foot_8</ref> . All datasets include a unique identifier for each respondent, making it easy for researchers to link respondents to previous or subsequent waves or to merge different data types.</p><p>All datasets are available in .sav format. These files can be read using R, Python, SPSS, and Stata statistical software. A survey questionnaire text file accompanies each dataset.</p><p>The survey questionnaires also include information on the coding protocol for each answer option and, if applicable, any randomisation or split sample procedures. We also provide a codebook for each dataset in table format. The codebooks provide extensive details of all the variables in each dataset, such as numerical codes for all questions and numeric values for missing/don't know or prefer not to say answers. We complement these files with a data table file that provides summary statistics for key selected variables. We also make available a readme file that summarises some of the meta-data of each dataset, such as the type of data, the topics covered, the fieldwork dates, and the sample size.</p><p>Interested parties can download all these files, freely available for non-commercial use, from the DEL's Harvard Dataverse: <ref type="url" target="https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/devengagement">https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/devengagement</ref>.</p><p>We separated the datasets into three Dataverses: Panels, Trackers, and Sandboxes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R Data Package</head><p>We also created an R Package called DELdata to facilitate access to the DEL database. Researchers using DELdata can easily load datasets from the DEL repository using very few commands. We also made additional documentation of this package available through Github: <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/ftraposo/DELdata/tree/gh-pages">https://github.com/ftraposo/DELdata/tree/gh-pages</ref>. We also include a vignette that explains how researchers can load the data into an R session. The vignette is available at <ref type="url" target="https://ftraposo.github.io/DELdata/docs/reference/get_del_data.html">https://ftraposo.github.io/DELdata/docs/reference/get_del_data.html</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Technical Validation</head><p>We employed several strategies to validate the data throughout the survey design and data collection life cycle. Before rolling out the surveys, we pre-tested the questionnaires amongst the DEL research team in collaboration with consultants from all participating countries. This test ensured that the survey features, such as question randomisation, skip logic, and answer recording, were functioning correctly and consistently. Country consultants' participation was essential to highlight and resolve any issues with the translation and wording of the questions, both for country-specific surveys and for those we fielded in multiple geographies to allow for cross-country comparisons. In collaboration with YouGov research managers, we also conducted extensive pre-testing to ensure that all the survey questions were appropriately displayed, particularly for experiments containing complex randomisation of information or response options displayed or those question modules which employed imagery or large amounts of text.</p><p>Once the DEL team approved the questionnaire, we piloted the surveys using small samples of around 100 respondents. In these pilots, we checked the numeric codes in the data</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Usage Notes</head><p>Academic Usage The benefits of longitudinal data should allow scholars to unlock new modelling approaches using dynamic data. A more comprehensive set of questions is essential to unlocking factor/latent class analysis (LCA) approaches to capture constructs better.</p><p>The current literature on public engagement with development and aid has been the lack of robust measures of public support for foreign aid <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Hudson and vanHeerde Hudson, 2012)</ref>, which would allow for accurate estimates of latent public opinion. DEL data allows for departing the existing single-question indicators and provide an unbiased, efficient underlying measure of foreign aid support<ref type="foot" target="#foot_9">foot_9</ref> .</p><p>Country-level indexes have been widely used to compare countries in specific dimensions such as corruption, democracy, and governance. DEL data and surveys can serve as templates for researchers interested in constructing a country-level foreign aid support index. Some of these indexes combine country-expert surveys with nationally representative surveys. With these new data available, researchers in the future could use the numerous items included in the 83 surveys to construct new forms of these indexes.</p><p>Pedagogical Usage Given its depth and structure, DEL data can also be an important pedagogical tool. Instructors of quantitative methods courses can use the data to teach introductory concepts such as regression analysis and hypothesis testing or more advanced methodologies such as panel data estimation or conjoint experiments. The data also allow researchers to conduct multivariate analyses. Instructors can teach students the different methods to measure unobservable underlying traits, including principal component analysis and item response theory, as the data contains several sets of items that aim to capture specific constructs such as morality, social norms, and perceptions of personal or aid effectiveness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NGO Usage</head><p>As DEL project stakeholders, international development NGOs have relied on DEL data to gain insight into the evolution of public attitudes and values around global poverty, development, and international cooperation and the factors that shape these atti-tudes. These data and insights can be used by users from the third sector and development agencies to improve advocacy, messaging, and communications strategies. In particular, these insights can provide evidence on the frames, messages, and messengers that resonate or are more persuasive for donor publics. Our analysis of messengers <ref type="bibr">(Hudson et al., 2020)</ref> is an example of where the data have proved particularly useful for NGOs and development agencies. Moreover, data and research around what attributes of campaign images lead to a greater sense of activation, efficacy, and urgency have been communicated to and used by international development NGOs(Oh et al., 2023) Table 4: Details Sandboxes Data Country Year Collection period Sample France 2019 8 to 30 May 2019 2020 5 to 13 February 2020 21 to 28 July 2021 30 April to 5 May 2021 5 to 10 August 2022 13 to 21 Jan 2022 7 to 15 June 2023 20 Feb to 1 Mar 2023 19 to 25 May Germany 2020 7 to 14 February 2020 15 to 23 July 2021 28 July to 3 Aug 2022 11 to 23 Mar 2022 22 to 29 June 2023 17 to 28 Feb 2023 10 to 16 October Great Britain 2020 26 to 17 Apr 2020 7 to 13 July 2021 11 to 18 June 2022 23 to 28 June 2023 20 to 28 Feb 2023 9 to 18 Oct United States 2020 28 May to 1st June 2020 10 to 14 July 2021 6 to 22 Sep 2023 21 to 24 Feb 2023 11 to 16 October Note: This table reports the collection times, sample size, retention rates, and retention samples of Sandboxes for all countries from the first round in 2019 until the last round in 2023.   Table 9: Topics covered across tracker surveys Country Topics France Areas of concern, SDGs, sense of connectedness, donation, concern for poverty and development, attitudes on aid, efficacy, refugees, battery of engagement GB Areas of concern, perception on state of the world, sense of connectedness, donation, concern for poverty and development, attitudes on aid, efficacy, trust in NGOs, battery of engagement Germany Areas of concern,donation, concern for poverty and development, arguments for aid, attitudes on aid, efficacy, trust in NGOs, battery of engagement US Areas of concern, perception on state of the world, sense of connectedness, donation, concern for poverty and development, attitudes on aid, efficacy, trust in NGOs  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>who take specific actions over others, how to communicate with them, and what 'drives' their actions. DEL data broadens the scope of research into public engagement with global poverty and sustainable development both methodologically and substantively. Methodologically, the Development Engagement Lab team have made use of a range of experimental approachese.g. survey, conjoint, and list experiments -aimed at teasing out people's preferences, beliefs, heuristics, and knowledge around a wide-range of development issues and the factors that affect these. Substantively, DEL data also provides deep dives into a broader set of thematic issues of importance for the development sector. Some issues are covered through ad-hoc surveys and experiments include public perceptions and engagement with climate change, COVID-19, global gender (in)equality and feminist development policy, and global conflicts, including the war in Ukraine.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure</head><figDesc>Figure 1: Small and Large NGOs Experiment</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 illustrates how Panel and Trackers datasets can be merged into a single file to examine long-term trends in levels of public support for aid. This figure shows the percentage of respondents who say they would like their government to keep or increase the current</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure</head><figDesc>Figure 2: Trend Support for Foreign Aid</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Note:</head><figDesc>The topics covered in the respective country's trackers are consistent across all trackers as it tracks individuals' attitudes over time, three times a year.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Details Panel DataThis table reports the collection times, sample size, retention rates, and retention samples of Panel for all countries from the first round in 2019 until the last round in 2023.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Country</cell><cell>Year</cell><cell>Collection Period</cell><cell>Sample</cell><cell>Sample retention</cell><cell>Retention rate (%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2019 27 September to 19 October</cell><cell>6073</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2020 21 September to 12 October</cell><cell>6001</cell><cell>4173</cell><cell>69</cell></row><row><cell>France</cell><cell cols="2">2021 24 September to 22 October</cell><cell>6106</cell><cell>3603</cell><cell>59</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2022 30 September to 4 November</cell><cell>6051</cell><cell>2668</cell><cell>44</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2023 15 September to 23 October</cell><cell>6028</cell><cell>2211</cell><cell>36</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2019 24 September to 10 October</cell><cell>6004</cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2020 10 September to 13 October</cell><cell>6000</cell><cell>4296</cell><cell>72</cell></row><row><cell>Germany</cell><cell cols="2">2021 22 September to 22 October</cell><cell>6000</cell><cell>3733</cell><cell>62</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2022 30 September to 3 November</cell><cell>6008</cell><cell>2665</cell><cell>44</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2023 19 September to 23 October</cell><cell>6050</cell><cell>2189</cell><cell>36</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2019 18 September to 10 October</cell><cell>8037</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2020 10 September to 12 October</cell><cell>8079</cell><cell>5932</cell><cell>74</cell></row><row><cell>Great Britain</cell><cell cols="2">2021 23 September to 25 October</cell><cell>8281</cell><cell>4456</cell><cell>55</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2022 30 September to 28 October</cell><cell>8008</cell><cell>3880</cell><cell>48</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2023 15 September to 18 October</cell><cell>8018</cell><cell>3680</cell><cell>46</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2019 20 September to 9 October</cell><cell>6004</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2020 11 September to 18 October</cell><cell>6018</cell><cell>3811</cell><cell>63</cell></row><row><cell>United States</cell><cell cols="2">2021 23 September to 27 October</cell><cell>6112</cell><cell>2680</cell><cell>45</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2022 30 September to 24 October</cell><cell>6102</cell><cell>2508</cell><cell>42</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2023 15 September to 16 October</cell><cell>6095</cell><cell>2178</cell><cell>36</cell></row></table><note><p>Note:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Retention rates Wave by Wave (%)This table reports the retention rates for subsequent waves for all countries.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Waves</cell><cell cols="4">France Germany Great United</cell></row><row><cell>Wave 1 -Wave 2</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>72</cell><cell>74</cell><cell>63</cell></row><row><cell>Wave 2 -Wave 3</cell><cell>72</cell><cell>68</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>52</cell></row><row><cell>Wave 3 -Wave 4</cell><cell>62</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>65</cell></row><row><cell>Wave 4 -Wave 5</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>61</cell></row></table><note><p>Note:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Retention rates Panel</figDesc><table><row><cell>Wave</cell><cell>Sample</cell><cell>Retention rate (%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(All countries)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Wave 1</cell><cell>26118</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Wave 2</cell><cell>18212</cell><cell>70</cell></row><row><cell>Wave 3</cell><cell>14472</cell><cell>55</cell></row><row><cell>Wave 4</cell><cell>11721</cell><cell>45</cell></row><row><cell>Wave 5</cell><cell>10258</cell><cell>39</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: This table reports the total sample from Panel by wave, aggregating all four countries. It also provides the retention rate by wave.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Demographics -TrackersCountryWave 1 Wave 2 Wave 3 Wave 4 Wave 5 Wave 6 Wave 7 Wave 8 Wave 9 Wave 10</figDesc><table><row><cell>Gender (Proportion of Women)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>France</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.02)</cell><cell>(0.02)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell></row><row><cell>Germany</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.50</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell></row><row><cell>Great Britain</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell></row><row><cell>United States</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.51</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.52</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell><cell>(0.01)</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>For more background on the Development Engagement Lab, including the team, history, blogs, reports, and other materials please go to https://developmentengagementlab.org/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Technically, it is Great Britain and not the UK as YouGov does not survey in Northern Ireland</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Forthcoming paper<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hudson et al. (2024)</ref> </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_3"><p>See Table5in the appendix reports the find retention rates by country. Table</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_4"><p>in the appendix reports the retention rates between two subsequent waves by country.6  For the U.S., we only collected ten questions from the Panel instrument that capture attitudes towards foreign aid.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="70" xml:id="foot_5"><p>2019-9 2020-01 2020-06 2020-10 2021-01 2021-06 2021-10 2022-01 2022-06 2022-10 2023-01 2023-06 2023-10 2024-01 country France Germany Great Britain United StatesNote: This figure shows the average level of support for foreign aid in all four countries. We measured support for overseas aid if respondents wanted to maintain or increase the money their government spends on overseas aid. Estimates are weighted to be nationally representative. Exact wording of the question and response options are in the appendix.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_6"><p>The imagery and video content used in these studies will not made available, as we do not have authorisation to share them with third parties.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_7"><p>We also used split sampling approaches whenever we needed to increase the number of questions while keeping the overall length of the survey fixed.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_8"><p>These countries are some of the largest donors by aid volume in the OECD Development Assistance Committee, see: https://www.oecd.org/en/data/indicators/net-oda.html?oecdcontrol-03506f24e9-chartId= bb70a1f537</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_9"><p>This approach has shown promise in the research of scholars in other fields such as on European integration (di Vettimo, 2022), or polarisation in the U.S.(Zhou, 2019)   </p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We acknowledge the generous support of the <rs type="funder">Gates Foundation</rs> (Research Grant number: <rs type="grantNumber">OPPID1199734</rs>). We also recognise the contribution of research assistants <rs type="person">Yu Xuan Cheng</rs> and <rs type="person">Clementine Bachelart</rs>, who helped us clean, organise, and audit the data deposit process. We would also like to thank <rs type="person">Marianne C. Stewart</rs>, <rs type="person">Harold D. Clarke</rs>, <rs type="person">Tom Black</rs>, <rs type="person">Kate Davies</rs>, <rs type="person">David Cantor</rs>, <rs type="person">Joe Twyman</rs>, <rs type="person">Tanya Abraham</rs>, <rs type="person">Fabrice Ferrier</rs>, <rs type="person">Arnaud Gaillard</rs>, <rs type="person">Will Tucker</rs>, <rs type="person">Molly Anders</rs>, <rs type="person">Sylvie Hahn</rs>, <rs type="person">Sergius Seebohm</rs>, the <rs type="funder">German Institute</rs> for Development Evaluation, and DEL interns who have contributed to the development of DEL data, research, and insights. We acknowledge <rs type="institution">Harvard Dataverse</rs> for providing an easy-access, user-friendly platform to store and disseminate the DEL data.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>gratefully received. We acknowledge the generous support of the <rs type="funder">Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">OPPID1199734</rs>) and the research assistance of <rs type="person">Yu Xuan Cheng</rs> and <rs type="person">Ingrid Humblen</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_fdjRWtt">
					<idno type="grant-number">OPPID1199734</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_tggnYSP">
					<idno type="grant-number">OPPID1199734</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Code availability</head><p>We make the DEL data available in a readily accessible format along with the R scripts used to clean the data in DEL's dataverse. These R code files include code to check that values fall within expected ranges and standardising variable names and values. We also made an annotated R script available to create the DEL behavioural segmentation variable DELseg available. This script allows researchers to replicate the segmentation created by the DEL team. This variable aims to capture different forms of engagement with development issues.</p><p>A description of this segmentation is available in DEL's Harvard Dataverse. 12 10 All the survey question variables follow this structure variablename wave or variablename wave number 11 Due to the long period through which the study was conducted, and due to limits both legal and technical about what demographic and political data can be collected across the four countries, there are some minimal differences in classification schemes across waves and countries and data types in some of the covariates such as party preferences, voting records, and employment status. 12  We have not validated this classification method.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>to ensure they matched the numeric values on the survey. We perform outlier and crosstabulation analysis to find suggestive evidence of leading/biased questions in the survey.</p><p>We also checked that survey logic testing worked, including checks that skip logic, branching, and other automated features worked as intended and were reflected in the data. We implemented a third quality control stage by obtaining and inspecting partial samples during the data collection period. These larger sets underwent the same quality controls undertaken during the pilot testing described above. We also extended our inspection by computing the proportion of respondents who systematically answered "Don't know/Prefer not to say" as a signal of low engagement or survey fatigue. We also checked for unusual skewness in the respondents' answers. A final set of similar tests were conducted on the final dataset once all data collection was completed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Post-Harmonisation</head><p>We recoded the original data to homogenise their structure across the different types of datasets. Specifically, we standardised the numeric codes for 5-point and 10-point Likert scale items. We also homogenised the naming conventions used in the datasets, so researchers can easily merge the datasets 10 . We inspected all codebooks, questionnaires, and data tables, ensuring this documentation matched with the datasets 11 . good. Economic Development and Cultural Change 33(2), 373-93. Oh, S., P. Morini, F. Torres, D. <ref type="bibr">Hudson, and J. Hudson (2023)</ref>. The power of activation: The effect of images in global poverty campaign appeals.  <ref type="table">Table 2:</ref>    Note: This table provides a summary of the main covariates for all ten waves of the Panel. The "Gender" category indicates the percentage of respondents who identified as women. "Age" refers to the age of the respondents at the time of the survey. "Partisanship" is based on a self-reported scale ranging from 0 to 10. The monthly income covariate is reported in USD for all four countries. For respondents in France and Germany, we used a conversion rate of 1.11 USD . For Great Britain, the conversion rate used was 1.32 USD. Survey weights were applied to ensure that the estimates are nationally representative. Standard errors are reported in parenthesis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix Figures &amp; Tables</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions statement</head><p>Professors </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual politics: The role of images in political communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Banducci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Karp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationships between mass media, public opinion, and foreign policy: Toward a theoretical synthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Baum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Potter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Polit. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new era of minimal effects? the changing foundations of political communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Iyengar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="731" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">UK Giving Report 2023</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-08-14">2023. 2023-08-14</date>
			<publisher>Charities Aid Foundation</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Finding Frames: New ways to engage the UK public in global poverty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Darnton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kirk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<pubPlace>Bond London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Germany Dashboard October 2023</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technical report, Development Compass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2023" to="2028" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>Development Compass</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring public support for european integration using a bayesian item response theory model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Di Vettimo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Union Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Internet, Phone, Mail, and Mixed-Mode Surveys: The Tailored Design Method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dillman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Christian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Wiley Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>4th ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Projections of power: Framing news, public opinion, and u.s. foreign policy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Entman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attrition and generalizability in longitudinal studies: findings from a 15-year population-based study and a monte carlo simulation study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gustavson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Soest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Karevold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">918</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">Rysamb. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How do people evaluate foreign aid to &apos;nasty&apos;regimes?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Heinrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The internet and democracy: The political economy of attention in the digital age</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hindman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual Review of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Explaining public support for foreign aid projects: Evidence from france, germany, great britain and the united states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Morini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-08">2024, August</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Forthcoming</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">a mile wide and an inch deep&apos;: Surveys of public attitudes towards development aid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Development Education and Global Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Who can communicate international development?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Morini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Not one, but many &quot;publics&quot;: public engagement with global development in france, germany, great britain, and the united states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Morini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">33633435</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development in Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="795" to="808" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the question of generosity: Who supports foreign aid to whom?-lessons from turkey and greece</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kiratli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Public Opinion Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Panel attrition: Separating stayers, fast attriters, gradual attriters, and lurkers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lugtig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Methods &amp; Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="699" to="723" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Private donations for international development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Micklewright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Immigration/Migration; Climate Change (Health/Well-being; Taxation); Gender Equality; Women&apos;s Leadership 2022 June Cooperation; Refugees; Africa; Terminology; France Role 2023 Mar Feminist Development Policy; Gender Equality; Aid allocation; Cooperation; Knowledge; Citizenship 2023 May Imagery; Donations Great Britain 2020 Apr COVID; Messenger Testing 2020 July Knowledge; Information; Misinformation; SDGs; Cooperation; Trust 2021 June Video/Images and donations; Budget allocation 2022 June Ukraine; Refugees; Feminist Development Policy 2023 Feb Gender equality; Feminist Development Policy 2023 Oct Imagery</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Great Britain; United States</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-01">2005. January 2020 3 to 7 June 2021 6 to 8 Jan 2021 7 to 9 June 2022 14 to 17 Jan 2022 1 to 2 June 2023 4 to 10 January 2023 30 May to 2 June 2024 8 to 15 January 2024 2024 3 to 9 June 2024 Germany 2020 9 to 16 January 2020 3 to 7 June 2021 6 to 7 Jan 2021 2 to 6 June 2022 13 to 14 Jan 2022 26 May to 6 June 2023 3 to 9 Jan 2023 30 May to 2 June 2024 8 to 13 January 2024 2024 3 to 7 June 2024. 2020 9 to 13 January 2020 3 to 4 June 2021 5 to 6 Jan 2021 2 to 3 June 2022 12 to 13 Jan 2022 30 May to 1 June 2023 5 to 6 January 2023 30 to 31 May 2024 8 to 9 January 2024 2024 4 to 5 June 2024. 2020 8 to 13 January 2020 3 to 4 June 2021 6 to 7 Jan 2021 4 to 9 June 2022 12 to 13 Jan 2022 27 to 31 May 2023 4 to 5 Jan 2023 30 to 31 May 2024 9 to 10 January 2024 2024 3 to 4 June 2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="155" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Table 3: Details Tracker Data Country Year Collection period Sample France 2020 9 to 13 Note: This table reports the collection times, sample sizes, and retention samples of Trackers for all countries from the first cross-section in 2019 until the last round in 2024. Table 8: Topics covered across sandbox surveys Country Year Month Topics France 2019 May Role of France Paris Agreement; Vaccines 2022 Jan COVID; Cooperation ; Feminist Development Policy; Gender equality; Development Finance; Health; Deservingness 2020 February Gender equality 2020 July Knowledge; Information; Misinformation; SDGs; Cooperation; Trust 2021 May Finance; Africa; Challenges; Outlook; COVID; Cooperation; Climate Change; Corruption; International ;Organisations 2021 August COVID; Migration; Climate; Change (Energy production; transportation; Impact)</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
