<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Housing Tenure, Housing Satisfaction, and Fertility Intentions in the Nordic Context of the Early 2020s</title>
				<funder ref="#_EH7aKV9 #_UXWwg8R">
					<orgName type="full">Academy of Finland</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">SRC</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">ROCKWOOL Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yuting</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Luxembourg</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="LU">Luxembourg</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Erik</forename><surname>Carlsson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">INVEST Research Flagship Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Turku</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jessica</forename><surname>Nisén</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">INVEST Research Flagship Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Turku</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Helsinki</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Helsinki Institute for Demography and Population Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Housing Tenure, Housing Satisfaction, and Fertility Intentions in the Nordic Context of the Early 2020s</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3571BC82A48324A03208F4BFD4FD2C90</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-19T16:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>low fertility</term>
					<term>fertility preferences</term>
					<term>homeownership</term>
					<term>residential satisfaction</term>
					<term>crossnational comparison</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objective:</head><p>The study aims to shed new light on current fertility behavior by examining the relationship between housing tenure, perceived housing satisfaction, and fertility intentions in the Nordic countries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background:</head><p>The declining fertility rate in the Nordic countries since the 2010s has challenged previous fertility theories. Among the many factors that may influence fertility behavior, housing has gained increased attention. Yet the link between housing and fertility intentions in the Nordic context remains insufficiently investigated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method:</head><p>We use microdata from the Generations and Gender Survey -Round 2 Wave 1 for Finland, Sweden, Norway, and Denmark (N = 13,420) collected in 2020-2022. Logistic regression is used to assess variation in the housing-fertility relation by country, age, and parity.</p><p>Results: Homeownership is positively linked to fertility intentions in Norway and Sweden, unrelated in Finland, and negatively associated in Denmark, likely reflecting Denmark's tenure-neutral housing system and extensive rental sector. Housing satisfaction shows no overall association, but negative associations emerge among the youngest (18-24) and oldest (40-44) age groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p>Combining objective measures of tenure with subjective housing satisfaction provides a more nuanced understanding of how housing conditions intersect with fertility intentions in the Nordic countries. The results underscore the importance of institutional context and life-course stage in shaping the housing-fertility relationship.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The Nordic countries have experienced declining fertility since 2010, which has challenged previous theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Hiilamo, 2019)</ref>. This unexpected development is particularly puzzling given that the Nordic countries are renowned for their successful reconciliation of workfamily conflicts among parents <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Esping-Andersen, 2009)</ref>. The fertility decline has taken place despite strong support systems, including generous parental leave policies, affordable childcare, and active encouragement of shared parenting responsibilities. This suggests that we should turn our attention to other factors and theories. Recently, an increasing number of studies have empirically demonstrated that changes to homeownership availability and housing prices can impact fertility, with evidence drawn from Australia, the Netherlands, and the U.K. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Atalay et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Tocchioni et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">van Wijk, 2024)</ref>. However, we have limited knowledge about the extent to which changes in housing status and housing markets may have contributed to the decline in fertility rates in Nordic countries since the 2010s. More importantly, relatively few studies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Du et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Jeon et al., 2021)</ref> have explored the role of subjective satisfaction with housing in shaping fertility intentions, although it may play a crucial role in understanding the linkage between housing and fertility.</p><p>Homeownership not only represents the largest single asset for households in most advanced economies <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Pfeffer &amp; Waitkus, 2021)</ref>, but also symbolizes adulthood, offers physical shelter, and provides economic security-often prerequisites for union formation and childbearing <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Mulder, 2006a)</ref>. Therefore, housing tenure-whether individuals live in owner-occupied or rented homes-has emerged as a central focus in previous fertility studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Brauner-Otto, 2023)</ref>. These studies have suggested that variations in housing regimes (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brauner-Otto, 2023)</ref> and housing prices (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Van Wijk, 2024</ref>) can explain the cross-national differences of postponement of first births and a decline in cohort fertility. At the individual level, owning an owner-occupied home has been found to be associated with positive fertility intentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Mulder, 2006a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Tocchioni et al., 2021)</ref>. Although the transition to homeownership may delay first-time parenthood in contexts where housing is expensive, it can also serve as a precondition for later but potentially higher fertility, particularly in societies where homeownership is the normative form of family housing <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Chudnovskaya, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Flynn, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Kulu &amp; Steele, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Kulu &amp; Vikat, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Mulder, 2006a)</ref>.</p><p>This study investigates how housing tenure, i.e., ownership or renting of homes, and individuals' satisfaction with their living arrangements relate to fertility intentions in the Nordic context, using data from the Generations and Gender Survey, Round 2 (GGS-II) Wave 1. By examining the relationship between housing and fertility in Denmark, Finland, Norway and Sweden, this study aims to provide region-specific empirical evidence that can inform theoretical developments more broadly. While these countries share similarities in their welfare state set-up, there are notable differences in their housing policies and economic conditions. A comparative analysis within the Nordic context allows for a more nuanced understanding of the housing-fertility relationship. These findings could also inform public policy efforts to address steeply declining fertility rates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Theoretical and Contextual Backgrounds</head><p>This section reviews the relationship between housing and fertility, with a particular focus on the Nordic context. We begin by introducing key theoretical arguments for why homeownership and housing satisfaction may relate to fertility intentions. Next, we provide a descriptive overview of fertility trends, housing systems, and family policies in the Nordic countries, highlighting both similarities and differences across the region.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Housing tenure and fertility intentions</head><p>Housing is closely related to family formation and childbearing behaviours during young adulthood -a demographically dense life stage characterized by several important events, such as leaving the parental home, moving into a rented or purchased home, forming partnerships, and becoming parents <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Flynn, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Kulu &amp; Steele, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Öst, 2012)</ref>. These events are not only interdependent but also shaped by both current housing conditions and anticipations of future housing transitions, which are in turn constrained by housing policy and market structures. Previous research has shown that housing is associated with fertility through various channels such as homeownership status, housing prices, locations, living space, and housing types (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brauner-Otto, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Du et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Kulu &amp; Steele, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Kulu &amp; Vikat, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Van Wijk, 2024)</ref>, as evidenced by both macro-level regional comparisons and micro-level analyses.</p><p>At the macro level, housing prices are generally negatively associated with fertility rates, as shown in studies from English-speaking countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Atalay et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Dettling &amp; Kearney, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Lovenheim &amp; Mumford, 2013)</ref>, Asia (J. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Liu et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Mizutani, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Yi &amp; Zhang, 2010)</ref>, Western Europe (van Wijk, 2024) and more recently from Nordic countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Chudnovskaya, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Daysal et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Florida et al., 2021)</ref>. This negative association arises because, as summarised by <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Van Wijk (2024)</ref>, individuals and couples in increasingly expensive housing markets tend to spend more time seeking stable accommodation, allocate a larger proportion of their income to housing costs, and delay leaving the parental home-thus indirectly postponing union formation. These mechanisms are further intensified by social norms and individual preferences for higher living standards when raising children <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Mulder, 2006b</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Mulder, , 2013))</ref>. As a result, rising housing prices impose greater barriers to securing suitable living arrangements, ultimately discouraging individuals or couples from having a(nother) child.</p><p>However, at the micro level, rising housing prices have heterogeneous effects depending on housing tenure, i.e., whether housing is owner-occupied or rented. For homeowners, an increase in housing prices often boosts financial wealth via rising housing equity, which can positively influence fertility behaviours and intentions. In contrast, rising housing prices increase financial pressure on tenants through higher rents and greater barriers to homeownership, such as larger down payments and higher mortgage repayments. These factors typically exert a negative impact on tenants' fertility behaviours and intentions (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Atalay et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Dettling &amp; Kearney, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Lovenheim, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Lovenheim &amp; Mumford, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Mizutani, 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Yi &amp; Zhang, 2010)</ref>. Consequently, homeownership is generally linked to higher fertility and a higher propensity to report positive fertility intentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Chudnovskaya, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Kulu &amp; Steele, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Kulu &amp; Vikat, 2007)</ref>. Nevertheless, the financial strain of saving for a down payment may initially delay childbearing among prospective buyers <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Clark, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">H. Liu et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Öst, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Simon &amp; Tamura, 2009)</ref>. Beyond financial implications, homeownership also provides access to symbolic status, sense of security, and protection against eviction <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Lersch, 2025;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Mulder, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Pfeffer &amp; Waitkus, 2021)</ref>; it may also allow accessing more family-friendly neighbourhoods <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(van Wijk, 2024)</ref> .</p><p>Yet despite extensive evidence on housing and fertility, most studies to date have focused on realized births rather than fertility intentions. Only a few have examined fertility intentions in this context (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Atalay et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Hu et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">J. Liu et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">Vignoli et al., 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Fertility intentions offer a forward-looking lens and are often strong predictors of eventual fertility outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ajzen, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Vidal et al., 2017)</ref>. They reflect individuals' anticipatory responses to structural constraints, including housing conditions, and are less affected by external factors such as unplanned pregnancies or miscarriages <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ajzen &amp; Klobas, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>However, fertility intentions may overestimate eventual fertility, particularly in high-income countries where widespread contraceptive use and intentions often remain unrealized <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ajzen &amp; Klobas, 2013)</ref>. Despite this limitation, this study will enrich the current discussion about the housing-fertility association.</p><p>In addition to this conceptual gap, the empirical relationship of housing and fertility is underexplored in the Nordic context during the 2020s. To the best of our knowledge, most existing studies are based on data from before the 2008 Global Financial Crisis, when housing markets were less volatile and price increases were moderate in most European countries (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Chudnovskaya, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Kulu &amp; Vikat, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Öst, 2012)</ref>. Notable exceptions include studies from the UK and the Netherlands, which have examined fertility responses under the conditions of severe rising housing prices and rents <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Tocchioni et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">van Wijk, 2024)</ref>.</p><p>These studies show that homeownership remains positively linked to childbearing in the postcrisis period, although the strength of this association has weakened since the 2010s <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Tocchioni et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">van Wijk, 2024)</ref>. Homeowners' declining fertility advantage in the UK and the Netherlands suggests that increasingly competitive housing markets have become a significant barrier to childbearing, as the cost of purchasing a home competes directly with the financial demands of raising children <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Mulder, 2006a)</ref>. Yet no comparable studies have addressed these dynamics in the Nordic region, where housing market conditions and welfare systems may yield different fertility responses.</p><p>Taken together, previous research shows that housing tenure is linked to both fertility behaviour and fertility intentions. Rising housing prices intensify the financial challenges faced by tenants, while homeowners may still benefit from increased housing equity, though the positive association between homeownership and fertility appears to have declined over time. These insights inform the following hypothesis:</p><p>Hypothesis 1: Homeowners are more likely than tenants to intend to have a (or another) child.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Subjective housing satisfaction and fertility intentions</head><p>Existing research has demonstrated a strong link between homeownership and fertility intentions, often highlighting the role of housing stability and security as a prerequisite for family formation and childrearing <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Kulu &amp; Steele, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Mulder, 2006a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">van Wijk &amp; Billari, 2024)</ref>. However, less attention has been paid to the psychological and subjective dimensions of housing conditions, such as housing satisfaction. This study builds on previous research by examining not only the association between homeownership and fertility intentions but also the potential independent and mediating role of housing satisfaction.</p><p>Although subjective perceptions of housing conditions are strongly correlated with material well-being (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Diaz-Serrano, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Elsinga &amp; Hoekstra, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Pekkonen &amp; Haverinen-Shaughnessy, 2015)</ref>, subjective and objective realities do not always align <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Inglehart, 1977)</ref>.</p><p>Two individuals living in objectively similar housing conditions may perceive their situation differently, depending on personal experiences, expectations, or prevailing social norms.</p><p>Subjective evaluations thus provide unique insights into how housing influences fertility intentions, adding a perspective that objective indicators alone may fail to capture.</p><p>Housing satisfaction, as a facet of overall life satisfaction, reflects the gap between an individual's aspirations and their perceived housing situations <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Amérigo &amp; Aragones, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Campbell et al., 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Vera-Toscano &amp; Ateca-Amestoy, 2008)</ref>. It also captures the cumulative and weighted importance individuals attach to various aspects of housing <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Inglehart, 1977)</ref>, such as tenure, quality, space, stability, affordability, symbolic value, and autonomy. Thus, housing satisfaction encompasses not only the physical attributes of housing but also its psychological and symbolic significance. Moreover, it represents a holistic assessment of one's living conditions, helping to explain why subjective perceptions and objective realities of housing are often correlated, yet may sometimes diverge. We can speculate that individuals who perceive their actual living situation as meeting or exceeding their expectations will report higher levels of housing satisfaction. In contrast, those who feel that their living situation falls significantly short of their aspirations are more likely to express dissatisfaction and frustrations with their living arrangements.</p><p>Housing satisfaction is therefore expected to have a direct impact on fertility intentions, relatively independent of individuals' housing tenure status. That is, higher levels of housing satisfaction-derived from a perceived alignment between an individual's living conditions and their aspirations-are likely to provide a sense of security, stability, and optimism about the future, all of which are critical when planning for children <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Aassve et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Vignoli et al., 2022)</ref>. Conversely, dissatisfaction with housing, whether due to physical inadequacies, financial strain, or a mismatch with personal expectations, may create psychological barriers that discourage childbearing. Building on this premise, we hypothesise that: Hypothesis 2: Housing satisfaction is positively associated with individuals' fertility intentions.</p><p>Additionally, while homeownership itself is expected to promote fertility intentions, housing satisfaction may act as a mediating factor in this relationship. Specifically, homeowners may be more satisfied than tenants with their housing conditions and thus more likely to intend to have a(nother) child. This implies a potential mediation effect, whereby the pathway from homeownership to fertility intentions is partially explained by housing satisfaction. Therefore, mediation analysis will be used to account for the potential mediating role of housing satisfaction and to disentangle its effect from that of homeownership.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">The Nordic context: shared features and country differences</head><p>From the late 20 th to the early 21 st century, the Nordic countries had period and cohort fertility rates close to the replacement level, which was higher than most other European countries.</p><p>Total fertility rates (TFRs) rebounded from the low levels (around 1.5) of the 1970s to approximately 1.7 by the mid-1980s, eventually recovering and stabilising at 1.8 or higher by 2005 <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Andersson et al., 2009)</ref>. The Nordic countries' relatively high fertility has often been attributed to their generous family benefits, gender-equal policies, and universal welfare systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Andersson et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Esping-Andersen, 1990)</ref>.</p><p>However, since 2010, fertility rates across the Nordic region have declined sharply, approaching or falling below the European average. As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>, the TFRs in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden have followed a similar downward trajectory since 2010, briefly interrupted by a rebound during the COVID-19 pandemic before reaching record lows. In 2024, Finland's total fertility rate (TFR) fell to 1.25, while the rates in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark declined to 1.43, 1.44, and 1.46 respectively,. Whereas period-based measures, such as the TFR, are influenced by temporary events and trends, often reflected in changes in the timing of childbearing, recent cohort fertility studies also indicate a decline in cohort fertility rates in the Nordic countries. Forecasts suggest that the completed cohort fertility in the region is expected to decline from approximately 2 for the 1970s cohort to around 1.8 for the late 1980s cohort <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Hellstrand et al., 2021)</ref>. The projected decline in cohort fertility is, however, more pronounced in Finland and Norway, while relatively milder decreases are expected in Denmark and Sweden <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Hellstrand et al., 2021)</ref>. This unexpected fertility decline, which is widespread, but particularly pronounced among younger age groups and childless individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Hellstrand et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Jónsson, 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Ohlsson-Wijk &amp; Andersson, 2022)</ref>, challenges earlier theories that portrayed Nordic fertility as persistently high and stable (OECD, 2023). Broader societal and economic changes, including cultural shifts, economic insecurity, and rising housing costs, may now play a more significant role in shaping fertility decisions (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Brauner-Otto, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Comolli et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">van Wijk &amp; Billari, 2024)</ref>. While family policies remain supportive, they may not be sufficient to fully offset these trends.</p><p>In recent decades, urban housing markets in the Nordic countries have undergone profound changes. Housing prices have increased sharply in larger cities, driven by strong economic and population growth and very low interest rates. The rising housing prices have been accompanied by a surge in household debt and growing housing cost-to-income ratios <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Anundsen, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Knoll et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Sørvoll et al., 2023)</ref>. At the same time, rental markets  <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1,</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_1">4   1,</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_1">6   1,</ref><ref type="table">8   2   2,</ref><ref type="table">2</ref> 2 0 0 0 2 0 0 1 2 0 0 2 2 0 0 3 2 0 0 4 2 0 0 5 2 0 0 6 2 0 0 7 2 0 0 8 2 0 0 9 2 0 1 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">2 0 1 1 2 0 1 2 2 0 1 3 2 0 1 4 2 0 1 5 2 0 1 6 2 0 1 7 2 0 1 8 2 0 1 9 2 0 2 0 2 0 2 1 2 0 2 2 2 0 2 3 2 0 2 4 Denmark Finland Norway Sweden EU</formula><p>have become increasingly precarious and deregulated <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Kettunen &amp; Ruonavaara, 2021)</ref> while social housing programs and subsidies have been scaled back <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Ruonavaara, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Sørvoll et al., 2023)</ref>. As such, Nordic countries increasingly exhibit features and challenges akin to liberal regimes-particularly the debt-driven escalation of residential property prices <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Blackwell &amp; Kohl, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Bryant et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Kohl &amp; Sørvoll, 2021)</ref>-despite continuing to be classified as social democratic welfare regimes with a strong preference for universalism and <ref type="bibr">de-commodification (Esping-Andersen, 1990)</ref>.</p><p>Despite shared trends, there are also important differences among the Nordic countries in housing policies and housing-related outcomes. The Nordic countries differ in tenure structure and the relative size of the social rental sector, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>. Norway and Finland exhibit the highest rates of homeownership, with homeowners accounting for approximately 70% to 80% of the total population. This pattern can be attributed to housing policies in both countries that favour mortgage-financed and tax-incentivized homeownership, offering structural advantages for property acquisition <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Ruonavaara, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Sørvoll et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Private rentals in Norway and Finland are regarded as "residual" or "transitional", operating mostly under market principles, with only means-tested or needs-tested housing allowances only provided for low-income groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Kettunen &amp; Ruonavaara, 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Ruonavaara, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Sørvoll et al., 2023)</ref>. Nevertheless, Finland maintains a larger public rental sector (10.9%)</p><p>than Norway (4.1%) in terms of total housing stock. Note: For Norway, social rental housing stock data only contains dwellings provided by municipalities (about 75% of all social housing). In Sweden, municipal housing associations provide a significant share of housing for low-income households.</p><p>However, since rents are not below market levels, these units are not classified as social housing in the OECD Affordable Housing Database. Still, public housing is estimated to comprise 15-20% of the total housing stock (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Blackwell &amp; Bengtsson, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>In contrast, Denmark and Sweden maintain a more tenure-neutral housing structure, with roughly 60% of the population being homeowners, a more regulated private rental market characterised by collective negotiations between tenant unions and landlord associations, and, in the case of Denmark, a larger share of cooperative rental housing supported by state subsidies (21.3% in total housing stock) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Blackwell &amp; Bengtsson, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Vestergaard &amp; Scanlon, 2014)</ref>. However, rental housing in Sweden has become increasingly market-oriented compared to Denmark, particularly in terms of rent levels, tenant selection, and security of tenure <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Blackwell &amp; Bengtsson, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Sørvoll et al., 2023)</ref>. Recent studies find that strong creating an "insider-outsider" divide in which newcomers often rely on precarious and costly subletting (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Grander, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Listerborn, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Data source: OECD Affordable Housing Database (http://oe.cd/ahd) -Indicator HC1.1.</p><p>Housing-related expenditure of households.</p><p>Note: Housing expenditure includes actual rentals for tenants, imputed rentals for homeowners, maintenance costs, water, and electricity.</p><p>Real house prices rose by about 147% in Sweden, 109% in Norway, 49% in Denmark, and 27% in Finland between 2000 and 2019 <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Anundsen, 2021)</ref>. Housing expenditure trends further illustrate affordability pressures and cross-country differences. Between 2000 and 2022, housing-related expenditure as a share of total household consumption expenditure increased most significantly in Finland, from 24% to 29% (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>). In contrast, Sweden experienced a slight decrease, from 27% to 25%. Denmark and Norway both saw slower, fluctuating increases, with Denmark consistently exhibiting higher average housing-related expenditure than Norway.</p><p>These variations in tenure structures and housing affordability underscore the complex and context-dependent relationship between housing and fertility (Brauner-Otto, 2023).</p><p>Specifically, tenure systems shape how young adults and families navigate affordability pressures, potentially influencing their willingness or ability to have children. In countries like</p><p>Finland and Norway, where homeownership is prevalent but rental markets are relatively limited and less regulated, young adults may delay family formation due to financial insecurity and difficulties in accessing affordable housing. By contrast, Denmark's more tenure-neutral system and larger cooperative rental sector may provide a buffer against housing-related pressures. Sweden is also regarded as tenure-neutral, but its increasingly marketized and precarious subletting rental sector may provide a weaker safeguard than Denmark's system, potentially exerting a less positive influence on young adults' childbearing intentions.</p><p>In sum, growing inequalities in wealth and housing cost burdens between homeowners and tenants continue to pose challenges and to manifest differently across national contexts with distinct tenure structures. These challenges are likely to be more pronounced for certain groups, such as young adults in the early stages of their housing careers or families considering a first or second child (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Atalay et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Grander, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Tocchioni et al., 2021)</ref>. Specifically, we expect that in countries with more constrained rental markets (i.e., Finland and Norway), homeownership will be more strongly associated with positive fertility intentions than in countries with more tenure-neutral housing systems, particularly Denmark.</p><p>Based on these considerations, we propose the following hypothesis:</p><p>Hypothesis 3a: The association between housing tenure and fertility intentions varies across Nordic countries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis 3b:</head><p>The association between housing tenure and fertility intentions varies across parity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis 3c:</head><p>The association between housing tenure and fertility intentions varies across age groups.</p><p>Furthermore, we expect that the association between housing satisfaction and fertility intentions will vary across Nordic countries due to differences in housing market structures and policy contexts. Low housing satisfaction may directly translate into financial or residential instability, thereby discouraging young adults from forming or expanding families.</p><p>By contrast, in countries with more tenure-neutral systems and stronger rental protections (especially in Denmark), institutional safeguards may mitigate the impact of suboptimal housing conditions, weakening the direct influence of housing satisfaction on fertility intentions. Beyond cross-national differences, the relationship between housing satisfaction and fertility intentions is also likely to vary across age groups and parity. Younger adults and childless individuals, who are typically at the beginning of both their housing and family careers, may perceive housing dissatisfaction as a more immediate barrier to childbearing.</p><p>But, older adults, often benefiting from greater residential stability, are less affected by their housing conditions when making fertility decisions. Therefore, we hypothesize the following:</p><p>Hypothesis 4a: The association between housing satisfaction and fertility intentions varies across Nordic countries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis 4b:</head><p>The association between housing satisfaction and fertility intentions varies across parity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis 4c:</head><p>The association between housing satisfaction and fertility intentions varies across age groups.</p><p>3 Analytical Approach</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Data</head><p>We used data from the first wave of the second round of the Generations and Gender Surveys (GGS-II W1), conducted in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden. Data collection in these countries was carried out between November 2020 and April 2022, using computer-assisted web interviewing (CAWI). For this study, we restricted the sample to respondents aged 18-44 (n=17,380) and further to those with two or fewer children (n=15,973), since fertility intentions are substantially lower among those with three or more children (only 5% of them intend to have more). Excluding respondents who were currently pregnant or biologically unable to have children yielded 14,536 individuals. The final sample after listwise deletion was 13,420.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Variables</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Fertility intentions</head><p>For Denmark, Finland, and Norway, fertility intentions were captured through the question, "Do you intend to have another child during the next three years? Please take into account only biological children." Responses were collected on a five-point scale: "definitely not" (34.8%), "probably not" (24.6%), "unsure" (13.7%), "probably yes" (15.7%), and "definitely yes" (11.3%)". Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Begall and Hiekel (2024)</ref>, we recoded these responses into a binary variable, with "unsure" classified as "not intending".</p><p>The Swedish GGS-II W1 used the same question about the fertility intentions as the other three countries but did not include the instruction to only consider biological children.</p><p>Moreover, the Swedish version of the survey included a screening question that narrowed the set of respondents to the intention question. Respondents who answered that they (or their partner) were currently trying to get pregnant were not asked about their three-year fertility intentions. To ensure cross-country comparability, we coded those Swedish respondents who were currently trying to get pregnant as having a positive three-year fertility intention.</p><p>We focus on short-term rather than long-term fertility intentions since the former should be more closely related to the individual's current housing situation <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Kulu &amp; Steele, 2013)</ref>, thus enhancing both predictive accuracy and practical relevance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Explanatory variables</head><p>The main independent variables in this study are housing tenure and housing satisfaction. In the Danish, Finnish, and Norwegian surveys, housing tenure was measured by the question:</p><p>"Does your household own or rent this accommodation, or does it come rent-free?" In these three countries, responses were categorized as owner (50.3%), tenant or subtenant paying rent (41.5%), tenant with rent-free (2.2%), and other (6.0%). For the analysis, this variable was recoded into a dummy indicator distinguishing homeowners from non-homeowners, with the latter group encompassing rent-paying tenants, rent-free tenants, and those classified as other.</p><p>The Swedish survey did not collect information on respondents' home ownership. Instead, we used self-reported property value as a proxy for housing tenure. Specifically, the question asked: "What is the combined approximate value of any property that you own? Include your accommodation and any other real estate that you own in the total amount". The response scale was ordinal, including "4,999 € or less (48.8%)", "5,000 to 9,999 € (0.1%)", "10,000 to 19,999 € (0.2%)", "20,000 to 49,999 € (1.1%)", "50,000 to 99,999 € (2.3%)", "100,000 to 249,999 € (13.7%)", "250,000 to 499,999 € (20.9%)", "500,000 € or more (13.2%)". We tested two recoding strategies: (1) classifying respondents with property valued 4,999 € or less as non-homeowners and those above as homeowners, and (2) classifying those with property valued below 99,999 € as non-homeowners. Both approaches produced similar results in terms of coefficients and significance levels. We report the results of the main analysis applying the first approach. Further justification of the measure and robustness checks are provided in Appendix 1.</p><p>Housing satisfaction was measured on an 11-point scale (0 = "not at all satisfied," 10 = "completely satisfied").We used the continuous measure in the main analyses, but also tested alternative codings: the continuous measure together with a quadratic term, quantiles, and other categorical specifications based either on the mean and one standard deviation below/above the mean (low, medium, high) or cut-off points suggested by visual inspection of the histogram (0-4, 5-7, 8-10). All approaches yielded consistent results in terms of coefficient direction, significance, and other key metrics. However, we chose the continuous specification since it provided the best model fit, as indicated by AIC and BIC comparisons.</p><p>Control variables include age group, parity, partnership status, gender, migrant background, education level, activity status, and intention to move. Age group was categorised into "18 to 24 years", "25 to 29 years", "30 to 34 years", "35 to 39 years", and "40 to 44 years". Parity was defined as "no child," "one child," and "two children" based on biological children with current or previous partners; adopted children and stepchildren were excluded. The number of biological children was derived following the harmonised coding procedures provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Jin et al. (2024)</ref>. Partnership status was grouped into "married", "cohabiting", "living apart together" (LAT), and "single". Gender and migrant background were dummy variables, where migrant indicates whether the respondent was born outside the country of residence.</p><p>Education level was recoded according to ISCED 2011 into three categories: "low education" (ISCED 0-2), "medium education" (ISCED 3-4), and "high education" (ISCED 5-8). Activity status was classified as "employed," "unemployed,", "in education or military service," and "other". The "employed" contains those who are employed (59.3%), self-employed (3.7%), helping family member in a family farm or business (0.3%), on maternity or paternity leave</p><p>(2.3%), or on parental or childcare leave (1.1%). The "unemployed" comprises 3.9% of the sample. "In education or military service" includes who are in education or training (25.0%), and in military or civic service (0.3%). "Other" refers to those who are retired (0.5%), taking care of the home or family (0.4%), ill or disabled for a long time or permanently (1.6%), and other (1.7%).</p><p>Intention to move was measured by asking respondents whether they planned to move within the next three years, with three categories: no, unsure, and yes. In models focusing on housing satisfaction, this variable is treated as a confounder, since it can capture individuals' livingstandard preferences that affect both satisfaction and fertility intentions. In contrast, in housing tenure models, moving intention is more plausibly a downstream consequence of tenure rather than its cause; thus, controlling for it may constitute overadjustment.</p><p>Additionally, we included two control variables in our robustness analyses: an indicator of whether a person lived in a capital region and household income. These variables were only used in robustness analyses because of issues with cross-country comparability (for more details, see Appendices 5 and 6). All subsequent results applied survey weights (including design and post-stratification adjustments) provided by the GGP Central Coordination Team.</p><p>These weights correct for sampling probabilities, non-response bias, and align the sample distribution with official population figures on age, gender, region, education, and marital status <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Gauthier et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Jablonski et al., 2022)</ref>. The use of these weights improves representativeness within countries and enhances the reliability of cross-country comparisons.</p><p>The descriptive summary of all variables by country is presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> below. Source: GGS-II Wave 1 in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden. Author's calculations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Methods</head><p>We employed multivariate logistic regression models to analyse how housing tenure and housing satisfaction relate to the binary outcome variable: whether or not individuals intend to have children within the next three years. Results are presented as average marginal effects (AMEs) to facilitate interpretation <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Mood, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>In addition, to investigate the potential mediating role of housing satisfaction and intention to move in the relationship between housing tenure and fertility intentions, we applied path diagram analysis alongside the Karlson-Holm-Breen (KHB) decomposition method. To obtain more robust estimates-particularly in contexts where the assumption of normality may not hold, as in logistic regression models-we used 1,000 bootstrap replications to derive confidence intervals <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Karlson &amp; Holm, 2011)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Bivariate associations</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> presents the bivariate associations between fertility intentions and other variables considered in our analyses.</p><p>The share of individuals with a positive fertility intention is between 24 and 28 % in Denmark, Norway, and Sweden, but only 17 % in Finland. A larger percentage of homeowners than tenants express a positive fertility intention (26% vs. 23%). Housing satisfaction is negatively associated with fertility intentions, with 31 % of the least satisfied but only 22 % of the most satisfied respondents expressing a positive intention. Educational attainment is positively associated with the propensity to state a positive intention, as is being employed compared to all other activity statuses. Cohabiting individuals were more likely to express a positive intention than married individuals, who in turn displayed a higher propensity than both partnered non-cohabiting individuals (LAT) and singles. Positive intentions were more common among migrants than natives, and among those planning to change residence compared to those who were not.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Multivariate analysis of fertility intentions</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> presents results from two multivariate logistic regression models. In both models, the dependent variable is the fertility intention, while the main explanatory variable differs between the models: housing tenure in Model 1 and housing satisfaction in Model 2. Both models control for the same set of covariates: country, gender, partnership status, migrant background, activity status, age group, education level, and parity. In addition, the satisfaction model includes moving intention as a covariate, while the tenure model does not.</p><p>The results of Model 1 in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> show that, net of controls, homeownership is not significantly associated with higher fertility intentions in the pooled Nordic sample, which does not support Hypothesis 1. In this model, we chose not to control for housing satisfaction and intention to move, as including potential mediators may obscure the total "effect" of homeownership on fertility intentions. Indeed, mediation analysis (see Appendix 2) reveals that the association between housing tenure and fertility intentions is primarily mediated by intention to move. When both housing satisfaction and intention to move are included as mediators, homeowners have 3.1 percentage points of higher probability to intend to have an(other) child (SE = 0.008, p &lt; 0.001). This pattern is mainly driven by the suppressive role of intention to move rather than housing satisfaction. Specifically, homeowners less often intend to move (-0.015, p&lt;0.001), and those intending to move are substantially less likely to report a positive fertility intention (-0.108, p&lt;0.001). Although the descriptive statistics (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>) show a positive association between intention to move and fertility intentions, this relationship reverses once key sociodemographic factors are controlled for in the housing tenure model. Overall, intention to move acts as a suppressor, accounting for roughly 50% of the total effect of homeownership on fertility intentions, thereby masking the positive effect of homeownership on fertility intentions.</p><p>Model 2 in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> suggests that housing satisfaction is not associated with fertility intentions, net of covariates, thus not supporting Hypothesis 2. We deliberately chose not to control for housing tenure in Model 2, as it may act as an upstream determinant of housing satisfaction. Controlling for tenure could therefore lead to biased estimates of the total association between housing satisfaction and fertility intentions. Appendix 3 presents stepwise logistic regressions for housing tenure and housing satisfaction, with covariates entered sequentially.</p><p>To sum, both homeownership and housing satisfaction appear not robustly associated with fertility intentions. However, when interactions by country, parity, and age are introduced, a more nuanced picture emerges, which will be presented in the next section. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Heterogeneity in the relationship between housing and fertility intentions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">Housing tenure and fertility intentions</head><p>The analysis in section 4.2 showed that, overall, housing tenure has no significant association with fertility intentions. To explore whether the null-association holds in different subgroups, The results reveal notable differences between the countries, with Denmark showing the highest average fertility intentions overall, while Finland exhibits the lowest across both homeowners and non-homeowners. More importantly, the relationship between homeownership and fertility intentions varies significantly across countries, in line with Hypothesis 3a. In Norway and Sweden (and Finland), homeowners are more likely than tenants to express a positive fertility intention, whereas the reverse holds in Denmark: homeowners are 5.2 percentage points less likely than tenants to express a positive intention.</p><p>Except Finland, the fertility intention gap between homeowners and tenants was statistically significant.</p><p>Parity also moderates the association between housing tenure and fertility intentions, in line with Hypothesis 3b. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref> shows that in the pooled Nordic sample homeowners are slightly more likely than tenants to express a positive intention at parity 0 and 1, although these gaps are not statistically significant. In contrast, among two-child parents, homeowners are significantly less likely than tenants to intend another child (p=0.029).</p><p>The relationship between tenure and fertility intentions also varies by age, in line with hypothesis 3c. Model 5 in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref> shows that tenants are significantly more likely than homeowners to express a positive fertility intention among 18-24 year olds (p = 0.004), while homeowners are instead significantly more likely than tenants to express a positive intention among 25-29 year olds (p = 0.000). In age groups <ref type="bibr">30-34, 35-39 and 40-44, differences</ref> between homeowners and tenants are small and non-significant. Notably, homeowners display a clear peak in the propensity to state a positive fertility intention at ages 25-29 and 30-34, whereas the corresponding peak among renters occurs at older ages and is less pronounced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">Housing satisfaction and fertility intentions</head><p>We further examine whether the association between housing satisfaction and fertility intentions varies across different groups. To do so, we estimate three extensions of Model 2 from Section 4.2, where we add an interaction term, between housing satisfaction and country (Model 6), housing satisfaction and parity (Model 7), and housing satisfaction and age (Model As shown previously (Section 4.2), we observed that the average marginal effect of housing satisfaction on fertility intentions was close to zero and statistically insignificant. In this interaction analysis, neither the cross-country differences (Model 6) nor the parity-specific variations (Model 7) in slopes reach conventional levels of significance, providing no robust support for Hypotheses 4a and 4b.</p><p>However, the interaction with age group in Model 8 reveals heterogeneity, supporting Hypothesis 4c. Housing satisfaction is negatively associated with fertility intentions among the youngest (18-24) and oldest (40-44) respondents, but shows no significant effect in the core childbearing ages (25-39). For those aged 18-24, each one-unit increase in housing satisfaction (0-10 scale) is associated with a 1.0 percentage-point decrease in the probability of reporting positive fertility intentions (AME = -0.010, p = 0.012). At the upper end of the age distribution (40-44), the effect is similar, with a 0.9 percentage-point decrease (AME = -0.009, p = 0.030). By contrast, among respondents aged 25-39, the slopes are small and statistically insignificant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Robustness analyses</head><p>We chose to omit variables indicating geographical region of residence and household income from the main analyses due to data limitations, such as missing information and comparability issues across the four countries. However, we performed robustness analyses where we added</p><p>(1) a dummy variable indicating whether the respondent lived in a capital region and (2) net household income to models 1 and 2 from Section 4.2. Adding these controls did not change the AMEs for housing tenure and housing satisfaction. Further information on these robustness analyses is available in Appendices 5 and 6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusions and Discussions</head><p>This study investigated how homeownership and housing satisfaction relate to fertility intentions in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden, using recently collected data from the second round of the Generations and Gender Survey. The relationship between housing and fertility preferences is underexplored in the Nordic context, with housing satisfaction's role as a predictor of fertility intentions largely neglected in earlier research. Thus, this study improves our understanding of the current low fertility landscape in the Nordic countries, shaped by steep declines in fertility rates since the early 2010s. Importantly, similar fertility downturns have been observed in a number of other Western countries, including the United States, where fertility rates have declined markedly since the Great Recession <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Kearney et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Matysiak et al., 2021)</ref>. This broader pattern highlights the wider relevance of examining housing-fertility linkages.</p><p>Our analyses show that, in Norway and Sweden, homeownership is positively associated with fertility intentions, whereas in Denmark it is negatively associated. Finland shows a positive yet non-significant association. The positive association between homeownership and fertility intentions aligns with previous research in Western Europe and North America (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Japaridze &amp; Sayour, 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Tocchioni et al., 2021)</ref>, while the Danish and Finnish cases stand out as divergences. Our results highlight that the positive association is concentrated to ages 25 to 29-a life stage when individuals are actively making family formation decisions and transitioning from student or rental housing into more permanent housing arrangements <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Mulder, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Öst, 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Although tenure-based differences in fertility intentions are small among individuals with zero or one child in the pooled Nordic sample, an interesting contrast appears at parity two: renters report higher fertility intentions than homeowners. One possible explanation is that by the time families reach two children, homeowners may face stronger financial constraints linked to their housing investment, whereas renters may still anticipate future upward mobility in the housing market and therefore express higher intentions for additional children.</p><p>While tentative, this pattern suggests that the relationship between housing and fertility may shift once families reach higher parities, underlining the importance of examining these dynamics across different stages of family expansion.</p><p>In terms of country differences, our results reveal two notable deviations from the general pattern. First, in Denmark, homeowners are less likely than tenants to express a positive fertility intention. This negative association may reflect country-specific institutional and structural contexts or cultural factors that shape the relationship between housing tenure and family planning. Denmark's strong tenure-neutral housing policy and its comparatively large rental sector, including an extensive provision of social rental housing <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Blackwell &amp; Bengtsson, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Grander, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Vestergaard &amp; Scanlon, 2014)</ref>, may reduce the social and economic pressure to transition into homeownership before starting or expanding a family. In such a context, renting is therefore less likely to be perceived as a temporary or inferior tenure type, but rather a stable and viable long-term option. Additionally, housing costs in Denmark-particularly in Copenhagen-are relatively high compared to other Nordic countries (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>). This may further encourage individuals to prioritize housing flexibility over ownership, because purchasing a home typically requires a substantial down payment and long-term mortgage commitment that may compete with childbearing. Second, in Finland, we find no significant association between homeownership and fertility intentions.</p><p>This absence of a relationship may partly reflect limited statistical power and generally low fertility intentions, which together make tenure-based differences less detectable.</p><p>Regarding housing satisfaction, our analyses show no overall association with fertility intentions, and the results do not vary by country or parity. A plausible explanation for the null result is that different mechanisms offset each other in the pooled sample. Among respondents in their mid-reproductive years, housing satisfaction is slightly positively, though not significantly, related to fertility intentions. By contrast, at both tails of the reproductive age range (18-24 and 40-44), higher housing satisfaction is associated with lower fertility intentions. For young adults, this may reflect postponement of parenthood as a lifestyle choice; for older adults, this likely signals the completion of childbearing. Another complementary explanation for the null association is reverse causality and simultaneity between housing satisfaction and fertility intentions: individuals who intend to have children might assess their current housing situation more critically. Conversely, those without plans for further children may evaluate their housing more positively, since their current living arrangement fits their current lifestyle. Therefore, housing satisfaction can both influence fertility intentions and be shaped by them, with these opposing processes offsetting each other and yielding no clear relationship in cross-sectional data.</p><p>In sum, these findings carry important theoretical and policy implications, highlighting the significant role housing can play in shaping fertility intentions, especially in the context of increased role of economic uncertainty following the 2008 financial crisis <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Fahlén &amp; Oláh, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Florida et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Hellstrand et al., 2024)</ref>. Housing is a unique component of an individual's life course due to its multifaceted nature-it functions not only as a major household asset or consumption good but also a source of symbolic value, a foundation for community engagement, and often a prerequisite for family formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Kulu &amp; Steele, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Mulder, 2006a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Mulder, , 2013))</ref>. The Nordic context provides a crucial lens for interpreting these findings. Unlike in many other advanced economies, Nordic countries are characterised by extensive welfare provisions, universal childcare, and strong labour market protections for dual-earner couples <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Andersson et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Esping-Andersen, 1990)</ref>. These institutional features are thought to reduce the obstacles to childbearing. Nevertheless, our findings show that housing conditions remain significantly associated with fertility intentions, even within this supportive welfare regime. Furthermore, we observe variation across the four countriesfor example, Denmark's well-regulated rental sector may reduce the need for ownership before childbearing, while in Norway and Sweden, homeownership appears linked to fertility planning.</p><p>Despite its contributions, this study has some limitations. In sum, the property value proxy produces lower estimates of homeownership rate in the Swedish GGS than Statistics Sweden's population figures. However, the discrepancy can be explained by definitional, sampling, and measurement differences. We therefore consider the proxy reasonably accurate for capturing relative variation in homeownership within the Swedish GGS sample, but also acknowledge that it is an imperfect measure and should be interpreted with caution.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Data source: Nordic statistics database (CHIL02). Retrieved 11 August 2025.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Trends of Total Fertility Rate in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Data source: OECD Affordable Housing Database -indicator HM1.3 Housing tenures and indicator and PH4.2. Social rental housing stock (https://oe.cd/ahd).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Share of the population in different housing tenure types in 2020 and social rental housing stock as share of the total housing stock in 2022 or latest available year for Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Housing expenditure as % of final consumption expenditure of households in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden (2000-2022)    </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Fertility intentions across various demographic and social factors (n=13,420)</figDesc><graphic coords="25,96.09,70.90,381.85,671.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Weighted logistic regression results of housing tenure (Model 1) and housing satisfaction (Model 2) on fertility intentions (n=13,420, CI=95%)</figDesc><graphic coords="28,16.15,100.60,808.65,288.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>we estimated three further models where we added interaction terms to Model 1, between tenure and country (Model 3), tenure and age group (Model 4), and tenure and parity (Model 5). The visualised results for the interacting variables are shown in Figure 6, and complete regression tables can be found in Appendix 4. Note: Models in Figure 6 are all weighted and controlled for gender, education level, migrant background, partnership, country, parity, age group, and activity status; Asterisks indicate statistically significant pairwise comparisons between homeowners and tenants within groups. *** p&lt;0.001, ** p&lt;0.01, * p&lt;0.05. Data source: GGS-II Wave 1 in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. The heterogeneous association between housing tenure and fertility intentions across country, parity, and age group (n=13,420, CI=95%)</figDesc><graphic coords="29,18.68,317.95,557.25,159.06" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>8). Results for the interacting variables are displayed in Figure 7. For full estimates of the interaction models, see Appendix 4. Note: Models in Figure 7 are all weighted and controlled for gender, education level, migrant background, partnership, country, parity, age group, activity status, and intention to move; Asterisks indicate slopes (marginal effects) that are statistically different from zero. *** p&lt;0.001, ** p&lt;0.01, * p&lt;0.05. Data source: GGS-II Wave 1 in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. The heterogeneity association of housing satisfaction and fertility intentions across country, parity, and age group (n=13,420, CI=95%)</figDesc><graphic coords="31,19.38,129.00,556.60,166.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The sample frames consisted of all permanent residents listed in national population registers, aged 18-59 in Sweden, 18-49 in Denmark, and 18-54 in Finland and Norway. The initial sample sizes were 42,116 individuals in Denmark, 19,600 in Finland, 30,000 in Sweden, and 15,000 in Norway. The number of respondents was 8,269 inDenmark, 3,388 in Finland, 5,374 in Norway, and 8,082 in Sweden, thus corresponding to    </figDesc><table /><note><p>response rates of 18.5% in Finland, 27% in Sweden, 18.8% in Denmark, and 35.8% in Norway. The total sample size across the four countries was 25,113 individuals.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Weighted descriptive statistics of all variables by country</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell cols="2">Denmark Finland</cell><cell>Norway</cell><cell>Sweden</cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell>Positive fertility intention (%)</cell><cell>24.9</cell><cell>17.0</cell><cell>24.3</cell><cell>27.6</cell><cell>24.5</cell></row><row><cell>Homeowner (%)</cell><cell>46.8</cell><cell>43.1</cell><cell>60.2</cell><cell>47.6</cell><cell>49.3</cell></row><row><cell>Housing satisfaction (mean)</cell><cell>7.7</cell><cell>8.0</cell><cell>7.5</cell><cell>7.7</cell><cell>7.7</cell></row><row><cell>Female (%)</cell><cell>47.5</cell><cell>49.2</cell><cell>49.7</cell><cell>48.5</cell><cell>48.5</cell></row><row><cell>Migrant (%)</cell><cell>10.0</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>14.1</cell><cell>12.0</cell><cell>10.8</cell></row><row><cell>Activity status (% of column total)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Employed</cell><cell>51.3</cell><cell>57.4</cell><cell>66.1</cell><cell>68.6</cell><cell>60.3</cell></row><row><cell>Unemployed</cell><cell>4.3</cell><cell>7.0</cell><cell>2.6</cell><cell>4.6</cell><cell>4.4</cell></row><row><cell>In education or military service</cell><cell>35.5</cell><cell>29.8</cell><cell>26.7</cell><cell>24.0</cell><cell>29.5</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>8.9</cell><cell>5.7</cell><cell>4.7</cell><cell>2.8</cell><cell>5.8</cell></row><row><cell>Parity (% of column total)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>0</cell><cell>67.7</cell><cell>71.2</cell><cell>63.9</cell><cell>68.8</cell><cell>67.7</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>13.5</cell><cell>12.2</cell><cell>12.8</cell><cell>10.9</cell><cell>12.4</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>18.9</cell><cell>16.6</cell><cell>23.3</cell><cell>20.4</cell><cell>19.9</cell></row><row><cell>Age group (% of column total)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>18-24</cell><cell>36.5</cell><cell>28.8</cell><cell>30.0</cell><cell>25.0</cell><cell>30.7</cell></row><row><cell>25-29</cell><cell>15.4</cell><cell>17.7</cell><cell>20.4</cell><cell>21.1</cell><cell>18.4</cell></row><row><cell>30-34</cell><cell>16.6</cell><cell>19.9</cell><cell>19.8</cell><cell>19.2</cell><cell>18.5</cell></row><row><cell>35-39</cell><cell>15.5</cell><cell>17.5</cell><cell>16.3</cell><cell>16.5</cell><cell>16.2</cell></row><row><cell>40-44</cell><cell>16.1</cell><cell>16.2</cell><cell>13.5</cell><cell>18.2</cell><cell>16.2</cell></row><row><cell>Education level (% of column total)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Low (ISCED 0-2)</cell><cell>41.4</cell><cell>18.3</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>14.9</cell><cell>23.0</cell></row><row><cell>Medium (ISCED 3-4)</cell><cell>26.5</cell><cell>49.6</cell><cell>51.3</cell><cell>48.1</cell><cell>41.2</cell></row><row><cell>High (ISCED 5-8)</cell><cell>32.2</cell><cell>32.2</cell><cell>43.2</cell><cell>37.0</cell><cell>35.8</cell></row><row><cell>Partnership (% of column total)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Married</cell><cell>24.6</cell><cell>23.3</cell><cell>19.7</cell><cell>22.3</cell><cell>22.7</cell></row><row><cell>Cohabiting</cell><cell>21.8</cell><cell>25.8</cell><cell>33.7</cell><cell>34.0</cell><cell>28.4</cell></row><row><cell>LAT</cell><cell>12.5</cell><cell>13.2</cell><cell>11.5</cell><cell>11.3</cell><cell>12.0</cell></row><row><cell>Single</cell><cell>41.1</cell><cell>37.8</cell><cell>35.2</cell><cell>32.4</cell><cell>36.9</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Intention to move (% of column total)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>No</cell><cell>39.2</cell><cell>34.7</cell><cell>55.9</cell><cell>43.9</cell><cell>43.4</cell></row><row><cell>Unsure</cell><cell>10.1</cell><cell>20.1</cell><cell>18.7</cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell>10.3</cell></row><row><cell>Yes</cell><cell>50.7</cell><cell>45.2</cell><cell>25.4</cell><cell>56.1</cell><cell>46.3</cell></row><row><cell>N</cell><cell>5,001</cell><cell>2,268</cell><cell>2,773</cell><cell>3,378</cell><cell>13,420</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table A1</head><label>A1</label><figDesc>Stepwise Logistic Regressions of Housing Tenure and Housing satisfaction on Reporting Average Marginal Effects. Standard errors in parentheses. * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001 Data source: GGS-II Wave 1 in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell cols="2">Housing Tenure Models (1a) (1b) (1c)</cell><cell cols="3">Housing Satisfaction Models (2a) (2b) (2c)</cell></row><row><cell>35-39</cell><cell>0.116 ***</cell><cell>0.097 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.120 ***</cell><cell>0.109 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.015)</cell><cell>(0.018)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.014)</cell><cell>(0.018)</cell></row><row><cell>40-44</cell><cell>-0.034 **</cell><cell>-0.055 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.031 **</cell><cell>-0.042 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell>(0.014)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell>(0.015)</cell></row><row><cell>Education level (ref. Low)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Medium</cell><cell>0.050 **</cell><cell>0.007</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.051 **</cell><cell>0.008</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.016)</cell><cell>(0.016)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.016)</cell><cell>(0.016)</cell></row><row><cell>High</cell><cell>0.113 ***</cell><cell>0.049 **</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.116 ***</cell><cell>0.048 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell>(0.017)</cell></row><row><cell>Migrant</cell><cell>0.054 ***</cell><cell>0.042 **</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.050 ***</cell><cell>0.048 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.015)</cell><cell>(0.014)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.014)</cell><cell>(0.017)</cell></row><row><cell>Partnership</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cohabiting</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.039 **</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.032 *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.014)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.014)</cell></row><row><cell>LAT</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.119 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.137 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.019)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.018)</cell></row><row><cell>Single</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.204 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.212 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.015)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.015)</cell></row><row><cell>Parity (ref. no child)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.014</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.024</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.014)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.014)</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.236 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.225 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.009)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.009)</cell></row><row><cell>Activity status (ref: employed)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Unemployed</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.047 *</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.048 *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.022)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.022)</cell></row><row><cell>Student/Military</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.083 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.089 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.012)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.012)</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.072 **</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.068 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.024)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.024)</cell></row><row><cell>Intention to move (ref. No)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Fertility Intentions Unsure</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.020</cell></row><row><cell>Variables Yes Homeowner Observations</cell><cell cols="2">Housing Tenure Models (1a) (1b) (1c) 0.023 * 0.013 0.002 (0.009) (0.009) (0.009) 13,420 13,420 13,420</cell><cell cols="3">(0.015) Housing Satisfaction Models (2a) (2b) 0.070 *** (2c) (0.010) 13,420 13,420 13,420</cell></row><row><cell>Housing satisfaction Note:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.010 ***</cell><cell>-0.004</cell><cell>-0.002</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.002)</cell><cell>(0.002)</cell><cell>(0.002)</cell></row><row><cell>Country (ref. Denmark)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Norway</cell><cell>-0.058 ***</cell><cell>-0.049 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.057 ***</cell><cell>-0.033 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell>(0.011)</cell></row><row><cell>Sweden</cell><cell>-0.015</cell><cell>-0.028 **</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.014</cell><cell>-0.032 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.010)</cell><cell>(0.010)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.010)</cell><cell>(0.010)</cell></row><row><cell>Finland</cell><cell>-0.103 ***</cell><cell>-0.109 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.101 ***</cell><cell>-0.107 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.012)</cell><cell>(0.011)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.012)</cell><cell>(0.011)</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>0.035 ***</cell><cell>0.035 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.036 ***</cell><cell>0.037 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.009)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.009)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell></row><row><cell>Age group (ref. 18-24)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.024)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>25-29</cell><cell>0.280 ***</cell><cell>0.176 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.276 ***</cell><cell>0.174 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell>(0.016)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.016)</cell><cell>(0.016)</cell></row><row><cell>30-34</cell><cell>0.315 ***</cell><cell>0.224 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.317 ***</cell><cell>0.230 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell>(0.018)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.016)</cell><cell>(0.018)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table A2</head><label>A2</label><figDesc>Logistic regressions of fertility intentions on housing tenure and satisfaction, including interaction terms. Odds ratios reported</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell cols="3">Housing Tenure Models Model 3 Model 4 Model 5</cell><cell>Housing Satisfaction Models Model 6 Model 7 Model 8</cell></row><row><cell>Homeowner</cell><cell>0.686 ***</cell><cell>1.066</cell><cell>0.592 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.078)</cell><cell>(0.081)</cell><cell>(0.115)</cell></row><row><cell>Housing satisfaction</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.970</cell><cell>0.986</cell><cell>0.908 *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.031)</cell><cell>(0.021)</cell><cell>(0.035)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Tenure × Country (ref. Homeowner × Denmark)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Homeowner × Norway</cell><cell>1.932 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.334)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Homeowner × Sweden</cell><cell>1.813 ***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.272)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Homeowner × Finland</cell><cell>1.857 **</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.360)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Tenure × Parity (ref. Homeowner × No child)</head><label></label><figDesc>Odds ratios from logistic regression models. Standard errors in parentheses. Odds ratios greater (less) than 1 indicate higher (lower) odds of positive fertility intentions. * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001 Data source: GGS-II Wave 1 in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables Variables</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Housing Tenure Models Model 3 Model 4 Model 5 Housing Tenure Models Model 3 Model 4 Model 5</cell><cell cols="3">Housing Satisfaction Models Model 6 Model 7 Model 8 Housing Satisfaction Models Model 6 Model 7 Model 8</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Intention to move (ref. No)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.074)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">HS × Parity (ref. HS × No child) Unsure</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.176</cell><cell>1.177</cell><cell>1.184</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">HS × one child</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.140)</cell><cell>1.020 (0.140)</cell><cell>(0.141)</cell></row><row><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.702 ***</cell><cell>(0.043) 1.714 ***</cell><cell>1.746 ***</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">HS ×two children</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.128)</cell><cell>0.991 (0.129)</cell><cell>(0.132)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Observations</cell><cell>13,420</cell><cell>13,420</cell><cell>13,420</cell><cell>13,420</cell><cell>(0.051) 13,420</cell><cell>13,420</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">HS × Age group (ref. HS × 18-24) AIC</cell><cell>11164</cell><cell>11189</cell><cell>11150</cell><cell>11094</cell><cell>11100</cell><cell>11083</cell></row><row><cell>HS × 25-29</cell><cell>BIC</cell><cell>11344</cell><cell>11362</cell><cell>11337</cell><cell>11289</cell><cell>11288</cell><cell>1.130 * 11285</cell></row><row><cell>HS × 30-34 Note:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.060) 1.142 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.057)</cell></row><row><cell>HS × 35-39</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.109</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.059)</cell></row><row><cell>HS × 40-44</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.988</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.062)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Country (ref. Denmark)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Norway</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.497 ***</cell><cell>0.697 ***</cell><cell>0.672 ***</cell><cell>0.453 *</cell><cell>0.780 **</cell><cell>0.785 **</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.065)</cell><cell>(0.055)</cell><cell>(0.054)</cell><cell>(0.168)</cell><cell>(0.063)</cell><cell>(0.064)</cell></row><row><cell>Sweden</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.623 ***</cell><cell>0.818 **</cell><cell>0.791 **</cell><cell>0.859</cell><cell>0.791 **</cell><cell>0.787 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.064)</cell><cell>(0.058)</cell><cell>(0.057)</cell><cell>(0.275)</cell><cell>(0.057)</cell><cell>(0.057)</cell></row><row><cell>Finland</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.317 ***</cell><cell>0.420 ***</cell><cell>0.409 ***</cell><cell>0.207 **</cell><cell>0.419 ***</cell><cell>0.416 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.043)</cell><cell>(0.041)</cell><cell>(0.040)</cell><cell>(0.112)</cell><cell>(0.041)</cell><cell>(0.041)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Parity (ref. no child)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.089</cell><cell>1.070</cell><cell>1.083</cell><cell>1.160</cell><cell>0.997</cell><cell>1.157</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.095)</cell><cell>(0.150)</cell><cell>(0.095)</cell><cell>(0.102)</cell><cell>(0.335)</cell><cell>(0.102)</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.113 ***</cell><cell>0.175 ***</cell><cell>0.115 ***</cell><cell>0.125 ***</cell><cell>0.134 ***</cell><cell>0.125 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.012)</cell><cell>(0.035)</cell><cell>(0.013)</cell><cell>(0.013)</cell><cell>(0.056)</cell><cell>(0.014)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Age group (ref. 18-24)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>25-29</cell><cell></cell><cell>3.294 ***</cell><cell>3.387 ***</cell><cell>2.541 ***</cell><cell>3.462 ***</cell><cell>3.457 ***</cell><cell>1.398</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.377)</cell><cell>(0.385)</cell><cell>(0.329)</cell><cell>(0.396)</cell><cell>(0.396)</cell><cell>(0.572)</cell></row><row><cell>30-34</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.256 ***</cell><cell>4.414 ***</cell><cell>3.652 ***</cell><cell>4.762 ***</cell><cell>4.754 ***</cell><cell>1.765</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.522)</cell><cell>(0.538)</cell><cell>(0.509)</cell><cell>(0.592)</cell><cell>(0.590)</cell><cell>(0.681)</cell></row><row><cell>35-39</cell><cell></cell><cell>2.027 ***</cell><cell>2.099 ***</cell><cell>2.157 ***</cell><cell>2.316 ***</cell><cell>2.315 ***</cell><cell>1.072</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.276)</cell><cell>(0.287)</cell><cell>(0.359)</cell><cell>(0.322)</cell><cell>(0.322)</cell><cell>(0.435)</cell></row><row><cell>40-44</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.534 ***</cell><cell>0.553 ***</cell><cell>0.661 *</cell><cell>0.638 **</cell><cell>0.640 **</cell><cell>0.724</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.083)</cell><cell>(0.086)</cell><cell>(0.131)</cell><cell>(0.100)</cell><cell>(0.101)</cell><cell>(0.357)</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.315 ***</cell><cell>1.304 ***</cell><cell>1.308 ***</cell><cell>1.320 ***</cell><cell>1.324 ***</cell><cell>1.318 ***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.081)</cell><cell>(0.080)</cell><cell>(0.080)</cell><cell>(0.081)</cell><cell>(0.081)</cell><cell>(0.081)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Education level (ref. Low)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Homeowner × one child Medium Homeowner × two children High Migrant Tenure × Age group (ref. Homeowner × 18-24) 1.093 (0.141) 1.461 ** (0.193) 1.371 ** Homeowner × 25-29 (0.137) Partnership Homeowner × 30-34 Cohabiting 1.207 * (0.100) Homeowner × 35-39 LAT 0.458 *** (0.057) Homeowner × 40-44 Single 0.212 *** (0.022) Activity status (ref: employed) HS × Country (ref. HS × Denmark) HS × Norway Unemployed 0.720 (0.124) HS × Sweden Student/Military 0.532 *** (0.050) HS × Finland Other 0.566 ** (0.111)</cell><cell>1.059 1.017 (0.136) (0.166) 1.442 ** 0.571 * (0.191) (0.125) 1.352 ** (0.134) 1.252 ** (0.104) 0.460 *** (0.057) 0.219 *** (0.023) 0.716 (0.123) 0.531 *** (0.049) 0.582 ** (0.114)</cell><cell>1.042 (0.133) 1.422 ** (0.187) 1.350 ** (0.134) 2.749 *** (0.635) 1.235 * 1.988 ** (0.104) (0.459) 0.467 *** 1.386 (0.058) (0.339) 0.220 *** 1.128 (0.023) (0.323) 0.730 (0.126) 0.550 *** (0.051) 0.582 ** (0.114)</cell><cell>1.067 (0.139) 1.433 ** (0.192) 1.331 ** (0.133) 1.198 * (0.099) 0.401 *** (0.050) 0.204 *** (0.021) 0.706 * 1.075 (0.121) (0.050) 0.504 *** 0.989 (0.047) (0.040) 0.591 ** 1.093 (0.118)</cell><cell>1.063 (0.139) 1.436 ** (0.193) 1.333 ** (0.133) 1.204 * (0.100) 0.404 *** (0.050) 0.205 *** (0.022) 0.704 * (0.120) 0.503 *** (0.047) 0.597 ** (0.119)</cell><cell>1.055 (0.138) 1.415 ** (0.190) 1.334 ** (0.133) 1.198 * (0.099) 0.403 *** (0.050) 0.205 *** (0.021) 0.699 * (0.119) 0.500 *** (0.046) 0.594 ** (0.118)</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank <rs type="person">Mirkka Danielsbacka</rs>, <rs type="person">Sofi Ohlsson-Wijk</rs>, and the participants of the <rs type="institution">Nordic Demographic Symposium 2025</rs> for their valuable comments and feedback on an earlier version of this paper. YL, EC, and JN were supported by the <rs type="funder">SRC</rs> of the <rs type="funder">Academy of Finland</rs>, FLUX consortium, decision number <rs type="grantNumber">345130</rs>. JN and EC were supported by the <rs type="funder">ROCKWOOL Foundation</rs> (Determinants of later and forgone parenthood in the Nordic countries) and <rs type="funder">Academy of Finland</rs> grant no. <rs type="grantNumber">320162</rs> (<rs type="grantName">INVEST Research Flagship</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_EH7aKV9">
					<idno type="grant-number">345130</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_UXWwg8R">
					<idno type="grant-number">320162</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">INVEST Research Flagship</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Availability Statement</head><p>The data that support the findings of this study are freely available for researchers from the Generations and Gender Program (https://www.ggp-i.org/).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendices</head><p>Appendix 1 Accuracy of the proxy measure of housing tenure in the Swedish sample This study used property value as a proxy for housing tenure among respondents in the Swedish GGS. In the main analysis, we coded those reporting owned properties valued at less than €4,999 as non-homeowners and those reporting more than €5,000 as homeowners.</p><p>Consequently, the housing tenure proxy indicates that 47.6% of the Swedish GGS respondents are homeowners (see Table <ref type="table">1</ref> in Section 3.2).</p><p>To evaluate the validity of this proxy, we attempted cross-country validation: that is, we aimed to examine whether respondents in other three Nordic countries who report low property values also tended to identify as non-homeowners. However, this approach is hampered by data limitations. The Norwegian sample is entirely missing the variable "inc01. value of property", while the Danish and Finnish samples have high levels of missing data (44% and 35%, respectively) that are inherent to the survey design and cannot be resolved ex post. As a result, direct comparisons between Sweden and these countries using property value as a tenure proxy are problematic.</p><p>We thus compared our estimate based on the property value variable in the Swedish GGS to Statistics Sweden's figures on the distribution of housing tenure among the Swedish population aged 18-44 (see Figure <ref type="figure">A1</ref>). According to Statistics Sweden, in 2021, 37% of this population lived in owner-occupied dwellings and 22% lived in tenant-owned home. As tenant-owned housing in Sweden today largely functions as owner-occupied housing <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">(Sørvoll et al., 2023)</ref>, the homeownership rate among the Swedish population aged 18-44 can be considered around 59% (owner-occupied plus tenant-owned).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix 2 Mediation analysis of housing satisfaction</head><p>This appendix presents supplementary mediation analyses examining whether housing satisfaction and intention to move mediate the relationship between homeownership and fertility intentions. We employ the Karlson-Holm-Breen (KHB) decomposition method with 1,000 bootstrap replications to obtain more robust and unbiased estimates, particularly in cases where the assumption of normality may not hold, such as in logistic regression models <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Karlson &amp; Holm, 2011)</ref>. The KHB decomposition using average partial effects (APEs), which are similar to average marginal effects in terms of interpretation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Breen et al., 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">A2</ref> shows that the effect of homeownership is partially mediated by intention to move.</p><p>In Model 1, without accounting for mediators, we found no significant association between housing tenure and fertility intentions. However, when both housing satisfaction and intention to move are considered as mediators, the direct effect becomes significantly positive: homeowners have a 3.1 percentage point higher probability of intending to have a child (APE = 0.031, SE = 0.008, p &lt; 0.001, 95% CI = [0.016, 0.046]). The decomposition further indicates that this suppression effect is primarily driven by intention to move. Specifically, homeownership is associated with a lower likelihood of planning to move (APE= -0.015, p&lt;0.001), and those who intend to move are substantially less likely to report positive fertility intention (APE= -0.108, p&lt;0.001). By contrast, housing satisfaction does not play a meaningful mediating role.</p><p>Overall, these results suggest a suppression effect of mediator: intention to move absorbs approximately 50% of the total association between homeownership and fertility intentions, thereby masking the underlying positive direct effect of homeownership.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix 4 Models with country, parity, and age group interactions</head><p>Table A2 reports the complete regression results for Models 3-8 in Section 4.3. Models 3-5 include housing tenure and its interactions with country, parity, and age group, respectively. Models 6-8 mirror this specification using housing satisfaction instead of tenure. Odds ratios are shown, with standard errors in parentheses. Interaction terms indicate deviations relative to the specified reference category (Denmark for country, no child for parity, ages 18-24 for age group). For ease of interpretation, average marginal effects of the main explanatory variables and interaction terms are presented in the main text and figures, while this appendix provides the full model estimates as a robustness reference.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix 5 Robustness analysis -Capital region dummy</head><p>This robustness check adds a dummy variable indicating whether respondents reside in a capital region to Models 1 and 2 in Section 4.2. The rationale is that the relationship between housing and fertility may confound by geographical contexts. In the Nordic countries, especially the capital areas may differ from other regions in housing affordability, labour opportunities, demographic composition, and prevailing housing norms.</p><p>Because the Danish sample lacks information on geographical subregions, this robustness check was limited to Finland, Norway, and Sweden. The definitions of capital region are not fully comparable, but they represent the most detailed subdivisions available: Helsinki-Uusimaa (the Helsinki metropolitan area, NUTS-2) in Finland, Oslo County (one of 11 counties) in Norway, and the East region (NUTS-1, including Stockholm and East Middle Sweden) in Sweden. Among respondents with valid data (n = 8,411), an average of 33% reside in a capital region-35% in Finland, 18% in Norway, and 42% in Sweden.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">A3</ref> presents the robustness analysis: Models 1 and 2 replicate the baseline models from Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> in Section 4.2; Models 1a and 2a add the capital region covariate to the baseline model; and Models 1b and 2b only exclude the Danish sample from the baseline model.</p><p>Comparing Model 1a with Model 1, the AME for homeownership shifts from non-significant to significant, while for housing satisfaction (Model 2a vs. Model 2) no change is observed.</p><p>However, in Models 1b and 2b-where the only difference is the exclusion of the Danish sample from baseline models-we observe the same shifts as in Models 1a and 2a, indicating that the changes are driven by sample composition rather than by the capital region control. In sum, the capital region variable itself does not alter the associations between housing and fertility intentions. The observed changes arise from the exclusion of Denmark, and the capital region dummy is not statistically significant in any specification, further indicating that subnational regional context is not driving the results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix 6 Robustness analysis -Net household income variable</head><p>There are important limitations to the income data available in the four GGSs. First, while income is measured as an ordinal variable in all four countries, both the number of intervals and the cut-off points between intervals vary between countries, which severely limits crosscountry comparability. Second, the share of respondents with missing information on income is high in Denmark (36 %), Finland (24 %), and Norway (27 %). Given these limitations, we constructed our net household income variable by dividing individuals within each country into three roughly equal groups: high-, medium-, and low-income households.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">A4</ref> documents how the original income categories were collapsed into these three groups. We are aware that this approach obscures between-country differences in absolute income, purchasing power, and more nuanced differences in income distributions, especially at the extremes of wealth and poverty. Table <ref type="table">A5</ref> shows that the inclusion or exclusion of the income variable in the baseline model has no significant effect on main results. Specifically, the estimated average marginal effect for the key independent variables remains stable in both direction and magnitude, and their statistical significance is unaffected. Furthermore, the model fit indices, such as the pseudo Rsquared, Akaike Information Criterion (AIC), and Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC), exhibit only minimal changes, suggesting that the income variable does not substantially influence the explanatory power of the model. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust and fertility in uncertain times</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aassve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Le Moglie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mencarini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00324728.2020.1742927</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00324728.2020.1742927" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fertility intentions: An approach based on the theory of planned behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ajzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Klobas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0749-5978(91)90020-TAjzen</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2013.29.8" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Demographic Research</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A theoretical and methodological approach to the study of residential satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Amérigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Aragones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/jevp.1996.0038</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1006/jevp.1996.0038" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cohort fertility patterns in the Nordic countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rønsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Knudsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lappegård</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Neyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Skrede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Teschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vikat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4054/DemRes.2009.20.14</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2009.20.14" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demographic Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">House price bubbles in the Nordic countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Anundsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nordic Economic Policy Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing wealth, fertility intentions and fertility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Atalay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Whelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jhe.2021.101787</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhe.2021.101787" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Housing Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101787</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Beyond the continuum: A micro-level analysis of the gender equalityfertility nexus in three Nordic countries (No. WP-2024-004)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Begall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hiekel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2024-004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2024-004" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">MPIDR Working Paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The resilience of social rental housing in the United Kingdom, Sweden and Denmark. How institutions matter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Blackwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bengtsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10/gkzgqp" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Historicizing housing typologies: Beyond welfare state regimes and varieties of residential capitalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Blackwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10/gd8s6p" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="298" to="318" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing and fertility: A macro-level, multi-country investigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brauner-Otto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02673037.2021.1893279</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02673037.2021.1893279" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="569" to="596" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">2023. 1993-2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on a reformulation of the KHB method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Breen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bernt Karlson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Holm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0049124118789717</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0049124118789717" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Methods &amp; Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="901" to="912" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing asset-based welfare capitalism: Wealth inequality, housing finance and household risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bryant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Spies-Butcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stebbing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02673037.2022.2056150</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02673037.2022.2056150" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="480" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Converse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rodgers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.russellsage.org/publications/book/quality-american-life" />
		<title level="m">The Quality of American Life: Perceptions, Evaluations, and Satisfactions. Russell Sage Foundation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing context and childbearing in Sweden: A cohort study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chudnovskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02673037.2018.1458288</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02673037.2018.1458288" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="488" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do women delay family formation in expensive housing markets?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4054/DemRes.2012.27.1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2012.27.1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demographic Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond the economic gaze: Childbearing during and after recessions in the Nordic countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Comolli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Neyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dommermuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fallesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jalovaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jónsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kolk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lappegård</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10680-020-09570-0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10680-020-09570-0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Population</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="520" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Home prices, fertility, and early-life health outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Daysal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lovenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Siersbaek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Wasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpubeco.2021.104366</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpubeco.2021.104366" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">104366</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="0198">2021. 198</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">House prices and birth rates: The impact of the real estate market on the decision to have a baby</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dettling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kearney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpubeco.2013.09.009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpubeco.2013.09.009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disentangling the housing satisfaction puzzle: Does homeownership really matter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Diaz-Serrano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.joep.2009.06.006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joep.2009.06.006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="745" to="755" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceptions of housing stability and fertility intentions among public housing renters in Guangzhou</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cities.2023.104643</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities.2023.104643" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cities</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104643</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<pubPlace>China</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homeownership and housing satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elsinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hoekstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10901-005-9023-4</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10901-005-9023-4" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Housing and the Built Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="424" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Three Worlds of Welfare Capitalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Esping-Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incomplete Revolution: Adapting Welfare States to Women&apos;s New Roles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Esping-Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://books.google.fi/books?id=4oPrLlEZuxgC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Polity</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Economic uncertainty and first-birth intentions in Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fahlén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Oláh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4054/DemRes.2018.39.28</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2018.39.28" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demographic Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="795" to="834" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing costs, self-employment, and fertility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Florida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mellander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/psp.2413</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/psp.2413" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population, Space and Place</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2413</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Delayed and depressed: From expensive housing to smaller families</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Flynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14616718.2016.1241936</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14616718.2016.1241936" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Housing Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="374" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data Brief: The Generations and Gender Survey second round (GGS-II)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gauthier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Grünwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bujard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Caporali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Deimantas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Emery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Jablonski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Koops</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rijken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.10220746</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10220746" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">GGP Technical Paper Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The inbetweeners of the housing markets-young adults facing housing inequality in Malmö, Sweden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02673037.2021.1893278</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02673037.2021.1893278" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="522" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Not just later, but fewer: Novel trends in cohort fertility in the Nordic countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hellstrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nisén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Miranda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fallesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dommermuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Myrskylä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1215/00703370-9373618</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1215/00703370-9373618" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1373" to="1399" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hellstrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nisén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Myrskylä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/esr/jcae001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/esr/jcae001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Educational field, economic uncertainty, and fertility decline in Finland in 2010-2019</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>jcae001</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Why fertility has been declining in Finland after the Global Recession? A theoretical approach. Finnish Yearbook of Population Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hiilamo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.23979/fypr.85090</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.23979/fypr.85090" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="51" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homeownership and fertility intentions among migrant population in urban China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02673037.2022.2108382</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02673037.2022.2108382" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1176" to="1198" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Values, objective needs, and subjective satisfaction among western publics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Inglehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/001041407700900403</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/001041407700900403" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="458" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technical Guidelines for Weighting in GGS-II: Instructions for National Teams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Jablonski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liefbroer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brilhault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Grünwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lugtig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Maslovskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rijken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.14024136</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14024136" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">GGP Technical Paper Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing Affordability Crisis and Delayed Fertility: Evidence from the USA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Japaridze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sayour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>11113- 024-09865-8</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population Research and Policy Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors influencing fertility intentions of newlyweds in South Korea: Focus on demographics, socioeconomics, housing situation, residential satisfaction, and housing expectation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3390/su13031534</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3390/su13031534" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustainability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1534</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to calculate the number of children in the Generations and Gender Survey Round 2 (Version 2) [Computer software]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Grünwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rijken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.10889300</idno>
		<ptr target="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.10889300" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">GGP Technical Paper Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jónsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.12765/CPoS-2024-07</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.12765/CPoS-2024-07" />
		<title level="m">Fertility decline in Iceland, 2013-2022: Trends and structures. Comparative Population Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="180" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decomposing primary and secondary effects: A new decomposition method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Karlson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Holm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.rssm.2010.12.005</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rssm.2010.12.005" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Social Stratification and Mobility</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The puzzle of falling US birth rates since the great recession</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kearney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pardue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/jep.36.1.151</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1257/jep.36.1.151" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Perspectives</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rent regulation in 21st century Europe. Comparative perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kettunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ruonavaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02673037.2020.1769564</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02673037.2020.1769564" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1446" to="1468" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">No price like home: Global house prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Knoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schularick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Steger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10/f9wzbd" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Varieties of social democracy and cooperativism: Explaining the historical divergence between housing regimes in Nordic and German-speaking countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sørvoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/ssh.2021.16</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/ssh.2021.16" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interrelationships between childbearing and housing transitions in the family life course</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kulu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Steele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13524-013-0216-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s13524-013-0216-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1687" to="1714" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fertility differences by housing type: The effect of housing conditions or of selective moves? Demographic Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kulu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vikat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4054/DemRes.2007.17.26</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2007.17.26" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="775" to="802" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wealth and Family Formation: Insights from First Cohabitation, Marriage, and Birth in Germany</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>10680- 025-09738-6</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Population</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The new housing precariat: Experiences of precarious housing in Malmö, Sweden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Listerborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02673037.2021.1935775</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/02673037.2021.1935775" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Housing Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1304" to="1322" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing wealth and fertility: Evidence from China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00148-021-00879-6</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00148-021-00879-6" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Population Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">House price, fertility rates and reproductive intentions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.chieco.2020.101496</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chieco.2020.101496" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">China Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101496</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of liquid housing wealth on college enrollment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lovenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/660775</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1086/660775" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Labor Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="741" to="771" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do family wealth shocks affect fertility choices? Evidence from the housing market</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lovenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mumford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1162/REST_a_00266</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1162/REST_a_00266" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Economics and Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="464" to="475" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Great Recession and fertility in Europe: A subnational analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Matysiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sobotka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vignoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10680-020-09556-y</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10680-020-09556-y" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Population</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mizutani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The effects of housing wealth on fertility decisions: Evidence from Japan</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2710" to="2724" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Logistic regression: Why we cannot do what we think we can do, and what we can do about it</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/esr/jcp006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/esr/jcp006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Home-ownership and family formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mulder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10901-006-9050-9</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10901-006-9050-9" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Housing and the Built Environment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006a</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Population and housing: A two-sided relationship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mulder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4054/DemRes.2006.15.13</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2006.15.13" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demographic Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="412" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Family dynamics and housing: Conceptual issues and empirical findings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mulder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4054/DemRes.2013.29.14</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2013.29.14" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demographic Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exploring Norway&apos;s Fertility, Work, and Family Policy Trends</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1787/f0c7bddf-en</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1787/f0c7bddf-en" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>OECD Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disentangling the Swedish fertility decline of the 2010s</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ohlsson-Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4054/DemRes.2022.47.12</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2022.47.12" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demographic Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing and children: Simultaneous decisions?-a cohort study of young adults&apos; housing and family formation decision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Öst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00148-010-0345-5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00148-010-0345-5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Population Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="366" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing satisfaction in Finland with regard to area, dwelling type and tenure status</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pekkonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Haverinen-Shaughnessy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21101/cejph.a4080</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.21101/cejph.a4080" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Central European Journal of Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The wealth inequality of nations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Pfeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Waitkus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10/gm7qsb" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="602" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How divergent housing institutions evolve: A comparison of swedish tenant co-operatives and finnish shareholders&apos; housing companies. Housing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ruonavaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14036090500375373</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/14036090500375373" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theory and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Home ownership and Nordic housing policies in &apos;retrenchment&apos;. In Beyond Home Ownership</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ruonavaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9780203182260-7/home-ownership-nordic-housing-policies-retrenchment-hannu-ruonavaara</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.4324/9780203182260-7/home-ownership-nordic-housing-policies-retrenchment-hannu-ruonavaara" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="107" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Retrenchment and social housing: The case of Finland</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ruonavaara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.13060/23362839.2017.4.2.382</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.13060/23362839.2017.4.2.382" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Critical Housing Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.regsciurbeco.2008.08.002</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.regsciurbeco.2008.08.002" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Do higher rents discourage fertility? Evidence from US cities</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1940">2009. 1940-2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="42" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Housing and welfare in Sweden, Norway and the wider Nordic region</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sørvoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Listerborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sandberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Routledge Handbook of Housing and Welfare</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The changing association between homeownership and the transition to parenthood</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tocchioni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Berrington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vignoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vitali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1215/00703370-9420322</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1215/00703370-9420322" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1843" to="1865" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">House prices and fertility: Can the Dutch housing crisis explain the post-2010 fertility decline? Population, Space and Place</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/psp.2787</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/psp.2787" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">2787</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fertility Postponement, Economic Uncertainty, and the Increasing Income Prerequisites of Parenthood</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Billari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/padr.12624</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/padr.12624" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population and Development Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relevance of social interactions on housing satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Vera-Toscano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ateca-Amestoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11205-007-9107-5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-007-9107-5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Indicators Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social housing in Denmark</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Vestergaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Scanlon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/9781118412367.ch5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118412367.ch5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Social Housing in Europe</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Scanlon</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Whitehead</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Arrigoitia</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="90" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fertility intentions and residential relocations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vidal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huinink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Feldhaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13524-017-0592-0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s13524-017-0592-0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1305" to="1330" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Narratives of the future affect fertility: Evidence from a laboratory experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vignoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Minello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bazzani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Matera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rapallini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10680-021-09602-3</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10680-021-09602-3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Population</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vignoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rinesi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mussino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/psp.1716</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/psp.1716" />
		<title level="m">A home to plan the first child? Fertility intentions and housing conditions in Italy. Population, Space and Place</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="71" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of house price on fertility: Evidence from Hong Kong</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1465-7295.2009.00213.x</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1465-7295.2009.00213.x" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economic Inquiry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
