<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">VISAP&apos;24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jenny</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jinrui</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tomas</forename><surname>Vancisin</surname></persName>
							<email>tvancisi@ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Law (PeaceRep</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laura</forename><surname>Wise</surname></persName>
							<email>laura.wise@ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Law (PeaceRep</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xinhuan</forename><surname>Shu</surname></persName>
							<email>xinhuan.shu@newcastle.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Newcastle</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tara</forename><surname>Capel</surname></persName>
							<email>tcapel@ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">School of Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Uta</forename><surname>Hinrichs</surname></persName>
							<email>uhinrich@ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">School of Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">VISAP&apos;24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D9E511E3E84F5F6D6DFDF23B135E58E9</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Peace Process</term>
					<term>Women in Peace Agreements</term>
					<term>Gender Equality</term>
					<term>Data Physicalization</term>
					<term>Debossing Data</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>With armed conflicts and wars continuing to occur globally, the pursuit of peace is an enduring concern. In the efforts to resolve these conflicts, a vast number of peace agreements have been signed. In this project, we examine the extent to which women and gender are explicitly acknowledged or addressed in peace agreements. Using debossing, we physicalize the mentions of women and gender in these agreements as a means to increase awareness and recognition of these often-overlooked constituencies.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>contestation about the nature of the state, played out through its formal institutions" <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref>. This means that any gaps in the way that the peace agreement understands or responds to 'gender', may become stuck and difficult to resolve through institutions captured by elite interests.</p><p>Building gendered language into peace agreements to act as 'hooks' <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7]</ref> can also serve as a practical strategy for improving the inclusiveness of a peace process. For example, gender equality advocates involved in peace mediation might refer back to vague commitments conflict parties made in a prenegotiation agreement to "respect gender equality" and use this reference as a building block to advocate for gender quotas in legislative bodies at a comprehensive phase of negotiations.</p><p>Finally, there is an international normative commitment to include gender perspectives when negotiating and implementing peace agreements, which was made through the adoption of United States Security Council Resolution 1325 in 2000. The Resolution 'calls on all actors involved, when negotiating and implementing peace agreements, to adopt a gender perspective, including, inter alia:</p><p>(a) The special needs of women and girls during repatriation and resettlement and for default. Peace agreements contain institutional configurations, security mechanisms, and human rights regimes that all shape different gendered outcomes, or impact women's lives.</p><p>Language in peace agreements that is perceived as 'neutral' in reality is 'gender blind,' in that it overlooks or ignores the role that gender plays in everyday life. This blindness has consequences for the lives of women and gender minorities in those contexts: "issues that are not specifically mentioned in the agreement can be difficult to prioritize post-agreement, and importantly, international implementation mechanisms and donor funding flow from the agreement's priorities" <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. The distinction between women and gender minorities is also important as they encompass different groups of people each with nuanced challenges and experiences.</p><p>Women generally refer to individuals whose gender identity matches their female sex assigned at birth, and gender minorities include individuals whose gender identity or expression differs from their sex assigned at birth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Peace agreements can also create 'sticky'</head><p>institutional arrangements that can be hard to re-negotiate later on. Rather than peace agreements instigating an interim transition to more majoritarian, democratic settlements, peace agreements can inadvertently create "a formalized political unsettlement" <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. In this scenario, "the peace processes institutionalize disagreement into a set of agreed political</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Peace agreements are a common practice in the resolution and regulation of modern conflict, with over 2000 peace agreements reached in more than 150 peace processes worldwide since 1990 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. These peace agreements often become blueprints for conflict transformation, formalizing the agreed way of resolving violent compatibility between political elites and, as such, shaping the political settlement that emerges following the signing of a peace deal.</p><p>Although there is no commonly agreed definition of what a peace agreement is, they can have both a legal status and a social status as to how actors understand the agreed rules and responsibilities of the transition <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Despite their important role, only 21% of peace agreements from 1990-2024 contain explicit references to girls, women, gender, or sexual violence <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Consequently, the arrangements and institutions created by a peace agreement can have implications for how girls, women, gender minorities, and sexual minorities experience the peace and transition which that agreement governs.</p><p>Whether a blueprint for a post-conflict settlement, or a peace process roadmap, peace agreements are not gender neutral by VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios.</p><p>The debossed text on paper is intentionally designed to be difficult to see unless actively engaged with. As such, the installation allows for interactions involving light and shading to enable people to better perceive the data presented on the paper. This intentional design choice symbolizes these often-overlooked issues, prompting viewers to engage more deeply to uncover these data insights.</p><p>We address the "Diversity Data" theme by implementing inclusive practices and contributing to building a more equitable world through peace initiatives. In this pictorial, we present our work that highlights the historically limited references to and involvement of girls, women, and gender minorities in peace agreements and the limited capacity in which gender-related issues are considered when these groups are mentioned.</p><p>To achieve this, we deploy debossing as a method and paper as a medium to foreground the gender-related text found in the 22 peace agreements (See Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>) that make up the Afghanistan 2000s post-intervention process. This installation is designed so that each piece of paper represents a peace agreement with gender-related text imprinted into the piece of paper according to where and how they are mentioned in the peace agreement. VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Peace Data</head><p>We began this project by collaborating with PeaceRep, a research consortium dedicated to rethinking peace and transition processes.  VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pieces of Peace</head><p>VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios.</p><p>deeply to uncover these critical insights.</p><p>We first introduce the main data encoding elements of this project: 'peace agreement display,' 'peace process layout,' and 'viewers' interactions. <ref type="bibr">'</ref> The first two encoding elements focus on the appearance of the data, such as the text expression, text position, and agreement layouts (See Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>).</p><p>The last element focuses on ways in which the viewer can interact with the work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Peace agreement display</head><p>Following the above idea, this section introduces our design on the chosen medium:</p><p>Paper. Each piece of paper represents a peace agreement, and we deboss genderrelated text information according to where and how it is mentioned in the agreement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">How do we select the text for debossing</head><p>The selected texts for debossing come from the PA-X GENDER database, which is structured </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Debossing data</head><p>In this project, we deboss gender-related text in a peace agreement on paper. We choose paper as a medium due to its inherent fragility and susceptibility to tearing, which serves as a symbol of the vulnerabilities experienced by populations affected by conflict and war.</p><p>By piecing together individual agreements, we can reveal a whole picture of one peace process, which allows us to critically examine the need to address and mend these vulnerabilities in peace processes.</p><p>Embossing and debossing are techniques used to create raised or recessed relief of text on a variety of materials, and for our project, we chose the latter (debossing). Unlike traditional 2D visualizations, which predominantly occur in digital formats and only target the user's sight, our approach leverages physicalization <ref type="bibr">[14]</ref> to engage additional senses. Debossing allows the paper texture to be seen and felt, adding a physical dimension to the visual experience.</p><p>In the scope of this project, debossing is employed to accentuate gender-related content within peace agreements. This technique subtly conveys information about text that has traditionally been noted with pen and ink, making it less immediately noticeable unless deliberately sought. This intentional design choice symbolizes the often-overlooked groups of people, prompting viewers to engage more VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios.</p><p>The primary aim is to ensure readability and print quality. After evaluating multiple fonts, sizes, widths, and tracking options, "Segoe UI Variable Display" was chosen. The software Sure Cuts A Lot 6 (SCAL) was used to create specific text settings for debossing. The chosen setup includes a line width of 1.0, a text width of 100%, text tracking at 100%, and a font size of 0.34 cm, ensuring clear visibility (See Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>).  VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios. The debossing is done using the Silver Bullet</p><p>Machine. It has 6 Pinch Wheels to allow the mat to move vertically. It also has two Tool</p><p>Holders for inserting tools such as cutting, engraving, drawing, and embossing (See Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8</ref>). The maximum length available between the pitch wheels has some mechanical constraints, which accommodates a paper width of up to 19 cm to prevent undesirable roller marks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">How do we locate text on paper</head><p>The exact positions of the gender-related texts The unified header height is set to 6 cm, and the title has a font size of 0.60 cm. This is to provide enough space and visibility, allowing viewers to recognize and relate the documents to specific historical contexts quickly.</p><p>VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Paper selection</head><p>Five types of paper were tested in varying grams per square meter (gsm) (Fig.  VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios. Peace process layout The arrangement of the 22 peace agreements from Afghanistan's post-intervention era spans the period 1990 -2024. These agreements are displayed on a wall with the x-axis serving as the temporal indicator. This chronological display allows viewers to visually trace the progression and timing of these agreements over the years. Given the varying time gaps between some agreements, the placement on the wall is adjusted accordingly. Agreements that are separated by larger time intervals are spaced further apart. This method visually emphasizes the periods of heightened or reduced activity in the peace process, offering an intuitive grasp of the pacing and frequency of agreement formation. Of the 9 agreements displayed (See Fig. 4), 2 documents do not mention PAX-Gender categorized contexts. Both of these documents have a timeline that begins in February 2020. The absence of text in these documents could potentially draw attention to the presence or absence of gender considerations in the agreements, while also subtly highlighting the evolution of women's issues and gender-related gaps. VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios.   VISAP'24, Pictorials and annotated portfolios. The use of physical pieces of paper, each designed to represent a single peace agreement and with only the gender-related text within them debossed, when placed together, highlights to viewers the insignificant amount of gender-related text. The debossed text is also intentionally designed to be difficult to see unless actively interacted with through light or shading. This installation asks viewers to critically engage and reflect on the implications that this limited representation has for girls, women, and gender minorities </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>rehabilitation, reintegration, and post-conflict reconstruction; (b) Measures that support local women's peace initiatives and indigenous processes for conflict resolution, and that involve women in all of the implementation mechanisms of the peace agreements; (c) Measures that ensure the protection of and respect for human rights of women and girls, particularly as they relate to the constitution, the electoral system, the police, and the judiciary' [8]. Almost 25 years since UNSCR 1325 was adopted, however, peace agreements often overlook or ignore the special needs of women, girls, and gender/sexual minorities in peace and conflict, and rarely take a comprehensive gender perspective throughout the agreement [9].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. One of the 22 peace agreements from the Afghanistan 2000s post-intervention process</figDesc><graphic coords="3,318.87,309.40,211.13,208.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>PeaceRep's work focuses on peace processes, which are structured efforts to resolve profound disagreements between conflicting entities [10]. They maintain the Peace Agreement Dataset (PAX), a publicly accessible archive that documents formally signed peace agreements that are part of over 150 peace processes, spanning the period 1990-2023 [11]. Our project draws from the PAX Gender sub-dataset [1], where domain experts have categorized the agreements into 11 areas concerning provisions on women, girls, gender, and/or sexual violence. These categories encompass areas such as Participation, Equality, Particular groups of women, International law, New institutions, Violence Against Women, Transitional justice, Institutional reform, Development, Implementation, etc. It is noteworthy that of the 2055 agreements compiled in the PAX, only 436 (21%) contain provisions addressing women, gender, and/or sexual violence (Fig. 3). In exploring the influence of gender perspectives across different peace processes, we worked extensively with experts at PeaceRep and chose the Afghanistan 2000s post-intervention process as our case study. Remarkably, a majority (73%) of these agreements enshrine the principles of gender equality in human rights and advocate for women's participation as protected under their constitution. Yet, despite these assurances, the Taliban's takeover of Afghanistan in 2021 has stripped women of their fundamental rights, dignity, and freedoms [12]. Many of these agreements fall short of their promises to transform patriarchal structures and elevate women's rights and security [13]. Delving into the provisions of Afghanistan's post-intervention agreements, we aimed to portray them in a manner that not only reflected the commitments in agreements but also highlighted the gaps in implementation, thereby igniting critical reflection and dialogue among our audience about these issues.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Example provision with text addressing women, gender, or sexual violence (ID848).</figDesc><graphic coords="4,90.61,261.00,439.37,267.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. An overview of the 9 peace agreements installed. The setup is part of the 22 agreements in the Afghanistan 2000s post-intervention process, which spans from July 22, 2010, to February 29, 2020.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,92.00,152.88,665.18,272.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc>into 11 categories. Domain researchers have coded the data in detail, focusing directly on women, girls, gender, or sexual violence. The selection process involved iterations and discussions about what to imprint, how and in what form (e.g., oval or square shapes or braille), and which words or sentences to use before deciding on selected texts (See Fig. 6).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Data encoding elements of ID 848.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,538.94,105.00,219.01,417.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Different iterations and ideas on text expression.Figure 7. Final text and expression choice. With the same font size</figDesc><graphic coords="7,90.93,148.94,335.08,361.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Different iterations and ideas on text expression.Figure 7. Final text and expression choice. With the same font size and settings, the embossed texts require more effort to read.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,439.98,29.14,321.78,483.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Silver Bullet Machine Embossing machine in working conditions.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,101.87,28.97,417.00,493.33" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><figDesc>within the document are calculated to ensure optimal placement relative to the overall document dimensions. The calculations were based on the position where the gender-related texts are located within the original document. We take the agreement ID 848 'Conclusions of the Conference on Afghanistan and the International Community: From Transition to the Transformation Decade (Bonn Conference)' as an example. It contains 3379 words, and the required paper height is approximately 58 cm, based on font size and visibility requirements. The debossed text covers approximately the area proportional to how much women, gender, and/or sexual violence content is mentioned relative to the whole document. To provide the viewer with more context, headers with the agreement title and date are printed in black.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><figDesc>9): Southbank Smooth (310gsm); Bread &amp; Butter (270gsm); Somerset Velvet Buff (250gsm); Seawhite Cartridge Paper (220gsm); and Seawhite Cartridge Paper (140gsm). The decision was made to use higher gsm paper for debossing. The higher gsm paper provides better quality debossing, ensuring the texts are clearly visible and well-defined.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Showcase of various papers used for debossing.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,320.00,240.66,436.88,252.86" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Peace agreements with and without light comparison.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,92.00,30.00,399.00,496.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><figDesc>To consider how to show historically 'missing' mentions of women, our installation employs debossed texts on paper. These texts are subtly crafted into the flat sections of the paper, typically difficult to see until revealed under specific lighting conditions. The installation is positioned on the wall to be viewed at an optimal upright angle. By altering the angle of light that strikes the paper, we can enhance the visibility of the text. When viewers use a phone torch, as shown in Fig. 10, the otherwise hidden texts become more visible, inviting proactive engagement and discovery. The installation also features sound recordings of the 'Agreement on Provisional Arrangements in Afghanistan Pending the Re-establishment of Permanent Government Institutions' (commonly known as the 'Bonn Agreement'). Recorded by two native speakers of Dari (one of Afghanistan's official languages), the audio will include all sections of the agreement, with a female voice narrating the sentences that contain provisions addressing women, gender, and/or sexual violence, and a male voice narrating the remaining sections. Other enhancing interactions include physically tracing the debossed text with a pencil, as depicted in Fig. 11. This interaction not only helps to make the text more legible but also serves as a metaphor for the necessary collective effort to uncover the 'missing' considerations of women. The interactions aim to address the fact that by inputting our collective efforts, we can illuminate important narratives.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11. Text expressions with the application of a pencil.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,91.13,28.97,363.94,149.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Peace agreements with light torch.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,477.92,30.00,279.97,499.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="1,319.12,209.25,210.88,313.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="12,90.95,376.00,667.00,173.18" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>Thanks to <rs type="person">Mursal Ahmadzai</rs> and <rs type="person">Amanullah Ahmadzai</rs> for recording the audio of the <rs type="institution">Bonn Agreement</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Throughout this pictorial, we have described the process of developing an installation designed to encourage critical reflection on the historically limited references to and involvement of girls, women, and gender minorities in the 22 peace agreements that make up Afghanistan  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christine</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sanja</forename><surname>Badanjak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adam</forename><surname>Farquhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Juline</forename><surname>Beaujouan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tim</forename><surname>Epple</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Forster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Astrid</forename><surname>Jamar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Mc-Nicholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sean</forename><surname>Molloy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kathryn</forename><surname>Nash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Pospisil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laura</forename><surname>Wise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://pax.pea-ceagreements.org/agreements/search/" />
		<title level="m">PA-X Version 8. Peace and Conflict Resolution Evidence Platform (PeaceRep)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Edinburgh</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peace Agreements: Their Nature and Legal Status</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of International Law</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="412" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Based on PA-X Version 8 excluding Agreement/Conflict Stage: Intrastate/Local</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peace Agreements or Pieces of Paper? The Impact of UNSC Resolution 1325 on Peace Processes and their Agreements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International and Comparative Law Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">947</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Navigating Inclusion in Transitions from Conflict: The Formalised Political Unsettlement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pospisil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Settlements Research Programme</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Briefing Paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ontopolitics at Play: Inclusion Between a Panacea and a Hook</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pospisil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peace in Political Unsettlement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<idno>S/RES/1325</idno>
		<ptr target="https://" />
		<title level="m">Security Council Resolution on women and peace and security</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
