<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Perceived value of video games, but not hours played, predicts mental well-being in adult Nintendo players</title>
				<funder ref="#_gTxYpgC">
					<orgName type="full">Forskningsrå det för hälsa</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Huo Family Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_5HVmYMu">
					<orgName type="full">UK Economic and Social Research Council</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nick</forename><surname>Ballou</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0009-0009-8292-2482</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Oxford Internet Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Oxford</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matti</forename><surname>Vuorre</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-0713-0556</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Oxford Internet Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Oxford</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Tilburg University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Hakman</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-4126-0696</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Oxford Internet Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Oxford</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kristoffer</forename><surname>Magnusson</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-4126-0696</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Oxford Internet Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Oxford</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Karolinska Institute</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Przybylski</surname></persName>
							<email>andy.pryzbylski@oii.ox.ac.uk</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-4126-0696</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Oxford Internet Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Oxford</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Perceived value of video games, but not hours played, predicts mental well-being in adult Nintendo players</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">35FFA41E5F119DED89D44B867C53658F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-23T15:08+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>video games</term>
					<term>digital trace data</term>
					<term>well-being</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Studies on video games and well-being often rely on self-report measures or data from a single game. Here, we study how 703 US adults' time spent playing for over 140,000 hours across 150 Nintendo Switch games relates to their life satisfaction, affect, depressive symptoms, and general mental well-being. We replicate previous findings that playtime over the past two weeks does not predict well-being, and extend these findings to a wider range of timescales (one hour to one year). Results suggest that relationships, if present, dissipate within two hours of gameplay. Our non-causal findings suggest substantial confounding would be needed to shift a meaningful true effect to the observed null. Although playtime was not related to well-being, players' assessments of the value of game time-so called gaming life fit-was. Results emphasise the importance of defining the gaming population of interest, collecting data from more than one game, and focusing on how players integrate gaming into their lives rather than the amount of time spent.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The extent to which games might be understood as be-13 haviorally addictive remains hotly debated <ref type="bibr">(Aarseth et al., 14 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Billieux et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Van Rooij et al., 2018)</ref> and the 15 broader scientific conversation has increasingly focused on 16 how not just quantity, but also quality of play relates to player 17 health. Although there is increasing recognition that not all 18 screentime-or in the case of games, playtime-is created 19 equal <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Orben, 2022)</ref>, it remains a major research focus. Re-20 search has identified a range of factors that co-determine how 21 time spent with games relates to health: for example, as-22 pects of a game's design such as its social affordances (Cren- PlayStation foreground time limits as a primary means of 31 enforcing healthy gaming behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Robertson, 2021)</ref>; for 32 adults, a growing array of self-control tools, apps, and dash-33 boards offer the ability to "limit or cut yourself off from 34 apps and games" (<ref type="url" target="https://focusme.com/how-it-works/">https://focusme.com</ref>), savings users "1.23 35 hours" (<ref type="url" target="https://www.opal.so">https://www.opal.so</ref>) or "up to 2.5 hours a day" 36 (<ref type="url" target="https://freedom.to/freedom-for-ios">https://freedom.to/</ref>). News media suggest time-based limits 37 (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Saveva, 2023)</ref>, often referencing the since-abandoned 2x2 rule from the American Academy of Pediatrics: no screen time for children under two, and no more than two hours per day for children older than two <ref type="bibr">(Blum-Ross &amp; Livingstone, 2018)</ref>. Likewise, the American Psychiatric Association's description of Internet Gaming Disorder characterises pathological engagement with games, in part, as involving '8-10 hours or more per day [and or] least 30 hours per week' (American Psychiatric <ref type="bibr">Association, 2013, p. 796)</ref>. On a larger scale, time-based limits such as Korea's 10-year Youth Protection Revision Act prohibited young people from playing games between 00:00 and 06:00 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Sang et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>More recently, China put in place a weekly three-hour limit for under-18s <ref type="bibr">(Feiner &amp; Kharpal, 2021)</ref>. The effectiveness of such regulatory steps has been challenged <ref type="bibr">(Choi et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zendle et al., 2023)</ref>.</p><p>A better understanding of how time spent with games relates to players' health, for good or ill, is needed. Given that play takes many forms and happens across many different games, researchers greatly benefit from access to digital trace data-histories of user actions generated when interacting with technologies such as a game or online platform. Digital trace data can provide much greater detail about what, when, and how much people play than is possible in self-report data, which consistently shows substantial discrepancies compared to digital trace data collected by online platforms <ref type="bibr">(Ernala et al., 2020)</ref> and independent researchers <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Parry et al., 2021)</ref> alike. Previous studies on games found that an additional hour of Animal Crossing: New Horizons trace data predicted just a 30-minute increase in self-reported play-a nearly 50% discrepancy <ref type="bibr">(Johannes et al., 2021)</ref>-and that Everquest 2 players' estimates correlated only r = .37 with logged estimates, with underestimates slightly more common than overestimates <ref type="bibr">(Kahn et al., 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Only a handful of studies have applied digital trace data to the study of games and well-being <ref type="bibr">(Brühlmann et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Johannes et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr">Larrieu et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr">see Vuorre et al., 2022)</ref>, in part because this data can be very difficult to acquire: researchers must build or rely on unstable technical systems to log data themselves, or negotiate individual agreements with games companies who have historically been reluctant to share data <ref type="bibr">(Ballou, 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr">Seif El-Nasr et al., 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Where digital trace data has been collected, however, results   sis test. We therefore operationalise this as an exploratory 144  or who had a session that took place in the future, indicating a technical problem or manipulation of the system clock for in-game benefits. We further excluded 34 participants who displayed signs of careless responding (e.g., so-called straightlining or seemingly random responses). In total, we excluded 487 participants (some participants were excluded on multiple grounds), leading to a final sample of 703.</p><p>Participants were paid £0.15 for the 1-minute screening questionnaire, £3 for linking their data plus a £2 bonus payment if data was successfully retrieved, and £4 for a 22-minute well-being survey. This study received approval from the University of Oxford Social Sciences and Humanities Interdivisional Research Ethics Committee (OII_C1A_23_107).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants and Exclusions</head><p>Participant demographics are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p>Participants completed a self-report survey that took on average 22 minutes to complete. The survey included background factors such as demographics and life circumstances, a series of cognitive tasks, as well as self-report measures of time use, and motivations for video game play. We detail those measures we used in this study below but all study data are available at OSF (see supplementary materials).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Video game playtime was measured by collecting a record</head><p>of each player's individual game sessions for all 1st party video games played on a Nintendo Switch. These data were provided by Nintendo of America. Playtime was calculated by summing the duration of all (partial) sessions that occur during a given time period relative to the participant's survey response, based on the logged session start and end times. For ease of interpretation, game play time in all observation periods longer 24 hours is reported as mean minutes of play per day. It is important to note that these data included only telemetry for games published by Nintendo and its close business partners (e.g. The Pokémon Company), but not games made by third party publishers (e.g. Electronic Arts). Nintendo-published games accounted for 63% of all playtime across our sample; the 37% of play data from 3rdparty games is therefore treated as missing. We return to this limitation in the discussion.</p><p>General mental well-being was measured with the WEMWBS <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Tennant et al., 2007)</ref>. Players rated 14 statements about how they felt during the past 2 weeks such as "I've been dealing with problems well" and "I've been feeling good about myself" on a 5-point scale from 1 ("none of the time") to 5 ("all of the time"). Scores were calculated by taking the mean of all items.</p><p>Depressive symptoms was measured with the PROMIS Short Form 8a <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Pilkonis et al., 2011)</ref>. Players rated 8 statements about how they felt in the past 7 days such as "I felt hopeless" and "I felt I had nothing to look forward to" on a 245 5-point scale from 1 ("never") to 5 ("always"). Scores were 246 calculated by taking the mean of all items. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>293</head><p>We conducted all statistical analyses with R version 4.3.2 294 (R Core Team, 2023). We use an alpha of .01. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Smallest Effect Size of Interest</head><p>We Note: this method of specifying an SESOI is predicated on a causal interpretation-it implicitly imagines a world where one can intervene on playtime (our predictor) and have an effect of a certain size on mental health (our outcomes). It is very unlikely that our cross-sectional analyses can provide unbiased causal estimates. Instead, our goal is to use associations to place boundaries on the size of a possible effect.</p><p>In other words, if there is no meaningful correlation between 316 playtime and mental health, there is even less likely to be a 317 meaningful causal effect between playtime and mental health.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>318</head><p>We support this reasoning with simulations presented in the 319 discussion.</p><p>320</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>321</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Descriptive results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>322</head><p>Given the lack of holistic or platform-level data available in 1H 2H 6H 12H 1D 3D 1W 2W 1M 3M 6M 1Y 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 Hours of (daily) play Observation Period A 0.00 0.25 0.50 0.75 1.00 0 200 400 600 Proportion Participants B tendo titles. We argue that this population is nonetheless an important one: if video games were to meaningfully affect</p><p>well-being, we may expect a larger impact for people who rarely play but happen to play for one hour, than for a highly engaged population of people who tend to play three hours per day, but happen to play four hours. We return to this limitation on generalizability in the discussion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H1: Previous 2 weeks of playtime and mental health</head><p>We began by analyzing H1, which concerned the relation- General well-being Life Satisfaction Affect Depressive Symptoms 0 15 60 120 240 420 0 15 60 120 240 420 1 2 3 4 5 1 2 3 4 5 Minutes of play per day during previous 2 weeks (Square Root Axis) Outcome (1-5 scale)</p><p>riods. In each case, playtime shortly before completing a survey was associated with higher affect, life satisfaction, and general mental well-being; and with lower self-reported levels of depressive symptoms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploratory analysis: Moderation by life fit</head><p>Next, we conducted exploratory analyses to investigate what other factors might influence who exhibits positive or negative relations between gaming and well-being. We explored age, gender, and life fit-the perceived harmful or beneficial value of gaming across various life domains outside of play. We expected that people who perceive gaming as supportive in other life domains would show positive relations between gaming and mental health, and those who perceived gaming to be harmful to other life domains would show negative ones.</p><p>To test this, we reran the models from H2, adding playtime * age, playtime * gender, and playtime * lifeFit moderation terms. We did not find evidence to support the presence of moderation; none of the moderation 399 terms were significant (0.064 &lt; ps &lt; 0.99). 400 However, we did find evidence of direct positive relation- Estimates for the relationship between playtime and well-being across various timescales, shown with 90% (dark blue) and 99% (light blue) confidence intervals. Dashed lines represent the positive and negative smallest effect size of interest (SESOI) of .06.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General Mental Well-being Depressive Symptoms</head><p>Life Satisfaction Affect  General Mental Well-being Life Satisfaction Affective Depressive Symptoms -2 0 2 -2 0 2 1 2 3 4 5 1 2 3 4 5 1 2 3 4 5 1 2 3 4 5 Mean Gaming Life Fit Wellbeing (1-5 Scale) range of outcomes, timescales of play, and model specifications adds to a growing body of work that suggests that simple time spent playing games is unlikely to affect well-being for the average player. Said differently, the findings we report place the onus on those who assert that there is a meaningful relationship between playtime and well-being. It should be a priority to identify and concretely articulate which confounds might bias a true effect towards the null associations reported in this and other research using player telemetry (Ballou et al., 2024; Johannes et al., 2021; Larrieu et al., 2023; Vuorre et al., 2022). To further elucidate this point, we conducted brief simulation tests to ascertain how strong such confounding might need to be (see Supplementary Materials). For example, if the true standardized effect of playtime on mental health was a moderate .2 SDs per additional hour of daily playtime, a confound C would need to be a very strong cause of both X (𝑏𝑒𝑡𝑎 = .5) and Y (𝑏𝑒𝑡𝑎 = -.5 ) to bias the true .2 effect to null. While we do not claim this is impossible, we do believe it unlikely. Approaching the topic along these lines-identifying confounds, testing the presence or absence of correlations for their sensitivity to potential confounds, and 474 systematically identifying factors that do (not) cause play-475 time and well-being-can help us achieve more systematic 476 progress (Ballou et al., n.d.). This work can be bolstered by 477 qualitative research aimed at more fully mapping the causal 478 system and by substantive theory development with greater 479 specificity in the aspects of media use expected to produce 480 effects, the hypothesized causal relationships, boundary con-481 ditions, and so forth (Ballou, 2023; Coenen, 2023; Eronen &amp; 482 Bringmann, 2021; Magnusson et al., 2024). 483 Who are "gamers"? 484 The steady attrition throughout the stages of the research 485 process from screening, to linking, to successful data retrieval 486 highlights the challenges for participant recruitment in video 487 games research. Despite a series of filtering steps wherein a 488 majority of participants were filtered out due to not playing 489 Switch games or being unwilling or unable to link data, our 490 final sample remains only minimally engaged with Nintendo 491 games-playing just 1.4 hours per week on average. As a  <ref type="bibr">nies (Johannes et al., 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr">Larrieu et al., 2023)</ref> or through social media forums for highly-engaged players <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Ballou et al., 2024)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1 H 2 H 6 H 1 2 H 1 D 3 D 1 W 2 W 1 M 3 M 6 M 1 Y 1 H 2 H 6 H 1 2 H 1 D 3 D 1 W 2 W 1 M 3 M 6 M</formula><p>As argued above, we believe this is a valuable group in its own right-those who rarely play video games may be particularly susceptible to their positive or negative effects on the occasions they do play. While the current study is unlikely to generalize to so-called "hardcore" players who play several hours per day or more and therefore may experience more accumulative effects, our findings align with previous studies of more highly engaged players and add a new subgroup of players to the body of work showing the absence of any meaningful relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Ballou et al., 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr">Larrieu et al., 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr">Vuorre et al., 2022)</ref>.</p><p>As the field progresses, however, differences in the level of engagement pose major challenges for study sampling and generalisability. Calls for representative samples need to specify the population of reference: should this be the general population (of whom many do not play games), people who play any games at all (of whom many do not play the games for which researchers have data access), people who play the particular game or platform of interest (of whom many may be only minimally engaged), or something else entirely? In the field's quest for more generalizable results, this will be a critical issue.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Timescales</head><p>While we are quick to caution that this is a preliminary finding that should not be relied upon without further validation, our data provide some initial evidence that effects of raw playtime might materialize and fade within a few hourspoint estimates indicated that playtime was more strongly linked with greater well-being in the 1-2 hours prior to survey completion. This finding is compatible with various causal explanations: for example, players who recently played are more likely be in a period of leisure time, which would be expected to generate more positive feelings than in peers doing obligatory activities such as work. However, if researchers do expect to see positive effects of gaming, our data suggest that they may need to search for highly proximal effects directly during and following a play session (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Vuorre et al., 2024)</ref>.</p><p>Should this finding be upheld, it would go a long way towards explaining previous null findings from studies that related well-being to playtime over timescales such as two weeks <ref type="bibr">(Vuorre et al., 2022)</ref>, one month <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Sibilla et al., 2021</ref><ref type="bibr">), six months (Weinstein et al., 2017)</ref>, and one year <ref type="bibr">(Kowert et al., 2015)</ref>. For most players, it may be the case that gaming is a recovery activity that helps to manage day-to-day stresses and mood fluctuations, without necessarily having substantial long-term impacts. The majority of players have several options for activities in their environment that would have</p><p>comparable effects on their well-being. Such activities are 545 thus "exchangeable", serving the same short-term goals with-546 out consequences for long-term adjustment. Studying rela-547 tionships over the course of hours has to date been possible 548 largely only in laboratory settings-rarely have researchers 549 had access to session-level data of naturalistic behavior that 550 they could link to momentary well-being. 551 Life fit 552 This study demonstrates the potential usefulness of life fit 553 as a theoretical construct (Ballou &amp; Deterding, 2023). Given 554 the accumulating evidence that playtime and well-being are 555 not meaningfully related at the population level alongside in-556 controvertible evidence that some players benefit and some 557 are harmed (Ballou et al., n.d., n.d.), the task for the field can 558 be framed as a search for the most important moderators. Life 559 fit-a player's self-assessment about the contribution of gam-560 ing to different aspects of their lives-stands as an effective 561 starting point, letting researchers trust the lived experiences 562 of players to guide them towards patterns of problematic or 563 particularly beneficial play. 564 Using this measure, we found no evidence that life fit mod-565 erated the relationship between playtime and well-being, but 566 we did find a direct correlation between the two. Notably, this 567 relationship was an order of magnitude stronger than any es-568 timates for playtime itself. Among several other possible ex-569 planations, this would fit a pattern of biased self-assessment: 570 it is possible that players who are generally feeling poorly 571 are more likely to appraise their gaming as harmful to their 572 mental health, regardless of whether that mechanism actually 573 takes place. This would align with some previous findings 574 that more depressed people tend to overestimate their smart-575 phone use due to a negative or guilt-laden appraisal process 576 distinct from the media use itself (Sewall &amp; Parry, 2021). 577 We caution that the measure applied here has not been val-578 idated, and is better viewed as a formative indicator than as a 579 true latent variable. More work will be needed to understand 580 the validity of this construct. 581 Holistic digital trace data 582 This paper demonstrates both the value and difficulty of 583 collecting holistic digital trace data: by capturing data across 584 an entire platform, rather than just one game, we can poten-585 tially account for a person's complete engagement with games 586 without self-report biases-but only if we sample players for 587 whom that platform constitutes the majority of their gam-588 ing. Our screening data indicates that participants play games 589 on average across 2.8 platforms, for example playing games 590 across Nintendo, Steam, and iOS. To fully capture players' 591 entire gaming diets, researchers will need to either subsam-592 ple participants who use only one platform or develop distinct 593 methods of collecting digital trace data for several platforms. In this same vein, although collaborations between aca-595 demics and digital media platforms are becoming incremen-596 tally more common (Larrieu et al., 2023; e.g., Nyhan et 597 al., 2023), these remain difficult to source and stubbornly 598 inequitably distributed across the research ecosystem. Re-599 searchers are actively exploring other ways to source digital 600 trace data, including through scraping methods (Ballou et al., 601 2024), APIs (e.g., <ref type="url" target="https://gameplay.science">https://gameplay.science</ref>), and subject data 602 access requests/data download packages (Breuer et al., 2022), 603 but more needs to be done. Relationships between games 604 firms and independent research teams are not scalable and the 605 providence of data collected by scraping and related tools is 606 difficult if not impossible to verify. Democratizing researcher 607 access in a way that protects participants' autonomy and right 608 to privacy will require the enactment of multisector-spanning 609 initiatives like the UK's Video Game Research Framework 610 (Department for Media &amp; Sport, 2023) that clearly prescribe 611 the responsibilities for those enabling, enacting, and benefit-612 ing from the scientific study of video game play. The time for 613 this is well past due. The idea that time spent playing is the key ingredient in 638 how games impact well-being will be with us for some time. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>23 shaw &amp; Nardi, 2016), the context of when and where one 24 plays (Drummond &amp; Sauer, 2020), and players' motivation 25 (Brühlmann et al., 2020). 26 In matters of health policy, overall time spent with 27 games-regardless of what or why one plays-remains cen-28 tral to how games are thought to influence player out-29 comes. Parental control tools on platforms like Xbox and 30</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>have been informative. Brühlmann et al. (2020) used playtime and in-game behavior to identify subgroups of League of Legends players who had more negative in-game experiences. Johannes et al. (2021) look at playtime in Animal Crossing: New Horizons and PvZ: Battle for Neighborville and found a positive but likely negligible correlation. A follow-up study expanded this to seven games, finding that changes in playtime over the course of 6 weeks were unlikely to affect subsequent well-being (Vuorre et al., 2022). Larrieu et al. (2023) follow high-intensity Rainbow 6: Siege players and find no link between playtime and quality of life across any identified player types. 92 Though informative, this early work has a vital scope lim-93 itation: digital trace data was only available for a single game 94 for each player-participant. It was not possible to know what 95 other games a participant was, or was not, electing to play. 96 Players regularly switch between games over the course of a 97 day or week based on mood, available time, and social con-98 text (Ballou et al., 2024; O'Neill et al., 2016); data collected 99 for one particular game may thus tell us little about overall 100 playtime or its relation to well-being. 101 An important frontier for the field, therefore, is to col-102 lect holistic digital trace data that reflects behavior in not just 103 one game, but all games played (which may include various 104 games on one platform, such as Nintendo Switch or Steam, or 105 all games played across several platforms a player uses). At 106 present, our understanding of even basic phenomena such as 107 the true volume of play in different demographics rely on the 108 same inaccurate self-report data, itself often provided by mar-109 ket research firms using opaque methodologies. Capturing 110 play at the platform level represents one step towards this goal 111 of studying a player's complete gaming diet. To our knowl-112 edge, the only study to platform-level digital trace data to in-113 vestigate player health is (Ballou et al., 2024), which found no 114 meaningful relationships between Xbox playtime and wellresearch we report on a study conducted in 118 collaboration with Nintendo of America, in which we inde-119 pendently recruited a large sample of adult video game play-120 ers, surveyed them about their motivation and well-being, 121 and joined these responses to digital trace data on Nintendo 122 Switch video game play. Our central aim was to test the ex-123 tent to which the amount of time participants spent playing 124 related to their psychological well-being. Our analysis plan 125 was preregistered at https://osf.io/sjqyt. 126 More specifically, our first hypothesis was to test whether 127 the null relations reported in earlier work (Ballou et al., 2024; 128 Johannes et al., 2021; Vuorre et al., 2022) would replicate 129 in an independent sample of Nintendo Switch play. In our 130 first hypothesis, we predicted that there will be no practically 131 significant association between video game playtime in the 132 previous 2 weeks and life satisfaction (H1a), affect (H1b),</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>135</head><figDesc>We were also interested in understanding how relation-136 ships between play and well-being might depend on the 137 choice of what timescale of play researchers consider rele-138 vant to investigate. . To this end, we examined relationships 139 between well-being and a wide range of time windows of play 140 preceding the well-being question. While preregistered, the 141 large number of models implicated in our analysis plan is 142 prohibitively large to be aptly framed as a narrow hypothe-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 Participant flow, from recruitment to final sample</figDesc><graphic coords="3,54.01,123.61,499.66,249.83" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc>US, and (4) active video game players (self-160 defined, based on a &gt;0 response to Prolific's built-in screening 161 item "How many hours per week do you play video games on 162 average?"). We first distributed a screening questionnaire to 163 7649 participants asking which video game platforms they 164 were active on; of these, 4184 indicated that they played 165 games on Nintendo Switch. 166 We invited these participants to a second survey wherein 167 they retrieved an account identifier from the Nintendo web 168 interface using the events QR code, available at https:// 169 accounts.nintendo.com/qrcode, and they shared these unique 170 identifiers with us. This identifier is separate from their user-171 name, and cannot be used by anyone besides Nintendo-172 including our research team-to link the player to personally 173 identifiable information. A total of 1823 participants com-174 pleted the linking process. We sent the account identifiers 175 to Nintendo of America, who in turn sent us each player's 176 pseudonymised play history from May 1, 2022 to present. 177 Data collection began with a pilot study of 100 participants 178 on Nov 15, 2023, which was combined with primary data col-179 lection from Feb 12, 2024 to May 6, 2024. 180 Of the participants who completed the linking process, 181 1607 had eligible Nintendo data (i.e., any play sessions of 182 a 1st party game-a game published by Nintendo or one of 183 its subsidiaries, as opposed to a third-party publisher-from 184 May 1, 2022 to present). These 1607 were subsequently sent 185 a well-being survey in Qualtrics detailed below. 1191 par-186 ticipants completed the well-being survey; our preregistered 187 stopping rule went into effect when 5 or fewer participants 188 per day completed the survey for three consecutive days. 189 As preregistered, we excluded 427 individuals who had 190 no playtime during the previous three months, indicating that 191 they are not active Nintendo players, and 26 people who 192 logged more than 24 hours of playtime on any single day 193</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>247</head><figDesc>Life satisfaction was measured with the one-item Cantril 248 self-anchoring scale(Cantril, 1965). Participants were 249 prompted with 'Please imagine a ladder with steps numbered 250 from 0 at the bottom to 10 at the top. The top of the ladder 251 represents the best possible life for you, and the bottom of the 252 ladder represents the worst possible life for you. On which 253 step of the ladder would you say you personally feel you stood 254 over the past two weeks?'. Participants responded on a scale 255 from 0 to 10, which was rescaled to 1-5 to match the other 256 well-being measures. 257 Affect was measured with a single item: "How are you 258 feeling right now?" (Killingsworth &amp; Gilbert, 2010). Par-259 ticipants responded using a 100-point visual analogue scale 260 (VAS) with endpoints "Very bad" and "Very good", which 261 we rescaled to 1-5 to match the other well-being measures. 262 Gaming life fit was measured with a draft measure asking 263 players to rate the contribution of gaming to 5 life domains 264 (work/school, social participation, cognitive health, emotion 265 regulation, and daily routines) on a 7-pt bipolar scale from 266 "greatly interfered" to "greatly supported". We took the aver-267 age of these to generate a formative indicator of the degree to 268 which players perceive their gaming to be beneficial or harm-269 ful to other aspects of their lives. This measure has not been 270 used or validated before, and we return to this in the discus-, we fit multiple regression models with playtime 274 over the previous 2 weeks as the primary predictor, all de-275 mographic variables as covariates (age, gender, highest level 276 of education, and employment status), and the corresponding 277 mental health variable as the outcome. For example, for H1a 278 (life satisfaction predicted by the previous 2 weeks of play), 279 the model in R is: 280 {{lm((life satisfaction) ~(playtime in the previous 2 281 weeks) + age + gender + education + employment)}} 282 We apply a similar analysis approach to our exploration of 283 H2 concerning other timescales; we primarily apply multi-284 ple regression with well-being predicted by playtime aggre-285 gated over various time periods and the same covariates, but 286 also explore potential non-linear alternatives and moderation 287 analyses (detailed below). 288 We interpret the playtime coefficient estimates from these 289 models in reference to pre-specified smallest effect sizes of 290 interest (see below): if the 99% confidence interval is fully 291 within the upper and lower equivalence bounds, this provides 292 evidence to reject a practically meaningful association.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc>specify the smallest effect size of interest (SESOI) as a 1-hour change in (daily) playtime associated with a .06 scale point change in mental health on a 1-5 scale, in line with Ballou et al. (2024), who justified that value based on previous research on minimally important differences (approximately .3-.4 scale points on a 1-5 scale for PROMIS and WEMWBS measures) and daily leisure time available to US adults (approximately 5 hours; Sturm and Cohen (2019)). Any association smaller than .06 indicates that the average person does not have enough time in the day to modulate their play to an extent that it would register a perceptible difference in their well-being.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>323Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2Description of playtime in the sample. Panel A shows the distribution of playtime across players for each observation period, with the mean shown in red; observations periods below the dashed line are shown as total hours, whereas periods above the dashed line reflect hours of player per day. Panel B shows the proportion of players who logged at least one play session in that period.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3Scatterplots depicting the relationship between video game playtime during the previous 2 weeks (mean minutes of play per day) and four types of well-being.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><figDesc>Figure 4</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><figDesc>ables * 12 playtime windows), just one of these (playtime in the previous one year and life satisfaction) showed a difference in AIC of more than two, indicating that nearly all relationships were adequately captured by linear terms. Next, we reran the analyses using session durations as calculated by Nintendo, as opposed to the implied duration based on the start and end timestamps; Nintendo's durations are shorter than the implied duration in approximately 10% of sessions due to internal methodology. Data show a similar pattern: no models showed a significant relationship between playtime and well-being at our specified alpha of .01. Next, we explored alternative models wherein playtime was separated into both a binary variable (1 if the player had any time logged in that period, 0 if not), and a continuous variable (how much a person played). Results were comparable; although three models indicated that among those who played in the previous 1-2 weeks, longer play is associated with higher affect and general mental well-being, the remaining 93 playtime variables were neither significant or nor within both equivalence bounds.not intend our study to test the causal 438 question most critical to heated debates surrounding video 439 game engagement and global health, our study is a concrete 440 step in the right direction, having independently recruited a 441 large sample of video game players [as opposed relying on 442 recruitment through games companies themselves; e.g. Jo-443 hannes et al. (2021)], collected validated measures of well-444 being, joined these with objective behavioral telemetry and 445 made minimal adjustments for age, gender, employment, and 446 education. Using these methods, we did not uncover robust or 447 consistent relationships between time spent playing and var-448 ious mental well-being outcomes. 449 Although not conclusive, our results point toward a pattern 450 whereby platform-wide video game play time does not predict 451 well-being to a meaningful degree. This trend, across a wide</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5Marginal relationship between gaming life fit (perceived harmful or beneficial effects of games for oneself) and wellbeing</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><figDesc>limitations and constraints on generalis-616 ability the merit mention. First, we could not analyse teleme-617 try generated when players engaged with third-party titles 618 (i.e. games not published by Nintendo or its closely associ-619 ated companies). As a result, our findings only hold for simi-620 lar Nintendo games (75% of which were rated for everyone or 621 everyone over 10), and it is not possible to rule out the possi-622 bility that third-party games with different content or themes 623 might show a different pattern of effects. Likewise, because 624 we collaborated with Nintendo of America, our sample con-625 sisted only of adults living in the United States, a group that 626 we found to be largely casually involved with first-party Nin-627 tendo games. Games are both global and played by those of 628 all ages, so it is not clear the degree to which our findings 629 do or do not apply to younger players, those who play other 630 games, or those who approach games from different cultural 631 and linguistic backgrounds. Finally, while we have longitudi-632 nal telemetry data, our self-report survey was cross-sectional 633 and this study is one step towards designs using daily diary 634 and experience sampling methods (Aalbers et al., 2021; e.g.,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>639</head><figDesc>Although our study was not designed to test a causal link, it 640 challenges the notion that simply playing more affects well-641 being, for better or for worse. The correlations we observed 642 were mostly too small to practically matter. Moreover, we 643 show that profound confounding would be required to sup-644 press a true causal effect to account for the null associations 645 we report. This is improbable but not impossible, and we 646 believe our results lend weight to calls for scholars and health 647 practitioners to embrace the gradual shift towards focusing 648 on the quality, rather than quantity of video game play as 649 the key factor for player health. If this can be done while 650 simultaneously improving data quality and access, a coher-651 ent and evidence-based method for studying the complex re-652 lationships linking video game play and well-being will be 653 possible.654Contributionsof legends players. Frontiers inPsychology, 11, 1307.   </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Participant Demographics</figDesc><table><row><cell>Descriptor</cell><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Value</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean (SD)</cell><cell>31.5 (7.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell>Median (IQR)</cell><cell>31.0 [26.0;36.0]</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Min / Max</cell><cell>18.0 / 68.0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Man</cell><cell>376 (53.5%)</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell>Woman</cell><cell>267 (38.0%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Non-binary or other gender identity</cell><cell>60 (8.5%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Working full-time</cell><cell>338 (48.1%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Working part-time</cell><cell>120 (17.1%)</cell></row><row><cell>Employment Status</cell><cell>Other employment status</cell><cell>97 (13.8%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Not currently employed</cell><cell>91 (12.9%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Student</cell><cell>57 (8.1%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>White</cell><cell>456 (64.9%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Asian</cell><cell>82 (11.7%)</cell></row><row><cell>Ethnicity</cell><cell>Mixed</cell><cell>75 (10.7%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Black</cell><cell>54 (7.7%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Other ethnicity</cell><cell>36 (5.1%)</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>R., &amp; Valcke, M. (2016). Players' perspectives on</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>&amp; Mekler, E. D. (2020). Motivational profiling of league</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>The authors declare no other competing interests. This research was supported by <rs type="funder">Huo Family Foundation</rs> and the <rs type="funder">UK Economic and Social Research Council</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">ES/W012626/1</rs>). KM was supported by <rs type="funder">Forskningsrå det för hälsa</rs>, arbetsliv och välfärd (<rs type="grantNumber">2021-01284</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_5HVmYMu">
					<idno type="grant-number">ES/W012626/1</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_gTxYpgC">
					<idno type="grant-number">2021-01284</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Data and materials are available at <ref type="url" target="https://osf.io/6xkdg/">https://osf.io/6xkdg/</ref>. Data for this study was provided by Nintendo of America. Nintendo of America had no role in the design of the study, the analysis of the data, or decision to publish any results.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Author roles were classified using the Contributor Role 656 Taxonomy (CRediT;<ref type="url" target="https://credit.niso.org/">https://credit.niso.org/</ref>) as follows: Nick  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/2987443.2987489</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2987443.2987489" />
		<title level="m">the 2016 internet measurement conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="95" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital diet: A 21st century approach to understanding digital technologies and development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Orben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/icd.2228</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/icd.2228" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">fant and Child Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic review and meta-analysis of discrepancies between logged and self-reported digital media use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Parry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J R</forename><surname>Sewall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mieczkowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Quintana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41562-021-01117-5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-021-01117-5" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Human Behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1535" to="1547" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Item banks for measuring emotional distress from the patient-reported outcomes measurement information system (PROMIS®): Depression, anxiety, and anger</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pilkonis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Reise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1073191111411667</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1073191111411667" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Assessment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="283" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Team</forename><surname>Core</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.R-project.org/" />
		<title level="m">R: A language and environment for statistical computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Taming gaming: guide your child to healthy video game habits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Unbound</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mobile Game Regulation in South Korea: A Case Study of the Shutdown Law</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Seo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-94-024-0826-3_4</idno>
		<ptr target="http://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-94-024-0826-3_4" />
		<editor>D. Y. Jin</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="72" />
			<pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Saveva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://thedigitalparents.com/technology-and-screen-time-management/healthy-video-game-time-limits-by-age/" />
		<title level="m">Healthy video game time limits by age. The Digital Parents</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Game analytics: Maximizing the value of player data</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-1-4471-4769-5</idno>
		<ptr target="http://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-1-4471-4769-5" />
		<editor>Seif El-Nasr, M., Drachen, A., &amp; Canossa, A.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Role of Depression in the Discrepancy Between Estimated and Actual Smartphone Use: A Cubic Response Surface Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J R</forename><surname>Sewall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Parry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/tmb0000036</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1037/tmb0000036" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technology, Mind, and Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Harmonious and obsessive involvement, self-esteem, and wellbeing. A longitudinal study on MMORPG players</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sibilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Musetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mancini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5817/CP2021-3-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5817/CP2021-3-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cyberpsychology: Journal of Psychosocial Research on Cyberspace</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Explaining variation in adolescents&apos; social media-related distraction: The role of social connectivity and disconnectivity factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Siebers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Beyens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pouwels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Valkenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31234/osf.io/g6na7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://web.archive.org/web/20240412044816/https://steamcharts.com/top" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PsyArXiv</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2024. April 12, 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In An ongoing analysis of Steam&apos;s concurrent players</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Free time and physi-856 cal activity among americans 15 years or older: Cross-857 sectional analysis of the american time use survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sturm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5888/pcd16.190017</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.8595888/pcd16.190017860" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pre-858 venting Chronic Disease</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">190017</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being 863 Scale (WEMWBS): development and UK validation. 864</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tennant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hiller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fishwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Platt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Parkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Secker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Stewart-Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1477-7525-5-63</idno>
		<ptr target="https:865//doi.org/10.1186/1477-7525-5-63866" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health and Quality of Life Outcomes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Rooij</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ferguson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Colder Carras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>867 Kardefelt-Winther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aarseth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">868</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">869 A weak scientific basis for gaming disorder: Let us err 870 on the side of caution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bergmark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Coulson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1556/2006.7.2018.19</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1556/2006.7.2018.19872" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Behavioral Addictions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">871</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Affective Uplift During Video</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vuorre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ballou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hakman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Magnusson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Przybylski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
