<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Method Sampling Method Data Collected Confidentiality &amp; Data Privacy Salary Analyses Equity Analyses Pay Gap Analyses Retention Analyses Results</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Method Sampling Method Data Collected Confidentiality &amp; Data Privacy Salary Analyses Equity Analyses Pay Gap Analyses Retention Analyses Results</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E444575A08FE97F9FBCA3440D40C49B7</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Lastly, this report doesn't constitute legal advice</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p>The farmed animal advocacy movement has professionalized and grown within the nonprofit sector over the last 50 years, with over 285 organizations in the United States alone and more than 800 groups worldwide <ref type="bibr">(Animal Charity Evaluators, 2023)</ref>. The movement continues to grow, with new organizations launching or being developed through incubation programs each year. This report will analyze pay and benefit trends among farmed animal organizations and how they compare with nonprofits in other cause areas. Our goal is to provide benchmarks, recommendations, and tools in order to help strengthen this rapidly growing movement.</p><p>In general, nonprofit organizations face many complexities and barriers to providing competitive pay and benefits: 66% cite budget constraints/insufficient funding and 72% cite pay competition as barriers to hiring and retaining employees (The National Council of Nonprofits, 2023). In particular, the farmed animal protection movement faces unique funding constraints: only 3% of charitable giving is awarded to animal and environmental causes combined (Giving USA, 2021), and most of the funding for animal charities goes towards companion animals <ref type="bibr">(Animal Charity Evaluators, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>Low pay and inadequate benefits can lead to employee turnover. <ref type="bibr">Faunalytics (2020)</ref> found that 21% of animal advocates in the U.S. and Canada left an animal advocacy job because of dissatisfaction with pay and benefits. In the same study, advocates who were members of marginalized groups (BIPOC, disability, LGBTQ2IA+) were significantly more likely to list low pay as a reason for leaving compared to non-marginalized advocates, indicating that the animal advocacy movement likely faces challenges in welcoming and retaining animal advocates from marginalized groups.</p><p>In order to provide more professional environments and competitive pay and benefits, we first need to understand how much pay and what type of benefits we're providing to employees. This is the first report to compare the pay of U.S. employees between farmed animal advocacy organizations of similarly-sized revenues, as well as the benefits offered by U.S. organizations.</p><p>We also examined whether pay gaps exist between marginalized and non-marginalized individuals in the farmed animal advocacy movement (hereinafter referred to as the movement), given that such pay gaps are common across many sectors. For example, as of 2016, white men in the U.S. earned $24 per hour, while Hispanic and Black women earned $12 to $13 per hour, even after accounting for any differences in education levels <ref type="bibr">(Pew Research Center, 2016)</ref>. Similar pay gaps have been found in the U.S. work sector between people with and without a disability <ref type="bibr">(American Institutes For Research, 2014)</ref> and between LGBTQ2IA+ and non-LGBTQ2IA+ individuals (Human Rights Campaign Foundation, 2022). We therefore hypothesized that people who are BIPOC (i.e., Black, Indigenous, or People of Color), women, non-binary, LGBTQ2IA+, and/or have a disability would earn less money than everyone else in our movement as well.</p><p>By addressing pay inequities and developing a purposeful approach to pay and benefits, organizations can create a more inclusive, equitable, and engaged work environment where staff feel more supported and rewarded. Such environments will also help employers attract and retain diverse talent within the organization and movement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Note On Interpretation</head><p>While this report attempts to summarize pay practices within the movement, readers should be aware that the final sample size is limited, based on 358 U.S. jobs from 40 organizations. We surveyed 27 of these organizations about their pay practices and most of them have a streamlined pay process and/or are already involved in promoting positive change (capacity-builders).</p><p>Similarly, BIPOC advocates, non-binary/other gender advocates, and advocates with a disability are likely underrepresented in our individual survey, while those with a graduate or professional degree are likely overrepresented.</p><p>In other words, our results don't represent the full range of pay practices within the movement, nor do they fully represent the advocate population. Organizational leadership is therefore advised to use multiple data sources in addition to this report to make any pay decisions at their organization.</p><p>This statistically significant difference (p &lt;.05) isn't due to employment differences such as job level or years of experience, which we accounted for in our analyses. Even though most participating organizations had transparent and formal pay practices, this finding suggests that these strategies alone may not be enough to prevent or eliminate these pay gaps.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Pay corresponds with job level to a greater extent at higher-revenue organizations. At organizations with a revenue over $1 million, the median salary was $67,250 for individual contributors, $84,500 for management, $114,000 for leadership, and $128,000 for executive directors. In contrast, median salaries at organizations with a revenue under $1 million were much flatter, around $70,000 at each job level.</p><p>4. Most U.S. farmed animal advocacy organizations we surveyed provide a medical plan, but dental, retirement, and vision benefits are less common. While 78% of participating organizations offered a medical plan, only 56% provided dental benefits, 52% offered a retirement plan, and 44% provided vision care benefits. For paid time off, all participating organizations offered a minimum of 15 vacation days, 84% offered at least five sick days, and 80% offered at least 10 holidays.</p><p>5. Median executive director (ED) salaries were generally lower than EDs of social advocacy and environmental organizations, especially for EDs of lower-revenue farmed animal advocacy organizations. Comparing our sample of EDs against U.S.-wide ED data from Candid, EDs of lower-revenue farmed animal advocacy organizations (&lt; $1 million) make $20,000 to $25,000 less than EDs of social advocacy and environmental organizations with a similar revenue, while EDs of higher-revenue farmed animal advocacy organizations ($1 million +) make approximately $2,000 and $7,000 less. Our median ED salaries tended to be higher than the median for Candid's category of "animal-related organizations" ($70,000 vs. $65,262 for organizations &lt; $1 million and $128,000 vs. $98,375 for organizations &gt; $1 million). However, we suspect this is due to Candid's category being dominated by direct work with animals (e.g., animal services, zoos, and aquariums).</p><p>6. 36% of farmed animal advocates said they were somewhat or very likely to leave the movement if offered a similar role with better pay, particularly if they belonged to a marginalized group. 45% of marginalized participants were somewhat or very likely to leave compared to just 29% of non-marginalized participants (p = 0.05). While we don't know whether this marginal difference would appear in a sample of advocates who haven't obtained higher education, it suggests that our movement is at risk of losing talent, especially those belonging to marginalized groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7.</head><p>When given an opportunity to discuss barriers to pay, most organizational leadership said that they want to increase pay and know their employees are worth more, but can't afford it due to funding constraints. Most organizations sampled have a formal pay process (70%) and determine raises based on cost of living 6 (70%), although a few participants said that considering cost of living standards made determining equitable pay more challenging (e.g., when employing individuals from different countries and regions). Despite such barriers, most participating organizations are transparent about pay with their staff (78%), which is an important step in establishing pay equity. To gain a more comprehensive understanding of organizational barriers, we suggest reading our accompanying blog on this subject.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recommendations</head><p>For Organization Leadership</p><p>• Be transparent with your staff about how you determine pay and benefits, including limitations, and regularly review these processes. When creating job listings, state the pay range and the types of benefits offered in the job description.</p><p>Ensure that staff understand how and when pay ranges, pay raises, and benefits are determined, including how funding constraints may limit the type of compensation offered (e.g., having the funds to only improve benefits, but not salaries). Encourage open dialogue around pay and benefits by surveying your employees' satisfaction on compensation and soliciting their feedback. We also recommend that you engage with a human resources or compensation specialist to periodically review and compare your salaries and benefits against current market rates, inflation, and legal requirements.</p><p>• Advocate for competitive pay and benefits for your employees, demonstrating the importance with our cost-of-turnover calculator. Increasing employee compensation can be expensive, but the hidden costs of turnover may be even more so. With this customizable calculator to help you estimate turnover costs that apply to your situation, we hope to provide a tool you can use to demonstrate the concrete impact of losing an employee when making difficult budgeting decisions and seeking funding. That said, beyond its economic impact, it is important to also convey that turnover may increase other team members' workloads, reduce morale, and contribute to work-related stress or burnout.</p><p>• Assess whether pay gaps exist in your organization and where they are stemming from. Collect self-reported demographic information from your employees on an optional basis, and compare pay between marginalized and non-marginalized staff to evaluate and address potential pay gaps. Additionally, you can work to challenge dominant practices that advantage privileged employees, as recommended by equity firms: Acknowledge the documented "white advantage" in nonprofit leadership positions, improve hiring and promotional practices to ensure that marginalized individuals are given equal opportunities for employment and advancement, and invest more in mentoring and professional development opportunities to support employees on their career journey. These steps can help minimize or prevent pay gaps.</p><p>• Consult a human resources or compensation specialist to help you implement a pay and benefit process that meets your organization's needs and budget. You can also incorporate information from online resources to inform your pay and benefit approach (e.g., salary.com or payscale.com). You can also engage a benefit specialist or broker to assess the feasibility of improving benefit offerings for your employees.</p><p>Additionally, be aware of changing laws (e.g., overtime eligibility) and increasing employer obligations around pay transparency regulations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>For Employees &amp; Potential Employees</head><p>• Request transparency from organization leadership about how pay and benefits are determined, and how funding affects that. Compensation transparency helps ensure employees are being treated fairly while holding employers accountable. If your employer doesn't do so already, encourage them to conduct employee feedback surveys and hold forums for employees to discuss how their employers can better support their needs. Further, it's important to learn and acknowledge that leaders work with a limited budget, especially across the long-term, meaning that leaders may not be able to improve pay and benefits if the organization runs the risk of losing funding or is simply not in a financial position to do so.</p><p>• Be realistic with yourself and prospective employers about what you need from a job, including salary and benefits. This report can't tell you what you should be paid for your work. It gives a rough sense of the current reality of the movement-within the limitations of a small sample-but everyone's needs are different. Change is unlikely to happen overnight. Our movement is underfunded compared to others and until that changes, many people will struggle to survive on our salaries, especially BIPOC, who are less likely to have another source of household income and are more likely to support other family members <ref type="bibr">(Building Movement Project, 2020)</ref>. If working in the movement doesn't provide you with a living wage and benefits, being transparent about that as a reason for working elsewhere is the most supportive action you can take.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>For Funders</head><p>Without major funders' support, it's difficult or impossible for organizations to compensate their staff at a level that encourages retention.</p><p>• Fund salaries and other operating costs. Our data point to the need for fair compensation to retain employees. High turnover makes it more expensive for nonprofits to help animals, as our cost-of-turnover calculator helps estimate. Aim to fund salaries that are closer to the nonprofit market rates. You can also support organizational health by providing funding to grantees for external human resources and compensation consultants to audit their pay and benefits package or help them develop a formal process for determining compensation. In addition, whenever possible, provide multi-year funding commitments so that organizations can strategize long-term.</p><p>• Encourage grantees to be transparent about their compensation practices and remove potential sources of bias. This can be done by providing funding for grantees to investigate whether pay disparities exist in their organizations and to put equitable pay in place for all staff.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Applying These Findings</head><p>We understand that reports like this have a lot of information to consider and that acting on research can be challenging. Faunalytics is happy to offer pro bono support to advocates and nonprofit organizations who would like guidance applying these findings to their own work.</p><p>Please visit our virtual Office Hours or contact us for support. Additionally, you can contact Culture Canopy for select pro bono People &amp; Culture support and guidance with developing or reviewing your organization's total compensation philosophy and strategy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Behind The Project</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Team</head><p>The project's lead author was Research Scientist Dr. Andrea Polanco (Faunalytics) and Dr. Jo Anderson (Faunalytics) reviewed and oversaw the work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Terminology</head><p>At Faunalytics, we strive to make research accessible to everyone. We avoid jargon and technical terminology as much as possible in our reports. If you do encounter an unfamiliar term or phrase, check out the Faunalytics Glossary for user-friendly definitions and examples.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Ethics Statement</head><p>As with all of Faunalytics' original research, this study was conducted according to the standards outlined in our Research Ethics and Data Handling Policy.</p><p>Additionally, this study was conducted in strict accordance with the ethical guidelines and principles outlined by the Research Ethics Board by Carleton University (approval reference number 119576).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method Sampling Method</head><p>We invited farmed animal advocacy nonprofit organizations with either U.S. or U.K. headquarters from an internal Faunalytics list of over 100 organizations, though we received only enough responses to include U.S. organizations. In addition, we invited organizations and individuals to participate through advocacy mailing lists, conference forums, and Slack channels. The full inclusion criteria can be found in Supplementary Materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Collected</head><p>We invited organizations' leadership (e.g., Executive Director or Operations Director) to provide data on behalf of their organizations. Those who agreed completed a confidential spreadsheet detailing the organization's pay by job role, as well as a survey about their organization's revenue, mission, pay philosophy, and more. Finally, they were also asked to distribute a separate, confidential survey to their staff, which asked participants to voluntarily self-report their salary, details of their employment, and demographics. Data were collected from July 16, 2023 to September 20, 2023. The full organization survey and individual survey can be found on the Open Science Framework. The compensation spreadsheet is described in detail in the Supplementary Materials.</p><p>We also incorporated salary data from two public job boards into the compensation spreadsheet. We included positions that were posted to Animal Advocacy Careers or Vegan Jobs between October 2023 and March 2024 by organizations that met our inclusion criteria.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Confidentiality &amp; Data Privacy</head><p>We followed strict principles to ensure that participant privacy was protected during data collection and storage, while still gathering the data we need to examine compensation in the movement. The data will be securely destroyed six months after publication of this report.</p><p>Before analyses began, all identifiable data (e.g., organization name) were removed to protect organizations and individuals from being identified. To further anonymize the results under U.S. Farmed Animal Advocacy Salaries below, we rounded all reported values up to the nearest fifty dollars to ensure that no value was recognizable.</p><p>In analyses based on the individual survey, we have avoided presenting salary data for demographics in ways where individual identities could be guessed, by combining data across a minimum of ten participants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Salary Analyses</head><p>To create salary benchmarks, we incorporated 358 U.S. employee job records from three sources: records submitted to us by the participating organizations (n = 310); records submitted to us by individual participants who worked at organizations that didn't participate as a whole (n = 9); and records extracted from two public job boards as described above (n = 39). This combined dataset, from a total of 40 organizations, does not include data from outside the U.S. or from contractor positions (see Supplementary Materials for more details).</p><p>We followed Safe Harbor Guidelines to ensure that there were at least five organizations represented in each benchmark analysis and that no organization should represent more than 25% of the salary data in a given analysis as to skew the results. In cases where this latter threshold wasn't met, we randomly removed records from that organization until it no longer represented more than 25% of that particular sample. To ensure that we present only reliable data, we then ran a sensitivity analysis to compare the results with and without those records removed. If salaries differed by more than $5,000 between the two analyses, we have provided only the median salary in the results, rather than all three percentiles.</p><p>To further preserve confidentiality, we present the full results (i.e., 25th, 50th, and 75th percentiles) if there were at least ten job records, in addition to at least five organizations. We therefore only display the median salary if there were at least five organizations but fewer than ten job records. See Supplementary Materials for details on the record removal process and sensitivity analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Equity Analyses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pay Gap Analyses</head><p>A key goal of this study was to test the hypothesis that, even if we account for employment factors like job level and organization size, BIPOC individuals, women/non-binary/other gender,</p><p>LGBTQ2IA+ individuals, and disabled individuals would earn lower pay than other employees.</p><p>We tested this hypothesis by running two linear mixed effect regression models. The first explored the unadjusted pay gap between members and non-members of each group, while the second model examined adjusted pay gaps between members and non-members (i.e., the pay gap adjusted for job level, country, age, and years of experience in one's job role). For the adjusted pay gap models, we applied Benjamini-Hochberg post hoc corrections to the p-values to correct for false discovery rate (FDR). Full details on these analyses can be found under Supplementary Materials.</p><p>Because BIPOC individuals (n = 35) and individuals with a disability (n = 33) were underrepresented, we also examined this hypothesis for a pooled marginalized group (i.e., BIPOC, LGBTQ2IA+, and people with disabilities). This pooling was statistically necessary but doesn't allow us to shed as much light on the unique challenges of each of these groups, which are further discussed in the Conclusions.</p><p>We additionally looked at whether members and non-members of each group differed across job level, country, age, and years of experience in one's job role, as a potential explanation for a pay gap. We ran ordinal logistic regressions for job level, age, and years of experience in one's job role, while we ran a chi-squared test for country. We didn't apply post hoc corrections to determine statistical significance as these tests were exploratory in nature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Retention Analyses</head><p>We also explored whether average reported likelihood of leaving the movement (if offered higher pay elsewhere) differed between members and non-members of the combined marginalized group with a t-test, and whether salary varied by one's likelihood of leaving the movement with a linear regression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>This study's pre-registration, survey instruments, and analysis code are available on the Open Science Framework. As mentioned under Confidentiality &amp; Data Privacy, the data was never publicly accessible and will be securely destroyed upon six months of publication of this report to protect participant confidentiality.</p><p>All salaries and revenues presented in the report are in USD currency, and salaries are shown as full-time equivalent (FTE). For graphs with error bars, the error bars represent the 95% confidence intervals (CIs).</p><p>For inferential statistics, we report marginally significant effects (0.05 &lt; p &lt; 0.10), in addition to statistically significant ones (p &lt; 0.05).</p><p>The individual survey had a final sample size of 244 respondents from 35 organizations (95% of participants in the individual survey worked at an organization that participated in the study). We received organization survey data from 40 organizations, benefit data from 36, and salary data from 27 organizations with U.S. employee records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organization Characteristics</head><p>Below is a table that shows the count and percentage of U.S. organizations that participated in both the organization survey and the compensation spreadsheet (n = 27) across different types of organizational-level characteristics.</p><p>Overall, most participating organizations were small (74% employed 1-10 full-time staff), had a mission related to movement building or collaboration (70%), and just over half had a revenue under $1 million (56%) and received funding from Effective Altruism (EA) funders (52%). Further, as discussed under Benefits At Participating Farmed Animal Advocacy Organizations, all participating organizations were either mostly or fully remote (Table <ref type="table">10</ref>).</p><p>As discussed at the start of the report, some of these characteristics suggest that our organization sample isn't fully representative of the movement. Most notably, the prevalence of EA funding and lack of on-site workplaces indicate gaps in our sample that the reader should bear in mind, although we found no evidence that EA-funded groups have higher salaries than non-EA funded groups in this sample (p = 0.86; see Supplementary Materials for more).</p><p>Table 1. Organization Characteristics Count Percentage Revenue Under $1 million 15 56% Over $1 million 12 44% Number of Staff (FTEs) 1-10 20 74% 11+ 7 26% Mission<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">foot_0</ref> Movement building and collaboration 19 70% Policy or legislative change 11 41% Research or program evaluation 10 37% Diet-change interventions (e.g., leafleting, meat-free challenge) 5 19% Menu-change programs (e.g., school or hospital meals) 4 15% Humane education 3 11% Multimedia advocacy work (e.g., publishing, web design, photo/video creation) 3 11% Conduct investigations of the animal agriculture industry 2 7% Alternative protein research and development 2 7% Other (e.g., grantmaking, supporting academic fields, consulting) 2 7% Hold protests or demonstrations 1 4% Animal care or rescue 1 4% EA Funding Yes 14 52% No 9 33% Unsure 4 15%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>U.S. Farmed Animal Advocacy Salaries</head><p>The tables below display the 25th, 50th (median), and 75th percentiles of salaries across all U.S. farmed animal advocacy positions. These percentiles indicate that 25%, 50%, and 75% of the reported salaries are below that particular value.</p><p>Table 2 shows U.S. salaries by four job level groups (individual contributor, management, leadership, and executive director) and by all staff.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Job Level Groups</head><p>Briefly, EDs are responsible for leading the organizations' strategic vision and are the most senior position within an organization. Staff in leadership positions are also responsible for organizational strategies, but to a lesser extent than an ED, such as being responsible for a specific department (e.g., Director of Function) and/or who develop strategic goals (e.g., Vice President of Function). Staff in management positions typically oversee other staff (e.g., Manager or Senior Manager) and/or are responsible for delivering on tactical goals (e.g., Entry Manager). Lastly, individual contributors don't manage other people, but range in the amount of supervision they require (e.g., Assistant and Coordinator levels typically require more than Senior Coordinator and Analyst/Specialist levels). See Table <ref type="table">18</ref> under Supplementary Materials for further job level descriptions.</p><p>The table below indicates that pay tends to be higher at each progressive job level, as expected, though please note that these are just descriptive of our sample-we didn't look at whether these differences were statistically significant. Across all organizations, individual contributors make a median salary of $67,250, management make $84,500, leadership make $108,850 and EDs make $97,550.</p><p>Although the higher pay for leadership compared to EDs in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> may appear strange, this reflects the larger number of leadership positions at higher-revenue organizations. Tables <ref type="table">3</ref> and <ref type="table">4</ref> provide a more nuanced picture of leadership versus ED salaries.</p><p>Table 2. Salaries Across All Participating Organizations Job Level Group Number of Organizations Number of Records 1 Salary Percentiles 25th Median 75th All Staff 40 345 $67,050 $80,000 $105,300 Executive Director/CEO 20 21 $72,500 $97,550 $129,300 Leadership<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">foot_1</ref> 20 112 $90,100 $108,850 $130,450 Management 2 22 93 $70,000 $84,500 $92,750 Individual Contributor 2 25 108 $56,200 $67,250 $74,600 1</p><p>The number of records for ED, leadership, management, and individual contributor don't add to 345 as some records were removed to ensure that no organization represented more than 25% of the salary data.</p><p>Table 3. Salaries At Organizations With Revenue Under $1 Million Job Level Group Number of Organizations Number of Records 1 Salary Percentiles 25th Median 75th All Staff 19 46 $42,350 $68,350 $77,800 Executive Director 2 9 9 $70,000 Leadership 3 7 12 $37,600 $69,350 $79,550 Management 2,3 7 8 $67,950 Individual Contributor 3,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">foot_2</ref> 8 14 $70,250 1 The number of records for ED, leadership, management, and individual contributor don't add to 46 as some records were removed to ensure that no organization represented more than 25% of the salary data. 2 There were not enough records to display the full range of results. 3 Leadership includes Director-and VP-level roles; Management includes Entry through Senior Managers; Individual Contributor includes Assistant through Specialist roles. Full details in Table 18 of the Supplementary Materials.</p><p>Table 4. Salaries At Organizations With Revenue Over $1 Million Job Level Group Number of Organizations Number of Records 1 Salary Percentiles 25th Median 75th All Staff<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">foot_3</ref> 20 277 $84,000 Executive Director 11 12 $95,800 $128,000 $213,650 Leadership 2,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">foot_4</ref> 13 85 $114,000 Management 3 15 80 $70,000 $84,500 $92,600 Individual Contributor 3 16 85 $56,850 $67,250 $73,950 1</p><p>The number of records for ED, leadership, management, and individual contributor don't add to 277 as some records were removed to ensure that no organization represented more than 25% of the salary data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Salaries By Organization Size</head><p>The following tables show U.S. salaries by job level groups at farmed animal advocacy organizations with a staff size below (Table <ref type="table">5</ref>) or above (Table <ref type="table">6</ref>) 11 FTE employees.</p><p>Based on the tables below, we observe that organizations with 10 employees or fewer tend to pay less (e.g., a median salary of $70,000 across all staff) compared to organizations with 11 employees or more (e.g., a median salary of $81,800 across all staff). As well, pay tends to be higher at each progressive job level, but only for organizations with 11 employees or more. Again, these are just descriptive trends for organizations in this sample.</p><p>Table 5. Salaries At Organizations With 1-10 Staff Job Level Group Number of Organizations Number of Records Salary Percentiles 25th Median 75th All Staff 22 76 $55,750 $70,000 $89,400 Executive Director 13 13 $43,700 $77,000 $111,850 Leadership 1 11 26 $65,500 $83,800 $105,300 Management 1 9 12 $60,500 $66,400 $77,500 Individual Contributor 1 12 25 $47,750 $64,500 $76,800 1 Leadership includes Director-and VP-level roles; Management includes Entry through Senior Managers; Individual Contributor includes Assistant through Specialist roles. Full details in Table 18 of the Supplementary Materials.</p><p>Table 6. Salaries At Organizations With 11+ Staff Job Level Group<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">foot_5</ref> Number of Organizations Number of Records 2 Salary Percentiles 25th Median 75th All Staff 3 14 210 $81,800 Executive Director 4 7 8 $162,050 Management 5 12 69 $70,000 $84,550 $94,300 Individual Contributor 3,5 11 72 $67,150 1 No results are shown for the leadership group as sensitivity analyses revealed that both the 25th and 50th percentiles were unreliable. 2 The number of records for ED, management, and individual contributor don't add to 210 as some records were removed to ensure that no organization represented more than 25% of the salary data. As well, we weren't able to display results for the leadership group (see footnote above). 3 Sensitivity analyses revealed that the 25th and/or 75th percentile(s) were unreliable. 4 There were not enough records to display the full range of results. 5 Management includes Entry through Senior Managers; Individual Contributor includes Assistant through Specialist roles. Full details in Table 18 of the Supplementary Materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Salaries By Job Family</head><p>Table 7 shows U.S. salaries by job family (type of work) across all farmed animal advocacy organizations. See Table 19 under Supplementary Materials for full examples of each job family. Table 7. Salaries By Job Family Across All Participating Organizations Job Family 1 Number of Organizations Number of Records Salary Percentiles 25th Median 75th External Communications 14 45 $62,150 $73,950 $91,250 Fundraising &amp; Grants 13 29 $66,350 $91,750 $120,900 Operations 22 72 $65,150 $81,550 $108,050 Program, Policy &amp; External Affairs 18 81 $71,400 $84,550 $104,100</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benchmarking Executive Salaries Against Other U.S. Nonprofit Sectors</head><p>We compared our executive salary benchmarks for farmed animal advocacy to Candid's comprehensive data on executive salaries at all 501(c)(3) nonprofits in 2021. While Candid only provides salary data for EDs and "top" positions (e.g., Director-level), we only had enough data for ED comparisons. For additional salary info for specific job levels and roles, readers can reference the U.S. Bureau Of Labor Statistics' (2022) data on salaries by occupation.</p><p>The figures below show how salaries from our sample of farmed animal advocacy EDs compare to the rest of the nonprofit sector, including environmental nonprofits (e.g., conservation), social advocacy nonprofits (e.g., civil rights), and animal-related nonprofits.</p><p>It's important to note that the animal-related nonprofits category, which is one of the lowest paying sectors across all U.S. nonprofits (Barron's, 2023), largely comprises direct work with animals: sanctuaries, veterinary services, animal training, wildlife protection, zoos, and aquariums. In comparison, direct work is almost unrepresented in our sample of farmed animal advocacy organizations, which may explain the higher salaries we observe in our sample compared to the animal-related non-profits category.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Executive Salary Comparison In Organizations With Revenues Under $1 Million</head><p>Note: Executive salaries of farmed animal advocacy organizations with a revenue below $1 million are from our sample (n = 9), while the remaining executive salaries are from organizations with a revenue between $500 thousand and $1 million from Candid (all nonprofits n = 17,791; animal-related nonprofits n = 371; environmental nonprofits n = 599; and social advocacy nonprofits n = 313).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2. Executive Salary Comparison In Organizations With Revenues Over $1 Million</head><p>Note: Executive salaries of farmed animal advocacy organizations with a revenue below $1 million are from our sample (n = 12), while the remaining executive salaries are from organizations with a revenue between $1 million and $5 million from Candid (all nonprofits n = 21,015; animal-related nonprofits n = 597; environmental nonprofits n = 947; and social advocacy nonprofits n = 558).</p><p>There are three descriptive trends to note. First, executive salaries in the U.S. farmed animal protection movement are lower than the executive salaries of social advocacy and environmental organizations across both revenue categories. Second, smaller-revenue organizations' executive salaries were lower than the median for U.S. nonprofits of similar revenue, while higher-revenue organizations' executive salaries were higher than the median. Third, regardless of organization revenue, executive salaries in our sample of farmed animal organizations were higher than the median of U.S. animal-related organizations. As discussed above, this is likely because our sample overrepresents indirect work compared to direct work with animals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pay Practices &amp; Philosophy At Participating Farmed Animal Advocacy Organizations</head><p>Below is a table that shows organizations' (n = 27) pay practices and philosophies.</p><p>Overall, most participating organizations had a formal pay process (70%), reviewed that process annually (59%), had pay bands for all positions (59%), and were transparent about pay with their staff (78%). The most common strategy for setting salaries was relying on pay processes set by other organizations, companies, or government institutions (44%), while most organizations set pay raises based on cost-of-living increases (70%). Further, only 26% of organization representatives said that they were 'very satisfied' with their organization's pay process.</p><p>As mentioned previously, our sample is likely affected by selection bias: organizations may have been more motivated to participate in our study if they had leadership who felt satisfied with their organization's pay and were already transparent to their staff about pay, so these breakdowns may not be very representative of the larger farmed animal movement.</p><p>Table 8. Organization Pay Practices &amp; Philosophy Count Percentage Organization Has A Compensation Process Yes 19 70% No 7 26% Unsure 1 4% Compensation Review Frequency Annually 16 59% Two or more times a year 4 15% Unsure 2 7%</p><p>We don't review compensation 5 19%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pay Bands</head><p>We have pay bands for ALL positions 16 59%</p><p>We have pay bands for SOME positions 0 0%</p><p>We don't have pay bands</p><p>10 37% Unsure 1 4% Organization Has Pay Transparency With Staff Yes 21 78% No 3 11% Unsure 3 11% Pay Determination Strategies 1 Salaries are set by using salary structures from other organizations, companies, or governmental institutions 12 44% Other (e.g., based on available budget, staff needs, or set by the board) 8 30% Salaries are set by using PAID tools or formal reports 6 22% Salaries are set with an algorithm 5 19% Salaries are set by using FREE online tools or reports 5 19% We don't have a set strategy for setting salaries 3 11% Salaries are set by a hired third-party organization or contractor 0 0% Pay Raise Strategies 1 Raises are based on cost-of-living increases 19 70% Raises are given annually 14 52% Raises are based on responsibilities (e.g., supervising an extra person) 10 37% Raises are based on performance 7 26% Other (e.g., raises are based on available budget or when moving to a new role; raises aren't given because the organization is new) 6 22% We don't have a set strategy for giving raises 5 19% Raises are based on length of service (e.g., after 3 or 5 years) 4 15% Raises are matched to similar roles in other organizations 3 11% Raises are based on professional development (e.g., new training or education) 1 4%</p><p>We ask staff directly if they need a raise 1 4%</p><p>Raises are typically given only when requested 0 0%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compensation Satisfaction</head><p>Very dissatisfied 1 4%</p><p>Somewhat dissatisfied 4 15%</p><p>Neither satisfied nor dissatisfied 5 19%</p><p>Somewhat satisfied 10 37% Very satisfied 7 26%</p><p>1 Percentages don't add to 100% because participants could choose more than one option.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefits At Participating Farmed Animal Advocacy Organizations</head><p>Below are the types of benefits offered by all participating farmed animal advocacy organizations (n = 27).</p><p>Table 9. Paid Time Off Count Percentage Paid Sick Days 1 5-10 days 10 42% 11 days or more 4 17% Unlimited 6 25% Part of vacation 2 4 17% Public Holidays Less than 10 days 6 25% 10-12 days 12 50% 13 days or more 4 17% Unlimited 3 13% Vacation Days 1 15-20 days 10 42% 21-24 days 3 13% 25 days or more 3 13% Unlimited 8 33% 1 Minimum at hire. 2 A single combined amount of paid time off that is used for both vacation and sick days.</p><p>Table 10. Remote &amp; Flexible Work Benefits Count Percentage Type Of Remote Work Fully Remote 24 89% Hybrid or Mostly Remote 3 11% Type Of Work Hours Fully flexible 16 59% Core hours 1 7 26% Core hours with flexibility 2 7% Reduced work week 2 2 7% 1 A specific set of hours during a workday when all employees are expected to be present at work. 2 Employees work fewer hours and/or fewer days than the traditional five-day 40-hour workweek (e.g., working four days a week or working less than eight hours a day across the workweek).</p><p>Table 11. Additional Benefits Count Percentage Type Of Benefit Allowance for professional development opportunities (e.g., conferences, webinars, learning wallet) 21 81% Medical plan/coverage 21 78% Utility reimbursement (e.g., phone, equipment, internet) 17 63% Dental coverage 14 56% Enhanced or extended parental leave (above statutory requirements) 14 54% Retirement plan (e.g., match program) 14 52% Remote work stipend, allowance, or reimbursement (e.g., coworking spaces, miscellaneous expenses) 13 50% Optical/vision coverage 11 44% Additional paid leave for wellbeing 11 41% Companion animal benefit (e.g., paid emergency/bereavement leave, pet insurance) 11 41% Overtime pay 8 32% Mental health services 7 27% Life insurance coverage 6 23% Bonus or performance-based compensation 3 11%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organizational Barriers To Providing Competitive Compensation</head><p>As part of the organization survey, we also asked organization representatives to elaborate on barriers faced by their organizations with respect to providing compensation to their employees. 25 organization representatives answered this question and we informally coded the responses.</p><p>Many respondents indicated that they want to increase pay and know their employees are worth more, but can't afford it due to funding constraints. For instance, one participant said, "we are unable to pay people what they deserve as funding in the space is sparse." Likewise, another person said, "[a barrier is] the inability to pay everyone a livable wage to our full-time employees because of our lack of funding." This is particularly true for small and new organizations.</p><p>Even when funding exists in the present, it may not be guaranteed in the future. As one participant said, "it is challenging to predict what our financial outlook will be like year over year, so we cannot guarantee annual salary increases to our staff."</p><p>Another barrier, mentioned by a few participants, was the difficulty in considering different cost-of-living standards and/or healthcare standards when determining equitable pay, an issue for both international organizations and national organizations that have staff living in different regions. One person said:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>It is also difficult knowing what is most fair and sustainable when hiring internationally, for instance if someone chooses to live in the most expensive city in the world, should you pay them 3 times that of another remote worker who intentionally chooses to live somewhere with a very low cost of living? Alternatively, if someone lives in a […] country with a low cost of living, but has dependents and other lifestyle factors influencing their need [, should you pay them less?].</head><p>However, another participant said, "it's reasonable to have significant pay disparities within the org[anisation] for people living in [different locations]." Indeed, some organizations tackle differences in cost-of-living by adjusting for it in a salary algorithm (e.g., different locations get different considerations that are then factored into the formula) or only adjusting for it if the position requires that the employee lives in a high-cost city (e.g., a U.S. lobbyist may be required to live in Washington, D.C.). It's also important to acknowledge that where one lives isn't always a personal choice and not everyone has the privilege of moving.</p><p>For a fuller picture of the organizational perspective on barriers, we recommend reading our accompanying blog on this topic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pay Equity Analyses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Respondent Characteristics</head><p>The data used in our pay equity analyses came from the individual survey of 244 staff members at farmed animal advocacy organizations. While our salary benchmarks were restricted to U.S. positions, our equity analyses are not.</p><p>Overall, our sample was mostly composed of employees (89%; vs. contractors) who worked 40+ hours a week (58%) in a mid-level role (42%), and who had worked in that role for 1 to 5 years (51%). Respondents represented a wide range of job groups, but the most common was program, policy, and external affairs (26%).</p><p>Table 12. Staff Employment Characteristics Count Percentage Employment Type Employee 217 89% Contractor 27 11% Hours Per Week 1-19 hours 12 5% 20-29 hours 9 4% 30-39 hours 81 33% 40+ hours 142 58% Job Group 1 Program, Policy &amp; External Affairs (e.g., campaign, outreach, policy development, legal representation) 63 26% External Communications (e.g., journalism, events, marketing, public relations, social media, website development, etc.) 52 21% Operations (e.g., finance, human resources, information technology, admin, etc.) 51 21% Organizational Strategy &amp; Leadership (e.g., Executive Director or CEO) 43 18% Research &amp; Analytics (e.g., research, academia, impact evaluation, investigations, etc.) 43 18% Fundraising &amp; Grants (e.g., grant-writing) 32 13% Volunteer Management (e.g., volunteer recruitment) 5 2% Humane Education (e.g., classroom education) 3 1% Other 4 2% 29 Animal care (e.g., animal caretaker) 0 0% Years In Current Role Less than a year 105 43% 1-5 years 123 51% 6 years or more 14 6% Job Level 2 Entry-level 19 8% Mid-level 102 42% Senior-level 32 13% Director-level 52 22% Executive-level 37 15% 1 Percentages don't add to 100% because participants could choose more than one option. 2 These broader job levels were used in the individual survey (vs. organization compensation spreadsheet) because it is easier for individuals without human resources training to answer and also protects confidentiality.</p><p>For demographics (Table <ref type="table">13</ref>), our sample tended to be women (71%), white (74%), between the ages of 25 and 34 (44%), living in the U.S. (65%), and holding a graduate or professional degree (56%).</p><p>This is similar to what we found in a previous study focused on animal advocates in the U.S. and Canada <ref type="bibr">(Faunalytics, 2020)</ref>, where 78% of paid advocates were women, 81% were white, 56% were between the ages of 25-34, and 53% had a graduate or professional degree. While the demographic composition between both studies is similar, it's important to note that both studies are likely affected by selection bias: less privileged advocates may have been less likely to participate due to time constraints or other factors (a point we return to in Conclusions). The high proportion of graduate degrees is particularly noticeable, given that under 15% of people in the general population hold them (U.S. Census Bureau, 2022).</p><p>Table 13. Staff Personal Characteristics Count Percentage Race/Ethnicity 1 White 181 60% Hispanic or Latino/a/x 27 35% South Asian 16 5% Other 26 12% Gender 2 Woman 170 71% Man 58 24% Non-binary/Other gender 10 4% Marginalized Identities 1 LGBTQ2IA+ 52 21% BIPOC 35 15% Person with a disability 33 14% Marginalized (BIPOC, LGBTQ2IA+, &amp; disability groups combined) 94 43% Age 18-24 years old 10 4% 25-34 years old 106 44% 35-44 years old 76 32% 45-54 years old 39 16% 55+ years old 10 4% Country Of Residence U.S. 156 65% 16% Other country 47 19% Education Graduate or professional 135 56% College diploma, university degree, or similar 97 40% High school graduate or equivalent 10 4% Less than high school graduate 0 0% 1 Percentages don't add to 100% because participants could choose more than one option. 2 Gender was asked as an open-ended question and then coded as man, woman, or non-binary/other gender after two coders reached consensus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Retention, Pay, &amp; Marginalized Identity</head><p>We asked participants in the individual survey their likelihood of leaving the movement if offered a similar role with better pay elsewhere. Overall, about a third of respondents (36%) indicated that they are somewhat or very likely to leave the movement. As shown in Table <ref type="table">14</ref> below, marginalized advocates (i.e., identifying as BIPOC, having a disability, and/or being LGBTQ2IA+) were slightly more likely to say they were thinking about leaving the movement than non-marginalized advocates (p = 0.05).</p><p>Table 14. Retention By Marginalized Identity Likelihood Of Leaving For A Similar Role With Higher Pay Outside Of The Movement All participants (n = 239) Marginalized Participants (n = 92) Non-Marginalized Participants (n = 125) Very unlikely 29% 24% 31% Somewhat unlikely 21% 22% 22% Neither likely nor unlikely 13% 10% 18% Somewhat likely 21% 25% 17% Very likely 15% 20% 12%</p><p>In addition to the above, a few participants shared write-in responses on the survey, of which the most frequently-mentioned topic was pay dissatisfaction. For example, one person said that they're leaving their role for a higher-paying position that will allow them to save for retirement or buy a home, while another person said:</p><p>I love my position, but I am barely making ends meet. There seems to be little opportunity for pay increases and promotions. I do not know how long I can do this without a second job, even though I love the work.</p><p>Despite this, average pay didn't significantly vary by one's likelihood to leave (p = 0.21), meaning we found no evidence that lower-paid individuals were no more likely to say they were thinking about leaving than higher-paid individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pay &amp; Marginalized Identities</head><p>In this section, we examined whether there are pay gaps between members of marginalized groups and others with linear mixed effect models. Specifically, the marginalized groups we considered include: BIPOC individuals, marginalized genders (women, non-binary, and other genders outside the traditional binary), LGBTQ2IA+ individuals, and disabled individuals.</p><p>We first present results for the combined marginalized identity group and then show separate results for each marginalized identity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overall Marginalized Identity</head><p>For this analysis, we compared marginalized individuals (identifying as BIPOC, having a disability, and/or being LGBTQIA+) against non-marginalized individuals and found a pay gap between the two groups (unadjusted pay gap: p &lt; .0001).</p><p>Adjusting for other factors that affect salary, the pay gap is approximately 15%-a marginalized person makes approximately 15% or $10,200 less on average than a non-marginalized person, accounting for differences in age, years in job role, country of residence, and job level (p = 0.006). In other words, a marginalized farmed animal advocate earns approximately 85 cents for every dollar that a non-marginalized advocate makes (see Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 3. Average Adjusted Pay By Marginalized Identity</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BIPOC Identity</head><p>To consider whether race/ethnicity specifically affects pay, we looked for evidence of a pay gap between BIPOC and non-BIPOC participants. Bear in mind that these findings are less reliable than those presented above for overall marginalized identity because this analysis was underpowered due to the small sample of BIPOC participants (n = 32).</p><p>In our sample, there was a small, marginally significant unadjusted pay gap between BIPOC and non-BIPOC participants (p = 0.08). However, it was non-significant when other influences on salary are accounted for (p = 0.21). Adjusting for other factors that affect salary, the pay gap is approximately 7% in our sample, though it did not reach statistical significance (see Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 4. Average Adjusted Pay By BIPOC Identity</head><p>These findings suggest that something about BIPOC participants' employment characteristics is different from non-BIPOC participants', which in turn affects their relative salaries. In an exploratory analysis of those other factors, we found that BIPOC participants' jobs were significantly lower-level than non-BIPOC participants' (p = 0.01; see Table <ref type="table">15</ref>) and BIPOC participants were significantly younger than non-BIPOC participants (p = 0.03; see Table <ref type="table">15</ref>).</p><p>While our findings are marginal and represent only a small sample of farmed animal advocates, they suggest that there may be a pay gap between BIPOC and non-BIPOC advocates, and that it may be partially due to BIPOC advocates being more likely to hold lower-level positions and being younger on average (therefore perhaps newer to the workforce).</p><p>Table 15. BIPOC &amp; Non-BIPOC Participants By Job Level, Age Group, &amp; Country BIPOC (n = 32) Non-BIPOC (n = 189) Job Level Entry 25% 4% Mid 41% 42% Senior 3% 15% Director 16% 23% Executive 16% 16% Age 18-24 years old 9% 2% 25-34 years old 50% 44% 35-44 years old 38% 32% 45-54 years old 3% 17% 55+ years old 0% 5%</p><p>LGBTQ2IA+ Identity</p><p>To consider whether sexual and gender minorities experience pay discrimination, we looked for evidence of a pay gap between participants who self-identified as LGBTQ2IA+ and those who didn't.</p><p>In our sample, there was a pay gap between LGBTQ2IA+ and other participants (unadjusted pay gap: p = 0.008) that was non-significant when other influences on salary were accounted for (p = 0.25). Adjusting for other factors that affect salary, the pay gap is approximately 5% in our sample, though it did not reach statistical significance (see Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 5. Average Adjusted Pay By LGBTQ2IA+ Identity</head><p>Similar to the findings for BIPOC participants, these findings suggest that something about LGBTQ2IA+ participants' employment characteristics is different from others', which in turn affects their relative salaries. In an exploratory analysis of these other factors, we found that LGBTQ2IA+ participants' jobs were significantly lower-level than other participants' (p &lt; 0.05; see Table <ref type="table">16</ref>) and LGBTQ2IA+ participants were significantly younger than other participants (p &lt; 0.001; see Table <ref type="table">16</ref>).</p><p>This suggest that there may be a pay gap between between LGBTQ2IA+ and other advocates, which could be due to LGBTQ2IA+ advocates being more likely to hold lower-level positions and being younger on average (and perhaps newer to the workforce).</p><p>Table 16. LGBTQ2IA+ &amp; Other Participants In Each Job Level &amp; Age Group LGBTQ2IA+ (n = 51) Non-LGBTQ2IA+ (n = 165) Job Level Entry 14% 7% Mid 51% 41% Senior 6% 16% Director 20% 22% Executive 10% 14% Age 18-24 years old 10% 2% 25-34 years old 57% 41% 35-44 years old 27% 35% 45-54 years old 6% 18% 55+ years old 0% 5%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disability Identity</head><p>To consider whether individuals with a disability experience pay discrimination, we looked for evidence of a pay gap between participants with and without any type of disability. Bear in mind that these findings are less reliable than those presented above for overall marginalized identity because this analysis was underpowered due to the small sample of participants with a disability (n = 33).</p><p>In our sample, the pay gap between participants with and without a disability was statistically significant even after accounting for other influences (p = 0.04). Adjusting for other factors that affect salary, the pay gap is approximately 13%: a person with a disability makes approximately 13% or $8,500 less than a person without a disability, accounting for differences in age, years of experience, country of residence, and job level. In other words, a person with a disability earns approximately 87 cents for every dollar that a person without a disability makes (see Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 6. Average Adjusted Pay By Disability</head><p>Upon further inspection of the data, we found similar proportions of disabled and non-disabled participants working at each job level and across different age groups. This suggests that such employment characteristics may not be contributing to the observed disability pay gap in our small sample, at least not to the same extent that we found for BIPOC and LGBTQ2IA+ participants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gender Identity</head><p>To consider whether gender affects pay, we looked for evidence of a pay gap between women/non-binary/other gender participants and male participants.</p><p>In our sample, there was a small pay gap between the unadjusted salaries of women/non-binary/other gender and male participants (p = 0.01). However, this was non-significant once other influences on salary are accounted for (p = 0.25). Adjusting for other factors that affect salary, the pay gap is approximately 4% in our sample, though it did not reach statistical significance (see Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 7. Average Adjusted Pay By Gender</head><p>In an exploratory investigation of other differences between the two gender groups, we found that men's jobs were significantly higher-level than women/non-binary/other gender participants' (p = 0.01; see Table <ref type="table">17</ref>), men in our sample were significantly older than the women/non-binary/other gender participants (p = 0.03; see Table <ref type="table">17</ref>), and women/non-binary/other gender participants were significantly more likely to live in the U.S. than male participants (p &lt; .01; see Table <ref type="table">17</ref>).</p><p>This suggests that there may be a pay gap between women/non-binary/other gender and men, and that this pay gap is at least partially due to women/non-binary/other gender advocates being more likely to hold lower-level positions and being younger on average (and perhaps newer to the workforce).</p><p>Table 17. Women/Non-binary/Other Gender &amp; Male Participants In Each Job Level &amp; Age Group Women/Non-binary/Other Gender (n = 173) Men (n = 52) Job Level Entry 9% 6% Mid 46% 31% Senior 13% 13% Director 20% 27% Executive 12% 23% Age 18-24 years old 4% 0% 25-34 years old 48% 40% 35-44 years old 33% 31% 45-54 years old 13% 23% 55+ years old 2% 6% Country Of Residence<ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">foot_6</ref> U.S. 69% 46% U.K. &amp; other countries 31% 54%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>The State Of U.S. Farmed Animal Advocacy Pay &amp; Benefits</p><p>Although this report is imperfect given the limited data available, it is the first report of its kind in our movement and we hope it will encourage advocates to have more discussions around pay and benefit equity within the movement.</p><p>We observed a few patterns in the median salaries that are worth highlighting. As is to be expected, salaries tend to be higher at organizations with a larger revenue and more staff, and salaries tend to increase with each progressing job level (particularly for larger-revenue and larger-sized organizations).</p><p>As well, median ED salaries from our sample of farmed animal advocacy organizations tended to be lower than those of EDs in social and environmental movements, especially for smaller-revenue organizations, but higher than those of EDs in the broader animal-related nonprofit sector (Candid), likely because of the prevalence of direct work with animals in that sector compared to in our sample. Direct work with animals accounts for some of farmed animal advocates' work (e.g., sanctuaries, rescues), but much of our movement's work is more similar to the social advocacy and environmental sectors, suggesting that they are a more appropriate salary benchmark.</p><p>Regarding benefits, while most organizations in our sample offered a medical plan, most didn't provide optical benefits, dental benefits, or a retirement plan. While we didn't ask advocates their benefits preferences, a recent sample of U.S. employees rated healthcare benefits, followed by life insurance and a pension/retirement plan, as the most important types of benefits. Farmed animal advocacy leadership may want to survey their employees on the types of benefits that they would like to have, while keeping in mind that minimum standards will vary according to regional regulations.</p><p>In our sample, none of the participating organizations offered fewer than 15 vacation days, which is higher than the average number of vacation days provided to those working at the U.</p><p>S. state or local government and those working in the private U.S. sector after one year (13 and 11 days, respectively: U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, 2023). In contrast, while the average number of sick days for those working at the U.S. state or local government after one year is 11 days (U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, 2023), only 42% of organizations sampled provided 11 sick days or more, including unlimited. Although only a minority of organizations in our sample provided unlimited sick days (25%) and unlimited vacation (33%), it should be noted that some people take less time off than what's typically offered when giving a set number of days due to workplace pressures. To avoid this, we encourage employers to set a minimum required amount of PTO if using an unlimited PTO structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pay Equity</head><p>This is also the first study to date that has examined whether pay gaps exist in the movement.</p><p>Even though most of our study participants worked at organizations with formal strategies to set pay bands and raises, marginalized advocates still earned, on average, 15% less than non-marginalized individuals. This statistically significant pay gap isn't due to differences in job levels or other employment factors, as we accounted for those in our analyses. This suggests that pay gaps do exist in the movement and that formal and transparent pay structures aren't necessarily enough to prevent or eliminate inequities.</p><p>Closing these pay gaps is crucial to attract, support, and retain advocates from marginalized groups, especially considering how marginalized advocates in this sample tended to be more likely to leave the movement if offered higher pay elsewhere, in addition to more marginalized advocates having left a role in the past due to insufficient pay <ref type="bibr">(Faunalytics, 2020)</ref>. Non-marginalized individuals may be more able to accept low-paying jobs due to facing fewer financial barriers, which is sometimes referred to as the "white advantage"-one study surveyed over 5,000 U.S. nonprofit employees and found that, compared to BIPOC employees, white employees reported more additional sources of income and were less likely to support family members outside of their household (Building Movement Project, 2020). Speculatively, this may be why we found that BIPOC and other marginalized advocates in our sample tended to hold lower-level jobs and be younger than other advocates: they may not be able to stay as long in the face of financial constraints. We therefore recommend that organizations address barriers to career advancement and invest more in developing competitive pay and benefit packages to attract, retain, and improve the experiences of marginalized talent within the workforce.</p><p>Such systematic barriers should be addressed in our movement by following the recommendations set out by the Building Movement Project (2020) and Fund The People (2019). These include acknowledging the "white advantage," developing equitable salary policies that raise the minimum level of pay, recruiting and promoting marginalized staff at higher job levels (e.g., Black women are less likely to be promoted to manager than other women and all men: LeanIn, 2018), and investing more in mentorship and professional development opportunities. It's also important to support marginalized individuals who are promoted so that they can succeed as they're more likely than non-marginalized individuals to be promoted during organizational instability <ref type="bibr">(Cook &amp; Glass, 2013)</ref>. Organizational leadership can also help close pay gaps by monitoring how pay varies by their employees' demographic traits (e.g., by distributing an optional self-identification survey to employees), and addressing any gaps identified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cost Of Turnover</head><p>Employee turnover, though not always a bad thing, can have a devastating impact on the organization as well. One individual can cost an organization 30% to 200% of their salary to replace. Turnover may also increase the workload of other team members as the responsibilities of the vacant position get redistributed, thereby affecting team morale and wellbeing, and further contributing to work-related stress and burnout. Establishing a competitive pay and benefit package is a key way to reduce employee turnover.</p><p>Other strategies include ensuring reasonable workloads, enacting work policies that reduce burnout, and establishing a psychologically safe and meaningful work environment where employees feel like they're supported and are able to make a difference <ref type="bibr">(Faunalytics, 2020)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Caveats &amp; Limitations</head><p>As with all reports, this one has some important caveats and limitations to bear in mind.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Small Sample Size</head><p>First, just 36 organizations completed the compensation spreadsheet, versus the 100 we had hoped for. Consequently, while we are very grateful to those organizations for helping to advance the conversation around compensation equity, there are some factors we were unable to examine fully due to limited data. As an example, while the geographical location of a position likely affects the actual pay for a specific role, we didn't have sufficient data to present results based on location. In the end, we only had enough data to present salary benchmarks for U.S. employees, based on 40 organizations after adding job records from the individual survey and public job boards. We also only had enough data to present salary benchmarks for broad groups of organizations based on job level and revenue.</p><p>In the future, we may consider replicating and updating this study if there's more interest from organizations in participating, as we would like to provide more specific salary benchmarks for job levels, families, organization revenue categories, and contractor positions.</p><p>The low sample size was also a problem for the pay gap analyses, forcing us to present results for combined subgroups (e.g., all BIPOC advocates together, and women, non-binary, and other gender advocates together). As a result, we were unable to draw strong conclusions about how being a member of a unique marginalized group influences pay.</p><p>The difficulties we faced finding participants from marginalized groups-particularly BIPOC and non-binary/other gender advocates-may either suggest that these groups are underrepresented in our movement, or that they couldn't or didn't want to participate in our study.</p><p>Due to the small sample, we were also unable to explore how gender and marginalized identity intersect to affect salary with sufficient statistical power. It's crucial that researchers continue to strive for this type of analysis because people's lived experiences are influenced by the combination of their identities, which can result in unique forms of discrimination and privilege (e.g., pay gaps widen after considering the combination of gender, sexual orientation, and race/ethnicity: National Women's Law Center, 2023).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Response Bias</head><p>Bias is also a concern when response rate is low. Many of the organizations that participated in the study indicated that they have a formal and transparent pay process-which have made them more willing to participate-so the results are likely more reflective of organizations that are already more engaged with ideas of compensation equity.</p><p>Similarly, our individual survey was prone to selection bias as well, with highly-educated advocates being more likely to participate than advocates with other educational levels. Our results are therefore more likely to be representative of privileged advocates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Materials</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method Details</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sampling Method</head><p>Our target population for this study was farmed animal advocacy organizations, which we defined as meeting the following criteria:</p><p>1. The organization has at least one program dedicated to farmed animal advocacy, capacity-building for farmed animal advocacy, and/or plant-based food tech (e.g., this excludes organizations that solely focus on animal care); 2. The organization is a nonprofit (e.g., this excludes for-profit plant-based businesses); 3. The organization is not a government body, academic institution, or an individual advocate; 4. The organization isn't solely a vegetarian or vegan food festival; and 5. The organization's main headquarters are based in the U.S. or the U.K (although we received only enough responses to include U.S. organizations).</p><p>Based on these criteria, we identified 131 organizations. However, due to a low response rate, we invited all groups on our internal list, in addition to recruiting organizations and individual staff from the Farm Animal Strategic Team listserv, the HIVE (formerly Impactful Animal Advocacy) Slack workspace, the EA operations Slack workspace, and the Animal &amp; Vegan Advocacy Summit Whova event application. Because we didn't have enough data outside the U.S., we chose to only add U.S. job records from Animal Advocacy Careers' and Vegan Jobs' job boards, so long as the organization inclusion criteria above were met.</p><p>The individual survey had the same criteria such that participants had to identify that they were employed at such an organization listed above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Collected Compensation Spreadsheet</head><p>For each job position, organizational leadership provided data on the following: employment type (employee vs. contractor), hours worked per week, salary, country of residence, job level, and job family. As part of the spreadsheet, we provided leadership with definitions and examples of job levels and families (see Tables <ref type="table">18</ref> and <ref type="table">19</ref>). If no job level or job family was inputted, then a Human Resource specialist assigned job level or job family categories for missing cases, based on the other available information. Additionally, organizational leadership were asked about whether their organization provided different types of benefits, such as paid time off, remote and flexible work, medical, and more.</p><p>Table 18. Job Level 46 Job Level Group Description Job Level 1</p><p>Executive Director/CEO Most senior position within the organization, answerable to the board. Responsible for leading the overall strategic vision and strategy for the organization and has ultimate responsibility for the organization's operating efficiencies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Executive</head><p>Director/CEO Leadership Senior leader over significant functions and workforce, or over multiple functions. Responsible for strategic direction within their remit and for ensuring operational efficiencies. Has influence and input on overall organizational strategy. Likely has significant responsibility for a specialized area, complex deliverables, or compliance related topics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chief of Function</head><p>Senior leader responsible for a large area or multiple function, who leads other senior leaders. Has an extremely high level of responsibility and accountability and expected to design complex long term and multi-year strategies for their area of responsibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SVP of Function</head><p>Senior leader responsible for a large area or multiple function, who leads other leaders. Has a high level of responsibility and accountability and expected to design complex mid-long term and multi-year strategies for their area of responsibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VP of Function</head><p>Has responsibility for a functional area or multiple functions, with input to strategic direction. Is responsible for operationalizing strategies within their area and leading their team to success. Responsible for collaborating closely with peer leadership team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Head of Function</head><p>Responsible for multiple/functional area and may be leading other members of the leadership team. High level of responsibility and accountability for ensuring the organizational strategy and vision is operationalized by their team. Responsible for making operational and budget decisions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Senior Director of Function</head><p>Responsible for functional area and may be responsible for leading other members of the team to deliver on set organizational strategies. May have input to strategic direction but primarily responsible for operationalizing strategic direction and defining tactical steps for delivery.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Director of Function</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>Senior Manager role which may lead other managers and team members. Experienced in defining tactical steps to deliver organizational decisions and has accountability to deliver on high level goals. May be managing a specific function or sub-function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Senior Manager</head><p>Responsible for delivery of tactical actions set at senior levels in the organization. Likely managers other members of the team. Expected to make decisions but often needs validation on certain decisions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manager</head><p>Entry level management position. Likely does not manage other members of the team. Expected to deliver on tactical directions set at higher levels of the organization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Entry Manager</head><p>Individual Contributor Individual Contributor level position which is usually highly skilled or specialized and expected to deliver on operational activities with little supervision or direction on the activities they are tasked with completing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analyst/ Specialist</head><p>Individual Contributor level position needing minimal supervision on activities they are tasked with completing.</p><p>Senior Coordinator Individual Contributor position needing supervision over activities they are tasked with completing. Coordinator Entry level position requiring high level of supervision over the activities they are tasked with completing. Assistant 1 Job level name doesn't necessarily indicate job title as roles vary by organization. For example, a 'Program Manager' might be categorized as 'Entry Manager' in one organization, but as 'Senior Manager' in another. Organizational leadership had to best match each position to this framework.</p><p>Table 19. Job Family Mapping 48 Job Family Group Job Family Executive Leadership Executive Director/CEO Program, Policy, &amp; External Affairs Program -Campaign Development Policy Development Outreach Corporate &amp; Stakeholder Engagement Legal Representation Fundraising &amp; Grants Fundraising Development &amp; Grant Writing Humane Education Humane Education Volunteer Management Volunteer Recruitment -Management External Communications Communication &amp; Marketing Public Relations &amp; Celebrity Relationships Events Journalism Social Media Website Development Media Assets (Film-Photo) Operations Finance Human Resources Legal, Compliance, &amp; Risk Information Technology Operations -Administrative Facilities Research &amp; Analytics Research &amp; Analytics Investigations Animal Care Animal Care Other Other</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Cleaning Salary Benchmarking Data</head><p>In total, 622 job records were submitted to us by participating organizations (of which 602 included salary data). Due to limited data submitted to us for contractor positions (n = 111) and non-U.S. positions (n = 257), we focused our salary benchmarking analyses on U.S. employee positions.</p><p>As described in the Method section, we followed the Safe Harbor Guidelines to ensure that no organization represented more than 25% of a particular analysis. To do so, we randomly excluded records from an organization when this threshold wasn't met. When an even number of cases needed to be removed from an organization, we removed an equal number of cases from both sides of the organization's median salary. When an odd number of cases needed to be removed, we removed the median case in addition to an equal number of cases from both sides of the median salary. If there was more than one case with the median salary, we picked one of them to remove at random.</p><p>The number of cases removed for any analysis ranged from 1 to 68. To understand the impact of removing these cases on the results, we ran a sensitivity analysis where we compared our original results (25th, 50th, and 75th salary percentiles) with the cases omitted to the sensitivity results with all of the cases included. If there was a discrepancy greater than $5,000 for either the 25th or 75th percentile, then we only presented the original median salary. Also, no results were presented if there was a discrepancy greater than $5,000 for the median itself.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Individual Survey</head><p>For the individual survey, two participants were removed from the dataset for completing the survey in less than one third of the median time (to avoid low data quality respondents) and three participants were removed as they worked for for-profit or academic institutions.</p><p>Because we included records from the individual survey in our salary benchmarking analyses, we used Guidestar to input organization revenue for these records as we didn't ask about organization revenue in the individual survey. For one of these organizations, revenue was confidentially shared with us.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 8. Distribution Of Individual Job Levels</head><p>Note: This is based on 318 records submitted to us by participating organizations as job level data was unavailable for individual survey records and job board records.</p><p>We also looked at the distribution of positions in our sample by job family (see Table <ref type="table">19</ref> above for job family descriptions). Positions are distributed across job families (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">9</ref>   Note: This is based on 318 records submitted to us by participating organizations and 39 job board records as job family data was unavailable for individual survey records. Additionally, the figure below shows the distribution of the four job level groups across the different job families in our sample. For job level, leadership includes Director-and VP-level roles, management includes Entry through Senior Managers, and individual contributor includes Assistant through Specialist roles.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>For</head><figDesc>employers who want to better understand the financial cost of turnover, you can use our calculator and fill out any cells that are relevant to your organization. Based on the Program Evaluation and Review Technique (PERT), this calculator is meant to help employers roughly estimate the total cost of turnover for a particular position, including the costs spent in hiring and training a replacement, and the loss of productivity during the position's vacancy. PERT calculates an expected time for each activity outlined by taking the average of 'optimistic time' (the minimum time required for completion), 'pessimistic time' (the maximum time required), and 'most likely time' (the best estimate under normal conditions). Each organization and position will have a unique cost of turnover profile.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>below), with the most frequent being program, policy, &amp; external affairs (24%) and operations (21%).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Distribution Of Job Family</figDesc><graphic coords="53,144.38,116.48,323.25,270.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="21,130.88,123.59,350.25,293.82" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="22,129.00,120.56,354.00,295.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="34,73.50,127.65,468.00,330.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="35,73.50,127.65,468.00,330.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="37,73.50,127.65,468.00,330.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="39,73.50,127.65,468.00,330.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="40,73.50,127.65,468.00,330.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Percentages don't add to 100% because participants could choose more than one option.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Leadership includes Director-and VP-level roles; Management includes Entry through Senior Managers; Individual Contributor includes Assistant through Specialist roles. Full details in Table18of the Supplementary Materials.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Sensitivity analyses revealed that the 25th percentile was unreliable.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Sensitivity analyses revealed that the 25th and/or 75th percentile(s) were unreliable.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Leadership includes Director-and VP-level roles; Management includes Entry through Senior Managers; Individual Contributor includes Assistant through Specialist roles. Full details in Table 18 of the Supplementary Materials.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_5"><p>No results are shown for the research and analytics job family as sensitivity analyses revealed that both the 50th and 75th percentiles were unreliable. Further, there were not enough records to display results for humane education and volunteer management.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_6"><p>U.K and other countries were pooled for the chi-square test of independence.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We would like to thank <rs type="person">Jay Barrett</rs> (<rs type="affiliation">Culture Canopy</rs>) and <rs type="person">Richard Gathercole</rs> (Reward Guru) for providing pro-bono support, including support with analyzing the pay and benefit data and advising on the research design, analyses, and reporting. We would also like to thank <rs type="person">Brooke Haggerty</rs> and several advocates who provided valuable input about this research throughout the process. Lastly, we would like to thank our funders for their generous support of this research.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Salaries By Organization Revenue</head><p>The following tables show U.S. salaries by job level groups at farmed animal advocacy organizations with revenues below (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) or above (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>) $1 million.</p><p>Based on descriptive trends, organizations with a revenue below $1 million tend to pay less than organizations with a revenue above $1 million. For example, the median salary across all staff is $68,350 at an organization with a revenue below $1 million compared to $84,000 at an organization with a revenue above $1 million. Interestingly, while we found that pay was higher at each progressive job level for organizations with a revenue above $1 million in this sample, median salaries at organizations with revenues under $1 million were much flatter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis Details</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Full-Time Equivalent Salary (FTE)</head><p>Across all datasets, we recoded raw salary values into Full-Time Equivalent (FTE), which is standard to allow comparison of salaries across individuals who work different numbers of hours.</p><p>In the organization spreadsheet, FTE was calculated using the following formula: FTE salary = annual salary/hours worked per week X standard organization weekly full-time hours</p><p>For example, if someone with an annual salary of $25,000 worked 15 hours per week at an organization where full-time employees work 40 hours, their FTE salary would be approximately $66,700 (25,000/15*40).</p><p>In the individual survey, work hours were presented in ranges, so we adjusted the above formula to use the midpoint of the range selected. The midpoint is 10 hours for participants who selected 1-19 hours, 24.5 hours for 20-29 hours, and 34.5 hours for 30-39 hours. For participants who selected 40+ hours, we used 40 hours. In cases where the organization's standard hours were not known, we assumed 40 hours per week.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pay Equity Regression Models</head><p>To examine pay gaps between marginalized and non-marginalized participants, we first explored the unadjusted pay gap by running separate linear regression models for each of these identities (BIPOC, disability, gender, and LGBTQ2IA+) and the pooled marginalized identity. For these models and the ones below, the outcome variable was FTE salary and organization ID was included as a random effect to account for shared variance between participants from the same organization. We used two-tailed p values and didn't correct for multiple testing, as these models were exploratory.</p><p>We then followed a manual stepwise model procedure to investigate pay gaps for these five groups adjusted for other factors that influence pay. In the first step, we ran a model with all possible influential extraneous variables, without any group membership variables. Predictors were employment type, job level, job group (participants were recoded as having "dual roles" if they selected more than one job group for this analysis), education, country of residence, age, organizational revenue, and years of experience (in the movement, in the organization, and in the current job role). All of these except for revenue were weighted effect-coded as they were treated as categorical, while the demographic group variables (e.g., BIPOC) were dummy-coded to facilitate group comparison. We used two-tailed p values and applied Benjamini-Hochberg post hoc corrections to the p-values to correct for FDR. We excluded extraneous variables from further analyses if they didn't significantly predict salary after FDR correction, which left just job level, country, age, and years in one's role.</p><p>Each of the final models therefore included these four covariates and a group of interest (with separate models for marginalized, BIPOC, disability, gender, and LGBTQ2IA+ identities). P values were again corrected for FDR with Benjamini-Hochberg post hoc corrections and they were one-tailed due to directional hypotheses.</p><p>Once the final multivariable models were built, we looked for influential observations. Salary analyses are susceptible to influential observations because factors like organization, job level, and location can produce major differences in salary. As such, very high or low earners could disproportionately impact the results. To avoid this, we removed influential cases from each model that had both a Cook's distance value greater than 4/n (where n is the number of observations) and a leverage value greater than 2*P/n (where P is the number of model parameters and n is the number of observations). A high leverage point is an observation with a value of an independent variable that is far from the mean, while an observation with a high Cook's distance is one that has a large influence on the estimates of the independent variables.</p><p>The sample sizes for these regression models are lower than our entire final sample (n = 244) due to missing data for some predictor variables and the removal of influential observations. The model for marginalized group included 211 participants, the model for BIPOC included 221 participants, the model for gender included 225 participants, and the models for LGBTQ2IA+ and disability included 216 participants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>U.S. Job Role Distributions</head><p>Organizational leadership may find it useful to understand the types of job levels and families that we sampled and how it compares to those within their organization. Based on all available U.S. job records (n = 366), 6% of farmed animal advocacy positions in our sample are executive director, 34% are leadership, 27% are management, and 34% are individual contributors. The graph below shows the distribution of positions by individual job levels (see Table <ref type="table">18</ref> above for job level descriptions).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 10. Distribution Of Job Levels Within Job Family</head><p>Note: This is based on 318 records submitted to us by participating organizations and 39 job board records as job family data was unavailable for individual survey records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional Exploratory Analyses</head><p>Pay By EA Funding</p><p>We explored whether an organization being EA-funded or not predicted FTE salary. Presence or absence of EA funding at the organization level was the only predictor variable (therefore excluding organizations that had responded "unsure" about their organization being EA funded) and organization ID was a random effect to account for multiple participants from the same organization.</p><p>Using the salary data provided by organizations, we were able to run this analysis on 475 records across 32 organizations, with 224 respondents working at an EA-funded organization versus 251 respondents working at a non-EA-funded organization.</p><p>Those working at an EA-funded organization made approximately $65,200 on average compared to $63,400 to those working at a non-EA-funded organization. This difference was not statistically significant (p = 0.86) meaning that organizations that received EA funding don't pay significantly higher salaries than organizations that don't receive EA funding. However, it's possible that we would have found salary differences across organizations if we had asked leadership about the amount of EA funding received versus just simply asking them if their organization currently received EA funding.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
