<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Green Supply Chain Management in Research Trend: Bibliometric Analysis Study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ari</forename><surname>Dyah</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Industrial Engineering Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Sarjanawiyata Tamansiswa</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Susanti</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Industrial Engineering Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Sarjanawiyata Tamansiswa</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bimo</forename><forename type="middle">Sunarfri</forename><surname>Hantono</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Electrical Engineering and Information Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Gadjah Mada</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Atik</forename><surname>Febriani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Industrial Engineering Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Institut Teknologi Telkom Purwokerto</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nada</forename><forename type="middle">Iman</forename><surname>Muvidah</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Industrial Engineering Program</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitas Sarjanawiyata Tamansiswa</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ID">Indonesia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Green Supply Chain Management in Research Trend: Bibliometric Analysis Study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">812405DCDAFCBFB4A55C8B39BB93848F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>green supply chain management</term>
					<term>bibliometric</term>
					<term>reserch trend)</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Impact on the environment has become an essential obligation for every company, both in products and services. Inter-supply chain management has transformed in responding to the need to pay attention to environmental impacts into environmental management in line with sustainable development goals (SDGs) called green supply chain management (Green SCM). Green SCM has been widely applied to large industries, but it is still a new thing for small and medium industries and lacks information about the concept and its application. This study explores the published Green SCM indexed in the Scopus database. We conducted a bibliometric analysis of 1,776 Scopus indexed documents from the first year of 1996 to determine the progress of GSCM research. Research trends and keywords that are still relevant and emerging have been explored and explained. Research gaps that require follow-up have been identified, and future research directions have also been discussed.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The supply chain generally collaborates to meet market demand by coordinating from the upstream industry to the downstream industry. Industries coordinate work from raw materials to products to consumers. The purpose of supply chain coordination is to increase supply chain efficiency with organizational effectiveness by distributing products and services to consumers at low costs and as soon as possible <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. In general, supply chain management tends to focus on costs and regulation of finished products. Still, it barely addresses the environmental impact, giving rise to the concept of sustainability called green supply chain management (GSCM). The GSCM concept aims to integrate environmental issues into supply chain management which refers to efforts to deal with the environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>The role of Supply Chain in the product and service industry cannot be separated from the impact on the environment, so competition has succeeded in overcoming environmental problems. The emphasis on industrial sustainability concerning the environment is mainly carried out by developing strategies to reduce the environmental impact of products and services. There are many publications published on green supply chain management, both literature reviews and research results in the field, but this green supply chain is growing <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The relevance of previous research with current research continues to grow, so new research is needed to update research related to bibliometric analysis. The bibliometric analysis demonstrates the evolution of influential and contributing articles in the field by further mapping the relationships among higher impact but unfinished analytical and objective works <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p><p>Bibliometric analysis of Green Supply Chain Management has been carried out by Fahimnia et al. (2015) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Mishra et al. (2017)</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Maditati et al. (2018)</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, (de Oliveira et al. (2018) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, Balon (2020) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, Carvalho et al. (2020) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, dan Choudhary &amp; Sangwan (2022) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> but have not analyzed the thesaurus keyword approach to remove the duplication of meaning or meaning of keywords that refer to the same concept <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. In this study, the thesaurus is used for processing using VOSviewer.</p><p>The research question is what keywords are still emerging and relevant to research now and in the future. This study aims to identify keywords expected to be used to explore future Green Supply Chain Management research. Although many bibliometric analysis studies have been carried out by combining literature reviews, there has not been much emphasis on the thesaurus, even though this thesaurus is essential to minimize errors in identified keywords when using VOSviewer software.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">METHODS</head><p>This study uses bibliometric citation and content analysis techniques to analyze the GSCM literature from relevant keywords established and eligible for future research on major GSCM topics. The research methodology has been adopted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Maditati et al. (2018)</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Still, the database used was sourced from the Scopus database on April 4, 2022, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The search term used was 'green supply chain management' in the article title, abstract, and keywords within a time frame of 1996 to 2022. Finally, 1,776 documents have been retrieved from 1,851 documents after filtration. The VOSviewer application is used to build a cooccurrence keyword network map <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Descriptive Analysis</head><p>In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, China has the highest publication of documents related to the topic of Green Supply Chain Management, followed by India, the US, the UK, and Malaysia in the top 5. The number of publications in China is almost double the number in India, three times in the US, four times in the UK, and Malaysia, which means much research has been carried out in China to other countries. Publications in China can be considered more experienced and can then be used as a reference for future research references. The subject area of publication in table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> shows that GSCM is mainly in the category of Business, Management and Accounting, followed by the field of Engineering and the field of Environmental Science. GSCM emphasizes a lot of environmental impacts, but Environmental Science is not the main publication area. It shows that research publications on GSCM are mainly in the field of management itself, followed by the field of Engineering. Journal of Cleaner Production as a publishing institution has the highest number of publications whose value is almost two times the second largest in Sustainability Switzerland, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>. The number of publications based on publishing institutions is not limited to journals; all publishing institutions are identified as publishing institutions about GSCM. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bibliometric Analysis</head><p>Bibliometrics is a method of statistical analysis of published articles and their citations to measure their impact <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> in the field of research based on author and institutional characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Using thesaurus in bibliometric analysis using VOSviewer aims to combine keywords with the same general meaning as the representing keywords so that keywords with the same meaning do not appear separately and are recognized as other keywords. This step is to minimize the repetition of keywords that have the same meaning but appear and are recognized as other keywords so that they have an impact on their occurrence. Analysis using VOSviewer from 6149 keywords to 692 keywords.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Keywords Analysis</head><p>The results of the network map of the relationship between keywords from VOSviewer can be seen in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> produces six large clusters of keywords: environmental management (32 keywords), green supply chain (30 keywords), and decision-making (22 keywords). ), management practices (28 keywords), performance measurement (16 keywords), and aspects (3 keywords). Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the research keywords based on the year of publication from dark to light, meaning that the more muted the color is, the more up-to-date the keywords in the study are.   This quadrant shows research keywords that are still relevant and are still widely used in current research, and can be used as references for future research topics. Keywords in the core quadrant consist of 6 clusters, cluster 1 (competitive advantage, developing countries, environmental performance, green manufacturing, green purchasing, green supply chain management practices, managers, operational performance, organizational performance, performance appraisal, structural equation modeling, surveys ), cluster 2 (carbon, carbon emissions, costs), cluster 3 (barriers, drivers, green economy, people, performance, small and medium enterprises), cluster 4 (hierarchical analysis processes, decision making, decision-making trials, and evaluation laboratories, fuzzy sets, green supplier selection, multi-criteria decision making, techniques for order preference based on similarities with ideal solutions), cluster 5 (conceptual framework, construction industry, human resource management, literature review, sustainable supply chain, sustainable supply chain management), and cluster 6 (corporate social responsibility). Relevant research keyword sequences were carried out for future all quadrants on the novel publication diagram (figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>). However, the number 5 is relevant for future research only in the mature quadrant, while the other quadrants are starting to be abandoned due to decreased centrality and density.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">CONCLUSION</head><p>This research results in keyword grouping based on total link strength, density/centrality, and novelty. Each cluster is part of an enhanced strategy diagram quadrant. However, this study has limited analysis that has not been carried out and can be a suggestion for further research. The analysis is about keyword clustering in VOSviewer to find research insights. The data in this study is also only sourced from the Scopus Database, so there is an opportunity to add other database sources and enrich research subject references in bibliometric analysis.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Methodology research</figDesc><graphic coords="2,125.15,278.43,344.30,261.79" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Network visualization of GSCM studied based on keywords co-occurrence analysis</figDesc><graphic coords="4,115.32,285.23,364.65,273.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .Figure 4 .Figure 5 .</head><label>345</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Temporal overlay on keywords GSCM co-occurrence map</figDesc><graphic coords="5,130.02,81.35,335.19,221.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,54.70,81.35,485.90,367.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Number of documents in gscm (1996-2022)</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Country</cell><cell>n documents</cell><cell>Country</cell><cell>n documents</cell><cell>Country</cell><cell>n documents</cell></row><row><cell>China</cell><cell>434</cell><cell>Australia</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>United Arab Emirates</cell><cell>29</cell></row><row><cell>India</cell><cell>276</cell><cell>Italy</cell><cell>47</cell><cell>Viet Nam</cell><cell>22</cell></row><row><cell>United States</cell><cell>191</cell><cell>South Korea</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>Saudi Arabia</cell><cell>20</cell></row><row><cell>United Kingdom</cell><cell>126</cell><cell>Turkey</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>Spain</cell><cell>20</cell></row><row><cell>Malaysia</cell><cell>125</cell><cell>Pakistan</cell><cell>41</cell><cell>Jordan</cell><cell>19</cell></row><row><cell>Taiwan</cell><cell>117</cell><cell>Denmark</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>Greece</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>Iran</cell><cell>91</cell><cell>France</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>Morocco</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>Indonesia</cell><cell>83</cell><cell>Canada</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>Poland</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>Brazil</cell><cell>74</cell><cell>Germany</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>South Africa</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>Thailand</cell><cell>56</cell><cell>Hong Kong</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>Bangladesh</cell><cell>17</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . Number of subject area document in gscm (1996-2022)</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Subject Area</cell><cell>n documents</cell><cell>Subject Area</cell><cell>n documents</cell></row><row><cell>Business, Management and</cell><cell>922</cell><cell>Agricultural and Biological Sciences</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell>Accounting</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Engineering</cell><cell>752</cell><cell>Earth and Planetary Sciences</cell><cell>28</cell></row><row><cell>Environmental Science</cell><cell>438</cell><cell>Physics and Astronomy</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>Decision Sciences</cell><cell>434</cell><cell>Multidisciplinary</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>Computer Science</cell><cell>420</cell><cell>Arts and Humanities</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>Social Sciences</cell><cell>255</cell><cell>Biochemistry, Genetics and</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Molecular Biology</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Energy</cell><cell>243</cell><cell>Chemistry</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>Economics, Econometrics</cell><cell>171</cell><cell>Psychology</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>and Finance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mathematics</cell><cell>126</cell><cell>Pharmacology, Toxicology and</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Pharmaceutics</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Materials Science</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>Health Professions</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Chemical Engineering</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>Neuroscience</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Medicine</cell><cell>35</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 . Top 10 of publication source title in gscm (1996-2022)</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Journals</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Green and low carbon matters: A systematic review of the past, today, and future on sustainability supply chain management practices among manufacturing industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Moshood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nawanir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mahmud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sorooshian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Adeleke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.clet.2021.100144</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clean. Eng. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">June, p. 100144, 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Green supply chain management A Review International Research Journal of Shri Param Hans Education &amp; Research Foundation Trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rastogi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aggarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-05">May, 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Green supply chain management pressures, practices and performance: a critical literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Choudhary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sangwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/BIJ-05-2021-0242</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Benchmarking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1393" to="1428" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Green supply chain management: A review and bibliometric analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fahimnia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sarkis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Davarzani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijpe.2015.01.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Prod. Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">162</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Green supply chain performance measures: A review and bibliometric analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mishra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gunasekaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Papadopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hazen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.spc.2017.01.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sustain. Prod. Consum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-02">February. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of green supply chain management: From bibliometric analysis to a conceptual framework and future research directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Maditati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Munim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schramm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kummer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.resconrec.2018.08.004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Resour. Conserv. Recycl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-12">December 2017. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic literature review on green supply chain management: Research implications and future perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>De Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Espindola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rocha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jclepro.2018.03.083</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clean. Prod</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">187</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="561" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Green supply chain management: Pressures, practices, and performance-An integrative literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Balon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/bsd2.91</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bus. Strateg. Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="244" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Green supply chain management and innovation: a modern review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>De Carvalho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Stefanelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Viana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Vasconcelos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/MEQ-12-2019-0283</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manag. Environ. Qual. An Int. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="470" to="482" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plastic waste recycling via pyrolysis: A bibliometric survey and literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Armenise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jaap.2021.105265</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Anal. Appl. Pyrolysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2021</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thematic analysis of multiple sclerosis research by enhanced strategic diagram</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shafin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/13524585221075542</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mult. Scler. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Profiling the Research Landscape on Cognitive Aging: A Bibliometric Analysis and Network Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Othman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fnagi.2022.876159</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
