<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Beyond rational choice: A typology of urban discovery</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bre%</forename><surname>Binst</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">imec-SMIT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lien</forename><surname>Michiels</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">imec-SMIT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Annelien</forename><surname>Smets</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">imec-SMIT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vrije Universiteit Brussel</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Beyond rational choice: A typology of urban discovery</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">631F7373ED5D0E936688A92C374567BD</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted for publication in Tourism Management.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-19T16:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Urban Discovery</term>
					<term>Ra9onal Choice</term>
					<term>Hospitality</term>
					<term>Consumer Behavior</term>
					<term>Informa9on Behavior</term>
					<term>User Generated Content</term>
					<term>Peer-review pla3orms</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>As the internet, smartphones, and review pla3orms transform how travelers discover urban a8rac9ons, understanding this process is cri9cal for harnessing a sustainable urban a8rac9on space.</p><p>Yet urban discovery remains poorly understood and exis9ng research is fragmented. To address this gap, we adapt Leiper's tourist a8rac9on systems framework to study urban discovery. Our grounded theory analysis on 126 interviews resulted in five dis9nct discovery modes: instrumental-ra9onal, gowith-the-flow, social, flaneur, and habitual. Besides richly describing these modes, we iden9fy personal, social, contextual, demographic, and affec9ve factors influencing them. We illustrate how playful discovery modes-go-with-the-flow, social, and flaneur-are compa9ble, leading to mixed discovery modes, while the remaining modes are incompa9ble. These findings challenge the dominance of ra9onal choice models by revealing a broader spectrum of discovery behaviors. They also provide a founda9on for designing a more inclusive urban a8rac9on content space and offer strategic implica9ons for urban a8rac9on management.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduc4on</head><p>The tourism and hospitality landscape has been transformed by digitaliza9on. Just two decades ago, travelers in Europe seldom used the internet for trip planning <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Gursoy &amp; McCleary, 2004)</ref>. In stark contrast, recent studies find that today's travelers rely almost exclusively on digital tools <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Gursoy et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">H. Kim et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Xiang et al., 2015)</ref>. The primary source of informa9on has shieed from guidebooks and flyers to pla3orms like TripAdvisor and Google, fundamentally changing how travel content is created and consumed <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(Navío-Marco et al., 2018)</ref>. These pla3orms centralize user-generated content, such as reviews and ra9ngs, revolu9onizing how consumers discover hotels, restaurants, and a8rac9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Buhalis &amp; Law, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. As powerful actors, they direct tourist a8en9on, shape expecta9ons, and ul9mately influence choices <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">(Sparks et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b104">Xiang &amp; Gretzel, 2010)</ref>. This power compels managers to adopt new strategies, from craeing "Instagrammable" décor to offering incen9ves for five-star reviews <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Gössling et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr">So9riadis, 2017)</ref>. Despite this profound transforma9on, significant gaps remain in our understanding. Li8le is known about how this new digital environment has reshaped the process of urban discovery, nor what cons9tutes effec9ve marke9ng strategy within it <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Hollebeek &amp; Macky, 2019)</ref>. This study addresses these ques9ons by focusing on urban a8rac9ons-defined here as shops, hospitality venues, and other city-based ac9vi9es. We focus on these sites because they are central to urban life, shaping decisions to visit or reside in a city while also determining the socio-economic outcomes for local communi9es. Furthermore, the city provides an interes9ng context to study the discovery of a8rac9ons because they suffer choice overload <ref type="bibr">(Ashworth &amp; Page, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Edwards et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Page &amp; Duignan, 2023)</ref>.</p><p>To study urban discovery, we build on <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Leiper's (1990)</ref> conceptual framework about tourist a8rac9on systems. <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Leiper (1990)</ref> theorized that an a8rac9on is not merely a physical "nucleus" (such as a restaurant or museum) but instead arises from the connec9on of three elements: a person with leisure needs (the tourist), the nucleus itself, and a marker that links the two.</p><p>In our study, we refer to Leiper's "marker" as "content," as this term be8er reflects its modern func9on. A marker would merely mark the loca9on of an a8rac9on, while content about the a8rac9on can serve many more func9ons. For example, online ra9ngs and reviews can reassure people of an a8rac9on's quality, while a magazine ar9cle can provide the context needed to understand it.</p><p>We further adapt Leiper's framework by not focusing exclusively on tourists. As Leiper himself noted <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Leiper, 1979</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Leiper, , 1997</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Leiper, , 2008;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Page &amp; Duignan, 2023)</ref>, many a8rac9ons also depend on other customers, a point especially true in urban setngs <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Leiper et al., 2008)</ref>. Because our research examines how digitaliza9on impacts discovery across the en9re urban ecosystem, our study focuses on the discovery behaviors of people in general.</p><p>Our conceptual framework is illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. We define "urban discovery" as a process that begins with informa9on behavior about urban a8rac9ons not yet visited, extends into decision-making about visi9ng an urban a8rac9on, and ripples into the experience of visi9ng that urban a8rac9on. The discoverer in our framework is similar to what Leiper calls the person with touris9c needs <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Leiper, 1990)</ref>.</p><p>A key adapta9on of Leiper's work is our focus on collec9ve spaces rather than individual elements. We term the complete set of a city's a8rac9ons the "urban a8rac9on space." People frequently discover these a8rac9ons through the "urban a8rac9on content space"-the full body of digital and physical informa9on available about them. This divergence is necessary because, since Leiper's 9me, digital content marke9ng has dras9cally changed the way consumers discover urban a8rac9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Hollebeek &amp; Macky, 2019)</ref>. The emergence of pla3orms centralizing content about the urban a8rac9ons in an urban a8rac9on ecosystem opens the vast number of op9ons to customers. Therefore, instead of looking at individual markers and a8rac9ons, as in Leiper's original framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Leiper, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Leiper, , 1997))</ref>, we adapt his framework to focus on the spaces cons9tu9ng the urban ecosystem, namely the urban a8rac9on space and its content space. This perspec9ve gives us a broader view on informa9on and discovery behavior, uncovering discovery pa8erns that would otherwise remain hidden.</p><p>Like <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Richards (2002)</ref> points out, Leiper's framework holds untapped poten9al for studying and explaining discovery pa8erns through variables like familiarity, distance traveled, length of stay, and cultural capital. Our adapted model allows for different expressions of urban discovery, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. For instance, a person might learn of a new museum from a local broadcaster (a 'genera9ng marker' in Leiper's terms) and decide to visit. In contrast, another person might stumble upon a charming bar and impulsively decide to have a drink (prompted by a 'con9guous marker').</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> Conceptual framework of urban discovery within an urban a8rac9on ecosystem.</p><p>Note. Two examples of urban discovery in our conceptual framework. This framework is inspired on <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Leiper, 1990)</ref>.</p><p>As previously stated, to navigate the abundance of urban a8rac9ons, people increasingly rely on digital pla3orms <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Gursoy et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">H. Kim et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Xiang et al., 2015)</ref>. However, we know li8le about how these pla3orms impact the process of discovering urban a8rac9ons, or what cons9tute good prac9ces for digital content marke9ng <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Hollebeek &amp; Macky, 2019)</ref>. What is known is that the rise of these pla3orms presents both promises and perils for the urban a8rac9on ecosystem.</p><p>First is the paradox of online reviews. In theory, user-generated content should bridge the knowledge gap between consumers and providers, helping travelers make be8er decisions and avoid "tourist traps"-establishments that seem authen9c but offer poor quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(Polus et al., 2025)</ref>. In prac9ce, however, research suggests that online reviews can strengthen the tourist trap phenomenon <ref type="bibr">(Ganzaroli, De Noni, &amp; Van Baalen, 2017)</ref>. Furthermore, while reviews may sa9sfy a desire for certainty, they can also frustrate the search for authen9city, serendipity, and new experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">(Ritzer, 2019)</ref>.</p><p>Second, the applica9on of recommender systems on these pla3orms helps consumers in discovering urban a8rac9ons they are likely to appreciate <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Massimo &amp; Ricci, 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Rabanser &amp; Ricci, 2005)</ref>. However, these recommender systems have also been associated with crea9ng overtourism <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Merinov, 2024)</ref>. For example, there is evidence for hotspots of restaurants in Belgian ci9es on TripAdvisor, suppor9ng the hypothesis that tourism a8racts tourism <ref type="bibr" target="#b94">(Van Der Zee et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b93">Van der Zee &amp; Bertocchi, 2018)</ref>. Another danger of recommender systems in the urban a8rac9on ecosystem is the crea9on of urban filter bubbles, i.e., people are, because of algorithmic personaliza9on, only exposed to a specific part of the city that differs from what others, with a different user profile, are exposed to <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">(Smets et al., 2019)</ref>.</p><p>In summary, ra9ngs, reviews, and personalized recommenda9ons are associated with problems in the urban a8rac9on ecosystem such as overtourism, urban filter bubbles, and reinforcing tourist traps. Understanding how people discover urban a8rac9ons is a vital first step in addressing these issues.</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, no prior work has developed a theore9cal framework that explains how urban a8rac9ons are discovered. Most exis9ng studies focus on des9na9on decisionmaking <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Moore et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>, which represents a different level of analysis with dis9nct characteris9cs. Des9na9on decisions typically involve higher costs and less immersion and are oeen made before the trip begins. In contrast, urban discovery unfolds within the city itself, allowing travelers to stumble upon a8rac9ons spontaneously and serendipitously. While des9na9onfocused theories offer valuable insights, they do not fully capture the dynamics of on-the-ground discovery. Other research concentrates on visitor a8rac9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Leask, 2016)</ref>, using a narrower defini9on centered on man-made or natural sites designed to entertain or educate-such as monuments like the Sagrada Familia or landmarks like the Grand Canyon. Our approach adopts a broader perspec9ve, since we also focus on shops, ac9vi9es, bars, and restaurants. Neither lens fully captures the dynamics of urban discovery.</p><p>To address this gap, we conducted a grounded theory study involving 126 semi-structured interviews, an approach well-suited for developing nuanced, process-oriented theories in tourism and hospitality research <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Decrop &amp; Snelders, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Moore et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Woodside et al., 2004)</ref>. Our analysis resulted in a typology of five dis9nct discovery modes: instrumental-ra9onal, go-with-theflow, social, flaneur, and habitual. In addi9on to describing each mode in depth, we link these discovery modes to their predictors, and to each other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Related literature</head><p>In the context of grounded theory, sensi9zing concepts, i.e., concepts that guide the researcher in their study <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Bowen, 2006)</ref>, serve as a bridge between prior research and the new theore9cal framework being developed. These concepts help direct the ini9al stages of the grounded theory process by offering a lens through which relevant pa8erns and themes can be iden9fied <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Bowen, 2006)</ref>. In this sec9on, we intend to discuss the concepts and models that have sensi9zed our grounded theory analysis.</p><p>In this study, we conceptualize urban discovery as a process that begins with informa9on behavior about urban a8rac9ons not yet visited, that extends into decision-making on visi9ng an urban a8rac9on, and that ripples into the experience of urban a8rac9ons. Given this conceptualiza9on, we structure our review of the related literature into three key areas: (2.1.) decision-making models, which examines the cogni9ve and behavioral mechanisms involved in choosing to visit an a8rac9on; (2.2.) informa9on behavior, which explores how individuals seek and process informa9on about urban a8rac9ons; and (2.3.) factors that influence informa9on behavior and decision-making.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Decision-making in tourism and hospitality</head><p>Decision-making within the context of tourism and hospitality refers to the process by which individuals determine whether to visit a par9cular loca9on or engage with a specific a8rac9on.</p><p>Research on this subject has predominantly employed two analy9cal approaches: the varianceanalysis approach and the process approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1.">Variance analysis vs process approach</head><p>The variance-analysis approach has been the most commonly used framework in studies of tourism and hospitality decision-making <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cohen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>. In this framework, the varia9on in outcomes-such as the decision to visit a par9cular des9na9on-is explained by a set of theore9cally significant inputs that are primarily chosen by researchers <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cohen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">McCabe et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>. Methodologically, this approach is oeen paired with sta9s9cal techniques, including Structural Equa9on Modeling (SEM) and regression analyses, which serve to validate the rela9onships between the selected variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>. While the variance-analysis approach is effec9ve in iden9fying the key variables that influence decision-making, it has been cri9qued for providing only a superficial account of the processes involved and failing to elucidate how and why these decisions unfold <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Decrop, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>In contrast, the process approach aims to capture the narra9ve of how a decision unfolds over 9me and in a specific context <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>, for example on-site tourist decisionmaking <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Moore et al., 2012)</ref>. It focuses on the socio-psychological processes involved in decisionmaking, including factors such as mo9va9on, mood, and individual decision-making style <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Decrop &amp; Snelders, 2005)</ref>. Several prominent scholars have argued that research should complement the variance-analysis approach with studies adop9ng a process perspec9ve since this perspec9ve focuses on how individuals in prac9ce make decisions, which is a complicated process <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cohen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Decrop, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>. The process perspec9ve recognizes this complexity, and therefore should lead to more accurate theories of decision-making <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Decrop, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>. Although this perspec9ve remains rare in the tourism and hospitality field, some previous studies have illustrated its poten9al for genera9ng insigh3ul and comprehensive theories of decision-making in specific contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Decrop &amp; Snelders, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Dunne et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Moore et al., 2012)</ref>.</p><p>Oeen, the process approach is combined with grounded theory, a methodological paradigm that allows researchers to explore nuanced and richly detailed theories of the phenomenon studied <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Decrop &amp; Snelders, 2005</ref>; Y. G. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Kim et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Moore et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Woodside et al., 2004)</ref>. Although its strength lies in untangling the complex interplay of factors that shape the decision-making process in a specific context, the process approach is frequently cri9cized for its limited generalizability to other contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b101">(Woodside et al., 2004)</ref>. In this work, we adopt a process approach, as our goal is to explore how urban discovery unfolds across various contexts and among diverse individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2.">Theore1cal Paradigms</head><p>In addi9on to these methodological approaches, several theore9cal paradigms have been used to understand decision-making in hospitality and tourism. Here, we discuss three of the most influen9al theories.</p><p>Ra9onal choice theory assumes that individuals make decisions that maximize their u9lity <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Decrop, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010</ref>). An example is the theory of planned behavior applied to the tourism and hospitality context <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">(Sirakaya &amp; Woodside, 2005)</ref>, which posits that tourists' decisions are determined by their attudes toward a des9na9on, the influence of subjec9ve norms as reflected by their social network's percep9ons, and their perceived behavioral control, such as financial capacity to travel <ref type="bibr">(Ulker-Demirel &amp; Cieci, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b112">Yuzhanin &amp; Fisher, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Choice set theories conceptualize decision-making as a funneling process whereby individuals move from a total set of op9ons to an awareness set, then a considera9on set, and ul9mately to a final choice <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">(Sirakaya &amp; Woodside, 2005)</ref>. Both ra9onal choice and choice set theories assume a ra9onal actor model <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">(Sirakaya &amp; Woodside, 2005)</ref>; however, cri9cs argue that these models describe how tourists should act according to micro-economic theory, which may not accurately reflect how tourists-in reality-act <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Decrop, 2014)</ref>. Consistent with their theore9cal underpinnings, these ra9onal actor models are most frequently examined using the variance-analysis approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ulker-Demirel &amp; Cieci, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Other paradigms challenge the assump9on of complete ra9onality. The concept of bounded ra9onality, for instance, acknowledges that prac9cal constraints-such as limited 9me and choice overload-oeen lead individuals to se8le for sa9sfactory rather than op9mal outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010</ref>). An example is the dual-system theory of tourism decision-making, in which variables like level of involvement and cogni9ve overload predict complex or heuris9c-based decision-making <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(McCabe et al., 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Lastly, naturalis9c theories offer an alterna9ve perspec9ve by deconstruc9ng real-world decision-making through detailed analyses of discourse, narra9ve, or observa9onal data <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Decrop, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>. Conversely to the theore9cal perspec9ves discussed above, naturalis9c theories are not grand, all encompassing, theories; they are delimited by a specific setng <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Gore et al., 2006)</ref>, for example, city break travel <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Dunne et al., 2011)</ref> or on-site decisionmaking <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Moore et al., 2012)</ref>. These theories are oeen combined with a process-approach. We will adopt this theore9cal framework in order to get a rich understanding of the process of discovering urban a8rac9ons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Informa;on behavior</head><p>Although informa9on behavior is oeen considered part of the decision-making process <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Buhalis &amp; Law, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">McCabe et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Sirakaya &amp; Woodside, 2005)</ref>, this perspec9ve assumes a func9onal informa9on need-one that individuals seek to fulfill through informa9on behavior. However, informa9on behavior is not always goal-driven. It can also be mo9vated by the pleasure of, for example, dreaming about vaca9ons, without necessarily leading to a decision <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Decrop &amp; Snelders, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. In many cases, travelers actually prefer serendipitous experiences, where they encounter informa9on about an interes9ng urban a8rac9on by accident, resul9ng in an impulsive decision to visit it <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Huang et al., 2014)</ref>. Thus, research on informa9on behavior offers a different lens on decision-making. In this sec9on, we discuss the informa9on behavior concepts and models that have shaped our grounded theory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.3.">The discovery process</head><p>One of the most dominant perspec9ves on informa9on behavior is the linear perspec9ve which conceptualizes it as ini9ated by a func9onal informa9on need (i.e., focused on solving a specific task) that triggers a process meant to solve this func9onal informa9on need <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cohen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. The traveler des9na9on choice model by <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">Woodside and Lysonski (1989)</ref> provides a good example of this perspec9ve. The model suggests that travelers follow a selec9on process that filters urban a8rac9ons from an awareness set to a set of preferences and finally towards a final choice. Seen from this perspec9ve, informa9on behavior is indeed part of the decision-making process.</p><p>The linear perspec9ve aligns with the sequen9al perspec9ve that is common in tourism and hospitality studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cohen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>, and makes a dis9nc9on between the pre-purchase and ongoing informa9on search stage <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">(Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. The prepurchase stage consists of planning the trip in advance while the ongoing informa9on search stage consists of informa9on behavior during the trip. A considerable amount of research emphasizes the pre-purchase stage, assuming that trips are me9culously planned <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cohen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. However, other research debunks this assump9on, showing that many decisions are made spontaneously during the trip <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Hyde &amp; Lawson, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b113">Zach &amp; Gretzel, 2011)</ref>, or based on habits <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bargeman &amp; van der Poel, 2006)</ref>. More recent studies have pivoted to acknowledge the significance of ongoing discovery during the trip itself, facilitated by the widespread adop9on of smartphones, the ubiquity of internet access, and the digital marketplace for apps (X. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Liu et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b98">Wang et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Xiang et al., 2015)</ref>.</p><p>The 'travel network perspec9ve' <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">(Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020</ref>) also stresses the spontaneity of urban discovery. It views travel not just as a des9na9on but as a collec9on of experiences, ac9vi9es, and places, interwoven with one's daily life <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">(Wang et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b113">Zach &amp; Gretzel, 2011</ref>). An example is the hedonic vaca9oner, a type of vaca9oner in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Decrop and Snelders' (2005)</ref> grounded typology about vaca9on decision-making who likes to dream and talk about their vaca9on plans.</p><p>In this context, the concept of 'informa9on encountering' becomes relevant, reflec9ng that people oeen acquire informa9on by encountering it rather than ac9vely seeking it <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Erdelez &amp; Makri, 2020)</ref>. Here the rela9onship between informa9on behavior and decision making is turned upside down; decision-making is part of informa9on behavior. One browses content for fun, and this impulsively leads to a decision when something a8rac9ve is found <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Huang et al., 2014)</ref>. Research does suggest that everyday informa9on behavior oeen entails informa9on encountering and serendipity <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Björneborn, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Foster &amp; Ford, 2003)</ref>. Non-linear informa9on models put more emphasis on informa9on encountering. An example is the berrypicking model by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bates (1989)</ref> which proposes that users "pick" bits of informa9on from various content over 9me, adjus9ng their search path and behavior as their understanding and needs evolve.</p><p>Although researchers differ in their perspec9ves on how informa9on behavior develops, they generally agree on its inherent duality-dis9nguishing between goal-oriented, convergent ac9vi9es like searching for specific informa9on and exploratory, divergent ac9vi9es such as browsing <ref type="bibr">(Björneborn, 2010a)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Dörk and colleagues (2011)</ref> recognize this inherent duality of informa9on behavior but cri9cize the exclusive focus on func9onal informa9on behavior. To promote a more human-centered view of informa9on behavior they introduce the no9on of the informa9on flaneur <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Dörk et al., 2011)</ref>. This figure is mo9vated by curiosity and discovers informa9on in a playful yet cri9cal manner through horizontal explora9on-where they navigate the content landscape spontaneously mo9vated by their curiosity <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Dörk et al., 2011)</ref>. Upon encountering cap9va9ng content, they transi9on into ver9cal immersion, delving deeply into the subject, which sparks a sense of wonder <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Dörk et al., 2011)</ref>.</p><p>Informa9on behavior can indeed be dis9nguished based on the mo9va9on underlying it. This viewpoint is closely linked to the popular but contested concept of informa9on needs <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Case &amp; Given, 2016)</ref>. Reflec9ng informa9on behavior literature in general, the tension between instrumental and playful mo9va9ons of informa9on behavior is also present in tourism and hospitality studies. For instance, <ref type="bibr">Gursoy (2019a)</ref> interprets travel informa9on behavior as primarily driven by a desire to reduce uncertainty, because the intangible and oeen costly nature of some urban a8rac9ons. This view aligns with a 'func9onal need' for u9lity, certainty, and efficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Vogt &amp; Fesenmaier, 1998)</ref>.</p><p>However, <ref type="bibr">Vogt and Fesenmaier (1998a)</ref> show that beyond func9onal informa9on needs, four other informa9on needs are relevant: hedonic, innova9on, aesthe9c and sign (i.e., social) informa9on needs.</p><p>2.1.4. The emergence of user generated content and review pla:orms Lastly, informa9on behavior can also be characterized by the content that communicates the informa9on <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">(Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. The advent and widespread accessibility of the internet have not only increased the frequency and spontaneity of informa9on searches but have also enabled consumers to connect with one another and share their experiences through User Generated Content (UGC). This phenomenon has become a cornerstone for the success of social media and review pla3orms-such as TripAdvisor and Booking.com-which now serve as some of the most influen9al actors in the hospitality and tourism sector <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Gössling et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Horner &amp; Swarbrooke, 2020)</ref>.</p><p>Empirical studies indicate that peer-to-peer review pla3orms are among the most frequently consulted sources of informa9on by consumers <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Dickinger, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Gursoy et al., 2017)</ref>. The aggregated ra9ngs provided by these pla3orms offer a straigh3orward metric for evalua9ng and selec9ng urban a8rac9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Pourfakhimi et al., 2020)</ref>. Moreover, the posi9ve rela9onship between higher ra9ngs and increased sales <ref type="bibr" target="#b107">(Ye et al., 2011)</ref> as well as larger booking transac9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b89">(Torres et al., 2015)</ref> suggests that consumers ac9vely incorporate these metrics into their decision-making processes.</p><p>The mechanisms underlying the influence of ra9ngs and reviews are complex <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Pourfakhimi et al., 2020)</ref>. Trust has been found to play a major role <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(Pop et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Pourfakhimi et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b77">Serra Cantallops &amp; Salvi, 2014)</ref>. Trust in user generated content, in general, is shaped by mul9ple antecedents, including perceived credibility, informa9on quality, and website quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Filieri et al., 2015)</ref>. Focusing more specifically on reviews, research has demonstrated that while both posi9ve and nega9ve reviews increase consumer awareness of hotels, they par9cularly influence consumer attudes toward lesser-known hotels <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">(Vermeulen &amp; Seegers, 2009)</ref>. Users interpret these reviews through heuris9c processes, relying on cues such as the perceived richness and factuality of the informa9on presented <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Papathanassis &amp; Knolle, 2011)</ref>. Moreover, affec9ve factors play a cri9cal role in this interpre9ve process. For example, the degree of homophily-the extent to which a reviewer is perceived to resemble the reader-can enhance trust, which in turn posi9vely influences attudes toward and the inten9on to visit urban a8rac9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Ayeh et al., 2013)</ref>. Addi9onally, a pronounced nega9vity bias oeen leads consumers to give dispropor9onate weight to nega9ve reviews, further impac9ng their decision-making <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Papathanassis &amp; Knolle, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Pourfakhimi et al., 2020)</ref>.</p><p>The prolifera9on of user-generated content (UGC) has expanded the availability of content on hospitality and tourism services to the point of crea9ng informa9on overload <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">(Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. Consequently, the role of recommender systems and the perceived trustworthiness of UGC has become increasingly important in helping consumers navigate this abundance of content <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">(Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. In our study, we aim to examine the extent to which individuals rely on UGC, and to explore how this reliance varies across different contexts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Factors influencing decision-making and informa;on behavior</head><p>To fully understand how people discover urban a8rac9ons, we argue that we need to combine insights from informa9on behavior and decision-making theory. Furthermore, we claim that how travelers discover urban a8rac9ons is dependent on personal characteris9cs as well as social and affec9ve factors. Below, we provide an overview of the factors we consider in this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1.">Personal factors</head><p>Familiarity: Returning tourists oeen seek more novel and unique experiences than less familiar travelers <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Vogt &amp; Fesenmaier, 1998)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Tse and Cro8s (2005)</ref> also find that familiarity is linked to novelty seeking, expressed by experimenta9on with Hong Kong's diverse culinary tradi9ons.</p><p>Familiarity also affects informa9on behavior; experienced visitors tend to focus on prac9cal aspects of a visit, whereas novice travelers engage in a more extensive search for informa9on <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Lehto et al., 2006)</ref>.</p><p>Personality: Individuals with a higher need for achievement tend to prefer adventurous vaca9ons, while those with a stronger need for affilia9on are more inclined toward cultural experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">(Tran &amp; Ralston, 2006)</ref>. Also <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Lepp and Gibson (2008)</ref> find that personality traits influence travel style, repor9ng that sensa9on seekers prefer a more independent style of travel and pursue novel ac9vi9es.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2.">Social factors</head><p>Travel party composi7on: Research indicates that the composi9on of a travel party significantly influences engagement with urban a8rac9ons. For instance, <ref type="bibr">Thornton and colleagues (1997)</ref> observed that younger children notably influence the distribu9on of 9me across ac9vi9es, leading to more 9me spent in child-friendly loca9ons, such as beaches, and less on traveling or relaxing. Generally, as interpersonal constraints grow, so does the complexity of decision-making within travel groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Kozak, 2010)</ref>.</p><p>Cultural distance: While travelers are generally more likely to enjoy culturally similar services, they are more tolerant towards culturally different services because these are perceived as authen9c <ref type="bibr" target="#b99">(Weiermair, 2000)</ref>. However, cultural openness of visitors is an important precursor in the par9cipa9on in authen9c cultural ac9vi9es <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Lin et al., 2021)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3.">Contextual factors</head><p>Mo7va7on: When a city serves as a main des9na9on, visitors oeen seek relaxa9on, an escape from rou9ne, or opportuni9es to reconnect with family and friends <ref type="bibr">(McKercher &amp; Wong, 2004)</ref>. These primary visitors are typically drawn to dining and shopping experiences, while secondary visitors show more interest in architecture, specific tourist sites, and local residents <ref type="bibr">(McKercher &amp; Wong, 2004)</ref>. However, <ref type="bibr">Huang and colleagues (2014)</ref> reveal no significant difference in independent travel styles between travelers at main des9na9ons and those on stopovers; both groups exhibit a preference for serendipitous travel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Length of stay:</head><p>Research indicates that the length of stay significantly influences travel behavior. <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Moore et al. (2012)</ref> found that shorter stays are typically characterized by extensively planned i9neraries, whereas longer stays oeen involve more spontaneous, on-site decision making.</p><p>Addi9onally, <ref type="bibr">Tse and Cro8s (2005)</ref> find that extended stays are associated with a greater propensity for novelty-seeking and a willingness to experiment with local culture.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.4.">Demographic factors</head><p>Age: <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Kim et al. (2015)</ref> highlight genera9onal differences in online informa9on behavior. They observe that older genera9ons prefer direct contact with suppliers of hospitality products while younger genera9ons prefer intermediaries such as TripAdvisor or Google. Furthermore, younger genera9ons also more frequently use social networking sites and UGC, while older genera9ons use online content that can be printed because they prefer tacit informa9on sources (H. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Kim et al., 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Gender: Men and women tend to play different roles in the decision-making process within tourism and hospitality. Women are less involved in financing trips yet play a greater role in planning them <ref type="bibr" target="#b114">(Zalatan, 1998)</ref> and take the ini9a9ve in decision-making <ref type="bibr">(Motar &amp; Quinn, 2004)</ref>. Research on informa9on behavior further reveals gender differences: women rely more oeen on word-of-mouth recommenda9ons during travel planning <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Murphy et al., 2007)</ref>, and rely more oeen on landmarks for naviga9on during wayfinding compared to men <ref type="bibr" target="#b102">(Xia et al., 2008)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.5.">Affec1ve factors</head><p>Des7na7on image: A fun and friendly des9na9on image is an important pull factor for city break vaca9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Dunne et al., 2011)</ref>. A des9na9on's image is shaped by both cogni9ve and affec9ve factors; however, affec9ve factors not only mediate the influence of cogni9ve factors but also serves as a stronger predictor of the overall image among tourists <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">(Stylidis et al., 2017)</ref>. This overall des9na9on image significantly influences key outcomes such as des9na9on sa9sfac9on, revisit inten9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Kani et al., 2017)</ref>, and inten9on to recommend the des9na9on (Afshardoost &amp; Eshaghi, 2020; <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">Stylidis et al., 2017)</ref>.</p><p>Emo7ons: emo9ons also play an important role in informa9on behavior and decision making. For example, emo9onal 9tles of UGC a8ract more a8en9on than informa9onal 9tles <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Fu et al., 2024)</ref>. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Liu et al's (2023)</ref> found that celebrity endorsements s9mulate inten9ons to visit a des9na9on only when they evoke emo9onal arousal. Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">Scarpi et al. (2019)</ref> find that involvement with an event par9cularly increases place a8achment when the event feels authen9c.</p><p>The preceding review highlights the complex nature of decision-making in tourism but also reveals a fragmented body of literature. This fragmenta9on shows the need for a more integrated understanding, promp9ng our central research ques9on: How do people discover urban a8rac9ons in the contemporary digital age? The following sec9on details the methodology we employed to develop a holis9c typology that addresses this ques9on by integra9ng and extending the insights discussed above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Methodology</head><p>To understand how users discover urban a8rac9ons, we conducted semi-structured interviews with 126 par9cipants in Belgium. Subsequently, we used the grounded theory framework to analyze this data <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">(Strauss &amp; Corbin, 2015)</ref>. Below, we describe our Sampling approach (Sec9on 3.1), Interview protocol (Sec9on 3.2), and Grounded theory (Sec9on 3.3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Sampling approach</head><p>Our study employed a two-phase sampling strategy, combining convenience and purposive sampling that resulted in a diverse sample of inhabitants of the Brussels and Flemish region of Belgium. In the first phase (October-December 2019), we relied on a convenience sampling approach, where 119 university students conducted each one interview, with a par9cipant outside their class, as part of a methodology course. Prior to conduc9ng the interviews, we introduced the students to the research context and research aim by guiding them through the topic guide provided by the researchers (see Appendix and Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). This ensured that the students understood the aim of the study, and that their interviews were comparable.</p><p>Upon analyzing the demographic composi9on of this ini9al sample, we iden9fied an age bias; we were missing the perspec9ve of par9cipants over 50. To address this, we (the researchers) conducted a second phase of purposive sampling (July-August 2024), purposively selec9ng seven par9cipants over 50. We applied two selec9on criteria during this phase: age, to ensure representa9on across different life stages, and gender, to ensure that each age category included at least one man and one woman. We do this because, as discussed in Sec9on 2.3.4, both demographic variables are related to tourism and hospitality behavior. This sampling approach deviates from the typical purposive sampling approach in grounded theory. However, due to the explora9ve nature of this study, it is especially important to have a diverse sample. As Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> illustrates, our sampling approach indeed resulted in a diverse sample. Note: all par9cipants are inhabitants of the Flemish or Brussels region of Belgium</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Interview protocol</head><p>Par9cipants received an informed consent document outlining the study's purpose, data handling prac9ces, and privacy safeguards, following our ins9tute's template and data protec9on guidelines. Consent was obtained before recording began. Next, the interviewers started the recording and went through the topic guide ques9ons (see Appendix). We outline the general themes men9oned in the topic guide in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. These topics relate to our central ques9on of how the rise of digital pla3orms, specifically, UGC review and ra9ng pla3orm have impacted the discovery of urban a8rac9ons. Interviews typically lasted between 40-70 minutes. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Grounded theory</head><p>We use grounded theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">(Strauss &amp; Corbin, 2015)</ref> to develop a theory of urban discovery.</p><p>This approach suits our focus on urban a8rac9ons, an understudied concept in need of fresh theore9cal development. Because grounded theory is induc9ve, it provides the originality necessary to explore this topic <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">(Strauss &amp; Corbin, 2015)</ref>. Furthermore, it allows for a rich and nuanced descrip9on (Ma8eucci &amp; Gnoth, 2017; <ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Woodside et al., 2004)</ref>. As explained in Sec9on 2.1.1, the process approach and grounded theory create an effec9ve combina9on <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Decrop &amp; Snelders, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Moore et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b101">Woodside et al., 2004)</ref>. Lastly, grounded theory seeks to explain phenomena, offering insight into why urban discovery unfolds as it does <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">(Strauss &amp; Corbin, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>The grounded theory analysis started by immersing ourselves in the data by reading a random sample of interviews without coding <ref type="bibr">(Mehmetoglu &amp; Al9nay, 2006)</ref>. Subsequently, we started open coding of interviews u9lizing MAXQDA soeware. This open coding facilitates the iden9fica9on and descrip9on of various concepts, as well as the me9culous documenta9on of analy9cal insights via memos. Such detailed documenta9on is essen9al as it aids in refining the codes-whether by discarding, modifying, or merging them as necessary-thus enabling the iden9fica9on of higher-level concepts and their respec9ve proper9es <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">(Strauss &amp; Corbin, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Subsequently, axial coding was employed to connect the different iden9fied concepts during open coding. This process was further enhanced by compara9ve analysis, which involves contras9ng incidents to discern similari9es and differences <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">(Strauss &amp; Corbin, 2015)</ref>.</p><p>We also followed <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">Strauss and Corbin's (2015)</ref> guidelines to determine when theore9cal satura9on had been achieved. Their main criterion is the theory's internal consistency and logical coherence. In our case, this means that the different discovery modes must be clearly dis9nguished, their elements thoroughly conceptualized, and their processual development free of gaps. Based on our theore9cal framework, summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>, we believe this criterion has been met.</p><p>We further tested theore9cal satura9on during the final five interviews, which were conducted by the lead author. At the end of each interview, we presented our theore9cal model (see</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>) and asked par9cipants if it resonated with their experiences. Par9cipants oeen recognized themselves in the different discovery modes and recalled how they had discovered urban a8rac9ons through various discovery modes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discovery modes</head><p>Our grounded theory analysis revealed five dis9nct discovery modes: instrumental-ra9onal, go-with-the-flow, social, flaneur, and habitual. Sec9on 4.1 offers a detailed descrip9on of each mode, which are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>.</p><p>It is important to note that our theore9cal framework does not prescribe a value hierarchy;</p><p>the value and adop9on of the five discovery modes are highly situa9onal, and an individual may adopt different modes depending on the context. To build on our ini9al descrip9ons, we therefore analyze the factors influencing the adop9on of a par9cular discovery mode (Sec9on 4.2) and then explore the rela9onships between the discovery modes themselves (Sec9on 4.3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Instrumental-ra5onal</head><p>Go-with-the-flow Social Flaneur Habitual Key values Price-quality ra.o, certainty, predictability Serendipity, ease, spontaneity Social contact Resonance, dis.nc.on, authen.city Tradi.ons, feeling at ease, predictability, certainty</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mo5va5on of discovery process</head><p>Func  In instrumental-ra9onal discovery mode, individuals primarily value predictability and price-quality in their search for urban a8rac9ons. These discoverers try to ensure their limited 9me and money is invested wisely in worthwhile hospitality experiences, aiming to avoid disappointment.</p><p>The explora9on process in this mode is mo9vated by a 'func9onal informa9on need' <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Vogt &amp; Fesenmaier, 1998)</ref>. Typical situa9ons are for example finding a restaurant for a roman9c date or planning an important event as Par9cipant 21 illustrates "If I want to go somewhere special to eat with someone, say for a birthday or for Christmas, I do want it to stand out, that it's special. That's why I will look for a place with good reviews."</p><p>Func9onal informa9on needs are intertwined with an instrumental view on informa9on and discovery. Instrumental-ra9onal discoverers are solely focused on iden9fying the best places to visit and hence driven by extrinsic mo9va9on. Their primary concern is that the discovery process be efficient and effec9ve. For example, when asked which kind of recommenda9on is preferred, by a friend or by an algorithm, Par9cipant 50 answers pragma9cally: "I think the algorithm, because it knows more," which is in stark contrast to the intrinsically mo9vated informa9on behavior in playful discovery modes, as is discussed later.</p><p>This instrumental attude manifests in their discovery prac9ces. They primarily leverage review pla3orms and search engines as their interface to discover the city. In par9cular ra9ngs, reviews, and filters are deemed indispensable as they allow a thorough comparison of the urban a8rac9on space through the urban a8rac9on content space. Instrumental-ra9onal discoverers use filters to dis9l a relevant set of urban a8rac9ons and subsequently thoroughly compare them before deciding on the highest-rated and best-reviewed op9ons. Par9cipant 6 provides an apt example of this explora9on and immersion process: </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">"</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Playful discovery modes</head><p>We use the label playful discovery modes to refer to the go-with-the-flow, social, and flaneur discovery modes, since all these modes describe a discovery process driven by intrinsic mo9va9on.</p><p>In these modes enjoying urban discovery is as important as the quality of the outcome. The inherent pleasure associated with the discovery process oeen transforms it into a story worth sharing, as Discoverers who adopt a go-with-the-flow mode are mo9vated by inspira9onal informa9on needs. Unlike the me9culous scou9ng of flaneurs or the systema9c searching of instrumental-ra9onal discoverers, they engage with their environment spontaneously and impulsively.</p><p>Consequently, their explora9on unfolds haphazardly as they inspect their immediate surroundings, immersing themselves instantly when something intriguing is encountered. This all expresses itself in their discovery prac9ces. They prefer to lead their own explora9on rather than depending on recommenda9ons, ra9ngs, or reviews. Their laid-back approach has them meandering through the city-typically by foot-open to the allure of aesthe9c details that may draw them impulsively into a restaurant, even if it deviates from their original i9nerary.</p><p>Interes9ngly, the rise of online reserva9ons means that ac9vi9es oeen require advanced planning. Weijts (2023) captures this loss of spontaneity well, cri9cizing the growing challenge of, for example, dining in a good restaurant without prior reserva9ons. This loss clearly reverberates in our interviews. For example, Par9cipant 120 men9ons: "It is annoying for example when I want to do a trip, I have to make reserva9ons for everything well in advance … I do miss some flexibility on vaca9on." This clashes with the go-with-the-flow ethos, which thrives on unscripted discovery.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.3.">Social discovery mode</head><p>Social interac9ons lie at the heart of the social discovery mode. Social discoverers leverage their social network as an interface to discover the city. However, the value placed on social interac9ons transcends mere informa9on gathering; it is a conduit for nurturing rela9onships, offering a base for future conversa9ons as Par9cipant 30 encapsulates when explaining why he prefers recommenda9ons by friends over digital recommenda9ons: "because I want to know more about this friend of course. What does he like, then we can chat about that, do I like this?"</p><p>Social discoverers engage with urban a8rac9ons through a con9nuous stream of social interac9ons, ranging from direct encounters-such as conversa9ons with colleagues-to more indirect touchpoints, like scrolling through social media feeds. What dis9nguishes these individuals is their drive to be both inspired and informed by their social network. They are mo9vated by a social informa9on need, or what <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">Vogt and Fesenmaier (1998)</ref> refer to as a "sign need"-the reliance on the opinions and experiences of their social contacts regarding urban a8rac9ons.</p><p>Beside exploring the urban a8rac9on space through their social network, they also immerse themselves in specific urban a8rac9ons by consul9ng their social network. Par9cipant 27 describes this reliance on her social network for discovering and deciding what is worthwhile to visit: "In both cases, both domes9c and foreign, I am more likely to rely on people I know. For example, before the trip to Norway, I talked about it with a friend who had taken a very long trip there, and with whom I looked at her i9neraries, the places they had been and even went through photo albums. I listened to what they recommended; people rather than digital recommenda9ons."</p><p>Social discoverers rely on social informa9on sources because they trust them over other sources. They believe their network understands their preferences be8er than any algorithm could.</p><p>The in9mate understanding of their preferences by their social network is seen as the expression of true friendship. Addi9onally, feelings of affec9on towards individuals who make recommenda9ons also cons9tutes an important explana9on in the preference for social informa9on sources. When asked which kind of recommenda9ons are preferred-by a friend or an algorithm-Par9cipant 97's response is telling: "A friend because they love you, it's that simple. That goes far beyond pleasing me, it is about enriching each other and sharing."</p><p>On the other hand, we also observe that digitaliza9on and the internet might facilitate social connec9on. While not the UGC pla3orms that were the focus of our interview topics, other digital pla3orms, such as social media, can foster the social connec9ons valued by social discoverers.</p><p>Indeed, our smartphones give us easy access to interact with our social networks at all 9mes. A different example of how technology can support social discoverers is the app "ManyGuide", men9oned by Par9cipant 50. These tools connect visitors of Brussels and Amsterdam with locals providing "a combina9on of what technology is good at and what people are be8er at."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.4.">Flaneur mode</head><p>At the heart of the urban flaneur is a roman9c attude towards the city. This roman9c attude drives the urban flaneur to discover their big love, expressing itself in unbridled curiosity. Their quest is to find resonance within the city-a concept championed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">Rosa (2019)</ref> to describe a touching connec9on with the world.</p><p>Urban a8rac9ons that are perceived as authen9c typically resonate with the flaneur. This is illustrated by Par9cipant 37's preference for Brussels over Geneva: "The shops are really nice. It is much be8er than Geneva. Geneva, it's mostly brands and it's quite expensive. And the shops are not that interes9ng in Geneva. They spark my interest in Brussels actually. You have a lot of small shops, bou9ques, much smaller, with a soul," illustra9ng the urban flaneur's a8rac9on to places that resonate through character and vibe.</p><p>The flaneur is par9cularly enthusias9c to discover the city's hidden gems, like Par9cipant 12:</p><p>"I look for hidden spots where most tourists don't come, but where for example locals or young people oPen write about on their blog: 'ah I discovered that park over there,' and actually, in that way I find cool, ar9s9c, different things than in the average guidebooks." As illustrated above, they aspire to dis9nguish themselves from regular tourists by leveraging informa9on sources beyond what regular tourists use. As outlined in <ref type="bibr">Bourdieu's Dis9nc9on (1984)</ref>, the pursuit of dis9nc9on-the desire to differen9ate oneself from others-is deeply embedded in social prac9ces and iden99es.</p><p>Bourdieu argues that individuals leverage various forms of capital, such as social, economic, and cultural capital, to establish and maintain their dis9nc9veness. For example, someone with extensive social capital might u9lize their connec9ons to access exclusive venues, setng themselves apart from those with a less pres9gious social network. Similarly, individuals with significant economic resources purchase premium hospitality services to assert their dis9nc9on over those with more modest financial backgrounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ahmad, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">T. Liu &amp; Li, 2020)</ref>. Being a flaneur is also part of one's iden9ty and follows a similar pursuit of dis9nc9on but by harnessing their cultural capitalknowledge and familiarity with the city and its background-to differen9ate themselves explicitly from tourists or others unfamiliar with the city's hidden charms, as is also supported by the findings in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ahmad, 2014)</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, flaneurs are characterized by their recep9vity to and respect for their surroundings. Their recep9vity is expressed by prac9ces that enable them to fully absorb their environment, like Par9cipant 97: "Yes, my eyes. I wander of course. I explore, hence the wandering. I try out a lot." Dörk and colleagues' (2011) describe the urban flaneur as someone who wanders without a specific goal, with the primary purpose of immersing themselves in the vibrancy of city life.</p><p>Therefore, they are par9cularly fond of content which s9mulates the senses and triggers telepresence <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">(Steuer, 1995)</ref>, aligning with their desire for resonance and 'aesthe9c informa9on need' <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Vogt &amp; Fesenmaier, 1998)</ref>.</p><p>Their respect is a logical consequence of their roman9c rela9onship with the city. This respect is expressed by Par9cipant 123: "We try to learn some basics of the language. To travel with respect for the city. With respect for the climate and environment. I also consciously avoid visi9ng interna9onal chains that are known for tax fraud … We want to contribute to the local economy."</p><p>The flaneur explores and immerses themself in the city by using a rich plethora of informa9on prac9ces such as talking to locals or experts about the city, reading books about the city, and wandering through the city. Similarly to instrumental-ra9onal discovery mode, this might result in rigorously planning a trip. However, in this case the planning process is not instrumental for guaranteeing a worthwhile trip, but inherently pleasant. Indeed, it is a pathway to get hyped about a trip as Par9cipant 121 states: "Witness our roadbook. But for me, that contributes to the success of the vaca9on. You also have the pleasure of planning the trip, of ge[ng excited in an9cipa9on of it."</p><p>Lastly, their discovery prac9ces are characterized by a desire for agency because they desire to forge a unique bond with the city.</p><p>Their roman9c rela9onship with the city and extensive informa9on behavior results in affec9ve decision-making. They follow their refined and informed taste as a guide through the city, deciding what to visit depending on how strongly it resonates: "It does happen on vaca9on that we spontaneously enter a store, preferably not a touris9c one, but for example, a glassblower. Sure, it's pricey, but we will take a look because the ar9stry is excep9onal."</p><p>At the same 9me, they are cri9cal observers of the city. Because of their in9mate rela9onship with the city, they have strong opinions about its evolu9on. Par9cipant 97, for example, cri9cizes popularity bias in recommender systems: "that aggressive dynamic of apps, of something where a lot of people go, ... You only have a subgroup that gives ra9ngs, that system is not right at all. It's conceptually flawed, you certainly no9ce that with restaurants and tourists, they visit en masse the same places." The flaneur, in pursuit of authen9city and resonance, oeen feels alienated in these overly touris9c loca9ons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.5.">Habitual discovery mode</head><p>Habitual discovery mode is characterized by a preference for the familiar, offering ease, predictability, and certainty. Although discovery typically implies venturing into the unknown, these travelers deliberately seek out familiar urban a8rac9ons-even within unfamiliar setngs. By anchoring their experiences with recognizable elements, such as global franchises, they balance the thrill of new experiences with the comfort of the familiar.</p><p>Habitual discovery mode resembles instrumental-ra9onal discovery mode in its desire for predictability and certainty. Yet, habitual discoverers do not care to find the best urban a8rac9on for their money; they desire to feel at ease. In this sense, they are similar to go-with-the-flow mode.</p><p>However, while people in go-with-the-flow mode are open and recep9ve for new experiences, people in habitual discovery mode are looking for anchors of familiarity. Par9cipant 97 aptly expresses this desire for familiarity: "Some9mes you seek the familiar, but that depends very much on your emo9onal state, some9mes you just want the familiar because you want to 'come home'."</p><p>These familiar places engender one's comfort zone, which is created through rituals, i.e., repeated scripts of ac9ons in a certain situa9on. An example of a ritual is visi9ng the Hard Rock Café on each city trip. Indeed, the Hard Rock Café company smartly taps into this discovery mode. In his book Interac9on ritual chains, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Collins (2004)</ref> lays out a theory on how rituals can lead to strong emo9onal and moral associa9ons to symbols through the effervescence created during these rituals.</p><p>This theory helps us understand why in habitual mode, we can have such desire to visit the same places and why this has posi9ve psychological effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">(Singh et al., 2020)</ref>. Research shows that rituals can increase enjoyment of consump9on <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">(Vohs et al., 2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Linking the discovery modes to their determinants and moderators</head><p>In Sec9on 4.1., we thoroughly described the five discovery modes. In this sec9on, we delve deeper into how personal, social, contextual, demographic, and affec9ve factors guide individuals toward one mode or another, as illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p><p>Our interviews suggest that personality, par9cularly openness to experience and need for cogni9ve closure, are important predictors. People high in openness to experience-characterized by curiosity, sensi9vity to aesthe9cs, and a8en9veness to internal feelings <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Costa Jr &amp; McCrae, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">McCrae &amp; Costa, 1997)</ref>-are more likely to discover in go-with-the-flow or flaneur mode. Conversely, those lower in openness typically gravitate toward habitual discovery.</p><p>In contrast, a pronounced need for cogni9ve closure-discomfort with ambiguity and preference for clear outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">(Roets &amp; Van Hiel, 2011</ref>)-discourages go-with-the-flow discovery.</p><p>Par9cipant 10 illustrates how this need instead favors instrumental-ra9onal discovery: "I am the kind of person who likes to have control over situa9ons, so I want an ac9vity to be planned quite a while in advance. According to me, that ensures that I never or at least rarely experience any surprises." The desire for spontaneity, characteris9c in go-with-the-flow mode, contrasts sharply with the need for cogni9ve closure.  In heterogeneous travel par7es, people are also more likely to desire cogni9ve closure since there are varied interests and physical constraints which make it more difficult to spontaneously encounter something sa9sfying, hence favoring instrumental-ra9onal discovery. For example, Par9cipant 120 shares that, when she is on vaca9on with her mother, she looks on the internet for a place that fits the following criteria: "something that is accessible for a person with mobility problems, with a parking place nearby, and with a nice view so it feels different than si[ng in her own house." A heterogeneous travel party also favors habitual discovery mode; par9cularly kids enjoy the familiarity of interna9onal fast-food chains, and it oeen becomes a tradi9on to visit these places during vaca9ons. On the other hand, homogeneous travel par7es are more likely to discover in a spontaneous way and make affec9ve decisions since their taste and intui9on guiding them through the city is similar. For example, Par9cipant 121 explains how she discovers places more spontaneously with her younger daughter compared with her older daughter because: "We are very similar. We can discover and decide where to go based on intui9on."</p><p>Also charm is an important trigger for affec9ve decision-making, s9mula9ng go-with-theflow and flaneur discovery. As Par9cipant 27 describes: "Recently, we were in Paris and wanted to go to Musée Bourdelle, to a fashion exposi9on. But on our way, we like to enjoy Paris, discover some new places; and when we stumbled upon a charming café, we said: 'Oh, this looks lovely; let's stop for a coffee!'" In flaneur mode, charm is oeen 9ed to authen9city, shaped by one's cultural understanding of the city. In contrast, those in go-with-the-flow mode follow personal taste without considering authen9city, making them more prone to tourist traps.</p><p>Regarding social discovery mode, here mainly taste of the other person giving the recommenda9on is important. Some people's recommenda9ons are trusted more than others. While certain recommenda9ons are blindly followed, others are verified through sources like TripAdvisor, resul9ng in an instrumental-ra9onal way of discovering. As Par9cipant 37 explains: "I think you need to know the people. Recently, we have been recommended a restaurant by our neighbors, and it was not great for us… If some of my friends recommend me a place, I will go; without checking the internet, because I know their taste and I know it will get along with mine. For other people, it's a bit difficult; I will always crosscheck on the internet, like TripAdvisor."</p><p>Lastly, we note that age is also related with the adopted discovery mode. Younger individuals tend to favor go-with-the-flow and instrumental-ra9onal discovery for their ease and efficiency.</p><p>Older individuals, with more accumulated knowledge, life experience, and available 9me, are more likely to explore in flaneur mode.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Linking the discovery modes to each other</head><p>Not all discovery modes are equally compa9ble. While playful modes can blend to create mixed types, the instrumental-ra9onal and habitual modes are incompa9ble with others. The following sec9on explores these compa9bili9es in detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1.">Compa1ble modes</head><p>The playful discovery modes are mutually compa9ble, each characterized by an inherently enjoyable process of explora9on. Although they do not always occur simultaneously-otherwise, they would not be conceptualized as dis9nct modes-they some9mes overlap. Indeed, our par9cipants gave some anecdotes that can be both characterized as flaneur and social discovery mode. Flaneurs enjoy gathering diverse content about the city and par9cularly value sugges9ons from locals since they oeen result in authen9c experiences. Par9cipant 126 recalls an anecdote illustra9ng the discovery of a viewpoint that embodies both discovery modes:</p><p>"We were in Josselin, si[ng in our car, ready to leave for our next accommoda9on. First, we stopped at a local bakery. As we cha8ed with the baker, he asked, 'Have you been up the basilica tower?'</p><p>'No, we walked all over the city and saw everything-but go up the tower-no, that we didn't do yet. You can't do it all, can you?' 'But you can't leave without going up! You'll thank me later-the view is magnificent.'' So we decided to go, messaging our next host that we'd be late. And the baker was rightthe view was incredible. We took photos, saw the city and castle from above, and aPerward, we returned to the bakery to tell him, 'You were right. It was absolutely worth it.'" Our par9cipants also shared discoveries that could be characterized by both social and gowith-the-flow mode. Social discovery mode emphasizes the role of social interac9ons, while go-withthe-flow mode highlights the ease and tranquility of unplanned explora9on. Par9cipant 120 recalled serendipitously encountering friends she had not seen in years and how their sugges9ons inspired her plans during the trip: "We encountered friends that we hadn't seen for at least fiPeen years. They gave us a couple of 9ps for things to do with the kids. In that way, we have discovered many things to do. I like that, to discover a8rac9ons at the des9na9on itself."</p><p>Lastly, also go-with-the-flow and flaneur mode some9mes occur together. While flaneur mode is characterized by thorough informa9on behavior, it also involves exploring the city on foot-a behavior that naturally leads to the spontaneous encounters characteris9c of go-with-the-flow mode. Par9cipant 37 gives an example of a combina9on of both: "At the beginning I used digital sources for everything. I went on internet and then you end up at websites about Brussels, like the official one, but also other websites and blogs. You find what to do in the city, also through books about the city. And then you walk and discover; I discovered actually most of the shops by walking around."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2.">Incompa1ble modes</head><p>While playful discovery modes seamlessly blend into one another, they remain dis9nct from instrumental-ra9onal and habitual discovery modes. These modes are shaped by fundamentally opposing values, attudes, and informa9on prac9ces.</p><p>For example, social and instrumental-ra7onal discovery mode contrast sharply in informa9on behavior. Social discoverers rely on personal networks for recommenda9ons, while instrumental-ra9onal discoverers place greater trust in online ra9ngs and reviews, as illustrated by Conversely, social discoverers priori9ze human connec9on and personal interac9on in their discovery process, as illustrated by Par9cipant 18: "I trust my friends' recommenda9ons moresomeone who has actually been there makes it feel more personal. Just because the internet says something is good doesn't mean you should go-it lacks the human touch."</p><p>Flaneur and instrumental-ra7onal mode are also incompa9ble. While instrumental-ra9onal discoverers seek objec9ve metrics to ensure they receive value for money, flaneurs pursue a more subjec9ve and roman9c rela9onship with the city. They seek out hidden gems known only to true connoisseurs. As Par9cipant 21 puts it: "I don't brainlessly follow reviews or the whole crowd. When everybody says that a restaurant is really good, everybody will go eat there, and this is not what I want. I want to find something special."</p><p>Although both Instrumental-ra7onal and go-with-the-flow are more common among younger travelers, they also are incompa9ble. Go-with-the-flow discoverers embrace spontaneity and serendipitous encounters, whereas instrumental-ra9onal discoverers seek certainty and predictability. Par9cipant 24 illustrates this contrast: "If a recommenda9on has a very good ra9ng, by a lot of people, we will definitely follow it," When asked whether they would s9ck to their plan-even if they encountered something par9cularly a8rac9ve, they firmly replied: "Yes, we would, because looks can be deceiving."</p><p>Habitual discovery mode is incompa7ble with all other discovery modes. It is seldomly one's first choice like Par9cipant 123 explains: "If we really have no clue, then we just go to something Italian" but a bit later in the interview, she adds: "Italian food for us, it is not our first choice. Definitely not. We eat Italian if we really don't know where to go; if we are 9red; if we have to catch a train." This mode oeen leads travelers back to their comfort zones, par9cularly aeer an unexpected setback. Par9cipant 126 recounts such an experience: "My daughter's train had stood s9ll in a field for hours. We had planned to eat Indian, because a colleague who had lived in Paris had recommended a place. But when she arrived, it was already super late, so we decided to go for a hamburger."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Discussion</head><p>5.1. Theore;cal contribu;on</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1.">Ontological contribu1on</head><p>This study shows that <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Leiper's (1990)</ref> framework, even 35 years aeer its publica9on, remains a produc9ve tool for genera9ng new insights. Inspired by his work, we developed a conceptual framework for urban discovery (see Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>), adap9ng his original theory in two key ways. First, we shieed the focus from tradi9onal tourist sites to all a8rac9ons. Second, we zoomed out from</p><p>individual "markers" to analyze a collec9ve "urban a8rac9on content space." These adapta9ons were necessary to suit the modern context, where digital pla3orms expose people to en9re ecosystems of a8rac9ons and where "pull" marke9ng strategies are as important as tradi9onal "push" methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Godin, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Hollebeek &amp; Macky, 2019</ref>).</p><p>To answer our research ques9on-How do people discover urban a8rac9ons today?-we conceptualized urban discovery as a dynamic process, responding to calls for a process-oriented ontology in tourism research <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Decrop, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">Smallman &amp; Moore, 2010)</ref>. This ontology allowed us to develop a rich and nuanced typology of urban discovery modes, and to associate these different discovery modes to personal, social, contextual, demographic, and affec9ve factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Decrop, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">Sirakaya &amp; Woodside, 2005)</ref>.</p><p>Finally, our conceptual framework helps interpret pressing challenges in the urban a8rac9on ecosystem. For instance, cri9cal consumer culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Gössling et al., 2018)</ref> can be understood as the influence of ra9ngs and reviews in the urban a8rac9on content space on urban discovery and consequently on the success of urban a8rac9ons. Urban filter bubbles-i.e., people might only see a par9cular part of the city, which is different from what other people are exposed to, because of algorithmic personaliza9on <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">(Smets et al., 2019)</ref>-can be understood as a consequence of too much personaliza9on in the urban a8rac9on content space. And lastly, tourist traps <ref type="bibr">(Ganzaroli, De Noni, &amp; van Baalen, 2017)</ref> can be understood as a lack of informa9on about the authen9city and quality of urban a8rac9ons during urban discovery. By contextualizing these challenges within our framework, we offer fresh theore9cal and prac9cal perspec9ves to address them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2.">Mechanis1c contribu1on</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2.1.">The five discovery modes</head><p>Our conceptual framework, inspired by Leiper's tourist a8rac9ons systems, tourist a8rac9on system, defines the universe in which urban discovery occurs. Our typology of discovery modes, in turn, adds flesh to the bone by describing the dis9nct pa8erns and forms urban discovery can take.</p><p>Metaphorically speaking, our conceptual framework provides the hardware on which our five discovery modes, the soeware, runs. By developing this typology, our study taps into the poten9al that <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Richards (2002)</ref> iden9fied in Leiper's work to explain how people interact with informa9on in different contexts.</p><p>We iden9fied five dis9nct discovery modes: instrumental-ra9onal, go-with-the-flow, social, flaneur, and habitual. Beyond richly describing these modes, we examined the personal, social, contextual, demographic, and affec9ve factors that influence their likelihood. We also analyzed their rela9onships, demonstra9ng that the playful discovery modes-go-with-the-flow, social, and flaneur-are compa9ble because they all three capture an inherently enjoyable discovery process, leading to mixed modes of discovery. In contrast, the remaining modes are incompa9ble, shaped by opposing values, attudes, and mo9va9ons-which cannot co-occur. In the next paragraphs, we connect the five discovery modes to exis9ng literature, illustra9ng how our typology integrates and synthesizes a lot of previously more fragmented research.</p><p>Instrumental-ra7onal discovery aligns with the dominant perspec9ve of consumer behavior in the field of tourism and hospitality <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cohen et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref>. It can be described by linear informa9on behavior models <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">(Woodside &amp; Lysonski, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Xiang &amp; Fesenmaier, 2020)</ref> driven by func9onal informa9on needs, where individuals seek goal-directed solu9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Björneborn, 2010b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b96">Vogt &amp; Fesenmaier, 1998)</ref>. Decision-making in this mode follows ra9onal choice and choice-set theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">(Sirakaya &amp; Woodside, 2005)</ref> and review pla3orms play a crucial role in this process <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Dickinger, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Gursoy, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Pourfakhimi et al., 2020)</ref>. This mode aligns closely with <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Decrop and Snelders' (2005)</ref> concept of the "ra9onal vaca9oner," who me9culously plans and researches their trip.</p><p>Go-with-the-flow discovery, in contrast, aligns with non-linear models of informa9on behavior, par9cularly the no9on of informa9on encountering <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Erdelez &amp; Makri, 2020)</ref>. Unlike instrumental-ra9onal discoverers, who rely on comparisons of ra9ngs on pla3orms, these travelers engage directly with their surroundings, embracing serendipity over systema9zed evalua9on <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Huang et al., 2014)</ref>. Decisions are made on the spot, guided less by calculated trade-offs and more by immediate impressions, intui9on, and charm. When something in the environment sparks a strong emo9onal response-such as the appeal of a cozy café or a picturesque alley-it can prompt a spontaneous decision to visit, bypassing delibera9on en9rely <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Dai et al., 2022)</ref>. This reflects the affect heuris9c, in which choices are driven by posi9ve or nega9ve feelings rather than by analy9cal reasoning <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">(Slovic et al., 2006)</ref>. This discovery mode fits <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Hyde's (2008)</ref> descrip9on of the independent traveler, who feels the need to discover the unplanned and takes advantage of serendipitous opportuni9es. Smartphones and review pla3orms both support and hinder this discovery style.</p><p>While they allow travelers to quickly look up places that sa9sfy impromptu desires (X. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Liu et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b98">Wang et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b105">Xiang et al., 2015)</ref>, the widespread prac9ce of advance reserva9ons can frustrate flexibility, oeen leaving no availability for last-minute discoveries.</p><p>Social discovery's main contribu9on to the literature is that habitual word-of-mouth remains highly influen9al in discovering urban a8rac9ons <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Gildin, 2022)</ref>. Despite the growing reliance on digital pla3orms, personal recommenda9ons from friends, family, and acquaintances con9nue to shape urban explora9on. It also illustrates that, beyond peer-review pla3orms, social media plays a crucial role in urban discovery, offering a dynamic and visually driven way for travelers to explore urban a8rac9ons in a social way. Therefore, "Instagrammability" of urban a8rac9ons is important for a8rac9ng social discoverers browsing their social media <ref type="bibr" target="#b111">(Yu et al., 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b110">Yu &amp; Sun, 2019)</ref>. Social media influencers also play an important role in this process, as their recommenda9ons oeen guide travel decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(Pop et al., 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b106">Xu et al., 2021)</ref>. Regarding decision-making, we find evidence for the homophily effect described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Ayeh et al. (2013)</ref>, not only on digital pla3orms but also in the context of recommenda9ons received through one's social network more broadly. Furthermore, affec9on towards the person recommending something is also an important factor influencing the decision to follow recommenda9ons, implying that especially the engagement of the fanbase of social influencers is important for their "influence."</p><p>Flaneur mode involves broad informa9on behavior, mirroring <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">Xiang and Fesenmaier's (2020)</ref> travel network perspec9ve, which views tourism as an extension of daily life. In this sense, our findings resemble <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Decrop and Snelders (2005)</ref> depic9on of the hedonic vaca9oner, who enjoys dreaming, thinking, and talking about their journey. Our findings also support <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Dörk et al.'s (2011)</ref> no9on of the "informa9on flaneur," whose pursuit of knowledge is guided by aesthe9c and hedonic informa9on needs <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">(Vogt &amp; Fesenmaier, 1998)</ref>, rather than purely func9onal ones. Regarding informa9on sources, the flaneur focuses on alterna9ve channels such as travel blogs, habitual guidebooks, and direct interac9on with locals, rather than the peer-review pla3orms common in other modes. In terms of decision-making, flaneurs are also guided by the affect heuris9c <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">(Slovic et al., 2006)</ref>, like people in go-with-the-flow mode, but the affec9ve evalua9on is here based on the criterium of authen9city. This mode of visi9ng urban a8rac9ons is intertwined with the discoverers iden9ty which is highlighted by dis9nguishing oneself by leveraging one's knowledge of the city <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bourdieu, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b109">Yolal, 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Lastly, habitual discovery aligns strongly with Decrop and Snelders' (2005) "habitual vaca9oner," who revisits the same places to feel at home. Reflec9ng  <ref type="formula">2004</ref>) theory of interac9on ritual chains, these habitual prac9ces create strong emo9onal and moral associa9ons with par9cular symbols due to the effervescence experienced during the ritual itself. This theore9cal insight helps explain why travelers in habitual mode repeatedly revisit familiar places, deriving posi9ve psychological benefits from such rituals <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">(Singh et al., 2020)</ref>. Indeed, exis9ng research supports the idea that rituals enhance the enjoyment derived from consump9on <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">(Vohs et al., 2013)</ref>. Recognizing these ritualis9c decisionmaking processes has clear implica9ons for tourism and hospitality management, sugges9ng that fostering symbolic and ritualis9c associa9ons with hospitality brands can effec9vely increase customer loyalty and overall sa9sfac9on.</p><p>The ini9al goal of this exploratory interview study was to understand the impact of peerreview pla3orms and UGC on urban discovery. While we observed that they can play an important role, we find that travelers s9ll turn to a wide range of content and prac9ces beyond comparing online reviews. UGC pla3orms most strongly influence instrumental-ra9onal discoverers who want to be sure they get the best value for their money and 9me. However, this study also emphasizes the importance of alterna9ve informa9on sources such as word-of-mouth or simply wandering the city.</p><p>In contrast, those in go-with-the-flow mode seek serendipity and flexibility, while people in flaneur mode are looking for enchantment, authen9city, and taste broadening. Future research can inves9gate how to capture the a8en9on of people in these la8er modes. For example, through alterna9ve features and affordances, such as maintaining mystery through non-standardized ra9ngs</p><p>or removing the op9on to make reserva9ons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2.2.">Implica7ons for the urban a=rac7on ecosystem</head><p>These five discovery modes have important implica9ons for contemporary challenges within the urban a8rac9on ecosystem. For instance, the self-propelling effect of UGC observed by Van Der Zee and colleagues (2018, 2020) appears to stem primarily from instrumental-ra9onal discovery.</p><p>Travelers in this mode are most likely to select a8rac9ons with the largest number of highly rated reviews, thus reinforcing a cycle in which popular a8rac9ons a8ract s9ll more a8en9on.</p><p>However, flaneur and go-with-the-flow mode hold poten9al to break these hotspot-effects by their desire for serendipity and discovering hidden gems. Flaneurs ac9vely seek out less-traveled routes and unique experiences. They priori9ze exploring local culture and contribute posi9vely to the local economy. Based on our research findings, we argue that such attudes foster sustainable interac9ons with urban environments, encouraging respect for local culture and heritage, suppor9ng</p><p>local businesses, and mi9ga9ng the ecological impacts associated with travel.</p><p>People discovering in go-with-the-flow mode do not necessarily seek these less-traveled routes but like to casually wander through ci9es, spontaneously deciding where to go based on immediate surroundings and personal impulses. Unlike flaneurs, who possess cultural capital that allows them to appreciate historically or culturally rich but visually less appealing areas, go-with-theflow travelers might lack such background knowledge. Consequently, they might gravitate toward easily accessible, a8rac9ve, and oeen tourist-heavy areas. However, as noted previously, these two playful modes can blend, meaning a go-with-the-flow discoverer might also possess the cultural capital needed to avoid tourist traps.</p><p>Despite this poten9al for blending, our research suggests that tourismifica9on-the prolifera9on of inauthen9c or low-quality establishments-arises predominantly from purely gowith-the-flow or habitual discovery. Iconic sites like Barcelona's Sagrada Familia or Brussels' Grand Place are typically surrounded by global fast-food chains and businesses that masquerade as authen9c local experiences <ref type="bibr">(Ganzaroli, De Noni, &amp; Van Baalen, 2017)</ref>. Discoverers in habitual or gowith-the-flow modes, who oeen prefer an unplanned approach, can be easily lured by these convenient op9ons that cater to high foot traffic and brand recogni9on.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2.3.">Mul7ple factors influence which discovery mode is adopted</head><p>This study emphasizes that-while various models and theories of informa9on behavior and decision-making shed valuable light on urban discovery-no single approach fully captures the complexity of how individuals discover a city. Consistent with <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Lepp and Gibson (2008)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">Tran and Ralston (2006)</ref>, our study confirms the important role of personality, par9cularly openness to experience and need for cogni9ve closure, in shaping discovery behavior. However, our findings show that the expression of these traits depends on the situa9on.</p><p>In line with previous research <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Lehto et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tse &amp; Cro8s, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b96">Vogt &amp; Fesenmaier, 1998)</ref>, we observe that familiarity with a city s9mulates novelty seeking, as captured by the go-withthe-flow mode. Our findings extend this literature by revealing that familiarity not only encourages spontaneous explora9on but also enhances social and flaneur discovery, since travelers possess richer background knowledge and stronger social connec9ons within familiar environments.</p><p>Conversely, unfamiliarity amplifies a traveler's desire for cogni9ve closure, resul9ng in more reliance on instrumental-ra9onal decision-making, while significant cultural unfamiliarity triggers habitual discovery, exemplified by travelers seeking out familiar comfort foods from global chains.</p><p>Furthermore, our findings support <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Kozak's (2010)</ref> claim that interpersonal constraints increase decision-making complexity in travel groups. Heterogeneous groups, facing diverse interests and physical constraints, typically favor instrumental-ra9onal decision-making. For example, one par9cipant described carefully researching loca9ons to accommodate mobility constraints. Habitual discovery also arises in these groups due to preferences for predictable environments, especially among families with children who value familiar, comfor9ng experiences. In contrast, homogeneous travel par7es rely more on shared tastes and intui9ons, enabling spontaneous affec9ve decisionmaking typical of go-with-the-flow or flaneur discovery.</p><p>Consistent with <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Moore et al. (2012)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Tse and Cro8s (2005)</ref>, our findings highlight 7me constraints as influen9al contextual factors. Limited 9me and unforeseen changes in planning leads travelers to seek predictable experiences, hence adop9ng habitual discovery mode. Conversely, ample 7me s9mulates spontaneous explora9on, consistent with go-with-the-flow mode.</p><p>Age also emerged as a significant factor influencing discovery modes, paralleling findings by <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Kim et al. (2015)</ref>. Younger travelers, seeking efficiency and convenience, oeen prefer instrumental- </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Prac;cal implica;ons</head><p>Besides theore9cal contribu9ons, our research offers valuable guidance to pla3orm providers about how to design pla3orms that meet a variety of user needs and how hospitality service providers best present themselves on these pla3orms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1.">Prac7cal implica7ons for industrializa7on and business strategy</head><p>Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Leiper (2008,</ref> We understand tourism not as a single industry but as a collec9on of industries). Leiper conceptualizes industrializa9on as the combina9on of collabora9on and specific targe9ng to the same customer group <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Leiper et al., 2008)</ref>. The rise of digital pla3orms has introduced new industrializa9on strategies, from collabora9ng with influencers to managing online ra9ngs. In this context, our findings suggest that industrializa9on is most effec9ve when targeted not just to customers, but to their specific discovery modes. Different discovery modes can be swayed by different industrializa9on strategies, leading to different urban a8rac9on industries.</p><p>Instrumental-ra9onal discoverers will be most effec9vely a8racted by a high volume of posi9ve ra9ngs on review pla3orms. Strategies to achieve this include offering incen9ves for posi9ve reviews or, as some have noted, even pos9ng fake ones <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Filieri, 2016</ref>). An alterna9ve strategy could be to develop an independent review organiza9on to build trust with this discerning group.</p><p>Go-with-the-flow discoverers, on the other hand, are more effec9vely a8racted by eyecatching markers that trigger their impulsivity. This requires collabora9on through though3ul urban planning and nudging people to discover different parts of the city.</p><p>The social discovery mode is best targeted by s9mula9ng people to talk about the urban a8rac9on. This can be done, for example, by cul9va9ng posi9ve word-of-mouth, collabora9ng with social media influencers to make and distribute content about the urban a8rac9on, and by crea9ng an instagrammable décor.</p><p>Flaneurs, on the other hand, are best swayed by an interes9ng story behind the urban a8rac9on. This can be done by integra9ng the history of the loca9on into the service provided and by collabora9ng with historians, writers, or documentary makers.</p><p>Lastly, people in habitual mode are best swayed by familiarity, brand recogni9on, and customer loyalty programs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2.">Prac7cal implica7ons for plaEorm providers</head><p>Our findings show that the discovery mode influences which pla3orm features and content are u9lized and valued. For instance, when users explore in instrumental-ra9onal mode, filter func9onali9es and access to reviews and ra9ngs are important. In this mode, individuals are looking for high afforded diagnos9city, i.e., how well a pla3orm affords to "systema9cally and effec9vely</p><p>search and compare relevant alterna9ves un9l reaching a final choice" <ref type="bibr">(Yi et al., 2010, p. 4)</ref>.</p><p>Conversely, for individuals in flaneur mode, reviews and ra9ngs hold li8le value. Instead, they are drawn to detailed background informa9on and resources that allow a deeper explora9on of urban a8rac9ons' history, authen9city, and an aesthe9c presenta9on on the pla3orm. We discuss the prac9cal implica9ons of our findings more extensively in the a8ached impact statement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Limita;ons and future studies</head><p>Although our data was primarily collected pre-COVID-19, we observe that our findings remain relevant today. The abstrac9on of our discovery modes allows to incorporate new emerging discovery prac9ces (e.g., the role of TikTok in urban discovery). Furthermore, our most recent interviews corroborate our earlier results. Specifically, we iden9fied few new codes, and those we did find did not challenge our typology. Instead, they added addi9onal nuance, enriching the framework.</p><p>While our qualita9ve methodology was well-suited for this exploratory study, it imposes limits on the generalizability of the results. Although we iden9fy five discovery modes, we cannot es9mate their prevalence. To address this, future research could employ diary studies, where par9cipants log discovered urban a8rac9ons and their discovery process. These could be coupled with interviews to gain insights into decision-making and the experience of visi9ng these sites.</p><p>Future studies could expand upon our findings using quan9ta9ve methods to further explore and validate these discovery modes and their contextual rela9onships. For instance, experimental designs could simulate specific scenarios-such as planning a birthday dinner-to inves9gate preferred content and the primary mo9va9ons behind urban a8rac9on selec9on in such contexts.</p><p>Addi9onally, our findings can poten9ally be generalized to other domains. While our focus has been on hospitality and tourism, the discovery modes we propose may have broader relevance and could be adapted to markets such as e-commerce or video-on-demand.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion</head><p>This ar9cle adapts and extends Leiper's tourist a8rac9on systems framework to the context of modern urban discovery. Using a grounded theory approach, we developed an exploratory typology of five dis9nct discovery modes. Instrumental-ra9onal discoverers seek certainty and systema9cally compare a8rac9ons, while habitual discoverers favor familiarity over the op9mal choice. In contrast, playful discoverers value the journey more than the des9na9on. This group encompasses go-with-the-flow travelers, who explore spontaneously; social discoverers, guided by social interac9ons; and flaneurs, who cul9vate a roman9c rela9onship with the city.</p><p>Our typology's main contribu9on is its demonstra9on that urban discovery is not a single behavior but a spectrum, shaped by a nuanced interplay of personal, social, and contextual factors.</p><p>We iden9fied key psychological determinants-such as openness to experience, need for cogni9ve closure, and social trust-that predict which discovery mode a person will adopt in a given situa9on.</p><p>Furthermore, while acknowledging the importance of peer-review pla3orms, our findings challenge the narra9ve of digital dominance. We show that travelers con9nue to rely on a diverse range of informa9on prac9ces, from talking with locals and reading guidebooks to simply wandering through the city. By iden9fying and detailing these varied modes, par9cularly underexplored behaviors like the flaneur, this study integrates fragmented research and offers a more holis9c founda9on for understanding how people discover the contemporary city.</p><p>7. Declara4on of genera4ve AI and AI-assisted technologies in the wri4ng process</p><p>During the preparaCon of this work the authors used GPT-4o by OpenAI to improve language. The tool has only been used to correct spelling and improve language usage. ASer using this tool, the authors reviewed and edited the content as needed and take full responsibility for the content of the publicaCon. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Bibliography</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>when I have something in my mind, let's say a restaurant, then I try to look at one site; see what people are saying about it; I also try at another site; again see what the reac9ons are. Then I try to make a synthesis of whether it's 'YES' or 'NO' and what the opinion of the majority is."Furthermore, instrumental-ra9onal discoverers me9culously plan their trips to op9mize their 9me-spending and to ensure the success of their travels. Par9cipant 23 underlines the benefits of this approach: "it's easier to figure out everything in advance so that you get the most out of your visit." Once ra9onal-instrumental discoverers se8le on a plan, they s9ck to it, valuing predictability and certainty above spontaneous decisions: "yes, I really do follow the recommenda9on strictly. Then I'm sure I won't be disappointed by going somewhere else." (Par9cipant 10). Their quest for predictability leads them to leverage remote access affordances extensively, for instance making reserva9ons and buying 9ckets online beforehand.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Theore9cal framework of the five discovery modes</figDesc><graphic coords="31,73.40,83.27,451.18,249.73" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Par9cipant 22 :</head><label>22</label><figDesc>"If I receive a recommenda9on from someone, and I'm not familiar with the place, I'll usually google it. I check what kind of restaurant it is, what descrip9ons are available, what comments it gets, and what ra9ng it has. I wouldn't easily walk into a place I know nothing about and have no background informa9on on."</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ra9onal modes, leveraging intermediaries like TripAdvisor or Instagram. Simultaneously, younger travelers also embrace go-with-the-flow discovery more readily than older individuals. Older travelers, leveraging cultural capital and experience, are more inclined toward flaneur discovery, consistent with<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Kim et al. (2009)</ref>, reflec9ng their desire for authen9c urban explora9on.Moreover, our study breaks new ground by explicitly highligh9ng affec9ve factors-par9cularly mood and charm-as pivotal elements shaping discovery behaviors. A posi9ve mood fosters openness to experience and encourages spontaneous, affec9ve decision-making. Conversely, nega9ve moods such as discomfort or fa9gue elevate cogni9ve closure, steering travelers toward instrumental-ra9onal or habitual modes. Charm, as noted by par9cipants, significantly enhances affec9ve decision-making and prompts spontaneous explora9on.By integra9ng these personal, social, contextual, demographic, and affec9ve dimensions, our grounded typology of discovery modes deepens exis9ng theore9cal understandings of tourism decision-making. It reveals how travelers fluidly shie between modes based on internal predisposi9ons and external condi9ons, underscoring the complexity and context-dependency of urban explora9on behaviors.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Afshardoost, M., &amp; Eshaghi, M. S. (2020). DesCnaCon image and tourist behavioural intenCons: A meta-analysis. Tourism Management, 81, 104154. h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2020.104154</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="4,73.40,301.67,435.38,272.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Summary sta9s9cs of sample</figDesc><table><row><cell>Frequency</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Summary of our grounded theory</figDesc><table><row><cell>4.1. The five discovery modes</cell></row><row><cell>4.1.1. Instrumental-ra1onal discovery mode</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Individuals discovering the city in go-with-the-flow mode prefer spontaneity over predictability, oeen eschewing certainty in favor of serendipity. As Par9cipant 12 reflects: "serendipity is the fact that in a city, you let yourself be led by the unexpected and actually end up by chance in streets or</figDesc><table><row><cell>neighborhoods that you don't know, but that always gives me a very posi9ve feeling. I like it very</cell></row><row><cell>much 'serendipity'. It oPen leads to the best experiences because you don't have any expecta9ons</cell></row><row><cell>beforehand."</cell></row></table><note><p>Par9cipant 121 expresses: "It's sa9sfying when you can say that you did a good job discovering a hidden gem. If you tell others about it-a nice discovery by chance-that makes you a bit proud." 4.1.2. Go-with-the-flow discovery mode</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This is nicely illustrated by Par9cipant 46: "I know the city, so I don't have to check if everything is good online, because I already know it or heard</figDesc><table><row><cell>While a posi7ve mood encourages openness to experience and affec9ve decision-making, a</cell></row><row><cell>nega7ve mood discourages openness to experience and instead encourages cogni9ve closure, as</cell></row><row><cell>Par9cipant 37 explains: "If I am starving; it is raining; I am soaked; yeah, maybe I will be happy that</cell></row><row><cell>Google will suggest me anything. Why not? You don't have fuel anymore; it's raining, whatever. But</cell></row><row><cell>otherwise, I s9ll make my own decisions."</cell></row></table><note><p>about it. Or like I said, I've seen it on Instagram… But also, I like to walk around, and if I encounter something lovely, I keep it on a list on my phone." Conversely, unfamiliarity enhances the desire for cogni9ve closure, making instrumental-ra9onal discovery more appealing: "If you go to a new city and something is popular and scores really well on TripAdvisor and if you go and look on Instagram it also looks really nice, even if it's popular I'll go there. Then I make a reserva9on if necessary. If it's in my own city I'm more likely to look for a place that's really new and less popular." Moreover, cultural unfamiliarity promotes habitual discovery, as Par9cipant 126 explains: "Certainly if you go to a country that is very unfamiliar, let's say Vietnam or Thailand, aPer a while you had enough, and you just want comfort food. You want to go to a McDonalds, KFC or Burger King."</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Habitus, Capital, and Pa%erns of Taste in Tourism ConsumpCon: A Study of Western Tourism Consumers in India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1096348012461550</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1177/1096348012461550" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Hospitality &amp; Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Between post-flâneur and smartphone zombie: Smartphone users&apos; altering visual a%enCon and walking behavior in public space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Argin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Turkoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISPRS InternaGonal Journal of Geo-InformaGon</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">700</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Examining credibility percepCons and online travelers&apos; ajtude toward using user-generated content</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ayeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Au</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Do we believe in TripAdvisor?</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of rouCnes in the vacaCon decision-making process of Dutch vacaConers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bargeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Van Der Poel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="720" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The design of browsing and berrypicking techniques for the online search interface</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Online Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="424" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design dimensions enabling divergent behaviour across physical, digital, and social library interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Björneborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Persuasive Technology: 5th InternaGonal Conference, PERSUASIVE 2010</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Copenhagen, Denmark</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-06-07">2010. June 7-10, 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="149" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>a)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design dimensions enabling divergent behaviour across physical, digital, and social library interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Björneborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010b</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="149" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three key affordances for serendipity: Toward a framework connecCng environmental and personal factors in serendipitous encounters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Björneborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of DocumentaGon</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">DisGncGon: A social criGque of the judgement of taste</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bourdieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grounded Theory and SensiCzing Concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/160940690600500304</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1177/160940690600500304" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of QualitaGve Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progress in informaCon technology and tourism management: 20 years on and 10 years aSer the Internet-The state of eTourism research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Buhalis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="609" to="623" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Looking for informaGon: A survey of research on informaGon seeking, needs, and behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Case</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Given</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Emerald Group Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consumer behaviour in tourism: Concepts, influences and opportuniCes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Prayag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moital</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Issues in Tourism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="872" to="909" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">InteracGon ritual chains</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton university press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Costa</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccrae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Neo Personality Inventory</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Psychological AssociaCon</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Travel inspiraCon in tourist decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kirillova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104484</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theorizing tourist behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Decrop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9781315858265-24&amp;type=chapterpdf</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://api.taylorfrancis.com/content/chapters/edit/download?idenCfierName=doi&amp;idenCfierValue=10.4324/9781315858265-24&amp;type=chapterpdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Routledge handbook of tourism markeGng</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="267" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A grounded typology of vacaCon decision-making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Decrop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Snelders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2003.11.011</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2003.11.011" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The trustworthiness of online channels for experience-and goaldirected search tasks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dickinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The informaCon flaneur: A fresh look at informaCon seeking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dörk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Carpendale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in CompuGng Systems</title>
		<meeting>the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in CompuGng Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1215" to="1224" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a decision making model for city break travel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dunne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Flanagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Buckley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of Culture, Tourism and Hospitality Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">InformaCon encountering re-encountered: A conceptual re-examinaCon of serendipity in the context of informaCon acquisiCon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Erdelez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Makri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of DocumentaGon</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="731" to="751" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What makes an online consumer review trustworthy?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Filieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why do travelers trust TripAdvisor? Antecedents of trust towards consumer-generated media and its influence on recommendaCon adopCon and word of mouth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Filieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Alguezaui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mcleay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2015.05.007</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2015.05.007" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serendipity and informaCon seeking: An empirical study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Foster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of DocumentaGon</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Catching eyes of social media wanderers: How pictorial and textual cues in visitor-generated content shape users&apos; cogniCve-affecCve psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2023.104815</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2023.104815" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104815</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vicious advice: Analyzing the impact of TripAdvisor on the quality of restaurants as part of the cultural heritage of Venice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ganzaroli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>De Noni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Baalen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2017.03.019</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2017.03.019" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="510" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vicious advice: Analyzing the impact of TripAdvisor on the quality of restaurants as part of the cultural heritage of Venice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ganzaroli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>De Noni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Baalen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="510" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Understanding the power of word-of-mouth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Gildin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="106" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>RAM. Revista de Administração Mackenzie</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Permission markeGng: Turning strangers into friends and friends into customers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Godin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Simon and Schuster</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NaturalisCc Decision Making and OrganizaCons: Reviewing PragmaCc Science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Millward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kyriakidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0170840606065701</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">OrganizaGon Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="925" to="942" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The manager&apos;s dilemma: A conceptualizaCon of online review manipulaCon strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gössling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-C</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Issues in Tourism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="484" to="503" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A criCcal review of determinants of informaCon search behavior and uClizaCon of online reviews in decision making process (invited paper for &apos;luminaries&apos; special issue of InternaConal Journal of Hospitality Management)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gursoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of Hospitality Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preferences regarding external informaCon sources: A conjoint analysis of visitors to Sardinia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gursoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Del Chiappa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Italy. Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism MarkeGng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="806" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An IntegraCve Model of Tourists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gursoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mccleary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InformaCon Search Behaviour. Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="373" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital Content MarkeCng&apos;s Role in Fostering Consumer Engagement, Trust, and Value: Framework, Fundamental ProposiCons, and ImplicaCons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hollebeek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Macky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.intmar.2018.07.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of InteracGve MarkeGng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Consumer behaviour in tourism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Horner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Swarbrooke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serendipity and Independent Travel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mcgehee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcgee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Goetcheus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/02508281.2014.11081765</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism RecreaGon Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Independent traveler decision-making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hyde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S1871-3173(08)02003-X/full/html</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1016/S1871-3173(08)02003-X/full/html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in culture, tourism and hospitality research</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Emerald Group Publishing Limited</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="151" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nature of independent travel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hyde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antecedents and outcomes of desCnaCon image of Malaysia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aziz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sambasivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bojei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jhtm.2017.05.001</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhtm.2017.05.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Hospitality and Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of the internet for trip planning: A generaConal analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fesenmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism MarkeGng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building a model of local food consumpCon on trips and holidays: A grounded theory approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Scarles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of Hospitality Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Holiday taking decisions -The role of spouses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kozak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2010.01.014</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2010.01.014" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="494" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visitor a%racCon management: A criCcal review of research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Leask</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2016.06.015</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2016.06.015" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="334" to="361" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2016. 2009. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of prior desCnaCon experience on online informaCon search behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Lehto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D.-Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Morrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism and Hospitality Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="160" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The framework of tourism: Towards a definiCon of tourism, tourist, and the tourist industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Leiper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourist a%racCon systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Leiper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0160-7383(90)90004-B</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/0160-7383(90)90004-B" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="384" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Big Success, Big Mistake, at Big Banana: MarkeCng Strategies in Road-Side A%racCons and Theme Parks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Leiper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1300/j073v06n03_07</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism MarkeGng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why &apos;the tourism industry&apos; is misleading as a generic expression: The case for the plural variaCon, &apos;tourism industries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Leiper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2007.03.015</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2007.03.015" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Leiper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Firth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13683500802140299</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1080/13683500802140299" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ParCal IndustrialisaCon in Tourism: A New Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="235" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SensaCon seeking and tourism: Tourist role, percepCon of risk and desCnaCon choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lepp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2007.08.002</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2007.08.002" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="740" to="750" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourists&apos; cultural competence: A cosmopolitan perspecCve among Asian tourists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">X F</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Tsaur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-R</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2020.104207</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2020.104207" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104207</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Celebrity endorsement in tourism: A%enCon, emoConal arousal and familiarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Moyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kralj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2023.104750</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2023.104750" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104750</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leisure &amp; travel as class signifier: DisCncCon pracCces of China&apos;s new rich</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tmp.2019.100627</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tmp.2019.100627" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management PerspecGves</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">100627</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On-site decision-making in smartphone-mediated contexts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Gretzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104424</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building EffecCve Recommender Systems for Tourists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Massimo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ricci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/aaai.12057</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1002/aaai.12057" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AI Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ElaboraCng on grounded theory in tourism research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ma%eucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gnoth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time for a Radical Reappraisal of Tourist Decision Making? Toward a New Conceptual Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mccabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">(</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Spring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0047287515592973</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ConcepCons and Correlates of Openness to Experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mccrae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/B978-012134645-4/50032-9</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/B978-012134645-4/50032-9" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Personality Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="825" to="847" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ExaminaCon of grounded theory analysis with an applicaCon to hospitality research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mehmetoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Alcnay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of Hospitality Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards Sustainable RecommendaCons in Urban Tourism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Merinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/3640457.3688016</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1145/3640457.3688016" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">18th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1330" to="1334" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic in-desCnaCon decisionmaking: An adjustment model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Smallman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Simmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2011.07.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="645" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Couple dynamics in household tourism decision making: Women as the gatekeepers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Mojar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Quinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/135676670401000205</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1177/135676670401000205" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of VacaGon MarkeGng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring word-of-mouth influences on travel decisions: Friends and relaCves vs. other travellers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mascardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Benckendorff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1470-6431.2007.00608.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of Consumer Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="517" to="527" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progress in informaCon technology and tourism management: 30 years on and 20 years aSer the internet-RevisiCng Buhalis &amp; Law&apos;s landmark study about eTourism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Navío-Marco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ruiz-Gómez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sevilla-Sevilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="460" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progress in Tourism Management: Is urban tourism a paradoxical research domain? Progress since 2011 and prospects for the future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Duignan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2023.104737</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2023.104737" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104737</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the adopCon and processing of online holiday reviews: A grounded theory approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Papathanassis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Knolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Caught in the maze: ExploraCon of the &apos;tourist trap&apos; phenomenon. Tourism Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Polus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Naucyal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Naucyal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2024.105009</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2024.105009" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105009</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of social media influencers on travel decisions: The role of trust in consumer decision journey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R.-A</forename><surname>Pop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Săplăcan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D.-C</forename><surname>Dabija</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-A</forename><surname>Alt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Issues in Tourism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="843" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electronic word of mouth in tourism and hospitality consumer behaviour: State of the art</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pourfakhimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Coetzee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="661" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recommender systems: Do they have a viable business model in e-tourism?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Rabanser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ricci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">InformaGon and CommunicaGon Technologies in Tourism 2005</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="160" to="171" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourism a%racCon systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1016/s0160-7383(02)00026-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1048" to="1064" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ritzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The McDonaldizaGon of society: Into the digital age</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SAGE Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Item selecCon and validaCon of a brief, 15-item version of the Need for Closure Scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Roets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Hiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.paid.2010.09.004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Individual Differences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Resonance: A sociology of our relaGonship to the world</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">To Rome with love: A moderated mediaCon model in Roman heritage consumpCon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Scarpi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Raggio%o</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2018.10.030</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2018.10.030" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="401" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New consumer behavior: A review of research on eWOM and hotels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Serra Cantallops</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Salvi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijhm.2013.08.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of Hospitality Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time investments in rituals are associated with social bonding, affect and subjecCve health: A longitudinal study of Diwali in two Indian communiCes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tewari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kesberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Karl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bulbulia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical TransacGons of the Royal Society B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">375</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1805">2020. 1805. 20190430</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building and tesCng theories of decision making by travellers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sirakaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Woodside</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2004.05.004</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2004.05.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="815" to="832" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The affect heurisCc</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Finucane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Macgregor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ejor.2005.04.006</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejor.2005.04.006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of OperaGonal Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">177</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1333" to="1352" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PROCESS STUDIES OF TOURISTS&apos; DECISION-MAKING</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Smallman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.annals.2009.10.014</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.annals.2009.10.014" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Montero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ballon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Does the bubble go beyond?: An exploraGon of the urban filter bubble. 3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sharing tourism experiences in social media: A literature review and a set of suggested business strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Socriadis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/IJCHM-05-2016-0300</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online travel reviews as persuasive communicaCon: The effects of content type, source, and cerCficaCon logos on consumer behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sparks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Perkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Buckley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2013.03.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining virtual reality: Dimensions determining telepresence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Steuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">CommunicaGon in the Age of Virtual Reality</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="39" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Corbin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Basics of qualitaGve research techniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sage publicaCons</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TesCng an integrated desCnaCon image model across residents and tourists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stylidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Belhassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2016.10.014</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2016.10.014" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourist group holiday decision-making and behaviour: The influence of children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Thornton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0261-5177(97)00017-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consumer reviews and the creaCon of booking transacCon value: Lessons from the hotel industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Robertson-Ring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InternaGonal Journal of Hospitality Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourist preferences influence of unconscious needs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ralston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.annals.2005.10.014</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.annals.2005.10.014" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antecedents of novelty seeking: InternaConal visitors&apos; propensity to experiment across Hong Kong&apos;s culinary tradiCons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cro%s</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="965" to="968" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systemaCc literature review of the theory of planned behavior in tourism, leisure and hospitality management research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ulker-Demirel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cisci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jhtm.2020.04.003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Hospitality and Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding pa%erns in urban tourist behaviour: A social network analysis approach based on TripAdvisor reviews</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van Der Zee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bertocchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">org/10.1007/s40558-018-0128-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InformaGon Technology &amp; Tourism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DistribuCon of tourists within urban heritage desCnaCons: A hot spot/cold spot analysis of TripAdvisor data as support for desCnaCon management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van Der Zee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bertocchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vanneste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13683500.2018.1491955</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Issues in Tourism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tried and tested: The impact of online hotel reviews on consumer consideraCon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vermeulen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Seegers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expanding the funcConal informaCon search model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fesenmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="578" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rituals enhance consumpCon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Vohs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Norton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1714" to="1721" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of smartphones in mediaCng the tourisCc experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fesenmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourists&apos; percepCons towards and saCsfacCon with service quality in the cross-cultural service encounter: ImplicaCons for hospitality and tourism management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Weiermair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Managing Service Quality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general model of traveler desCnaCon choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Woodside</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lysonski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grounded theory of leisure travel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Woodside</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Macdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Burford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism MarkeGng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The wayfinding process relaConships between decision-making and landmark uClity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">(</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Cecilia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Arrowsmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cartwright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2007.05.010</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2007.05.010" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Travel informaCon search. Handbook of E-Tourism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fesenmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of social media in online travel informaCon search</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Gretzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2009.02.016</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2009.02.016" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">InformaCon technology and consumer behavior in travel and tourism: Insights from travel planning using the internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Magnini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fesenmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="244" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reaching audiences through travel vlogs: The perspecCve of involvement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Mohammadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pearce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2021.104326</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2021.104326" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104326</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of user-generated content on traveler behavior: An empirical invesCgaCon on the effects of e-word-of-mouth to hotel online bookings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="634" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Towards organized search and unexpected discoveries: The impacts of product tags and featured users on online product search</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Benbasat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="h%ps://aisel.aisnet.org/icis2010_submissions/189/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AuthenCcity, commodificaCon, and McDonaldizaCon of tourism experiences in the context of cultural tourism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yolal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The handbook of managing and markeGng tourism experiences</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Emerald Group Publishing Limited</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="233" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b110">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of Instagram in the UNESCO&apos;s creaCve city of gastronomy: A case study of Macau</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-E</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2019.05.011</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2019.05.011" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b111">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coloring the desCnaCon: The role of color psychology on Instagram</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-E</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tourman.2020.104110</idno>
		<ptr target="h%ps://doi.org/10.1016/j.tourman.2020.104110" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b112">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The efficacy of the theory of planned behavior for predicCng intenCons to choose a travel desCnaCon: A review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yuzhanin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/TR-11-2015-0055</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tourism Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b113">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tourist-acCvated networks: ImplicaCons for dynamic bundling and en route recommendaCons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Gretzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InformaGon Technology &amp; Tourism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b114">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wives involvement in tourism decision processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zalatan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Tourism Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="890" to="903" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
