<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The affective and linguistic roots of gender stereotypes Does grammatical gender influence the affective meanings attached to social categories in French and German?</title>
				<funder ref="#_SmcjKav #_pJfaTUv">
					<orgName type="full">Agence Nationale de la Recherche</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">ANR</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_dfRvdxC">
					<orgName type="full">DFG (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Diego</forename><surname>Dametto</surname></persName>
							<email>diego.dametto@fh-potsdam.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Potsdam University of Applied Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Urban Futures</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Potsdam University of Applied Sciences Kiepenheuerallee</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14469</postCode>
									<settlement>Potsdam</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Luc</forename><surname>Vieira</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Paris Cité</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tania</forename><surname>Noël</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Liège</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tobias</forename><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Potsdam University of Applied Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cristina</forename><surname>Aelenei</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Paris Cité</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christophe</forename><surname>Blaison</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Paris Cité</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The affective and linguistic roots of gender stereotypes Does grammatical gender influence the affective meanings attached to social categories in French and German?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8E7B14924173EB052D02F7360984CC18</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.23668/psycharchives.14237</idno>
					<note type="submission">The affective and linguistic roots of gender stereotypes</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>gendered language</term>
					<term>affective meanings</term>
					<term>EPA dimensions</term>
					<term>generic masculine</term>
					<term>gender fair language</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper compares the affective meanings attributed to feminine and masculine versions of the same social categories. We collected semantic differential ratings for 192 pairs of masculine and feminine social categories from two representative samples of n = 700 French and n = 700 German participants. We investigated how lexical and grammatical gender influences the affective meaning of social categories on Osgood's dimensions of evaluation, potency, and activity, as well as how differences in affective meaning are related to known gender stereotypes. Our results suggest that gender does produce only small effects. However, they are not randomly distributed and consistent with well-known gender stereotypes.</p><p>The results enrich social psychological research on gender as well as the cultural debate on the use of gender-fair language in grammatically gendered languages by providing a more nuanced assessment of the affective roots of gender stereotypes conveyed by language.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Symbolic interactionism <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Mead, 1934;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Goffman, 1959)</ref> sees language as key to socialization and the maintenance of social order <ref type="bibr">(Heise et al., 2015)</ref>. Beyond practical knowledge conveyed through denotative meanings <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Berger &amp; Luckmann, 1966)</ref>, language carries affective meanings shared among members of the same culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Heise, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ambrasat et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dametto et al., 2023)</ref> and captured by the cross-cultural dimensions Evaluation-Potency-Activity (EPA; <ref type="bibr">Osgood et al., 1957;</ref><ref type="bibr">Osgood et al., 1975)</ref>. In fact, culture can be seen as the totality of socially transmitted and intersubjectively shared affective meanings that constrain and guide social interaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Heise, 2007)</ref>. Through everyday encounters and interactions, this affective knowledge is continuously enacted and, according to Affect Control Theory (ACT), underlies the impression formation process by providing the backbone of situational appraisal <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Heise, 2007)</ref>. In this way, the affective meanings encapsulated in the language are inextricably intertwined with stereotypes <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Schröder et al., 2013)</ref>. The overall research goal of this paper is to understand how the use of the feminine versus masculine version of various social categories relates to affective meanings attributed to these social categories¹. Such a goal is of particular importance in the context of grammatically gendered languages <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Sczesny et al., 2016)</ref>. Contrary to English, in gendered languages like French and German, gender is salient, promoting and reinforcing gender associations and stereotypes encapsulated in semantics <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Gygax et al., 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Garg et al., 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Lewis &amp; Lupyan, 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Charlesworth et al., 2021)</ref>. Usage of gender-fair language can reduce gender stereotyping by counteracting the representativity bias elicited by the generic masculine in French <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Vervecken et al., 2015)</ref> and German <ref type="bibr">(Irmen &amp; Roßberg, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Horvath et al., 2016)</ref>. Nevertheless, in the context of professional roles, researchers have identified a potential negative impact of the feminine form on women. This is due to the activation of stereotypical representations, which may result in less favorable judgments <ref type="bibr">(Formanowicz et al., 2013)</ref> and lower salary estimates <ref type="bibr">(Horvath et al., 2016)</ref>. The present study contributes to this debate by examining how affective meanings ascribed to gendered social categories vary across semantic categories and affective space as defined by the EPA dimensions. The analysis is based on EPA ratings for 192 social categories in both genders, totaling 384 items, collected from 700 French and 700 German participants, representative of their countries by age, gender, and location.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theoretical background</head><p>Osgood and colleagues identified and validated three key dimensions for affective meanings across cultures <ref type="bibr">(1957,</ref><ref type="bibr">1975)</ref>. The Evaluation dimension (E) assesses a social category's goodness vs. evilness, Potency (P) its strength and power, and Activity (A) its dynamism vs. passivity. Studies have applied the EPA framework to link masculine/feminine traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Langford &amp; MacKinnon, 2000)</ref>, roles <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Kroska &amp; Cason, 2019)</ref>, and tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kroska, 2003)</ref> with their affective meanings. However, these studies, conducted in English, capture gender-driven affective meanings indirectly through stereotypes <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Kroska, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Kroska &amp; Cason, 2019)</ref> or perceived gender associations <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Langford &amp; MacKinnon, 2000)</ref>. In contrast, to the best of our knowledge no EPA studies have been conducted in gendered languages like French and German where separate masculine and feminine forms (e.g., der Arzt vs. die Ärztin) directly invoke and highlight gender, making it salient <ref type="bibr">(Ridgeway, 2011)</ref>.</p><p>In the following we present three pre-registered hypotheses² about the way gender is expected to be reflected in the affective meanings associated with social categories along the EPA dimensions. To do so, we draw on social psychological work based on attitudes <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Mladinic, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr">Eagly et al., 1991)</ref> or on the "warmth/competence" framework of social perception <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Glick et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fiske et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cuddy et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Martin &amp; Slepian, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Evaluation. <ref type="bibr">Eagly and colleagues (Eagly &amp; Mladinic, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr">Eagly et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr">Eagly &amp; Mladinic, 1994)</ref> shows that women's as well as men's attitudes are more positive toward women than toward men, i.e., the "women are wonderful" effect. Similarly, using the Ambivalent Sexism Inventory <ref type="bibr">(Glick &amp; Fiske, 1997)</ref>, studies reveal a bias for viewing women in traditional roles more favorably than men <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Glick et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">2004)</ref>. This difference in attitudes toward gender reflects the segregation of roles whose evolutionary roots compelled women and men to assume communal and agentic traits, respectively <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Wood, 1999)</ref>. This separation of positive and agentic characteristics among genders, also seen in other marginalized groups <ref type="bibr">(Conway et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr">Judd et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cuddy et al., 2008)</ref>, implies that viewing lower-status groups more positively may compensate for societal structures that regard them as less capable in terms of agency <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Ridgeway, 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Yzerbyt, 2018)</ref>. Research using the Stereotype Content Model <ref type="bibr">(Fiske et al., 2002)</ref> and ACT <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Langford &amp; MacKinnon 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kroska 2001</ref>) supports women's positive evaluation. Thus, we hypothesize (HpE) that the more positive evaluation ascribed to women in general will be systematically reflected in a more positive evaluation ascribed to the feminine versions of social categories.</p><p>Potency. Status and power are fundamental for understanding social interactions and their macro-social effects <ref type="bibr">(Kemper &amp; Collins, 1990)</ref>. Repeatedly observing gendersegregated roles, especially men in power, leads to inferring power based on gender <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Steffen, 1984)</ref>. From both an evolutionary <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Schwartz &amp; Rubel-Lifschitz, 2009</ref>) and a social role perspective <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Wood, 1999)</ref>, such segregation presses men to engage in power-and status-seeking behaviors, fuelling expectations about men as more powerful and agentic. Research on the Stereotype Content Model finds men seen as "bad but bold", with their competence and agency counterbalanced by negative views <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Glick et al., 2004)</ref>.</p><p>Within ACT, <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Heise (2007)</ref> found masculine forms rated as more potent in family-related social categories (e.g., mother-father). <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Langford &amp; MacKinnon (2000)</ref> reported that stereotypically masculine traits were consistently rated as more potent compared to feminine traits. Therefore, we formulate our hypothesis as follows: social categories presented in the feminine form will mostly be perceived as less potent compared to the corresponding masculine version of the same social categories (HpP).</p><p>Activity. The effect of gender is less clear for activity. Men are perceived as more competent and agentic <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Glick et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ridgeway, 2011)</ref>, potentially raising the activity ratings of masculine categories. Conversely, feminine roles, seen as more communal, might imply greater dynamism and interpersonal agency, thus higher activity levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Kroska, 2001)</ref>. However, considering the strong correlation between potency and activity in social categories <ref type="bibr">(Osgood et al., 1957;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cuddy et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Rogers et al., 2013)</ref>, we hypothesize (HpA) that social categories presented in the feminine form will be mostly perceived as less active than the corresponding masculine social categories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cross-dimensional patterns</head><p>So far, we have proposed three one-dimensional hypotheses. According to these, feminine social categories should be rated as more positive (HpE), less potent (HpP), and less active (HpA) than their masculine counterparts. However, gender discrimination affects women in multiple ways <ref type="bibr">(Ellemers, 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barreto &amp; Doyle, 2023)</ref>, suggesting interdependence between the hypotheses. To understand how single-dimensional effects merge into crossdimensional patterns, we refer to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>'s matrix. Given the high overlap between potency and activity, we focus on evaluation and potency. The x-axis of the matrix is defined by differences on the evaluation dimension between the feminine and masculine versions of the same social category, while the y-axis is defined by differences on the potency dimension.</p><p>Evolutionary and social role perspectives hold that society accepts and encourages dominance and power-seeking in men, but not in women. Conversely, society prescribes communality more strongly for women than for men <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Wood, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Prentice &amp; Carranza, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Schwartz &amp; Rubel-Lifschitz, 2009)</ref>. As the more positive evaluation ascribed to the feminine versions of social categories (HpE) may compensate for the lower potency ascribed to them (HpP), many social categories can be expected to confirm both HpE and HpP, which corresponds to the benevolent sexism stereotype <ref type="bibr">(Glick &amp; Fiske, 1997)</ref>.</p><p>Social categories that refute both hypotheses will sit in the lower right quadrant.</p><p>Research demonstrates that when women are in powerful roles, their assertiveness is often exaggerated and perceived as dominance, which has a negative impact on their likability <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Rudman, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">Eagly &amp; Karau, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Rudman &amp; Fairchild, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rudman et al., 2012a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Williams &amp; Tiedens, 2016)</ref>. Therefore, social categories that contradict HpP are also expected to violate HpE, this way mimicking the case of hostile sexism <ref type="bibr">(Glick &amp; Fiske, 1997)</ref>.</p><p>The other two quadrants represent cases confirming one hypothesis but not the other. The lower left quadrant shows feminine categories rated more positively (HpE confirmed) and more potent (HpP disconfirmed) than masculine ones. Prior research indicates this applies to stereotypically feminine roles interpreted by men, as in the cases of passive <ref type="bibr">(Costrich et al., 1975)</ref> and modest men <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Moss-Racusin et al., 2010)</ref>, nurturing professors <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Meltzer &amp; McNulty, 2011)</ref>, and male primary school teachers <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Moss-Racusin &amp; Johnson, 2016)</ref>. Here, violating masculinity norms makes masculine categories seem less potent than feminine ones, without positive evaluation compensation <ref type="bibr">(Rudman et al., 2012b)</ref>.</p><p>Finally, In the upper right quadrant, feminine categories are viewed more negatively (HpE disconfirmed) and less potent (HpP confirmed). The glass escalator effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Williams, 1992)</ref> exemplifies this, where men gain from benevolent attitudes by advancing in traditionally feminine roles <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Meltzer &amp; McNulty 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gaunt, 2013)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods and materials</head><p>The analysis presented below is based on EPA ratings collected online in 2022 from n = 700 German and n = 700 French participants who rated the stimuli in German and French, respectively. We defined quotas with respect to gender, age, and region to obtain a stratified representation of both countries for each word set. Respondents were recruited through a commercial access panel (Bilendi S.A.) and received monetary compensation for their participation. The current results are the fruit of a secondary analysis run on a data set -the "French-German EPA dictionary" (Dametto et al., 2024) -openly available to researchers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stimuli construction</head><p>The social categories contained in the "French-German EPA dictionary" were sampled from the 929 social categories enlisted in the "2015 USA Combined Surveyor Dictionary" <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Smith-Lovin et al., 2016)</ref>, with the goal of covering the entire EPA space. Cluster analysis divided the US affective dictionary into five clusters, from which 188 categories were chosen³. The social categories were then translated into French and German genderspecific versions, e.g. a male artist: ein Künstler (German), un artiste (French); a female artist: eine Künstlerin (German), une artiste (French) through a back-translation approach.</p><p>Additionally, four categories related to sexuality and gender identity (androgynous, homophobic, transgender, asexual) were included⁴. Therefore, the final dictionary consisted of 192 social category pairs, for a total of 384 gendered social categories. Social categories were split into ten subsets (37-40 words each), ensuring a gender balance. Each subset was rated by a representative sample of 70 French and 70 German participants, totaling 140 participants, following a balanced incomplete block design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research design</head><p>Our research, rooted in ACT's classic rating procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Heise, 2007)</ref>, aims to compare EPA affective meanings between gendered social categories <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Heise, 2010)</ref>. Our method expands <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Langford and MacKinnon's (2000)</ref> approach, exploring how gender affects EPA profiles in grammatically gendered languages. Additionally, our method aligns with Goldberg's (1968) paradigm, where only the target gender changes while assessing social categories on EPA dimensions <ref type="bibr">(Rudman et al., 2012b)</ref>. Crucially, we employed a betweensubjects design, ensuring no participant rated both masculine (e.g., ein Student, un étudiant) and feminine (e.g., eine Studentin, une étudiante) versions of a category. Hence, the methodology avoids a comparison bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Biernat, 2005)</ref> and decreases any demand characteristics <ref type="bibr">(Orne, 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr">Corneille &amp; Lush, 2023)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rating procedure and semantic differential scales</head><p>Respondents rated social categories one at a time on three EPA dimension scales, with no option to skip, using bipolar semantic differentials. In the Supplementary Materials, the instructions as well as the rating instruments are presented. Participants knew the study aimed to evaluate affective perceptions of social categories, without clues on gender differences. We randomized the order of the identities and the direction of the EPA scales across participants. The bipolar anchors for the EPA dimensions have long been established in German <ref type="bibr">(Schröder, 2011)</ref> and have recently been defined in French <ref type="bibr">(Dametto et al., 2023)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>We first tested our three single-dimensional hypotheses and, secondly, explored crossdimensional interactions. The article's Supplementary Materials offer a preliminary analysis on whether respondents' gender and language affect perceptions of gendered social categories. Findings indicate no interaction between the perceiver's gender and the social category's gender, for both German and French participants. Thus, while men and women tend to produce slightly different affective ratings <ref type="bibr">(MacKinnon &amp; Keating;</ref><ref type="bibr">1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Chapman et al., 2022)</ref>, the difference between the affective meanings attributed to feminine and masculine versions of social categories is not affected by the gender of the perceiver. Therefore, we merged the ratings from both genders and both cultures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis testing: single-dimensional analysis</head><p>To test our hypotheses, we provide our results at two levels of analysis. (I) Cohen's d effect sizes were calculated for the EPA dimensions of each pair of social categories in order to quantify the differences in mean affective ratings between the masculine and feminine versions of the social categories in relation to the overall variability of the ratings⁵. A positive Cohen's d indicates the masculine version scored higher on a dimension, while a negative value indicates the feminine form was rated higher. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> lists the strongest positive and negative Cohen's d values and social categories where grammatical gender doesn't influence affective ratings. We interpreted effect sizes using thresholds from <ref type="bibr">Lovakov and Agadullina (2021)</ref>, assessing how gender impacts affective perceptions across no, small, moderate, or strong effect levels for each hypothesis. Because variation in effect size among our 192 identities could be due to type II statistical error, we analyzed their distribution to assess consistency and direction.</p><p>(II) Participant-level analysis included a mixed-effects regression model, regressing each EPA dimension ratings (dependent variable) on social category gender (independent variable). The gender of the social category was contrast coded with weights equal to -0.5 (feminine) and +0.5 (masculine). Given the balanced incomplete block design's random allocation of participants and social categories to word subsets, we used crossed random effects for both.</p><p>Evaluation. Our hypothesis (HpE) was that feminine social categories would receive more positive evaluations. Table <ref type="table">2</ref> shows mostly negative effect sizes, indicating feminine versions were indeed often rated more positively. However, gender's effect was mainly null or small, exceeding a moderate threshold in just 14 of 192 cases. Female versions were rated clearly more positively for many negatively connotated social categories (e.g. vandal, mafioso, daredevil, robber, ex-convict). Next we focused on the distribution of effect sizes for all social categories in our dataset (see Supplementary Materials Figure <ref type="figure">S2</ref>). A one sample t-test revealed that the mean effect size (M = -.09, SD =0.16) was significantly different from zero, t(191) = -8.417, p &lt; .001. In addition, the distribution was left-skewed (γ = -.41). Both results show that the gender effect is robust, with feminine categories, on average, rated more positively than masculine ones. In the same line, the mixed-model (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>) showed that participants generally rated masculine categories less positively (b = -.16, t(192) = -11.74, p &lt; .001, 95% CI <ref type="bibr">[-.19; -.13]</ref>). Thus, feminine versions of social categories receive higher average evaluation ratings, though the effect is moderate or large only in a few cases.</p><p>Potency. Following our hypothesis (HpP), we expected that masculine categories would be seen as more potent than their feminine counterparts. Table <ref type="table">2</ref> shows that the effect sizes are not systematically positive: only in relatively few cases does gender have at least a small effect on potency, such that masculine versions are rated more potent than the feminine version. Mainly, these instances involve physical jobs (garbage collector, butcher, boxer), authority figures (soldier, police agent), seduction roles (top-model, playboy), and leadership (manager, capitalist). Against our hypothesis, 24 categories, including sexual identities <ref type="bibr">(gay, androgynous, asexual, homosexual, queer, bisexual)</ref> and those linked to passivity (bum, malingerer) and creativity (artist, musician), are seen as more potent when interpreted by women, with effect sizes from small to moderate. A one-sample t-test rejected the null hypothesis (M = .03, SD = .17) with t(191) = 2.70, p = .007, indicating masculine forms were rated more potent on average than feminine.</p><p>Furthermore, the potency effect sizes were right-skewed (γ = .48; refer to Supplementary Materials Figure <ref type="figure">S3</ref>). In line with HpP, participant-level mixed-model (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>) reveals a significant yet small effect of social category gender on potency ratings (b = .05, t(192) = 3.75, p &lt; .001, 95% CI [.02; .08]). Thus, the second hypothesis appears to be only marginally supported. Participants do rate the masculine versions of social categories as slightly more potent than the corresponding feminine version. Yet, the average effect size is close to zero, and only slightly more social categories were rated as more potent in the masculine version than would be expected by chance. Nevertheless, the distribution is right-skewed, suggesting that in some cases grammatical gender does bias potency ratings in favor of the masculine version.</p><p>Activity. Contrary to our hypothesis of feminine forms being seen as less active, effect sizes are mostly negative indicating that social categories were often viewed as more active when interpreted by women (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). Among those cases, intellectual professions (judge, scientist, white collar worker, computer programmer, physician, priest, artist) stand out. The mean effect size (M = -.05, SD = .15) is significantly different from zero, t(191) = -5.15, p &lt; .001, and slightly right skewed (γ = .19; see Supplementary Materials Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4</ref>). The mixed model confirmed that the masculine forms were rated less active (b = -.09, t(192) = -6.73, p &lt; .001, 95% CI [-.12; -.07], see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref>). Thus, the results did not support our third hypothesis, but showed the opposite pattern.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploratory analysis of cross-dimensional effects</head><p>Though gender's effects on social category perceptions were generally small, we used linear regression models to examine under which conditions the effect of gender is larger <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">(Figures 2.1,</ref><ref type="table">2.2,</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2.3,</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_6">Table 6</ref>). In each model, Cohen's d effect size for an EPA dimension served as the dependent variable. Independent variables included average EPA ratings (Avg. E, Avg. P, Avg. A) aggregated over both masculine and feminine forms. To identify which form was rated higher, three variables were contrast coded (HigGenE, HigGenP, HigGenA) with -0.5 for feminine and +0.5 for masculine. We also explored interaction effects between average EPA means and contrast variables (Avg. E * HigGenE, Avg. P * HigGenP, Avg. A * HigGenA), examining how the average ratings and higher ratings by gender interacted on each dimension.</p><p>The first model assessing the gender effect on evaluation (R² = .490, F(9, 182) = 21.37, p &lt; .001) shows a significant impact of HigGenE (b = -.24, t(182) = -12.424, p &lt; .001, η2 = .46, 95% CI [-.28; -.20]), indicating stronger gender effect sizes when feminine categories score higher in evaluation than masculine ones. Thus, the latter case is more likely due to chance. Nonetheless, effect size is unaffected by the average ratings on evaluation, potency, and activity, showing stability across the affective space. There is a significant but small interaction between average potency and HigGenP (b = -.04, t(182) = -2.367, p = .019, η2 = .03, 95% CI [-.08; -.01]) indicating that in case of social categories that were rated more potent in the feminine version, the higher the potency rating, the larger the effect size on evaluation.</p><p>The second model investigates the determinants of the effect size on potency (R² = .624, F(9, 182) = 36.18, p &lt; .001) shows a significant effect of HigGenP (b = -.22, t(182) = -11.751, p &lt; .001, η2 = .53, 95% CI [-.25; -.18]), indicating weaker gender effect sizes when feminine categories score higher in potency than masculine ones. HigGenA also shows a significant, though weaker, effect (b = -.05, t(182) = -2.473, p = .014, η2 = .06, 95% CI [-.10; -.01]). Moreover, average potency affects potency effect size. The more powerful the social category, the larger the potency difference in favor of the masculine version ( = .03, t(182) = 1.845, p = .067, η2 = .02, 95% CI [.00; .06]). Thus, the absolute gender effect size is larger at the extremes, but in the opposite direction: it is larger and positive -indicating that the masculine versions are seen as more potent -when the social categories are potent. In contrast, it is larger and negative -indicating that the feminine versions are seens as more potent -when social categories are weak (i.e. the Avg. P is negative). Average evaluation also affects potency effect size (b = -.01, t(182) = -1.872, p = .063, η2 = .01, 95% CI [-.02; .00]), with negative categories showing a trend towards masculine form being seen as more potent, and positive categories trending towards feminine form being seen as more potent.</p><p>Finally, the third model examining gender effect on activity (R² = .656, F(9, 182) = 38.63, p &lt; .001) shows a significant effect of HigGenA (b = -.23, t(182) = -11.946, p &lt; .001, η2 = .57, 95% CI [-.27; -.19]), indicating stronger gender effect sizes when feminine categories score higher in activity than masculine ones. HigGenP also shows a significant, though weaker, effect (b = -.04, t(182) = -2.636, p = .009, η2 = .07, 95% CI [-.07; -.01]).</p><p>Remarkably, average activity has a significant positive effect (b = .03, t(182) = 2.346, p = .020, η2 = .03, 95% CI [.00; .06]). Thus, the more active the category, the greater the effect size, trending toward seeing the masculine form as more active. Lastly, average potency rating has a negative significant effect (b = -.03, t(182) = -1.988, p = .048, η2 = .02, 95% CI [-.06; .00]). Thus, the more potent the category, the smaller the effect size, trending toward seeing the feminine form as more active.</p><p>In summary, the analyses confirmed two out of the three hypotheses on the effect of gender on the affective meanings attributed to social categories. Our effect size analysis shows that while gender impacts on EPA dimensions are small, they reveal significant patterns. As expected, feminine versions of social categories tend to be rated more positively overall (HpE). This gender effect is constant along the entire range of the evaluation dimension. The second hypothesis (HpP) on gender's impact on potency was only partly confirmed: the masculine version of a social category is not perceived as systematically more potent than its feminine counterpart. Especially when social categories are rated as neutral on the potency dimension, the gender effect appears to be randomly distributed around zero. By contrast, the gender effect is stronger when social categories are either very potent or very impotent. Lastly, our hypothesis for activity was not supported (HpA), with feminine categories rated more active and gender effect sizes increasing oppositely at activity extremes. Contrary to our expectation, feminine social categories were rated as slightly more active, and we found a slight tendency for the intensity of the effect sizes to become larger -in the opposite direction of our expectation -at the extremes of the activity range.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploratory semantic analysis</head><p>Using Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>'s theoretical matrix, we examine the combined impact of evaluation and potency rating differences between gendered social categories. Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> locates social categories according to the effect size on the evaluation (x-axis) and potency (y-axis) dimensions. To identify categories that either support (upper left quadrant) or refute (lower right quadrant) both HpE and HpP hypotheses, we focus on 118 of 192 categories with effect sizes on evaluation or potency exceeding the small effect threshold (0.15) as defined by <ref type="bibr">Lovakov and Agadullina (2021)</ref>.</p><p>With feminine categories often rated more positively and slightly more often as less potent than masculine ones, many confirm both HpE and HpP, landing in the upper left quadrant. Moreover, many categories aligned with HpE but not HpP, with fewer cases in the remaining quadrants (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">7</ref>). To validate our approach, we inspected the quadrants to detect meaningful semantic patterns, which will be commented on in the general discussion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HpE and HpP confirmed (n = 55</head><p>). Feminine versions of traditionally threatening <ref type="bibr">(bully, gangster, mafioso, outlaw, prisoner, racist, pusher, robber, kidnapper, ex-convict, sadist, shoplifter)</ref> or somewhat intimidating (boxer, bouncer, bodyguard, neurotic, psychotic, psychiatric patient, punk) categories, along with leadership roles (banker, consultant, manager, governor, lobbyist, boss), are seen as less potent but more positive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HpE and HpP disconfirmed (n = 16</head><p>). Categories seen as less positive yet more powerful in feminine form include marginalized roles (e.g., homeless person, beggar) and sexual identities (e.g., asexual, transgender, queer, gay).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HpE confirmed and HpP disconfirmed (n = 36).</head><p>In feminine form, categories like entrepreneur, politician, army officer, attorney, prosecutor attorney, judge, and scientist are viewed as both more positive and potent.</p><p>HpE disconfirmed and HpP confirmed (n = 11). We could not identify any clear semantic patterns related to the social identities located in this quadrant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General discussion</head><p>This study explored how grammatical gender influences the affective meaning in terms of Evaluation, Potency and Activity connotations attached to social categories in French and German. Affective meanings are fundamental for the maintenance of social order <ref type="bibr">(Heise et al., 2015)</ref> because they act as vectors for disseminating norms and values. Affective meanings shape social interactions by providing the fundamental sentiments for forming impressions <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Heise, 2007)</ref> and building expectations <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Ridgeway &amp; Correll, 2006)</ref>. By doing so they not only mirror stereotypes but contribute to their sedimentation within a culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Schröder et al., 2013)</ref>. This research, therefore, plays a pivotal role in understanding the subtle yet profound ways in which language and perception interlock to perpetuate gender norms. Overall, while the direct impact of gender on affective meanings appears small at first glance, a closer look reveals nuanced, gender-specific patterns in how feminine and masculine social categories were perceived.</p><p>Evaluation. We found consistent evidence in support of our first hypothesis regarding the evaluation dimension. Social categories were often seen more positively in feminine forms, suggesting a "women are wonderful" effect embedded in French and German affective meanings <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Mladinic, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Langford &amp; MacKinnon, 2000)</ref>. This trend is consistent along the entire evaluation dimension, applying to good, neutral, and bad categories alike. Notably, we might expect that the feminine form of criminal and deviant social categories would be judged more harshly than the masculine one, due to higher evaluation standards for women <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Biernat &amp; Kobrynowicz, 1997)</ref>. However, there is no such contrast effect, and these feminine social categories are assimilated to the reference standard, suggesting -so to speak -that women cannot be so evil <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Biernat, 2005)</ref>. These findings align with gender stereotype congruence theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Rudman, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">Eagly &amp; Karau, 2002)</ref>, suggesting traits like communality and goodness are prescribed rather than inherent to gender hierarchy <ref type="bibr">(Prentice &amp; Carranza, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rudman et al., 2012a)</ref>, thus preserving positive evaluations despite violations.</p><p>Potency. The hypothesis predicting masculine categories as more potent than feminine was partly confirmed. Our results align with more recent research arguing that the perceived competence gap between genders is narrowing <ref type="bibr">(Ebert et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Eagly et al., 2020)</ref>. The analysis we presented shows a more nuanced effect of gender on potency, influenced by (I) the average potency rating and (II) gender salience. In the former case (I), gender differences are larger when either weak or strong social categories are considered, but smaller or even absent when social categories are neutral on the potency dimension. Our findings limit the "men are bold" stereotype <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Glick et al., 2004)</ref> to potent categories (e.g. banker, manager, millionaire, governor, police agent, boss). Conversely, masculine forms of weak categories (e.g., coward, beggar, looser) are seen as less potent than their feminine counterparts. One explanation is that traits like agency, dominance, and assertiveness -underpinning potency -are central to gender hierarchy, proscribing men from showing weakness <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Rudman, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">Eagly &amp; Karau, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Prentice &amp; Carranza, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rudman et al., 2012b;</ref><ref type="bibr">Krauth-Gruber &amp; Aelenei, 2022)</ref>. By violating the potency proscription, weak masculine social categories are perceived as undermining the gender hierarchy, which cause them to be contrasted away from the masculine stereotype <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Biernat &amp; Kobrynowicz, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Biernat, 2005)</ref>. From this perspective, the evaluation and potency dimensions operate differently.</p><p>However, gender still affects neutral potency-rated social categories when (II) semantics make gender salient <ref type="bibr">(Ridgeway, 2011)</ref>. Social categories related to sexual identities and behaviors (e.g., queer, homosexual, asexual) are seen as less potent in masculine forms, suggesting that masculine social categories that openly challenge the gender hierarchy are contrasted away from the gender stereotype. Potency is thus closely linked to gender <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Steffen, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Martin &amp; Slepian, 2021</ref>): Gender differences emerge when potency is salient, and potency differences emerge when social categories make the gender structure of society salient.</p><p>Activity. Feminine social categories were consistently rated more active. Contrary to our hypothesis, feminine categories were rated more active, despite strong correlation between potency and activity (r = .84). Differences in average ratings for potency (masculine M = .59, feminine M = .53) and activity (masculine M = .64, feminine M = .73) illustrate distinct gender interactions with these dimensions. Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kroska (2001)</ref>, one explanation may be that feminine social categories seem more communal, and thus more dynamic and interpersonally agentic, and active. In addition, <ref type="bibr">Freeland and Hoey (2018)</ref> suggest potency, indicating symbolic power, better reflects gender status differences than activity. This suggests that activity levels attributed to women in professional roles (e.g. scientists, programmers, physicians) reflect their perceived effort towards achieving these positions <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Tiedemann, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ellemers, 2018)</ref>.</p><p>In sum, despite small effects, clear patterns emerge showing the influence of gender on the affective meanings attributed to social categories. These patterns show how affective knowledge enacted in everyday interactions is intertwined with gender stereotypes, consistent with theories proposing that social order follows from affective meanings <ref type="bibr">(Heise et al., 2015)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploratory analysis</head><p>This paper also explores the link between social categories' affective meanings and established gender discrimination patterns. Though gender's effect on affective perception is small, cumulative small biases can result in significant societal impacts <ref type="bibr">(Payne et al., 2017)</ref>. Analysis shows that social categories mostly confirm HpE and HpP, indicating benevolent sexism <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Glick et al., 2000)</ref>. Among these, we found many deviant and criminal categories. The differing affective views on negative social categories may stem from men's higher criminal statistics <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Spjeldnes &amp; Goodkind, 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Statistisches Bundesamt, 2022a</ref>; 2022b; Ministère de la justice, 2022), likely causing women's crimes to seem more affectively dissonant <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Boyle, 2023)</ref> and less severe <ref type="bibr">(Rachlinski &amp; Wistrich, 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Our results align with findings regarding marginalized and sexual social categories that violate both HpE and HpP. Sexual categories are subject to gender-specific contrast effects and, as hypothesized in previous research <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Rudman &amp; Fairchild, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rudman et al., 2012b)</ref>, are subject to overt hostile sexism. They are systematically rated as more powerful and usually less positive when interpreted by women rather than men. Thus, by reversing the prescription for women to be 'wonderful' and for men to be 'bold', these social categories violate both HpE and HpP.</p><p>Yet, our findings only partially align with prior research on bias against female leaders <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Karau, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rudman et al., 2012a)</ref>. Our data shows some leadership roles (banker, consultant, manager, governor, lobbyist, boss) support both HpE and HpP, while others (entrepreneur, politician, army officer, attorney, prosecutor attorney, judge, scientist) confirm HpE but not HpP. Just one category (minister) contradicts both HpE and HpP, as would theoretically be expected for leadership roles. A possible explanation may be that in "business and work" contexts (MacKinnon &amp; Heise, 2010), negatively viewed leadership roles (e.g., banker, lobbyist) rate more positive in feminine forms, as women are perceived less able to fulfill these 'tough' roles' demands. Contrarily, state institution leaders (e.g., judge, prosecutor attorney) and positive leaders (e.g., entrepreneur, scientist) in the feminine form are less likely to conflict with role expectations <ref type="bibr">(Eagly &amp; Karau, 2002)</ref>. Our findings align with <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bye et al. (2022)</ref>, noting no perceived competence gap in academic, political, and leadership roles across genders. This view resonates with theories positing competence and potency's high context dependency <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Martin &amp; Slepian, 2021)</ref>, meaning ascribed potency to women and men varies with institutional leadership demands.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations</head><p>Our study, using a gender, age, and region-representative sample from Germany and France, yields findings specific to these nations, not extendable to all grammatical gender languages. Furthermore, our analysis, with a statistical power of .80 to detect effect sizes of d = .25 at .001 significance level (see Supplementary Materials "Power Analysis"), shows few cases of moderate or large gender effects. This way, we can confidently make the argument that there are consistent similarities in the affective meanings attributed to the masculine and feminine forms of social categories. Nevertheless, our analysis shows that gender has small effects on the social categories we studied, and that these effects appear to be consistent with previous theorizing and documented patterns of gender discrimination. However, more power is needed to definitively assess the magnitude and direction of these small effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contributions</head><p>The present study contributes to the social psychological but also cultural discussion on gender, especially the public debate about the use of gendered forms in grammatical gender languages. While the usage of the generic masculine form leads to overrepresentation of men against women <ref type="bibr">(Irmen &amp; Roßberg, 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Vervecken et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Sczesny et al., 2016)</ref>, researchers also noted the negative impact of gendered language on women <ref type="bibr">(Formanowicz et al., 2013</ref><ref type="bibr">, Horvath et al., 2016)</ref>. In this context, our results provide encouraging insights: the effect of gender seems to be mostly small. Mostly, the affective meanings attached to gendered social categories resemble a t-shaped rather than a bimodal distribution (Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>). Whether the increased use of feminine forms will lead to a drifting apart of affective perceptions of gendered social categories, or to a merging of affective meanings previously biased by masculine overrepresentation, is an open question that should be explored in future research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>This research investigated the interaction between gender and affective meanings attached to social categories. Our approach merged Heise's cultural survey method ( <ref type="formula">2007</ref>) with Goldberg's paradigm (1968) to test three hypotheses concerning the differences in affective meanings between feminine and masculine versions of social categories. Overall, the differences between gender forms were small. Feminine forms were generally seen as more positive, in part less potent, and somewhat more active. Moreover, differences on the evaluation and potency dimensions combine to reproduce well-known patterns of gender biases. Our research provides a detailed examination of how gender stereotypes are embedded in the affective connotations within French and German linguistic contexts, contributing to discussions on gender language and equality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Notes</head><p>[1] Aligned with social psychology, we employ "social categories" to denote the fundamental labels society uses to classify individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Haslam et al., 2000)</ref>. Within the Affect Control Theory (ACT) framework, MacKinnon and Heise (2010) and Smith-Lovin (2007) embrace a definition akin to that of <ref type="bibr">Thoits and Virshup (1997, 106-107)</ref>, who characterize social identities as "socially-constructed and meaningful categories acknowledged by individuals as representative of themselves or their group." This paper maintains the use of "social category." Consequently, we include professional roles (e.g., insurance agent, baker), identities derived from psychological or emotional traits (e.g., hothead, paranoid), and behaviors (e.g., criminal, miser, know-it-all) under the umbrella of social categories. The term gendered social categories will refer to the grammatically or lexically gender-specific versions of these social categories.</p><p>[2]</p><p>The pre-registration is available at https://osf.io/fq9a2/?view_only=4249aefea99245368180e8c387553345. All data and the analysis script are available at:</p><p>https://osf.io/jxhs2/?view_only=7df2fc30b5c543619a4781ad5fd1f6b1. Note that the present hypotheses are pre-registered in the second part of the pre-registration form. The verification of the first hypothesis was presented elsewhere (Dametto et al., 2023).</p><p>[3] A more precise description of this approach is provided in the Supplementary Information to Dametto and colleagues (2023).</p><p>[4] While acknowledging the effort of categories like androgynous, queer, or transgender to transcend gender binaries, interactions often revert to grammatical or semantic gender assignments. Thus, we translated non-binary identities to German and French, maintaining gender markers: "ein androgyner Mann," "eine androgyne Frau," "un homme androgyne,"</p><p>"une femme androgyne" for androgynous; "ein transgender Mann," "eine transgender Frau," "un transgenre," "une transgenre" for transgender; and "ein queer Mann," "eine queer Frau," "un homme queer," "une femme queer" for queer.</p><p>[5] In the pre-registration, we planned to assess differences based on mean differences.</p><p>This analysis is now proposed in the Supplementary Materials ("Statistical significance analysis") to this article. In the main article, we decided to use Cohen's d effect sizes as they also take into account the variability in the data.       Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>.1: Scatter plots of the average evaluation calculated using the ratings for the masculine and feminine version (x-axis) and gender effect size on the evaluation dimension (y-axis). The red regression line represents the social categories whose masculine version is rated higher; the blue line represents the social categories whose feminine version is rated higher. The gray lines mark the threshold for small effects defined by Lovakov and Agadullina Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>.2: Scatter plots of the average potency calculated using the ratings for the masculine and feminine version (x-axis) and gender effect size on the potency dimension (y-axis). The red regression line represents the social categories whose masculine version is rated higher; the blue line represents the social categories whose feminine version is rated higher. The gray lines mark the threshold for small effects defined by <ref type="bibr">Lovakov and Agadullina (2021)</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>.2: Scatter plots of the average potency calculated using the ratings for the masculine and feminine version (x-axis) and gender effect size on the potency dimension (y-axis). The red regression line represents the social categories whose masculine version is rated higher; the blue line represents the social categories whose feminine version is rated higher. The gray lines mark the threshold for small effects defined by <ref type="bibr">Lovakov and Agadullina (2021)</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>: Social categories plotted according to the effect size of gender along the evaluation (x-axis) and potency (y-axis) dimension. For instance, the social category mafioso is located in the upper left quadrant because the feminine version is rated as more positive (negative effect of gender on evaluation;</p><p>HpE confirmed), as well as more potent (positive effect of gender on potency; HpP confirmed) than the corresponding masculine version. Effect sizes are interpreted following the meta-analysis conducted by <ref type="bibr">Lovakov and Agadullina (2021)</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>: On the left, the density plot of the ratings for a "call center agent". On the right, the density plot of the ratings for the potency of a "gangster".</p><p>In both cases, the ratings for the female version are colored in red and the ratings for the male version are colored in blue. The social category "call center agent" represents the case where there are no differences in effect size and the distribution is t shaped. The social category "gangster" represents an extreme case where there are significant differences in effect size and the distribution is bimodal.</p><p>effects for gender (GndPart) and language culture (LCPart) of the participant as well as for the gender of the rated social category (GndSocCat) which was contrast coded. The models include crossed random slopes for participants and social categories. Three interaction terms were also included. First, the effect of perceiver's gender on affective perception may vary across cultures (GndSocCat * LCPart). Second, the gender of the social category may activate ingroup and outgroup biases (GndSocCat * GndPart) orthird -culture-specific affective patterns (GndSocCat * LCPart). Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">S1</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref> report the results of the three models, which show that the gender of the participants affects the perception of social category on the EPA dimensions. Given the negative sign of the coefficients, male participants perceive social categories as more neutral along all three EPA dimensions than female participants (for evaluation: b = -. German and France as well as male and female participants do rate social categories differently, such differences do not significantly interact with the gender of the social category and are consequently irrelevant for the main purpose of our research.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>: Differences in affective meanings for evaluation, potency, and activity by gender of participants (GndPart), language culture of participants (LCPart), and gender of the social category rated (GndSocCat). Horizontal Bars correspond to interaction-term coefficients of the corresponding mixed-effects models (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">S1</ref>).</p><p>Number As a next step, we calculated Cohen's d by comparing the ratings given by female and male respondents for the same social category. A negative effect size indicates higher ratings by female participants, while a positive effect size indicates the opposite. In this way, we aim to identify social categories that elicit greater gender differences in affective perceptions. Given the significant effect of language culture on ratings and potency, we computed Cohen's d separately by country and compared the results to detect cross-national differences and consistencies. As Table <ref type="table">S2</ref> shows, in most cases the gender of the participant has small or no effect on the affective perception. Moreover, female participants tend to rate social categories as more positive, potent, and active than male participants. This pattern is consistent in both countries.</p><p>Lastly, we were led by the hypothesis that differences in affective perception between men and women are mainly related to specific social categories that make gender salient, i.e.</p><p>in the case of sexual social categories <ref type="bibr">(Smith-Lovin 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Heise, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ridgeway, 2011)</ref>. In In summary, we propose the following answer to the question of whether the gender of the perceiver interacts with the affective perception of gendered social categories. Our results</p><p>show that the effect of the perceiver's gender on the affective meanings attributed to gendered social categories tends to be null or small, roughly corresponding to the effect size reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Hyde's (2005)</ref> meta-analysis. Despite the consistent similarities, there are also patterns of dissimilarity that persist in both countries. First, we found some anecdotal evidence that when gender becomes semantically salient -as in the case of sexuality or sexual social categoriesthe effect size becomes larger. Second, the gender of the perceiver leads to greater differences in affective meaning produced by men and women when social categories are evaluated far from the neutral anchor <ref type="bibr">(MacKinnon &amp; Keatings;</ref><ref type="bibr">1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Chapman et al., 2022)</ref>. Nevertheless, and most importantly for our research project, the gender of the perceiver does not interact with the gender of the social category, neither for German nor for French participants. Following this finding, we developed our analysis merging ratings provided by male and female as well as French and German participants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical significance analysis</head><p>In the following, we integrate the effect size based analysis presented in the main article with an analysis of statistical significance. To this purpose, we performed for each EPA dimension 192 twosample unpaired Student t-tests assessing whether the null hypothesis that the two means are equal should be rejected. We considered two levels of significance: the canonical 0.05 level and a very conservative alpha value (.0003) obtained after a Bonferroni correction. Moreover, we also considered absolute differences between the means.</p><p>Evaluation. We advanced the hypothesis (HpE) that the more positive evaluation ascribed to women will be systematically reflected in a more positive evaluation ascribed to the feminine versions of social categories. As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">S3</ref>, when looking at absolute differences, feminine social categories are consistently rated more positively than their masculine counterparts (141 of 192 social categories, 73%). However, few differences are significant at the 0.05 level (42 of 192, 21%) and almost none after Bonferroni correction (5 of 192, 3%). When pairs of social categories are statistically different, feminine versions are rated as more positive in 38 out of 42 cases. Although there are some small differences, this pattern of results also holds when only the masculine and feminine subsamples of respondents are considered. Overall, these results confirm the effect size based analysis: few pairs of social categories are statistically different. Nonetheless, when differences are statistically significant the feminine versions of a social category are mostly evaluated more positively.</p><p>Potency. Following our hypothesis (HpP), we expected that the masculine version of a social category would be rated as more potent than the same social category interpreted by a woman. Our data (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">S4</ref>) show that 103 out of 192 (54%) masculine social categories are rated as more potent than the corresponding feminine version. This number is only slightly higher than what would be expected by chance. In terms of ratings, only a few differences are significant at the 0.05 level (34 out of 192, 18%) and almost none after Bonferroni correction (4 out of 192, 2%). However, when statistically different pairs of social categories are considered, masculine versions are rated higher in 29 out of 34 cases. Thus, the second hypothesis appears to be only marginally supported: feminine versions of a social category are not systematically rated as less potent, and the differences are mostly not large enough to reach statistical significance. However, when looking at statistically significant differences, there is a slight tendency for masculine social categories to be rated as more powerful.</p><p>Activity. We hypothesized (HpA) that social categories presented in the feminine form will be perceived as less active than the corresponding masculine social category. According to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">S5</ref>, feminine social categories are instead considered to be more active than their masculine counterparts in 129 out of 192 cases. Again, only a few differences are significant at the 0.05 level <ref type="bibr">(30 out of 192, 16%)</ref> and none after Bonferroni correction. Nevertheless, when statistically different pairs of social categories are considered, feminine versions are rated higher on the activity dimension in about 70% of cases (21 of 30, 70%). Thus, because in most cases women interpreting social categories have been rated as more active, our third hypothesis is not supported.</p><p>Overall, the analysis of the differences in mean ratings between the masculine and feminine versions of the social categories in our dictionary confirms the results of the analysis based on effect sizes. The absolute differences confirm that feminine social categories are mostly judged as more positive (HpE), in slightly more cases as less potent (HpP), and -contrary to our hypothesis (HpA)mostly as more active than their masculine counterparts. However, in most cases the differences are not large enough to reach statistical significance. Thus, the gender of social categories leads to statistically significant differences in affective meanings only in relatively few cases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Power analysis</head><p>The analysis presented in the main article is based on EPA ratings collected from n = 700 German and n = 700 French participants. Since we organized the social categories into 10 sets of words that are identical between French and German, each social category was rated by     </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FiguresFigure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figures</figDesc><graphic coords="51,92.10,186.69,429.80,136.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of participants = 1.400; number of social categories = 192. Signif. codes: '***' 0.001, '**' 0.01, '*' 0.05.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>this regard, we find anecdotal support for this hypothesis, especially with regard to the evaluation dimension. Considering the French data, the top five social categories by effect size are (masculine) worker, d = -1.02; (feminine) sadist, d = .77; (feminine) playboy, d = .77; (masculine) pornographer, d = .76; (masculine) homosexual, d = .76. A similar pattern can be observed for Germany: (masculine) welfare recipient, d = -.81; (masculine) queer, d = -.73; (masculine) transgender, d = -.71; (feminine) queer, d = -.69; (feminine) laborer, d = -.69. For both countries, at least three out of the top five social categories eliciting differences in affective perception between genders are either related to sexuality (pornographer, playboy, sadist) or are sexual social categories (queer, transgender, homosexual).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>n = 70</head><label>70</label><figDesc>German and n = 70 French participants. Therefore, the average ratings presented in the study are based on n = 140 French and German participants. Since we compared the ratings given in French and German for the masculine (n = 140) with the ratings given for the feminine version of the social categories (n = 140), we have a total sample size of n = 280 participants organized in two groups. Under these conditions, we have statistical power of .80 to detect an effect size of d = .25 at a highly reliable significance level of .001. A Cohen's d effect size of .25 is above the threshold for small and below the one for moderate effects in social psychology derived empirically byLovakov and Agadullina (2021).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure S4 :</head><label>S4</label><figDesc>FigureS4: Effect size (x-axis) and sample size (y-axis). The threshold for small, moderate and large effects are defined followingLovakov &amp; Agadullina (2021). The red line intersecting the y-axis indicates the sample size of this study. The red line intersecting the x-axis indicates the resulting effect size that we can detect.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="63,140.13,92.55,351.18,181.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="63,140.13,309.69,351.18,181.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="63,140.13,525.69,351.18,181.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="70,72.00,92.55,453.48,299.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. The contrasting anchors of the bipolar scales are as follows: for evaluation angenehm/plaisant [pleasant], freundlich/agréable [friendly], gut/bien [good],</figDesc><table><row><cell>versus unangenehm/déplaisant [unpleasant], unfreundlich/désagréable [unfriendly].</cell></row><row><cell>schlecht/mal [bad]; for potency: kraftvoll/puissant [powerful], stark/fort [strong],</cell></row><row><cell>groß/grand [large] versus zart/délicat [gentle], schwach/faible [weak], klein/petit [small];</cell></row><row><cell>for activity: schnell/rapide [quick], lebhaft/vif [lively], geräuschvoll/bruyant [noisy]</cell></row><row><cell>versus langsam/lent [slow], träge/inerte [inert], still/silencieux [quiet]. We used the</cell></row><row><cell>following verbal labels to mark the 9-point scale: etwas/un peu [slightly], ziemlich/plutôt</cell></row><row><cell>[quite], sehr/très [very], äußerst/extrêmement [extremely], with neutral/neutre marking the</cell></row><row><cell>center.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 : Top 3 most positive, negative, and neutral Cohen's d effect sizes by dimension</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Beyond prejudice as simple antipathy: Hostile and benevolent Heise, David R. 2007. Expressive Order: Confirming Sentiments in Social Actions. Order on the Edge of Chaos, edited by E. J. Lawler, S. R. Thye and J. Yoon. New York: Cambridge University Press. Horvath, Lisa K., Elisa F. Merkel, Anne Maass, and Sabine Sczesny. 2016. Does genderfair language pay off? The social perception of professions from a cross-linguistic perspective. Frontiers in psychology, 6, 2018. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2015.02018. Martin T. [1962] 2009. "Demand characteristics and the concept of quasi-controls". Pp. 110-137 in: Artifacts in behavioral research: Robert Rosenthal and Ralph L.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Chapman, Robert M., Margaret N. Gardner, and Megan Lyons. 2022. Gender differences</cell></row><row><cell>in emotional connotative meaning of words measured by Osgood's semantic</cell></row><row><cell>differential techniques in young adults. Humanities and Social Sciences</cell></row><row><cell>Communications, 9(1), 1-11. doi: 10.1057/s41599-022-01126-3.</cell></row><row><cell>Charlesworth, Tessa E. S., Victor Yang, Thomas C. Mann, Benedek Kurdi, and Mahzarin</cell></row><row><cell>R. Banaji. 2021. Gender stereotypes in natural language: Word embeddings show</cell></row><row><cell>robust consistency across child and adult language corpora of more than 65 million</cell></row><row><cell>words. Psychological Science, 32(2), 218-240. doi: 10.1177/0956797620963619.</cell></row><row><cell>Conway, Michael, Teresa M. Pizzamiglio, and Lauren Mount. 1996. Status, communality,</cell></row><row><cell>and agency: Implications for stereotypes of gender and other groups. Journal of</cell></row><row><cell>Personality and Social Psychology, 71(1), 25-38. doi: 10.1037/0022-</cell></row><row><cell>3514.71.1.25.</cell></row><row><cell>Corneille, Olivier, and Peter Lush. 2023. Sixty years after Orne's american psychologist</cell></row><row><cell>article: a conceptual framework for subjective experiences elicited by demand</cell></row><row><cell>characteristics. Personality and Social Psychology Review, 27(1), 83-101. doi:</cell></row><row><cell>10.1177/10888683221104368.</cell></row><row><cell>Costrich, Norma, Joan Feinstein, Louise Kidder, Jeanne Marecek, and Linda Pascale.</cell></row><row><cell>1975. When stereotypes hurt: Three studies of penalties for sex-role reversals.</cell></row><row><cell>Journal of experimental social psychology, 11(6), 520-530. doi: 10.1016/0022-</cell></row><row><cell>1031(75)90003-7.</cell></row><row><cell>Cuddy, Amy J. C., Susan T. Fiske, and Peter Glick. 2008. Warmth and competence as</cell></row><row><cell>universal dimensions of social perception: The stereotype content model and the</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>Eagly, Alice H., and Steven J.</p>Karau. 2002</p>. Role congruity theory of prejudice toward female leaders. Psychological review, 109(3), 573. doi: 10.1037//0033-Eagly, Alice H., and Wendy Wood. 1999. The origins of sex differences in human behavior: Evolved dispositions versus social roles. American psychologist, 54(6), 408. doi: 10.1037/0003-066X.54.6.408. Ebert, Irena D., Melanie C. Steffens, and Alexandra Kroth. 2014. Warm, but maybe not so competent?-Contemporary implicit stereotypes of women and men in Germany. Gaunt, Ruth. 2013. Breadwinning moms, caregiving dads: Double standard in social judgments of gender norm violators. Journal of family issues, 34(1), 3-24. doi: 10.1177/0192513X12438686. Glick, Peter, Susan T. Fiske. 1997. Hostile and benevolent sexism: Measuring ambivalent sexist attitudes toward women. Psychology of women quarterly, 21(1), 119-135. doi: 10.1111/j.1471-6402.1997.tb00104.x. Glick, Peter, Susan T. Fiske, Antonio Mladinic, Jose L. Saiz, Dominic Abrams, Barbara Masser, Bolanle Adetoun, Johnstone E. Osagie, Adebowale Akande, Amos Alao, Osgood, Charles E., George J. Suci, and Percy H. Tannenbaum. 1957. The Measurement of Meaning. Urbana: University of Illinois Press. Payne, Keith B., Heidi A. Vuletich, and Kristjen B. Lundberg. 2017. The bias of crowds: How implicit bias bridges personal and systemic prejudice. Psychological Inquiry,</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Feminine form rated higher Masculine form rated higher → Table 2: Number of Cohen's d effect sizes by dimension, direction, and intensity</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Evaluation</cell><cell cols="2">Potency</cell><cell cols="2">Activity</cell></row><row><cell>Effect size</cell><cell>F d&lt;0</cell><cell>M d&gt;0</cell><cell>F d&lt;0</cell><cell>M d&gt;0</cell><cell>F d&lt;0</cell><cell>M d&gt;0</cell></row><row><cell>no effect abs(d) &lt; .15</cell><cell>81</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>68</cell><cell>56</cell><cell>85</cell><cell>41</cell></row><row><cell>small .15 &lt; abs(d) &lt; .36</cell><cell>49</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>moderate .36 &lt; abs(d) &lt; .65</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>large abs(d) &gt; .65</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>Note: F → Feminine version of the social category rated higher on given dimension; M → Masculine version of the social category rated higher on given dimension. The magnitude of the effect sizes is based on</p>Lovakov   and Agadullina (2021)</p>.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 : Mixed-effects regression coefficients for social categories' evaluation</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">95% CI</cell></row><row><cell>Effects</cell><cell>Estimate</cell><cell>SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>LL</cell><cell>UL</cell></row><row><cell>(Intercept)</cell><cell>-.05</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell>-.39</cell><cell>-.28</cell><cell>.19</cell></row><row><cell>Gender of the social category: Masculine form</cell><cell>-.16***</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell>-11.74</cell><cell>-.19</cell><cell>-.13</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Participants: 1,400; Social category pairs: 192</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>Note: Signif. codes: 0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1. SE = standard error; t = t-statistic; CI = confidence interval; LL = lower limit; UL = upper limit.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 : Mixed-effects regression coefficients for social categories' potency</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">95% CI</cell></row><row><cell>Effects</cell><cell>Estimate</cell><cell>SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>LL</cell><cell>UL</cell></row><row><cell>(Intercept)</cell><cell>.56</cell><cell>.07</cell><cell>7.69</cell><cell>.42</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gender of the social category: Masculine form</cell><cell>.05***</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell>3.75</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>.08</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Participants: 1,400; Social category pairs: 192</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>Note: Signif. codes: 0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1. SE = standard error; t = t-statistic; CI = confidence interval; LL = lower limit; UL = upper limit.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5 : Mixed-effects regression coefficients for social categories' activity</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">95% CI</cell></row><row><cell>Effects</cell><cell>Estimate</cell><cell>SE</cell><cell>t</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>LL</cell><cell>UL</cell></row><row><cell>(Intercept)</cell><cell>.69</cell><cell>.07</cell><cell>9.89</cell><cell>.55</cell><cell>.82</cell></row><row><cell>Gender of the social category: Masculine form</cell><cell>-.09***</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell>-6.73</cell><cell>-.12</cell><cell>-.07</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Participants: 1,400; Social category pairs: 192</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="6">Note: Signif. codes: 0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1. SE = standard error; t = t-statistic; CI =</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">confidence interval; LL = lower limit; UL = upper limit.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 6 : Regression analysis with average ratings, and "highest gender" as independent variable, and the gender effect size as dependent variable</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Evaluation</cell><cell></cell><cell>Potency</cell><cell></cell><cell>Activity</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Effects</cell><cell>Est SE 95% CI</cell><cell>p</cell><cell>Est SE 95% CI</cell><cell>p</cell><cell>Est SE 95% CI</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>LL UL</cell><cell></cell><cell>LL UL</cell><cell></cell><cell>LL UL</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(Intercept)</cell><cell cols="2">-.03 .01 -.05 -.00 .025 *</cell><cell cols="4">.01 .01 .01 .04 .175 *** -.01 .01 -.03 .00 .124</cell></row><row><cell>Avg. E</cell><cell cols="2">.00 .00 -.01 .02 .379</cell><cell cols="2">-.01 .01 -.02 .00 .063 .</cell><cell cols="2">.00 .00 -.01 .01 .628</cell></row><row><cell>Avg. P</cell><cell cols="2">-.02 .02 -.05 .02 .342</cell><cell cols="2">.03 .02 .00 .06 .066 .</cell><cell cols="2">-.03 .01 -.06 .00 .048 *</cell></row><row><cell>Avg. A</cell><cell cols="2">.00 .02 -.04 .03 .762</cell><cell cols="2">.00 .02 -.03 .03 .989</cell><cell cols="2">.03 .01 .00 .06 .020 *</cell></row><row><cell>HigGenE Feminine</cell><cell cols="2">-.24 .02 -.28 -.20 .000 ***</cell><cell cols="2">.01 .02 -.02 .05 .402</cell><cell cols="2">-.02 .01 -.05 .01 .161</cell></row><row><cell>HigGenP Feminine</cell><cell cols="2">-.01 .01 -.05 .03 .583</cell><cell cols="4">-.22 .02 -.25 -.18 .000 *** -.03 .02 -.08 .01 .009 **</cell></row><row><cell>HigGenA Feminine</cell><cell cols="2">.00 .01 -.05 .04 .908</cell><cell cols="2">-.05 .02 -.10 -.01 .014 *</cell><cell cols="2">-.23 .02 -.27 -.19 .000 ***</cell></row><row><cell>Avg. E * HigGenE Avg. E * Feminine</cell><cell cols="2">.01 .01 -.01 .03 .424</cell><cell cols="2">.02 .01 .00 .04 .054 .</cell><cell cols="2">-.01 .01 -.03 .01 .389</cell></row><row><cell>Avg. P * HigGenP Avg. P * Feminine</cell><cell cols="2">-.04 .02 -.08 .01 .019 *</cell><cell cols="2">-.02 .02 -.05 .01 .257</cell><cell cols="2">-.01 .01 -.04 .01 .341</cell></row><row><cell>Avg. A * HigGenA Avg. A * Feminine</cell><cell cols="2">.02 .02 -.02 .06 .434</cell><cell cols="2">.01 .02 -.04 .03 .734</cell><cell cols="2">.00 .02 -.03 .03 .970</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Note: Signif. codes: 0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1. Est. = Estimate; SE = standard error; CI = confidence interval; LL = lower limit; UL =</cell></row><row><cell>upper limit; p = p-value.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 7 : Social categories with at least a small effect size (abs(d) &gt;= 0.15) on the evaluation or potency dimension sorted by HpE and HpP.</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Quadrant</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table S3 : Differences in evaluation ratings of pairs (m/f) of social categories</head><label>S3</label><figDesc>Ridgeway, Cecilia L. 2011. Framed by gender: How gender inequality persists in the modern world. New York: Oxford University Press. Smith-Lovin, Lynn. 1987. Impressions from events. Journal of mathematical sociology, 13(1,2), 35-70. doi: 10.1080/0022250X.1987.9990026. .</figDesc><table><row><cell>Level of analysis</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>Feminine social categories are rated more positively</cell><cell>141</cell><cell>.73</cell></row><row><cell>Significant ∆ at 0.05 level</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>.22</cell></row><row><cell>thereof feminine social categories are rated more positively</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>.90</cell></row><row><cell>Significant ∆ after Bonferroni correction</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>.03</cell></row><row><cell>thereof feminine social categories are rated more positively</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1.0</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: n = 192 social categories. N = Number of cases; Freq. = relative frequency.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table S4 : Differences in potency ratings of pairs (m/f) of social categories</head><label>S4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Level of analysis</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>Masculine social categories are rated as more powerful</cell><cell>103</cell><cell>.54</cell></row><row><cell>Significant ∆ at 0.05 level</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>.18</cell></row><row><cell>thereof masculine social categories are rated as more powerful</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>.85</cell></row><row><cell>Significant ∆ after Bonferroni correction</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>.02</cell></row><row><cell>thereof masculine social categories are rated as more powerful</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>.75</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: n = 192 social categories. N = Number of cases; Freq. = relative frequency.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table S5 : Differences in activity ratings of pairs (m/f) of social categories</head><label>S5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Level of analysis</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>Freq</cell></row><row><cell>Feminine social categories are rated as more powerful</cell><cell>129</cell><cell>.67</cell></row><row><cell>Significant ∆ at 0.05 level</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>.16</cell></row><row><cell>thereof feminine social categories are rated as more active</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>.70</cell></row><row><cell>Significant ∆ after Bonferroni correction</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>thereof feminine social categories are rated as more active</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: n = 192 social categories. N = Number of cases; Freq. = relative frequency.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>This work was supported by the <rs type="funder">ANR (Agence Nationale de la Recherche</rs>, grant # <rs type="grantNumber">ANR-20-FRAL-0008</rs>) granted to <rs type="person">Christophe Blaison</rs>, the <rs type="funder">DFG (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</rs>, grant # <rs type="grantNumber">SCHR1282/6-1</rs>) granted to <rs type="person">Tobias Schröder</rs>, as part of the collaborative <rs type="programName">French-German funding program</rs> for the Humanities and Social Sciences (FRAL). The study was also supported by the <rs type="funder">IdEx Université Paris Cité</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">ANR-18-IDEX-0001</rs>, granted to <rs type="person">Christophe Blaison</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_SmcjKav">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-20-FRAL-0008</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_dfRvdxC">
					<idno type="grant-number">SCHR1282/6-1</idno>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">French-German funding program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_pJfaTUv">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-18-IDEX-0001</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Availability Statement</head><p>The data that support the findings of this study are openly available in PsychArchives at https://doi.org/10.23668/psycharchives.14237.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Informed Consent</head><p>In the data collection of the study, participants provided their informed consent at the beginning of the online questionnaire.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethics Statement</head><p>The study reported in this manuscript involves human participants and was approved by the ethical board of Université Paris Cité <ref type="bibr">(N° 2021-75)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest Statement</head><p>All authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary information to:</head><p>The affective roots of gender stereotypes Does grammatical gender influence the affective meanings attached to social categories in French and German?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis by gender and language of respondents</head><p>Researchers have demonstrated that gender stereotypes are extensively shared across language cultures and -at least partially -between genders <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Glick et al., 2000)</ref>. As a preliminary step in our research project, we wanted to assess whether gender and language of the participant have a moderating effect on the affective perception of gendered social categories. The following analysis is structured as follows: firstly, we performed regression analysis to investigate whether the gender and language culture of the participant interacts with the gender of the social categories. Secondly, we compared ratings provided by female and male participants and used Cohen's d effect size to assess the magnitude of difference as well as to identify social categories that are consistently judged differently between male and female participants.</p><p>Due to the balanced incomplete block design typical for EPA surveys <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Heise, 2007)</ref>, we computed mixed effects regression models -one for each EPA dimension -with fixed   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distributions of effect sizes by dimension</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rating instrument -Germany</head><p>The affective and linguistic roots of gender stereotypes Tables <ref type="table">Table S1:</ref>  Note: F → Female participants rated the social category higher on given dimension; M → Male participants rated the social category higher on given dimension. Effect size interpretation is defined following the empirical guidelines provided by <ref type="bibr">Lovakov and Agadullina (2021)</ref>.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus and Stratification in the Affective Meaning of Human Sociality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Ambrasat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Von Scheve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Conrad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Schauenburg</forename><surname>Gesche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tobias</forename><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1313321111</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8001" to="8006" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Benevolent and hostile sexism in a shifting global context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Manuela</forename><surname>Barreto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Doyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s44159-022-00136-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature reviews psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Luckmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Social Construction of Reality: A Treatise in the Sociology of Knowledge</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Penguin</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966. 1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Standards and expectancies: Contrast and assimilation in judgments of self and others</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monica</forename><surname>Biernat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender-and race-based standards of competence: lower minimum standards but higher ability standards for devalued groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monica</forename><surname>Biernat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diane</forename><surname>Kobrynowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0022-3514.72.3.544</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">544</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Doing Gender, Avoiding Crime: The Gendered Meaning of Criminal Behavior and the Gender Gap in Offending in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kaitlin</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Boyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/01902725231167845</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Psychology Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stereotypes of women and men across gender subgroups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hege</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martine</forename><surname>Solianik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mehri</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Five</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Agai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.881418.</idno>
		<idno>10.1037/0022-3514.79.5.763</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="763" to="775" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Frontiers in Psychology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bad but Bold: Ambivalent Attitudes Toward Men Predict Gender Inequality in 16 Nations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Glick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Lameiras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Susan</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fiske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Eckes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename><surname>Masser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chiara</forename><surname>Volpato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><forename type="middle">Maria</forename><surname>Manganelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jolynn</forename><forename type="middle">C X</forename><surname>Pek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Li-Li</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nuray</forename><surname>Sakalli-Uğurlu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yolanda</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D'avila</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tineke</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Luiza Willemsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Annetje</forename><surname>Brunner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robin</forename><surname>Six-Materna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.86.5.713</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="728" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The presentation of self in everyday life. Garden City: Double Day</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erving</forename><surname>Goffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/BF03180445</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans-action</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959. 1968</date>
			<pubPlace>Goldberg, Philip</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Are women prejudiced against women?</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A language index of grammatical gender dimensions to study the impact of grammatical gender on the way we perceive women and men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pascal</forename><surname>Gygax</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sandrine</forename><surname>Elmiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><surname>Zufferey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sabine</forename><surname>Garnham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><surname>Sczesny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frederike</forename><surname>Von Stockhausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jane</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Oakhill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpsyg.2019.01604</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1604</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Essentialist beliefs about social categories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nick</forename><surname>Haslam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Louis</forename><surname>Rothschild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Donald</forename><surname>Ernst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1348/014466600164363</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/360823243_An_intersectional_approach_to_gender_and_social_class_stereotypes" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Kroska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/3090148</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Do we have consensus? Examining the relationship between gender ideology and role meanings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="40" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating gender differences in the meaning of household chores and child care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Kroska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1741-3737.2003.00456.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of marriage and family</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="456" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The gender gap in business leadership: Exploring an affect control theory explanation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Kroska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Trent</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0190272518806292</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Psychology Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The affective bases for the gendering of traits: Comparing the United States and Canada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tom</forename><surname>Langford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2695879</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Psychology Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender stereotypes are reflected in the distributional structure of 25 languages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Molly</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Lupyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41562-020-0918-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature human behaviour</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1021" to="1028" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empirically derived guidelines for effect size interpretation in social psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrey</forename><surname>Lovakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Agadullina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ejsp.2752</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Heise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Self, identity, and social institutions</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Palgrave MacMillan</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Structure of Emotions: Canada -United States Comparisons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leo</forename><surname>Keating</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2786905</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Psychology Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The primacy of gender: Gendered cognition underlies the big two dimensions of social cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ashley</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Slepian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1745691620904961</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspectives on Psychological Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1143" to="1158" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Mind, self, and society</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chicago</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Chicago press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1934">1934</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contrast effects of stereotypes:&quot;Nurturing&quot; male professors are evaluated more positively than &quot;nurturing&quot; female professors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Meltzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mcnulty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3149/jms.1901.57</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Men&apos;s Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Séries statistiques des personnes placées sous main de justice 1980 -2022</title>
		<idno>09.11.2023</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.justice.gouv.fr/sites/default/files/migrations/portail/art_pix/PPSMJ_2022_vf.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>Ministère de la justice</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Backlash against male elementary educators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Corinne</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moss-Racusin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jasp.12366</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="393" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When men break the gender rules: status incongruity and backlash against modest men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Corinne</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moss-Racusin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julie</forename><surname>Phelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurie</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rudman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0018093</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology of Men &amp; Masculinity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">140</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cecilia</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ridgeway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Status: Why Is It Everywhere? Why Does It Matter?</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Russell Sage Foundation</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus and the creation of status beliefs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cecilia</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ridgeway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shelley</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Correll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1353/sof.2006.0139</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Forces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="453" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kimberly</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tobias</forename><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wolfgang</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0190272513480191</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The affective structure of stereotype content: Behavior and emotion in intergroup context</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="150" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-promotion as a risk factor for women: the costs and benefits of counterstereotypical impression management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurie</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rudman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037//0022-3514.74.3.629</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">629</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reactions to counterstereotypic behavior: the role of backlash in cultural stereotype maintenance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurie</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rudman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kimberly</forename><surname>Fairchild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.87.2.157</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2012a. Status incongruity and backlash effects: Defending the gender hierarchy motivates prejudice against female leaders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurie</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rudman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Corinne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julie</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Moss-Racusin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sanne</forename><surname>Phelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nauts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jesp.2011.10.008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of experimental social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="179" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reactions to vanguards: Advances in backlash theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurie</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rudman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Corinne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Moss-Racusin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julie</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Glick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Phelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/B978-0-12-394286-9.00004-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in experimental social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affective Meanings of Stereotyped Social Groups in Cross-Cultural Comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kimberly</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tobias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shuichirou</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julija</forename><surname>Ike</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wolfgang</forename><surname>Mell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1368430213491788</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Group Processes &amp; Intergroup Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="717" to="733" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-national variation in the size of sex differences in values: effects of gender equality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shalom</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tammy</forename><surname>Rubel-Lifschitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0015546</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of personality and social psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">171</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can gender-fair language reduce gender stereotyping and discrimination?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sabine</forename><surname>Sczesny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Magda</forename><surname>Formanowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Franziska</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpsyg.2016.00025</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The strength of weak identities: Social structural sources of self, situation and emotional experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lynn</forename><surname>Smith-Lovin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/019027250707000203</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social psychology quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Smith-Lovin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dawn</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bryan</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jesse</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Cannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Freeland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kimberly</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://research.franklin.uga.edu/act/" />
		<title level="m">Mean Affective Ratings of 929 Identities, 814 Behaviors, and 660 Modifiers by University of Georgia and Duke University Undergraduates and by Community Members in Durham</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>NC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2016. 2012-2014</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Georgia</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender differences and offender reentry: A review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Solveig</forename><surname>Spjeldnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sara</forename><surname>Goodkind</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10509670902850812</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Offender Rehabilitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anzahl der rechtskräftig verurteilten Personen in Deutschland nach Geschlecht von</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Statistisches</forename><surname>Bundesamt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>09.11.2023</idno>
		<ptr target="https://de.statista.com/statistik/daten/studie/1068769/umfrage/rechtskraeftig-verurteilte-personen-in-deutschland-nach-geschlecht/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2022. 2011 bis 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anzahl der Strafgefangenen in den Justizvollzugsanstalten in Deutschland nach Geschlecht und Alter am 31. März 2022 (geschlossener und offener Vollzug</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Statistisches</forename><surname>Bundesamt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>09.11.2023</idno>
		<ptr target="https://de.statista.com/statistik/daten/studie/1353153/umfrage/strafgefangene-in-deutschland-nach-geschlecht-und-alter/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender-related beliefs of teachers in elementary school mathematics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joachim</forename><surname>Tiedemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1023/A:1003953801526</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Educational studies in Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="207" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Me&apos;s and we&apos;s: Forms and functions of social identities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peggy</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Thoits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lauren</forename><surname>Virshup</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Self and identity: Fundamental issues</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ashmore</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jussim</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="133" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Warm-hearted businessmen, competitive housewives? Effects of gender-fair language on adolescents&apos; perceptions of occupations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vervecken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pascal</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ddries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ute</forename><surname>Gygax</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Gabriel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bettina</forename><surname>Guillod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hannover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fpsyg.2015.01437</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1437</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The glass escalator: Hidden advantages for men in the</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christine</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/3096961</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">female&quot; professions. Social problems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The subtle suspension of backlash: A meta-analysis of penalties for women&apos;s implicit and explicit dominance behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Melissa</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Larissa</forename><surname>Tiedens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/bul0000039</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">165</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender differences in emotional connotative meaning of words measured by Osgood&apos;s semantic differential techniques in young adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Margaret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Megan</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lyons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1057/s41599-022-01126-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Humanities and Social Sciences Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond prejudice as simple antipathy: Hostile and benevolent sexism across cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Glick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Susan</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Peter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antonio</forename><surname>Fiske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jose</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mladinic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dominic</forename><surname>Saiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename><surname>Abrams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bolanle</forename><surname>Masser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Adetoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Adebowale</forename><surname>Osagie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amos</forename><surname>Akande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Annetje</forename><surname>Alao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tineke</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Brunner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kettie</forename><surname>Willemsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Chipeta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ap</forename><surname>Benoit Dardenne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Dijksterhuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Wigboldus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miguel</forename><surname>Eckes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Margaret</forename><surname>Moya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hyun-Jeong</forename><surname>Foddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><forename type="middle">Jose</forename><surname>Lameiras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Angelica</forename><surname>Sotelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Myrna</forename><surname>Mucchi-Faina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nuray</forename><surname>Romani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bola</forename><surname>Sakalh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mariko</forename><surname>Udegbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Miyoko</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Ui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cristina</forename><surname>Ferreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wilson</forename><forename type="middle">Lopez</forename><surname>Lopez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0022-3514.79.5.763</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="763" to="775" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Iris Six-Materna, Francisca Exp6sito</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Expressive Order: Confirming Sentiments in Social Actions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Heise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The gender similarities hypothesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Janet</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hyde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/0003-066X.60.6.581</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American psychologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">581</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empirically derived guidelines for effect size interpretation in social psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrey</forename><surname>Lovakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Agadullina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ejsp.2752</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Structure of Emotions: Canada -United States Comparisons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mackinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leo</forename><surname>Keating</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2786905</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Psychology Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
