<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Experiential Space: Neural Binding of Predicates into a Unified Sensory Experience</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elliott</forename><surname>Bonal</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambridge</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Experiential Space: Neural Binding of Predicates into a Unified Sensory Experience</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8D221E81992A6992023E3DE6D4F0DC2E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:29+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Binding Problem</term>
					<term>Neural Binding</term>
					<term>Unity of Consciousness</term>
					<term>Predicate Coding</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work introduces the concept of an "experiential space", a space of all possible sensory experiences. Indeed, an experience is represented as a point in "experiential space" and is given by the output of a "binding function" applied to the solution to a neural network coding equation, introduced in "Predicate Coding" (Bonal, 2025,[3]), for the sensory nervous system at a given time. This work aims to address the "Neural Binding Problem", understood here as explaining the unity of conscious experience yielded through the activity of a distributed system, such as the sensory nervous system. Finally, this model yields testable hypotheses, such as: (i) TMS-induced perturbations to regions responsible for processing a subset of perceivable predicates should selectively distort corresponding dimensions in experiential space ; (ii) The implementation of a Brain-Computer Interface directly interacting with the sensory nervous system, would yield phenomenal representations coming from the interface within the experience's coordinates ; (iii) The presentation of a gradually changing sequence of stimuli with diverse predicate values during a fixed time interval should yield a higher path-average speed within the experiential space, than the presentation of unchanging stimuli during the same fixed time interval ; (iv) The presentation of unchanging stimuli followed by a rapid change in stimuli with diverse predicate values during a fixed time interval should yield a higher distance speed within the experiential space, than the presentation of unchanging stimuli during the same fixed time interval.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>There is a fundamental difficulty, in the fields of neuroscience, psychology and cognitive science, to describe how different properties of perception, through different sensory modalities, yield a single unified conscious experience. This is often labeled the "Neural Binding Problem". Such a difficulty, however, comes with nuances. Indeed, Feldman (2012, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>), divided the issue in the four distinct problems:</p><p>1. General Coordination 2. Visual Feature-Binding 3. Variable Binding 4. Subjective Unity of Perception This work provides a mathematical model aiming to address "4. ", i.e. the "Subjective Unity of Perception", which Revonsuo (1999, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>) defines as follows: "How are [...] phenomenally unified entities, constructed by the brain as neurally unique entities, considering that the neural mechanisms necessary for creating different phenomenal contents (e.g., color, movement, vision, audition, touch) are distributed all around the cortex." - <ref type="bibr">(Revonsuo, 1999, [17]</ref>) .</p><p>In order to do address this issue, this work builds upon "Predicate Coding" <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025,[3]</ref>), to bind the stimuli-encoded values yielded by the sensory nervous system during a given time interval, to a trajectory in "experiential space", i.e. the space of all possible experiences. In doing so, the model effectively turns a distributed vector of the encoding-neural activity into a singular unified point in experiential "space". This allows to give a formal resolution to neural binding regarding the subjective unity of perception, as it unifies distributed encoding values into a point or trajectory within the space of all possible experiences. It is to be noted, however, that the suggested answer to the "Subjective Unity of Perception" presented here is aiming to resolve a formal issue, i.e. how can such unity be mathematically and computationally assessed, not the mechanistic issue of surrounding such subjective unity.</p><p>There have been several approaches aiming to resolve the neural binding problem, including the "synchronization hypothesis" (von der Malsburg and Schneider, 1986, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>), feature integration theory <ref type="bibr">(Treisman, 1998, [21]</ref>) (Treisman and Gelade, 1980, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>), and the enhancement of firing rates <ref type="bibr">(Roelfsema, 2023, [18]</ref>). However, these approaches mainly address "1-3.", and "4. " is often disregarded as too philosophical and empirically intractable.</p><p>Yet, some theories of consciousness, have aimed to address more firmly the problems arising from subjective unity of perception from a distributed neural system. For instance, through Integrated Information Theory, Balduzzi and Tononi <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Balduzzi and Tononi, 2009</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>), have defined a "qualia space", which aims to assess the "quality" of an experience, and thereby also addressing its unity. The "experiential space" introduced in this work is rooted in a Neural Encoding model, not a consciousness model, whereas the "qualia space" (Balduzzi and Tononi, 2009, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>) is rooted in Integrated Information Theory <ref type="bibr">(Tononi, 2004, [20]</ref>), which does not directly address neural encoding.</p><p>Finally, when understanding the experiential space as a readout of neural activity it bears similarity to "representational similarity analysis" (Kriegeskorte et al., 2008, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>) (Dimsdale-Zucker et al., 2018, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>), "neural population geometry" <ref type="bibr">(Chung et al., 2021,[6]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Chen et al., 2025, [5]</ref>) and "perceptual manifolds" <ref type="bibr">(Seung et al., 2000, [19]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Chung et al., 2018, [7]</ref>), as it aims to translate neural activity into formal descriptions of sensory experience. However, the mapping from neural activity to the "experiential space" is here done through the framework of Predicate Coding <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>), which holds precise ontological commitments, and assigns predicate values to each neuron at a given time, therefore understanding neural activity through the lens of such predicates, in a deterministic way. Nonetheless, elements of each of those models, appear within the "experiential space": (i) the process relating neural activity to meaningful and computationally tractable values builds upon insights provided by representational similarity analysis <ref type="bibr">(Kriegeskorte et al., 2008, [12]</ref>) (Dimsdale-Zucker et al., 2018, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>), (ii) the concept of an "experiential space", containing all possible experiences yielded by neural activity builds upon insights provided by both neural population geometry <ref type="bibr">(Chung et al., 2021,[6]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Chen et al., 2025, [5]</ref>) and perceptual manifolds (Seung et al., 2000, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Chung et al., 2018, [7]</ref>) . Yet, none of the formalism of any of these models appear in this work, as it borrows its formalism and fundamental ontology from Predicate Coding <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Theory</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Background</head><p>The mathematical model introduced in this paper aims to describe how different encoding values, coming from different neurons, yield the unity of sensory experience, In order to do so, the model will rest upon "Predicate coding" <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>), according to which each neuron is tuned to properties of stimuli which can be represented by many-valued logic predicates with fuzzy logic (Łukasiewicz) semantics.</p><p>The model will here first describe the sensory nervous system as a network of interconnected neurons, each tuned to many-valued logic predicates applied to stimuli. Then, the model will describe how sparse and diverse encoding of predicates can yield a unified sensory experience, through the binding function "B".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Sensory Nervous System Network</head><p>Before constructing the experiential space, let us first conceive of a network representing the neurons and interconnections of the whole sensory nervous system. The sensory nervous system network, at a time interval "[t, t + k]", will be denoted "net sensory.[t,t+k] ". It will be defined through Predicate Coding notation, i.e. as a graph of anatomically connected neurons neur u.[t,t+k] , linked by synapses S:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">net sensory.[t,t+k] = (V sensory.[t,t+k] , E sensory.[t,t+k] )<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Where the vertices of the graph are all neurons within the sensory nervous system:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">V sensory.[t,t+k] = {neur u.[t,t+k] |neur u.[t,t+k] ∈ SNS} (2)</formula><p>Where "SNS" is a set denoting the sensory nervous system.</p><p>Such that for all neurons x in V sensory. <ref type="bibr">[</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(Oy) = Ix))] ) (3)</formula><p>And where the edges of the graphs are synapses connecting the neurons:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">E sensory.[t,t+k] = {S [t,t+k] u→z |S [t,t+k] u→z (O u ) = I z }<label>(4)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Unified Equations from Predicate Coding</head><p>Having now described the sensory nervous system as a network using Predicate coding notation, this subsection will here outline the two unified equations from Predicate Coding <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>). Indeed, the first equation aims to approximate the predicate value that a neuron encodes and the second equation aims to approximate the tuple of predicate values that a network encodes.</p><p>The first equation <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>), for a given neuron neur u.[t,t+k] and a given stimulus x, yields a value through the sum of all single-neuron codes c neur i (such as rate code, latency code...) multiplied by their respective weights w c neur i , divided by their respective maximum max c neur i given by neuron u during the time interval [t, t + k], and inputted into a non-linearity function ψ:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Code (0) (neur u.[t,t+k] , x) = ψ n i=1 w c neur i c neur i neur u.[t,t+k] , x max c neur i (5)</formula><p>Where ψ needs to yield a value in [0, 1] and the sum of all the weights w c neur i must be equal to one, and no weight can be negative. Moreover max c neur i cannot be zero.</p><p>The second equation <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>), for a given neural network net g.[t,t+k] and a given stimulus x, yields a value through the sum of all network codes c net i (such as population coding, correlation coding...) applied element-wise to the tuple of Code (0) values for neurons in the network, multiplied by their respective weights w c net i , divided by their respective maximum max c net i throughout the neural network, during the time interval [t, t+k], and inputted into a non-linearity function ψ applied element-wise :</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Code (1) (net g.[t,t+k] , x) = ψ( n i=1 w c net i c net i (Code (0) (neur u.[t,t+k] , x)) neur u.[t,t+k] ∈ V g.[t,t+k] max c net i ) (6) Such that: Code (1) (net g.[t,t+k] , x) ∈ [0, 1] V g.[t,t+k]<label>(7)</label></formula><p>And where each network codes t+k] , ψ needs to yield a value in [0, 1] and the sum of all the weights w c net i must be equal to one, and no weight can be negative. Moreover max c net i cannot be zero.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">c net i are maps from [0, 1] V g.[t,t+k] to R V g.[t,</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Experiential Space</head><p>Let us consider X as a function mapping the set of all stimuli S to [0, 1] n , where n is the cardinality (size) of the set of all predicates perceivable by a given sensory nervous system, applied to stimuli "P set ":</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">X : S → [0, 1] n ; such that: n = |P set |<label>(8)</label></formula><p>Where P set is defined in Predicate Coding <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025,[3]</ref>) as the set of all perceivable many-valued predicates P i.j mapping the set of all stimuli S to [0,1]:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">P set = {P i.j |Perceivable (P i.j ) ≥ τ }<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Where τ is a psychophysical threshold.</p><p>Such that each predicate P i.j<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> are those introduced in the "Framework for a Testable Metaphysical Science" (Bonal, 2024, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>) and are ordered as follows :</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">P i.j ≤ P n.m ≡ i &lt; n ∨ (i = n ∧ j ≤ m)<label>(10)</label></formula><p>The function X thus yields a tuple, representing coordinates in the experiential space, defined below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">X (x) = (P i.j (x)) P i.j ∈Pset<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Such that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">X (x) ∈ [0, 1] n<label>(12)</label></formula><p>Moreover, we can define the set E set of all outputs of the function X , which will be the foundation for our experiential space:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">E set = {X (x)|x ∈ S}<label>(13)</label></formula><p>The Experiential Space, is the set E set paired with a distance function d:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">E space = (E set , d)<label>(14)</label></formula><p>While the choice of metric d is ultimately up to experimental fit, one of the suggested metrics is the Minkowski metric, which defines the distance between two experience points X and Y in E space as :</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">d(X, Y ) = ( n i=1 |x i -y i | z ) 1 z (15)</formula><p>Where:</p><p>• X = (x 1 , ..., x n ) and Y = (y 1 , ..., y n ), such that each x i and y i are predicate values P i.j (x) such that P i.j is in P set and x is a stimulus in S</p><p>• z is the order of the distance, and is an integer in Z such that z ≥ 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">• |x i -y i | here represents the modulus of x i -y i not set cardinality.</formula><p>This metric has proven successful in modeling "Multidimensional Psychological Spaces" <ref type="bibr">(Micko et al., 1970, [16]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Wagner, 1985, [25]</ref>) and would therefore have potential to support the experiential space E space . Moreover, an experience E at a time interval [t 0 , t n ] is trajectory a through the experiential space. It is defined as a tuple of points within E space from t to t + k:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">E [t 0 ,tn] = (E t 0 , ..., E tn ) (16)</formula><p>Such that all entries in the tuple (E t 0 , ..., E tn ) are points in E space .</p><p>Finally, each sensory experience point E t i is equivalent to the output of a binding function B applied to the solution to the universal coding equation for the sensory nervous system network Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x):</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">E t i = B(Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x))<label>(17)</label></formula><p>Such that B is the defined as the function that maps the tuple in [0, 1] |V sensory.[t,t+k] | yielded by Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x) to an experience point E t i , i.e. a function that maps the set all the tuples yielded by Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x) through time, to E set :</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">B : n t=1 {Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x)} → E set<label>(18)</label></formula><p>In order to B assign an experience point E t i to Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x),B yields a value for each dimension of E space (where each dimension corresponds to a predicate in P set ) from entries in the tuple yielded by Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x) (where each entry value corresponds to an encoding value for a neuron in the network). Indeed, let us define the output of Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x) as a tuple of values κ i , each corresponding to a neuron in the vertices set V sensory.[t,t+k] of the sensory nervous system network:</p><p>Code (1) </p><formula xml:id="formula_19">(net sensory.[t,t+k] , x) = (κ 1 , ..., κ |V sensory.[t,t+k] | )<label>(19)</label></formula><p>Where </p><p>Such that A is to be assessed experimentally, with neurons neur u.[t,t+k] in V sensory.[t,t+k] significantly correlating (p &lt; 0.005) with the presentation of stimuli with high-valued P i.j in P set (P i.j (x) ≥ 0.8 ).</p><p>Finally, B is defined as the tuple of dimensions of experiential space e P i.j</p><p>where each P i.j is a predicate in P set , such tuple yields an experience point E t i : B(Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x)) = (e P i.j</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">) P i.j ∈Pset = E t i<label>(21)</label></formula><p>Moreover, in order to ensure that the values from Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x), which are in [0, 1] V sensory. [t,t+k] , are in the appropriate dimensions for E t i which is in [0, 1] |Pset| , each e P i.j is defined as 0 if the count of coding units κ i mapped to the given predicate P i.j is 0, and as the average of each κ i mapped to the given predicate P i.j otherwise, such that if there is only one coding unit κ i mapped to P i.j this value will be given for e P i.j and if there is more the average will be taken:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">e P i.j = 0 if N P i.j = 0 κ i ∈A set P i.j κ i N P i.j if N P i.j ≥ 1<label>(22)</label></formula><p>Such that N P i.j is the number of coding units κ i mapped to the given predicate P i.j , defined as the cardinality of the set of all neurons neur u.[t,t+k] in V sensory.[t,t+k] , mapped to P i.j from the assignment function A, denoted A set P i.j :</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">N P i.j = |A set P i.j |<label>(23)</label></formula><p>Where:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">A set P i.j = {neur u.[t,t+k] ∈ V sensory.[t,t+k] |A(neur u.[t,t+k] ) = P i.j }<label>(24)</label></formula><p>Such that for each neuron neur u.[t,t+k] in V sensory.[t,t+k] , there is a code κ i in Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x) :</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">∀neur u.[t,t+k] (neur u.[t,t+k] ∈ V sensory.[t,t+k] =⇒ ∃κ i (κ i ∈ Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x))<label>(25)</label></formula><p>This definition e P i.j allows to assess three possible scenarios encountered when aiming to relate neural activity Code (1) (net sensory.[t,t+k] , x) to sensory experience E t i : (i) the case where the sensory nervous system did not perceive or assess all the perceivable predicates<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">2</ref> applied to the given stimulus, in such a case, corresponding dimensions in experiential space are taken as 0 as if a predicate is not perceived the stimulus will be experienced as not possessing it; (ii) the case where the sensory nervous system perceived and assessed all the perceivable predicates, and each neuron assessed a given predicate, in such case the encoding values are taken as the experiential point values ; (iii) the case where the sensory nervous system more than one neuron to a given predicate, yielding more neural encoding values than they are perceivable predicates, in such a case, the average values of neurons encoding the same predicate are taken as the value for the appropriate dimension in experiential space.</p><p>Since an experience trajectory E [t 0 ,tn] is tuple of experience points E t i , it is given by a tuple of B outputs: (1) (net sensory.t 0 , x)), ..., B(Code (1) (net sensory.tn , x))) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> Such that a time t i in experiential space corresponds to a time interval [t, t+k] for network encodings Code (1) . Hence, the notation net sensory.t i refers to the network during a given time interval [t, t + k], such that this time interval is mapped to the instant t i in experiential time.</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">E [t 0 ,tn] = (B(Code</formula><p>Let us now define the path length L of an experience E [t 0 ,tn] , i.e. how far did an experience travel through the experiential space, as the sum of all the distances between each consecutive point in the trajectory E [t 0 ,tn] :</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">L(E [t 0 ,tn] ) = n-1 i=0 d(E t i+1 , E t i )<label>(27)</label></formula><p>Moreover, the distance speed s of an experience E [t 0 ,tn] can be defined as the the distance between the first and last experiential points within it d(E t+k , E t ), divided by their time difference ∆t:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">s(E [t 0 ,tn] ) = d(E tn , E t 0 ) ∆t<label>(28)</label></formula><p>Finally, path-average speed L s of an experience E [t 0 ,tn] can be defined as the path length L of that experience E [t 0 ,tn] , divided by the temporal duration of the experience ∆t:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">L s (E [t 0 ,tn] ) = L(E [t 0 ,tn] ) ∆t<label>(29)</label></formula><p>The distance and path-average speed equations allow to track how much perceptual changes occurred within an experience. This formalism allows for complex, multi-sensory processing of different predicates applied to stimuli, to be compressed into a singular, unified trajectory in experiential space:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">E [t 0 ,tn] .</formula><p>Indeed, let us consider a visual stimulus, in a toy system which can only represents three predicate P 1 , P 2 , P 3 , such that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">P 1 (x) ≡ (wavelength(x) = 560nm) , P 2 (x) ≡ (width(x) = 0.2cm) , P 3 (x) ≡ (orientation(x) = 90 • )<label>(30)</label></formula><p>P 1 thus expresses how "yellow (green-ish)" a stimulus is, i.e. 0 means not yellow (green-ish) at all, 1 means fully yellow (green-ish) blue ; P 2 expresses how wide in with respect to 0.2cm a stimulus is, and P 2 expresses how oriented compared to 90 • a stimulus. Since all predicates P n are maps from the set of all stimuli to [0,1], i.e. ∀P n (P n : S → [0, 1]), the experiential metric space associated with a system that processes "P 1 , P 2 , P 3 " is the set E set p1,2,3 , containing the outputs of the function X p1,2,3 : S → [0, 1] 3 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">E space p1,2,3 = (E set p1,2,3 , d)<label>(31)</label></formula><p>Such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">E set p1,2,3 = {X p1,2,3 (x)|X p1,2,3 (x) = (P 1 (x), P 2 (x), P 3 (x)) ∧ x ∈ S} (32)</formula><p>Thus, if the solution to the universal coding equation Code (1) for the network of the sensory nervous system net (123).t in this toy model yields the following values :</p><p>Code (1) (net (123).t ) = [0.7, 0.1, 1] , Code (1) </p><formula xml:id="formula_34">(net (123).t ) ∈ [0, 1] 3 (33)</formula><p>Then the coordinates of the sensory experience of the system with the experiential space will be:</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">E x = B([0.7, 0.1, 1]), E x ∈ E space p1,2,3<label>(34)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Main Hypotheses and Testable Predictions</head><p>Having now outlined the mathematical description of theory expressed in this work, this section will posit the main hypotheses and testable predictions of the model, in order to make it experimentally and empirically tractable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">How to test the model</head><p>1. First, one should define a set of stimuli S to present to participants, as well as a set of perceivable predicates P set applied to these objects. This should be done following the predicate coding methodology <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>): "Choose level 1 predicates (most "fundamental" and irreducible features of stimuli), then construct higher level predicates through combinations of lower-level predicates. Such higher level predicates can be evaluated through the predicate equation [and Łukasiewicz semantics (Lukasiewicz, 1970, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>) (Vincenzo, 2013, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Malinowski, 2007, [13]</ref>)]:</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">P i.j (x) = ⃝ L l=1 Φ op l ,a l ((P i-1.k (x)) P i-1.k ∈B i.j ) , such that i ̸ = 1 (35)</formula><p>[Where: x is the given stimulus, B i.j is the set of all the lower-level predicates used to "build" P i.j , Φ op l ,a l assigns the values of lower-order predicates using Łukasiewicz semantics, it assigns the value to every syntactic unit built from lower-level predicates, based on the l-th operator "op" applied to it, and the arity of the argument of the given operator op l is denoted "a l "; ⃝ L l=1 Φ op l ,a l is the composition of Φ op l ,a l for every syntactic unit, L is the number of units, ] Then choose a psychophysical threshold τ and reduce the assessed predicated to those for which Perceivable (P i.j ) ≥ τ ." - <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>) 2. Having constructed S and P set , one should then construct the X function as well as E set and E space . 3. Then, while presenting a stimulus x to participants, such that x ∈ S, one should record neural activity (spikes or BOLD signal) and estimate the solution to the universal coding equation for networks Code (1) . 4. Choose the distance function d in E space = (E set , d) and compare alternatives. 5. Finally, compare results given by B and E space to alternative metrics, such as representational similarity analysis <ref type="bibr">(Kriegeskorte et al., 2008, [12]</ref>) (Dimsdale-Zucker et al., 2018, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Testable Predictions</head><p>H1: TMS-induced perturbations to regions responsible for processing a subset of perceivable predicates should selectively distort corresponding dimensions in E space • Prediction: TMS-induced perturbations to regions responsible for processing a subset of predicates, should selectively distort the corresponding coordinates of a trajectory E [t 0 ,tn] . For instance, a TMS-induced perturbation to V4 in extrastriate visual cortex, should selectively distort corresponding color coordinates of the experience "E [t 0 ,tn] ".</p><p>• Construct a set of stimuli S, a set of perceivable predicates P set , a function X and an experiential space E space from the guidelines in section 3.1. Assess the assignment function A by presenting stimuli with given predicates and associating cells which significantly respond selectively to these predicates P set . Conduct two experimental sessions. In the first session, "session 1", present participant with stimuli in S and record neural activity in-vivo, through methods such as fMRI, MEG or single-neuron recording. During the second session, "session 2", present participants with the same stimuli as in session 1 and apply TMS-induced perturbations selectively to areas linked to the perception of given predicates of stimuli presented through the A function, and record neural activity in-vivo, through methods such as fMRI, MEG or single-neuron recoding. Compute Code (1) for both sessions, from Code (1) and A compute B for both sessions, and from B, compute trajectories E [t 0 ,tn] for both sessions. If E [t 0 ,tn] for session 1 contains higher values for predicates who were assigned, through A, to neurons in the area where TMS-induced perturbations were applied, than E [t 0 ,tn] for session 2, the hypothesis is validated, else it is falsified.</p><p>H2: The implementation of a Brain-Computer Interface directly interacting with the sensory nervous system, would yield phenomenal representations coming from the interface within the experience coordinates • Prediction: The implementation of a Brain-Computer Interface directly interacting with the sensory nervous system, would yield representations coming from the interface within the experience coordinates "E [t 0 ,tn] ".</p><p>• Experimental Design: Construct a set of stimuli S, a set of perceivable predicates P set , a function X and an experiential space E space from the guidelines in section 3.1. Assess the assignment function A by presenting stimuli with given predicates and associating cells which significantly respond selectively to these predicates P set . Conduct two experimental sessions. In the first session, "session 1", present participant with stimuli in S and record neural activity in-vivo, through methods such as fMRI, MEG or single-neuron recoding. In the second experimental session, while complying with ethical guidelines, implementation of a Brain-Computer Interface directly interacting with the sensory nervous system, preferably of a neuromorphic type. Such a Brain-Computer Interface should be trained to selectively respond to given predicates and interact with neurons which are assigned, through A, to similar predicates. During the second experimental session, "session 2", present no stimuli but generate activity in the Brain-Computer Interface assessing the presence of a stimuli with given predicates. Compute Code (1) for both sessions from neural data, from Code (1) and A compute B for both sessions, and from B, compute trajectories E [t 0 ,tn] for both sessions. If E [t 0 ,tn] from session 2 contains active predicate values, the hypothesis is validated, else it is falsified.</p><p>H3: The Path-average speed L s of an experience trajectory is higher when presenting a gradually changing sequence of stimuli with diverse predicate values than when presenting unchanging stimuli during the same fixed time interval.</p><p>• Prediction: The presentation of a gradually changing sequence of stimuli with diverse predicate values during a fixed time interval should yield a higher path-average speed L s , than the presentation of unchanging stimuli during the same fixed time interval.</p><p>• Experimental design: Construct a set of stimuli S, a set of perceivable predicates P set , a function X and an experiential space E space from the guidelines in section 3.1. Assess the assignment function A by presenting stimuli with given predicates and associating cells which significantly respond selectively to these predicates P set . Conduct one experimental session, "session 1", where participants are presented with a gradually changing sequence of stimuli in S with diverse predicate values during a fixed time interval. Conduct another experimental session, "session 2", where participants are presented with an unchanging stimulus in S during the same fixed time interval. Record neural activity in-vivo, through methods such as fMRI, MEG or single-neuron recoding. Compute Code (1) for both sessions from neural activity, from Code (1) and A compute B for both sessions, and from B, compute trajectories E [t 0 ,tn] for both sessions. Then compute the path-average speed L s for both sessions. If L s session 1 &gt; L s session 2, then the hypothesis is validated, else it is falsified.</p><p>H4: The distance speed s of an experience trajectory is higher when presenting unchanging stimuli followed by a rapid change in stimuli with diverse predicate than when presenting unchanging stimuli during the same fixed time interval.</p><p>• Prediction: The presentation of unchanging stimuli followed by a rapid change in stimuli with diverse predicate values during a fixed time interval should yield a higher distance speed s, than the presentation of unchanging stimuli during the same fixed time interval.</p><p>• Experimental design: Construct a set of stimuli S, a set of perceivable predicates P set , a function X and an experiential space E space from the guidelines in section 3.1. Assess the assignment function A by presenting stimuli with given predicates and associating cells which significantly respond selectively to these predicates P set . Conduct one experimental session, "session 1", where participants are presented with unchanging stimuli followed by a rapid change in stimuli (all stimuli must be in S) with diverse predicate values during a fixed time interval. Conduct another experimental session, "session 2", where participants are presented with an unchanging stimulus in S during the same fixed time interval. Record neural activity in-vivo, through methods such as fMRI, MEG or single-neuron recoding. Compute Code (1) for both sessions, from Code (1) and A compute B for both sessions, and from B, compute trajectories E [t 0 ,tn] for both sessions. Then compute the distance speed s for both sessions. If s session 1 &gt; s session 2, then the hypothesis is validated, else it is falsified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>The mathematical model introduced in this work allows for a description of a unified sensory experience, from neural activity analyzed through the lens of Predicate Coding <ref type="bibr">(Bonal, 2025, [3]</ref>). Indeed, it aims to provide a mathematical solution to the fourth instance of Feldman's Neural Binding Problem taxonomy (2012, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>), i.e. the subjective unity of perception, through the unification of diverse neural activity throughout the sensory nervous system, into a coherent unified experience, as a trajectory within "experiential space". However, while this model gives a mathematical readout from neural activity to phenomenal sensory experience, a major mystery still remains: the causal link between neural activity and phenomenal experience, which can be seen as a instantiation of the philosophical mind-body problem <ref type="bibr">(Chalmers, 1997, [4]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Descartes, 1641, [8]</ref>).</p><p>Indeed, one could aim to treat Binding function B as more than just a readout, and understood as a form of "communicative" link between the sensory nervous system and and an abstract experience, yielding phenomenal perception. However, if one aims to interpret the mathematics presented in this work in such a way, one problem arises: How can such link instantiate itself in an experimentally discoverable manner? For instance, the communicative link between motor neurons in the brain and voluntary somatic control can be traced back to corticospinal tracts <ref type="bibr">(Heffner et al., 2008, [11]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Ueno et al., 2018, [23]</ref>) <ref type="bibr">(Usuda et al., 2022, [24]</ref>). Presuming the existence of such a link would either require a complete reductionist approach, reducing phenomenal activity to neural activity, which would partly dismiss the problem rather than answer it, or accepting the existence of a link between a physiological process (neural encoding) and an abstract experiential space, which is empirically challenging and hard to falsify.</p><p>Hence, while this model aims to provide a clear mathematically solution to the presence of a unity of phenomenological sensory experience from diverse neural encodings, if one aims to extend the purpose of this readout to serve as "communicative" link, the philosophical mind-body problem arises.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, |V sensory.[t,t+k] | is the cardinality of V sensory.[t,t+k] , and each κ i is the code for neuron neur u.[t,t+k] in V sensory.[t,t+k] . Now let us define a total assignment A from the vertices set of the network to P set : A : V sensory.[t,t+k] → P set</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>These many-valued predicates, initially introduced in the "Framework for a Testable Metaphysical Science"(Bonal,  </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>2024,<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>), were later used for Predicate coding(Bonal,  2025,[3])</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_2"><p>A predicate being perceivable does not necessarily mean that it is always perceived.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Qualia: The geometry of integrated information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Balduzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tononi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000462</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000462</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000462" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Computational Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Framework for a testable metaphysical science: Type-theoretic system and computational experimentation using z3 smt solver</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bonal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.13140/RG.2.2.31992.87043/1</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.31992.87043/1" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Unified model of neural encoding and decoding of stimuli: Predicate-coding from applied category theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bonal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.5573913</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.5573913" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The conscious mind: In search of a fundamental theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chalmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<pubPlace>Oxford Paperbacks, Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Formation of brain-wide neural geometry during visual item recognition in monkeys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kunimatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Oya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Imaizumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Matsumoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tsubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hikosaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Minamimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Naya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.isci.2025.111936</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2025.111936" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111936</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural population geometry: An approach for understanding biological and artificial neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.conb.2021.10.010.computationalNeuro-science</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.conb.2021.10.010.computationalNeuro-science" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Neurobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification and geometry of general perceptual manifolds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sompolinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1103/PhysRevX.8.031003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. X</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31003</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Descartes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Meditations on First Philosophy</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1641">1641</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chapter 27 -representational similarity analyses: A practical guide for functional mri applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dimsdale-Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ranganath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/B978-0-12-812028-6.00027-6</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-812028-6.00027-6" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of in Vivo Neural Plasticity Techniques</title>
		<title level="s">Handbook of Behav-ioral Neuroscience</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Manahan-Vaughan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="525" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The neural binding problem(s)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11571-012-9219-8</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11571-012-9219-8" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cognitive Neurodynamics doi</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variation in form of the pyramidal tract and its relationship to digital dexterity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heffner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Masterton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000124401</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Behavior and Evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representational similarity analysis -connecting the branches of systems neuroscience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kriegeskorte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bandettini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/neuro.06.004.2008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Systems Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Many Valued and Nonmonotonic Turn in Logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Malinowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S1874-5857(07)80004-5</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S1874-5857(07)80004-5" />
		<editor>Gabbay, D.M., Woods, J.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="94" />
			<pubPlace>North-Holland, Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>of Handbook of the History of Logic</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A neural cocktail-party processor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Von Der Malsburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/BF00337113</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00337113" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biological Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Łukasiewicz logic: An introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Marra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Logic, Language, and Computation</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bezhanishvili</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Löbner</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Marra</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin Heidelberg, Berlin, Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The metric of multidimensional psychological spaces as a function of the differential attention to subjective attributes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Micko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0022-2496(70)90061-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/0022-2496(70)90061-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binding and the phenomenal unity of consciousness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Revonsuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/ccog.1999.0384</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1006/ccog.1999.0384" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Consciousness and Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solving the binding problem: Assemblies form when neurons enhance their firing rate-they don&apos;t need to oscillate or synchronize</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Roelfsema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neuron.2023.03.016</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2023.03.016" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1003" to="1019" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The manifold ways of perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Seung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.290.5500.2268</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">290</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2268" to="2269" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An information integration theory of consciousness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tononi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1471-2202-5-42</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2202-5-42" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feature binding, attention and object perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Treisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.1998.0284</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B: Biological Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">353</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1295" to="1306" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A feature-integration theory of attention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Treisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gelade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognitive Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Corticospinal circuits from the sensory and motor cortices differentially regulate skilled movements through distinct spinal interneurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ueno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Niehaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maezawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Crone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goulding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Baccei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.03.137</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2018.03.137" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1286" to="1300" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative comparison of corticospinal tracts arising from different cortical areas in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Usuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sugawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fukuyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakazawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Amemiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nishimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neures.2022.06.008</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neures.2022.06.008" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscience Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">183</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The metric of visual space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3758/BF03207058</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3758/BF03207058" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perception and Psychophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Selected Works</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Łukasiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
			<pubPlace>North-Holland, Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
