<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Dose response relationship between blood concentrations of THC and crash culpability risk: meta-regression of culpability studies Type: Mini review</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Albrecht</surname></persName>
							<email>matthew.albrecht@uwa.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Psychological Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Western Australian Centre for Road Safety Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Western Australia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Perth</settlement>
									<region>Western Australia</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Razi</forename><surname>Hasan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Psychological Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Western Australian Centre for Road Safety Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Western Australia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Perth</settlement>
									<region>Western Australia</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Damir</forename><surname>Kekez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Psychological Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Western Australian Centre for Road Safety Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Western Australia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Perth</settlement>
									<region>Western Australia</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Huaqiong</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Curtin School of Nursing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Curtin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Perth</settlement>
									<region>Western Australia</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Dose response relationship between blood concentrations of THC and crash culpability risk: meta-regression of culpability studies Type: Mini review</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">32888E870167E4D45305705F6790113B</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T06:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Recent meta-analyses on the risk associated with the detection of tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) in blood and crash risk indicate a ~10-80% increase in crash culpability for detection of THC. However, the meta-analyses did not analyse a dose-response relationship between blood concentrations of THC and risk necessary to better understand the crash risk associated with THC and to inform public risk tolerances surrounding THC and driving. Here, we leverage these recent meta-analyses to understand whether there is a blood concentration crash culpability risk relationship. We show that crash culpability risk increases with increasing THC concentration, with an inflection around 1.5-3.0 ng/ml where risk begins to increase. There is a doubling of risk around 5 ng/ml, and a potential quadrupling of risk around 10 ng/ml. Conversely, blood THC concentrations below ~1.5 ng/ml indicate practically no risk (&lt;30% increase). More studies are needed to better define risk for the lower and higher bands of blood THC concentrations. Consideration of blood concentration risk relationships are necessary for public discussions surrounding THC and crash risk.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Recent meta-analyses on the risk associated with the detection of THC in blood and crash risk have come to the conclusion that there is a 1.1-1.8 odds of an increase in culpability when THC is detected (Rogeberg 2019; <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Preuss et al. 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">White and Burns 2021)</ref>. Interestingly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">White and Burns (2021)</ref>  <ref type="table">stated:</ref> "Overall, the evidence for THC dose effects from the 17 studies is unconvincing" While a review published around the same time by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Preuss et al. (2021)</ref> stated: "High quality culpability studies (SIGN) noted that there is a dose effect of higher THC blood concentrations with increased risk for fatal crashes and those with injuries." Some of the disparity potentially comes from the lack of a formal meta-regression analysis on this same group of papers investigating the blood-concentration crash culpability risk relationship. Indeed, much of the discussion in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">White et al. (2021)</ref> on the lack of relationship is likely due to insufficient power present in any single study to properly identify the association and there was no attempt to formally pool studies that attempted to answer the dose question together into a single meta-regression analysis. Another component to the disparity is because of the high fat solubility of THC, and therefore its distribution kinetics are incredibly divergent between individuals and relates inconsistently to impairment. For example, a recent meta-analysis of neuropsychological performance studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">McCartney et al. (2022)</ref> demonstrates a fairly weak relationship between blood THC concentrations and cognitive impairment.</p><p>Although, the meta-analysis regressed performance on blood THC concentrations using a linear function, when most bloodconcentration or dose-response curves are sigmoidal on a logarithmic scale (or hyperbolic on a linear scale). It would also be beneficial to examine more specific domains (e.g., in their previous analysis where they broke down tests into sub-domains: <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">McCartney et al. 2021)</ref>.</p><p>Importantly, the failure to properly separate out blood concentrations and identify riskcurves has led to situations where the "detection"-based association with crash risk is presented as the crash risk for THC. For example, in a recent hearing before the New South Wales State Australian parliament, it was repeatedly stated that the crash risk from THC is a general modest increase of ~40% (Standing Committee on Law and Justice 2022). But this is a detection-only based crash risk, potentially missing important risk stratification for lower and higher blood concentrations of THC. A clearer delineation around blood-concentration crash culpability risk relationships is needed to better inform and calibrate risk tolerances.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Aims</head><p>Here, we leverage these recent meta-analyses to show that there is indeed a clear blood concentration crash-risk/culpability relationship. The risk is practically negligible for low concentrations under ~1 ng/ml, but increases to ~4x for concentrations &gt;~10 ng/ml and may be larger for concentrations &gt;~10 ng/ml due to uncertainty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Included papers and search</head><p>We extracted papers from three recent metaanalyses on THC associations with crash culpability risk (Rogeberg 2019; <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Preuss et al. 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">White and Burns 2021)</ref>. As the previous meta-analyses were thorough in their search criteria and execution, we do not repeat the whole meta-analysis procedure here. We attempted to update the meta-analyses by including more recent papers using the search strategy in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">White and Burns (2021)</ref>, amended to focus only on "culpability" or "responsibility" papers through inclusion of these search terms in the search. Search terms are included in the supplementary material (S1). A total of 37 records were retrieved from the initial search across 4 databases (PubMed, PsycInfo, Embase, Scopus), following removal of duplicates (n=15), 23 records remained to be assessed against inclusion criteria. Screening of the abstracts and full text was conducted by MA and HZ independently. No new papers were identified for inclusion.</p><p>We sub-selected papers in these metaanalyses that had attempted to better identify blood-concentration relationships with THC by presenting the outcomes from different bands of THC (e.g., &lt;1 ng/ml, 1-5 ng/ml, and &gt;5 ng/ml). Further inclusion criteria were that the papers needed to describe odds ratios adjusted for alcohol (and possibly other covariates) or present THC-alone odds ratios. Data were extracted for each category, and included the concentration band, odds ratio, and 95% confidence interval. Given that the presented data were in categories, we took the midpoint of bounded THC concentration categories and treated unbounded concentration categories by adding 0.5 ng/ml to the lower limit of the unbounded category. We also attempted to find reference in the paper to a median or average THC concentration for the unbounded category, but this was only available in 1 paper.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> presents the included papers excluding duplicate analyses <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Longo et al. 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Drummer et al. 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Drummer et al. , 2020;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Laumon et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Poulsen et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Martin et al. 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Brubacher et al. 2019)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis -Meta-Regression</head><p>Data were imported into R version 4.1.1 for analysis. The weights for each odds ratio were derived by calculating the standard error of the loge odds ratio ([upper 95% CI -lower 95% CI]/[2 * 1.96]) and taking the inverse square of the loge odds ratio standard error (1/se 2 ). The loge odds ratios were then entered into a mixed-effects regression model as the dependent variable, with random intercepts and slopes for each study. The fitting of the overall intercept was suppressed and defined as 0 at a log10 THC concentration of -0.8 (~0.16 ng/ml), and a sensitivity analysis was conducted by reducing the value to -2. The intercept suppression was done because -by definition -the control group has an odds ratio of 1 or loge odds ratio of 0. The relationship between the loge odds ratio and blood concentration of THC was modelled on the log10 scale using a restricted cubic spline with 4 knots, to account for any non-linearity in effect. Knots were located at the 5%, 40%, 60% and 95% quantiles, which corresponded to THC concentrations of 0.5, 2.5, 3.5, and 7.5 ng/ml (on the log10 scale, these were located at -0.30, 0.40, 0.54, and 0.88).</p><p>Restricted cubic splines were obtained from the "rms" package <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Harrell 2024)</ref>, fit using the "glmmTMB" package <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Brooks et al. 2017</ref>), and effects plot using "ggplot2" <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Wickham 2016)</ref> and the "ggeffects" (Lüdecke 2018) packages. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THC blood concentration and culpability risk relationship</head><p>There was a significant relationship between crash culpability risk and blood concentration (X 2 3 = 95.1, p &lt; 0.0001). Restricted cubic spline coefficients for log(THC) predicting loge(OR) are presented in table 2. Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the blood concentration vs crash risk relationship. Risk increased with increasing THC concentration, with an inflection around 1.5-3 ng/ml and a doubling of risk around 5 ng/ml. Risk was predicted to increase to the available limits of the data at ~10 ng/ml, estimated to confer an increased risk of culpability by 4.0x (95% CI = 3.0 -5.5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>We show a robust blood-concentration crash culpability risk relationship for THC.</p><p>Moreover, nearly every paper shows an increase in risk with increasing concentration. This suggests that previous Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Culpability risk vs blood concentration of THC. Solid black line is the predicted relationship from the restricted cubic spline with grey shading indicating the 95% CI. The increased delineation of risk also allows better identification of low-risk concentrations of THC. For concentrations under 1.5 ng/ml, the risk is very modest, probably under 30%. While the exact level of risk that should be publicly accepted is outside the scope of this paper, the clear blood-concentration risk relationship observed when all available studies that have attempted to stratify THC concentrations are analysed, can contribute to risk tolerance discourse. Concentration ranges around ~1.5-2.5 ng/ml shows the threshold upswing in the curve, with a cross-over to a crash risk of ~2x around a concentration of 5.0 ng/ml and ~4x around 10 ng/ml. This is roughly similar to the culpability risk associated with a blood alcohol concentration of 0.08-0.10 (Høye and Storesund Hesjevoll 2023).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations</head><p>There is a restricted number of studies that have delineated the upper end of blood THC concentrations on crash risk. Additionally, studies very rarely report the delay between the collection time of the sample and the time of the incident. Reporting sample/incident delays is crucial for determining whether the concentration of THC at the time of the incident may be substantially higher. Failure to report sampling delays also misses important key considerations about quantity and recency of use that likely elevate risk. Future studies should aim to report more detailed groupings of blood THC concentrations and the delays between obtaining a sample and the incident.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>These results indicate that the bloodconcentration risk relationship is relatively well-defined for THC. Questions remain surrounding how much of an increased risk is associated with a high blood concentration of THC, i.e., does the risk continue to increase beyond ~10 ng/ml or does risk plateau around an OR of 4. Similarly, low blood THC concentrations are consistent with other papers associating detection of any THC with risk, and estimates a &lt; 30% increase in risk for THC &lt; 1.5 ng/ml. Dose-response relationships should be considered for future discussions surrounding THC and crash risk. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="4,82.55,284.85,420.10,285.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Included papers and data extraction</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">THC Concentrations</cell><cell cols="2">Odds Ratios</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Study Characteristics</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Bands</cell><cell>Value</cell><cell></cell><cell>Lower</cell><cell>Upper</cell><cell>Sample</cell><cell>Adjusted/</cell></row><row><cell>Study Author</cell><cell>Year</cell><cell>Reported</cell><cell cols="2">Modelled Estimate</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell cols="2">Size Severity</cell><cell>THC-only</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 Drummer et al. 2020</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1728 Injured Adjusted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1-4.9</cell><cell>2.5</cell><cell>1.6</cell><cell>0.9</cell><cell>2.7</cell><cell>59</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>5-9.9</cell><cell>7.5</cell><cell>1.9</cell><cell>0.7</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>19</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt; 5</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>3.2</cell><cell>1.3</cell><cell>7.2</cell><cell>31</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt; 10</cell><cell>10.5</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1.3</cell><cell>82</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2 Brubacher et al. 2019</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1660 Injured Adjusted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0-1.9</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1.09</cell><cell>0.63</cell><cell>1.92</cell><cell>77</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2-4.9</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>1.16</cell><cell>0.66</cell><cell>2.13</cell><cell>68</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt; 5</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>1.74</cell><cell>0.59</cell><cell>6.36</cell><cell>20</cell></row><row><cell>3 Martin et al.</cell><cell>2017</cell><cell>&lt; 1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3734</cell><cell>Fatal</cell><cell>Adjusted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1-2.9</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1.4</cell><cell>0.86</cell><cell>2.23</cell><cell>159</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3-4.9</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1.92</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>4.42</cell><cell>64</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt; 5</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>2.47</cell><cell>1.2</cell><cell>5.09</cell><cell>102</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">4 Drummer et al. 2004</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1704</cell><cell>Fatal</cell><cell>THC-only</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 5</cell><cell>2.5</cell><cell>0.827</cell><cell>0.238</cell><cell>3.78</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt; 5</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>6.6</cell><cell>1.5</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>49</cell></row><row><cell>5 Laumon et al.</cell><cell>2005</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>9013</cell><cell>Fatal</cell><cell>Adjusted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 1</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>1.57</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>2.95</cell><cell>78</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1-2.9</cell><cell>1.5</cell><cell>1.54</cell><cell>1.09</cell><cell>2.18</cell><cell>298</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3-4.9</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>2.13</cell><cell>1.22</cell><cell>3.73</cell><cell>143</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt; 5</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>2.21</cell><cell>1.32</cell><cell>3.38</cell><cell>240</cell></row><row><cell>6 Poulsen et al.</cell><cell>2014</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>533</cell><cell>Fatal</cell><cell>Adjusted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 2</cell><cell>1.5</cell><cell>1.42</cell><cell>0.63</cell><cell>3.24</cell><cell>88</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2-4.9</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>0.98</cell><cell>0.44</cell><cell>2.21</cell><cell>80</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt; 5</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>1.61</cell><cell>0.62</cell><cell>4.22</cell><cell>72</cell></row><row><cell>7 Longo et al.</cell><cell>2000</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1887 Injured THC-only</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&lt; 1</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>0.36</cell><cell>0.07</cell><cell>1.85</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1-2</cell><cell>1.5</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell>1.33</cell><cell>19</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt; 2.1</cell><cell>2.5</cell><cell>1.79</cell><cell>0.67</cell><cell>4.79</cell><cell>18</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>-coefficients for THC from the meta-regression model</cell></row></table><note><p>* log(THC)' and log(THC)'' represents the restricted cubic spline variables</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>/ or car/ or (car or cars or automobile* or vehicle* or vehicular or traffic* or road or "off-road").tw.) and (accident* or crash* or collision* or collide* or injury or injuries or fatal*).tw. AND exp cannabis/ or exp cannabinoids/ or "cannabis use"/ OR (hemp OR cannabis OR marihuana OR marijuana OR pot OR hash OR hashish OR ganja OR thc OR tetrahydrocannabinol).tw. / or car/ or (car or cars or automobile* or vehicle* or vehicular or traffic* or road or "off-road").tw.) and (accident* or crash* or collision* or collide* or injury or injuries or fatal*).tw. AND cannabis/ or exp cannabinoids/ or "cannabis use"/ or cannabis smoking/ OR (hemp OR cannabis OR marihuana OR marijuana OR pot OR hash OR hashish OR ganja OR thc OR tetrahydrocannabinol).tw. Keyword (car OR cars OR automobile* OR vehicle* OR vehicular OR traffic* OR road OR "offroad") AND (accident* OR crash* OR collision* OR collide* OR injury OR injuries OR fatal*) AND hemp OR cannabis OR marihuana OR marijuana OR pot OR hash OR hashish OR ganja OR thc OR tetrahydrocannabinol AND (culpab* OR responsib*) Limit: English, 2020&gt;</figDesc><table><row><cell>Supplementary Material</cell></row><row><cell>S1 -Search</cell></row><row><cell>PubMed</cell></row><row><cell>"Accidents, Traffic"[mh]</cell></row><row><cell>OR</cell></row><row><cell>("Motor Vehicles"[mh] or ("Automobiles"[mh] OR car[tw] OR cars[tw] OR</cell></row><row><cell>automobile*[tw] OR vehicle*[tw] OR vehicular[tw] OR traffic*[tw] OR road[tw] OR off-</cell></row><row><cell>road[tw]) AND (accident*[tw] OR crash*[tw] OR collision*[tw] OR collide*[tw] OR</cell></row><row><cell>injury[tw] OR injuries[tw] OR fatal*[tw]))</cell></row><row><cell>AND</cell></row><row><cell>"Cannabis"[mh] OR "Cannabinoids"[mh] OR "Marijuana Smoking"[mh] OR "Marijuana</cell></row><row><cell>Use"[mh] OR hemp[tw] OR cannabis[tw] OR marihuana[tw] OR marijuana[tw] OR</cell></row><row><cell>pot[tw] OR hash[tw] OR hashish[tw] OR ganja[tw] OR thc[tw] OR</cell></row><row><cell>tetrahydrocannabinol[tw]</cell></row><row><cell>AND</cell></row><row><cell>(culpab* OR responsib*)</cell></row><row><cell>Limit: English, 2020&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>PsycInfo</cell></row><row><cell>motor traffic accidents/</cell></row><row><cell>OR</cell></row><row><cell>(motor vehicleAND</cell></row><row><cell>(culpab* OR responsib*)</cell></row><row><cell>Limit: English, 2020&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Embase</cell></row><row><cell>traffic accident/</cell></row><row><cell>OR</cell></row><row><cell>(motor vehicleAND</cell></row><row><cell>(culpab* OR responsib*)</cell></row><row><cell>Limit: English, 2020&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Scopus</cell></row><row><cell>Title/Abstract/</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Against quantiles: categorization of continuous variables in epidemiologic research, and its discontents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bennette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vickers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1471-2288-12-21</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2288-12-21" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Medical Research Methodology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">glmmTMB balances speed and flexibility among packages for zero-inflated generalized linear mixed modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kristensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Van</forename><surname>Benthem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The R journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cannabis use as a risk factor for causing motor vehicle crashes: a prospective study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brubacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Erdelyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/add.14663</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/add.14663" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Addiction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1616" to="1626" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Odds of culpability associated with use of impairing drugs in injured drivers in Victoria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Drummer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gerostamoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Rago</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.aap.2019.105389</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aap.2019.105389" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Australia. Accident Analysis &amp; Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105389</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The involvement of drugs in drivers of motor vehicles killed in Australian road traffic crashes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Drummer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gerostamoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Batziris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0001-4575</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0001-4575" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Accident Analysis &amp; Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">02</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Harrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">rms: Regression Modeling Strategies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alcohol and driving-How bad is the combination? A meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Høye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Storesund</forename><surname>Hesjevoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/15389588.2023.2204984</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/15389588.2023.2204984" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Traffic Injury Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cannabis intoxication and fatal road crashes in France: population based case-control study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Laumon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gadegbeku</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-L</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M-B</forename><surname>Biecheler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.38648.617986.1F</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.38648.617986.1F" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">331</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1371</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prevalence of alcohol, cannabinoids, benzodiazepines and stimulants amongst injured drivers and their role in driver culpability: Part II: The relationship between drug prevalence and drug concentration, and driver culpability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Longo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lokan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0001-4575</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0001-4575" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Accident Analysis &amp; Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ggeffects: Tidy Data Frames of Marginal Effects from Regression Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lüdecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Open Source Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cannabis, alcohol and fatal road accidents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-L</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gadegbeku</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0187320</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0187320" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">187320</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are blood and oral fluid Δ9tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) and metabolite concentrations related to impairment? A meta-regression analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mccartney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arkell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2021.11.004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2021.11.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">104433</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determining the magnitude and duration of acute Δ9tetrahydrocannabinol (Δ9-THC)induced driving and cognitive impairment: A systematic and meta-analytic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mccartney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arkell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mcgregor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2021.01.003</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2021.01.003" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The culpability of drivers killed in New Zealand road crashes and their use of alcohol and other drugs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Poulsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Moar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pirie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.aap.2014.02.019</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aap.2014.02.019" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Accident Analysis &amp; Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A meta-analysis of the crash risk of cannabis-positive drivers in culpability studies-Avoiding interpretational bias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Preuss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Huestis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.aap.2018.11.011</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aap.2018.11.011" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Accident Analysis &amp; Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2021. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Frontiers in Psychiatry</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The risk of being culpable for or involved in a road crash after using cannabis: A systematic review and meta-analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Burns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/205032452110</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/205032452110" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Drug Science, Policy and Law</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">55381</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Road Transport Amendment (Medicinal cannabis exemptions from offences) Bill 2021</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wickham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Standing Committee on Law and Justice</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2022</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York; Sydney, NSW, Australia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
