<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Democratic Deconsolidation Reconsidered: Support for Democracy Recovers Among Young Europeans, Broad Decline in Africa</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Abigail Branford</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Oxford Katja Salomo</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Kassel</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Democratic Deconsolidation Reconsidered: Support for Democracy Recovers Among Young Europeans, Broad Decline in Africa</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F5208714C70093916C7115EA0104ED8E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Recent debates on 'democratic deconsolidation' raise three key questions: are younger people less supportive of democracy; where is this occurring; and is the trend worsening? This paper addresses these questions by comparing African and European democracies using five rounds of the Integrated Values Survey and nine rounds of the Afrobarometer. We apply age-period-cohort-interaction models to assess generational support for democracy and openness to authoritarian alternatives; we also differentiate democratic trajectories across regions. In Africa, the dominant pattern is a general downward trend in democratic support and rejection of authoritarianism, in some cases led by younger cohorts. In Europe, although cohort effects continue to reflect declines in democratic support that were concentrated among younger age groups in the past, support for democracy subsequently recovered among more recent cohorts. However, some European electoral democracies show a rise in openness to authoritarianism, especially among young cohorts. deconsolidation; public opinion; young people; democratic attitudes; democratic support; APC analysis; regime preferences</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Recent years have seen intense debate over whether consolidated democracies face "deconsolidation," especially regarding declining public support for democracy. <ref type="bibr">Foa and</ref><ref type="bibr">Mounk (2016, 2017)</ref> argue this decline reflects a generational cohort effect, with younger cohorts less supportive than older ones, rather than a transient age effect. This claim has faced extensive critique <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Claassen and Magalhães 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr">Foa and</ref><ref type="bibr">Mounk 2016, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Grassi et al. 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kriesi 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Norris 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Voeten 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wuttke 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Zilinsky 2019</ref>) leaving no consensus on whether the trend exists, where it occurs, or how to interpret it.</p><p>This study addresses unresolved questions about generational support for democracy by employing age-period-cohort (APC) models, which reduce risks of conflating age and cohort effects or neglecting period influences. Unlike prior research largely focused on Europe and North America, this analysis compares European and African democracies which enables systematic cross-regional and cross-regime comparison.</p><p>Drawing on the World and European Values Surveys alongside the Afrobarometer, we evaluate whether younger cohorts show diminished democratic support, whether they display greater openness to authoritarian alternatives, and whether this trend is gradual or driven by a distinct "shock" cohort. These questions are situated within the broader literature on democratic (de-)consolidation. Consolidation involves entrenched democratic legitimacy, procedural norm commitment, civil society institutionalisation, and widespread liberal-democratic attitudes <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Inglehart 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Levitsky and Way 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Levitsky and Ziblatt 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Linz and Stepan 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr">Przeworski and Limongi 1997)</ref>. Deconsolidation is marked by rising anti-democratic actors, norm erosion, weakening public support for democracy, and openness to authoritarianism <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Foa and Mounk 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Linz and Stepan 1996)</ref>. While modernisation theory holds that support for democracy should be resilient due to a self-reinforcing cycle <ref type="bibr">(Lipset 1959)</ref>, recent declines in democratic freedoms in countries such as the US, Hungary, Poland, Mauritius, and South Africa challenge this assumption (V-Dem Institute 2025).</p><p>Generational attitudes are critical for assessing democracy's resilience. Public concerns mirror academic debates: for example, in 2025 a British news outlets claimed over half of UK Gen Z favoured dictatorship (Ahmed 2025). However, clarifying respondents' understanding of dictatorship, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Duffy and Morini (2025)</ref> found only 6% genuinely supported a dictatorial system and argued that such exaggerations were harmful. Similarly, <ref type="bibr">Mattes and Richmond (2015)</ref> challenged narratives of South African youth disillusionment, though 2024 election coverage depicted the "born-free" generation as alienated from democracy (Mark 2024; Onishi and Searcey 2024). These cases reveal widespread generational anxieties and underscore the need for comparative, methodologically rigorous analyses that accurately map generational political change.</p><p>Literature Review <ref type="bibr">Foa and</ref><ref type="bibr">Mounks' (2016, 2017)</ref> youth deconsolidation thesis argues that young people's democratic attitudes are pivotal to democracy's future. Since younger generations eventually supplant older ones, today's youth trends may shape tomorrow's politics. This has placed the question of whether younger cohorts are less supportive of democracy at the centre of debates on democratic deconsolidation. The youth deconsolidation thesis has sparked three interrelated debates: (1) whether younger generations genuinely support democracy less than older ones, and in which regions this occurs; (2) whether observed youth declines reflect disaffection with democracy or simply higher democratic expectations; and (3) whether each successive generation is less supportive than its predecessor, or if particular cohorts are uniquely affected by historical shocks.</p><p>(1) A major criticism of Foa and Mounk's thesis is that generational decline is geographically limited. While age-period-cohort (APC) studies on this topic are rare, one such study shows that younger cohorts in the USA are less supportive of democracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Claassen and Magalhães 2023)</ref>, another finds young people more open to alternatives to democracy in some European societies <ref type="bibr">(Wuttke et al. 2022, 426)</ref>. Studies without APC controls yield mixed results: declines in some European countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Foa and Mounk 2016)</ref>, in Eastern Europe specifically (Voeten 2016), or no decline <ref type="bibr">(Foa et al. 2020a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kriesi 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Zilinsky 2019</ref>).</p><p>In the Global South, evidence is sparse and there are seemingly no age-period-cohort studies. Afrobarometer data indicate higher acceptance of authoritarian alternatives among younger groups in many African countries, alongside a rise over time across age-groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Afrobarometer 2024)</ref>. The Open Society Foundation (2023) found similar patterns, while <ref type="bibr">Foa et al. (2020a)</ref> observed declining satisfaction with democracy across all age groups in sub-Saharan Africa, reversed in recent survey waves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H1:</head><p>Younger cohorts are less supportive of democracy than older cohorts.</p><p>(2) Another central debate concerns whether declines among youth reflect only specific support for democracy (short-term evaluations of current governments) or more fundamental diffuse support (long-term commitment to democratic values, norms, legitimacy) (Easton 1975). Foa and Mounk's thesis targets diffuse support, countering a prevalent view that lower youth support signals a desire for better, not weaker, democracies <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Norris 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr">Welzel 2021)</ref>. Supporters of this optimistic view argue that the youth deconsolidation thesis mistakes unconcerning declines in specific support for concerning declines in diffuse support. To reduce this ambiguity, we also analyse rejection of non-democratic alternatives, consistent with Linz and <ref type="bibr">Stepan's (1996, 16)</ref> conception of attitudinal consolidation as strong popular belief in democracy as the best form of governance and rejection of non-democratic alternatives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H2:</head><p>Younger cohorts are more open to authoritarian alternatives than older cohorts.</p><p>(3) The final debate concerns whether support for democracy declines progressively with each younger cohort or is concentrated in cohorts shaped by specific shocks. <ref type="bibr">Foa and Mounk (2016, 7-8)</ref> predict a continuous generational decline, with the youngest least supportive. In contrast, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Grassi, Portos, and Felicetti (2024)</ref> find 25-34-year-old Europeans less supportive than 18-24-year-olds, attributing this to formative experiences during the Great Recession and Euro Crisis. Similar regional effects are noted for southern <ref type="bibr">Europe (2021)</ref>. By contrast, of African countries were less affected by the financial crisis (Stewart 2012).</p><p>H3a: Support for democracy decreases progressively among younger cohorts.</p><p>H3b: A recession "shock" generation exists in Europe, but not in Africa.</p><p>Lastly, we consider variation in the extent and trajectory of democracy. Foa and Mounk's thesis emerged from the study of "wealthy consolidated democracies" in Western Europe and North America <ref type="bibr">(2016,</ref><ref type="bibr">14</ref>), yet little comparative research examines deconsolidation across different levels of democratic consolidation. To address this, we classify different types of democracies <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Lührmann et al. 2018)</ref>  .</p><p>The V-Dem Liberal Democracy Index <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Coppedge et al. 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pemstein et al. 2024)</ref> provides an expert-based, multidimensional measure of democratic quality and underpins the Regimes of the World (RoW) typology <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Lührmann et al. 2018)</ref>. We use this typology to distinguish electoral from liberal democracies and democratic trajectories (see Appendix A1). For example, South Africa, a liberal democracy from 1999, has been reclassified as electoral since 2013 and is therefore coded "Electoral Democracy: Downgraded." This yields three types of democracies in Africa and five in Europe (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). Appendix A1 provides detailed survey descriptions, respondent numbers, and ambiguous classifcations. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Variables</head><p>Diffuse support is measured using the Integrated Values Survey item rating "Having a democratic system" on a four-point scale, and the Afrobarometer item contrasting democracy with non-democratic preferences. Rejection of authoritarianism is assessed via disapproval of a "strong leader" or "army rule" in the Integrated Values Survey, and of abolishing elections or military governance in the Afrobarometer. For analysis, the two disapproval items were averaged into a single index, with all scales normalised to a 0-1 range. These measures are standard in studies of diffuse democratic support in Europe <ref type="bibr">(Erhardt and Filsinger 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Foa and Mounk 2019)</ref> and Africa <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Mattes 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ntodwa et al. 2024)</ref>. Full item wordings are provided in Appendix A2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Approach</head><p>We utilize the age-period-cohort (APC) framework to determine whether observed outcomes reflect ageing ("age"), socio-historical conditions affecting all individuals simultaneously ("period"), or birth-year groups sharing formative socio-political experiences ("cohort"). APC analysis estimates the relative contribution of these three temporal dimensions.</p><p>The dominant statistical approach employs generalised additive models (e.g., Grasso 2014) to estimate outcome = age + period + cohort. However, given the inherent interdependence of these dimensions, we assume that historical events exert maximal influence during the "formative years" (approximately ages 16-25) (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bietenbeck et al. 2025;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Helgason and Rehm 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mannheim 1928</ref><ref type="bibr">Mannheim /1952a))</ref>. This is addressed in age-period-cohort-interaction (APCI) models <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Luo and Hodges 2022)</ref>, which capture cohort effects via age-period interactions: if period effects are consistent across age groups, this absence of significant interactions indicates there are no cohort effects.</p><p>In our analysis, period is operationalised by survey rounds (e.g., Wuttke et al. 2022)and age is grouped into seven standard categories <ref type="bibr">(Foa et al. 2020b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Grassi et al. 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zilinsky 2019): 18-24, 25-34, 35-44, 45-54, 55-64, 65-74, and 75-84 years.</ref> Respondents aged 85+ are excluded due to small sample sizes. Further methodological details appear in Appendix A3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Hypothesis 1 H1: Younger cohorts are less supportive of democracy than older cohorts.</p><p>European liberal democracies. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> displays APCI estimates of period, age, and cohort effects, with cohorts defined by age-period interactions and periods aligned with Integrated Values Survey rounds. Significant deviations would indicate divergence from expected aggregate age and period effects. In European countries that have retained their liberal democratic status since 1994 ('stable liberal democracies'), democratic support, already high, has steadily increased (period effect, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>).</p><p>Younger cohorts generally follow this trend without significant deviation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2F</ref>), providing no support for Hypothesis 1. An age effect remains, with younger cohorts consistently less supportive than older groups (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E</ref>). In European democracies 'upgraded' from electoral to liberal since 1994, support stays generally high (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>). The 1980s birth cohort shows lower-than-expected support (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>), partially supporting Hypothesis 1, further discussed under Hypothesis 3. In stable and upgraded electoral democracies, the youngest cohorts display lower support than expected from age and period effects, supporting Hypothesis 1 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3F</ref>). However, the support of these young cohorts diverged from the general positive trends between 2005-2010, and has since risen again alongside older cohorts (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>). The cohort effect thus points only to a temporary youth decline, rejecting Hypothesis 1 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3K</ref>).  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4G</ref>). Downgraded democracies show a recent spike in support (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4G</ref>). Age effects show younger cohorts consistently have slightly lower support than middle-aged groups (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4E,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4H</ref>). Hypothesis 1 holds only for stable electoral democracies, where the youngest cohorts are less supportive beyond age and period effects (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4F</ref>). There is a mostly negative period trend since 2014, which means young cohorts lead a more general decline in democratic support in African stable electoral democracies (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D</ref>). In African democracies with regime changes -upgrades or downgrades -youth support aligns with age and period effects, rejecting Hypothesis 1 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4K</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis 2</head><p>H1b: Younger cohorts are more open to authoritarian alternatives than older cohorts European Liberal Democracies. In stable liberal democracies, rejection of authoritarian alternatives fell between 1999-2014, then recovered especially among the youngest and oldest (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>). Despite this recovery, the two youngest cohorts show significant negative cohort effects, supporting Hypothesis 3 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5B</ref>). In upgraded liberal democracies, rejection remains high but dropped sharply among the youngest groups between 1999-2005, with 18-24-year-olds' rejection continuing to decline until rising after 2017 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>). Despite this recovery, negative cohort effects linger for the youngest cohorts (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5D</ref>), indicating slower-than-average recovery of the rejection of rather than growing authoritarianism. An age effect persists in both stable and upgraded liberal democracies, as young age groups are less critical of authoritarianism than average throughout periods. European Electoral Democracies. European electoral democracies, independent of their trajectory, show cohort effects among the youngest cohorts (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>), supporting Hypothesis 3. Period effects clarify group differences: In upgraded electoral democracies, rejection has declined across all ages since 1999, remaining lower than in stable liberal democracies, with younger cohorts driving this trend (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6A,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6B</ref>). Stable electoral democracies also saw a post-1999 decline, before recovery in the most recent round (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6C</ref>); however, the youngest (18-24) experienced a sharper dip and retain negative cohort effects (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6D</ref>). In downgraded electoral democracies, rejection remains relatively high (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6E</ref>). However, it fell among 18-24-year-olds around 2010, with only partial recovery after and lingering negative cohort effects (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6E,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6F</ref>). Thus, Hypothesis 3 holds across all groups, though stable and downgraded democracies reflect temporary youth shocks, while upgraded democracies exhibit a sustained downward trend led by younger cohorts. African Electoral Democracies. All African electoral democracies have seen declining rejection of authoritarian alternatives over the past decade (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7A,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7C,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7E</ref>). In upgraded African democracies, youth rejection levels fall with the general trend but display a positive cohort effect, indicating relative resistance and leading to rejection of Hypothesis 3 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7B</ref>). Stable democracies show a sharper decline among the youngest (18-24) between 2017-2021, yielding a significant negative cohort effect that supports Hypothesis 3 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7D</ref>). In downgraded democracies, the overall decline is milder but steepens for the youngest after 2021, with this cohort driving the decline and showing a significant negative cohort effect, supporting Hypothesis 3 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7F</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypothesis 3</head><p>H3a: Support for democracy decreases progressively among younger cohorts.</p><p>H3b: A recession "shock" generation exists in Europe, not in Africa.</p><p>Hypothesis 3a initially appears to hold for stable electoral democracies in Europe and Africa, where the three youngest cohorts show progressively lower democratic support beyond age and period effects (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3F,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4F</ref>). In European stable democracies, younger cohorts diverged from older groups between 2005-2010 but have since partly converged, retaining a cohort effect amid overall gains. In stable African electoral democracies, the decline among younger cohorts continues through the latest survey round (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D</ref>), indicating sustained erosion; thus, Hypothesis 3a strictly applies only to Africa. No evidence supports a Great Recession "shock" generation in Africa (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4F,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4K</ref>). In European upgraded liberal democracies, the cohort aged 18-24 during the Recession and Euro Crisis shows notably lower support in, consistent with Hypothesis 3b.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion and Conclusion</head><p>Popular support for democracy is fundamental to the stability and resilience of democratic governance, a point emphasised by thinkers from Plato <ref type="bibr">(Plato et al. 2007)</ref> to <ref type="bibr">Dahl (1971</ref><ref type="bibr">), to Diamond (1999)</ref>. While democratic consolidation involves several dimensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Levitsky and Way 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Levitsky and Ziblatt 2019;</ref><ref type="bibr">Linz and Stepan 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr">Przeworski and Limongi 1997)</ref>, this study focused on the critical and contested domain of attitudinal (de)consolidation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Claassen and Magalhães 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr">Foa and</ref><ref type="bibr">Mounk 2016, 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Grassi et al. 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kriesi 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Norris 2017</ref>; Voeten 2016; Wuttke et al.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2022; Zilinsky 2019).</head><p>We compared African and European democracies using the Integrated Values Survey and the Afrobarometer. Applying age-period-cohort-interaction models <ref type="bibr">(Luo and</ref> Hodges 2022), we analysed generational support for democracy and openness to authoritarian alternatives, grouping countries by region and democratic trajectory via V-Dem's Regimes of the World index. Our analysis emphasises interpreting cohort effects alongside period effects, revealing five distinct patterns of democratic support and authoritarian rejection across the eight country groups:</p><p>(1) Youth-led Generalised Attitudinal Deconsolidation: Characterised by young people leading a broader decline in democratic support/rejection of authoritarianism, producing distinct youth cohort effects. It is the most concerning subtype, as society-wide declines spearheaded by young people combined with cohort replacement may accelerate democratic erosion.</p><p>(2) Generalised Attitudinal Deconsolidation: Here, period effects reveal a widespread decline in democratic support/rejection of authoritarian alternatives across most age groups, with youth declining at similar rates and no significant cohort effect. Although less alarming than the youth-led subtype, its broad scope remains a serious threat.</p><p>(3) Youth-resisted Generalised Attitudinal Deconsolidation: In this pattern, young people show a more cautious decline than older cohorts, generating a cohort effect counter to youth-led decline. Observed only in African upgraded electoral democracies' rejection of authoritarianism, this resistance may slow deconsolidation but does not negate the overall decline.</p><p>The remaining types share two features: a past decline and subsequent recovery, making subtypes (4) and ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) less concerning than (1), (2), and (3). The difference between (4) and ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) lies in whether the past decline is (4) only concentrated among younger age groups or (5) across all ages but more pronounced in youth.</p><p>(4) Youth Cohort Effect After Temporary Age-Sensitive Downturn: Characterised by past declines in youth support/rejection (sometimes including the oldest groups) while other cohorts remained stable or improved. These cohort effects then diminish as youth attitudes recover, narrowing generational gaps.</p><p>(5) Youth Cohort Effect After Temporary Generalised Downturn: This pattern involves a widespread decline in democratic support across most or all age groups, with particularly strong effects on youth during their formative years. Although this creates a distinct youth cohort effect, subsequent youth cohorts bound alongside a broader recovery, distinguishing subtype (5) from (1).</p><p>Building on <ref type="bibr">Wuttke et al. (2022, 423)</ref> who argue that openness to authoritarianism should inform analyses of democratic support, we treat both as distinct but equally important dimensions: Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> situates the eight country groups within a matrix intersecting both dimensions and see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1a</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1b</ref> for separate typologies.</p><p>Guided by this matrix (Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>), we revisit our three hypotheses.</p><p>Hypothesis 1 investigates whether and where youth attitudinal deconsolidation occurs <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Claassen and Magalhães 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Inglehart 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Voeten 2016)</ref>. Surprisingly, stable liberal European democracies -often the focus of scholarly attention in these debates <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Grassi et al. 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kriesi 2020;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wuttke et al. 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Zilinsky 2019</ref>) -show the least evidence of youth-led deconsolidation (see Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>). This discrepancy may arise from prior studies inadequately disentangling age, cohort, and period effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Foa and Mounk 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Voeten 2016)</ref>. In stable European liberal democracies, younger people consistently display lower democratic support (as an age effect), yet the overall pattern corresponds to Types (4) and (5) -past downturns followed by recovery. Although youth cohort effects exist in European democracies, they coincide with positive period trends, making them less alarming than generalised declines. An exception are upgraded European electoral democracies, where youth-led general declines in rejection of authoritarianism occur. Conversely, all African democracy groups exhibit at least one sub-type of generalised attitudinal deconsolidation (Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>). Downgraded African electoral democracies reveal declining rejection of authoritarian alternatives, whereas stable and upgraded democracies show erosion in both democratic support and authoritarian rejection across age groups.</p><p>Hypothesis 2 considers whether youth scepticism reflects constructive democratic critique <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Norris 2017)</ref> or signals a shift from democratic values <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Foa and Mounk 2016)</ref>, indicated by attitudes towards authoritarian alternatives. We find that younger cohorts in several regions exhibit declining rejection of authoritarianism compared to older cohorts (see Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>). Assessing both dimensions is vital; for example, downgraded African electoral democracies show little decline in democratic support but significant declines in authoritarian rejection (Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>). When negative trends appear in both dimensions among youth, it challenges the 'critical citizens' idea that youth simply hold higher democratic expectations.</p><p>Hypothesis 3 investigates whether support declines progressively across generations or if specific cohorts are uniquely affected by historical shocks. Both Type (4) and ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) correspond to a 'recession cohort,' shaped by the Great Recession/Eurozone crisis during formative years, as previously studied in Western and Southern Europe <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Grassi et al. 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tsatsanis et al. 2021)</ref>. Such shock-induced cohort effects could signal longterm political consequences of economic crises, i.e., possibly fostering cohorts especially susceptible to anti-democratic agitation even after the crisis passes.</p><p>In stable African electoral democracies, the three youngest cohorts exhibit declining democratic support compared to their predecessors. These countries remained stagnant electoral democracies without liberal democratic phases since at least 1999 discouraging younger generations who lack direct experience of democratic progress, unlike older cohorts who experienced third-wave transitions. Consequently, younger cohorts grow increasingly pessimistic. This stagnation-driven decline contrasts with <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Claassen (2020)</ref> who links declining democratic support to democratic improvements.</p><p>Further cross-regional research is necessary to ascertain whether generational disillusionment arises from democratic stagnation, backsliding or advancement.</p><p>Our findings reveal pronounced attitudinal deconsolidation in Africa, challenging the Europe-focused literature. Most European democracies, aside from upgraded electoral regimes, exhibit cohort effects tied only to past economic shocks rather than sustained decline. In contrast, youth-led deconsolidation in stable African electoral democracies is particularly concerning. Declining youth support is a key predictor of democratic backsliding <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Claassen 2020)</ref>, particularly in countries with large youth populations <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Kwak et al. 2020)</ref>.</p><p>While our analysis does not establish causality for regional or generational differences, it suggests that democracy's level of consolidation (RoW-types) and trajectory impact generational support for democracy and, in Europe, past economic shocks likely shaped youth attitudes. Future research could investigate these potential causes alongside political disengagement <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Belchior and Teixeira 2023)</ref>   Youth-led</p><p>(2) Generalised</p><p>(3) Generalised:</p><p>Youthresisted   of elections, the provisions for suffrage, the freedom of association and expression, the observance of legal equality, individual liberties, and the constraints imposed by the judicial and legislative branches on the executive <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Nord et al. 2025)</ref>. The resulting Liberal Democracy Index is continuous from 0 to 1, although the highest empirical score in 2024 was .88 for Denmark. The Regimes of the World typology draws on the Liberal Democracy Index to differentiate between 'electoral' and 'liberal' democracies <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Lührmann et al. 2018)</ref>. The two categories share the characteristics of multiparty, free and fair elections, and institutional prerequisites for democracy. However, electoral democracies do not satisfy minimal standards for liberal principles or the rule of law <ref type="bibr">(Lührmann et al. 2018, 63)</ref>. While such a clear-cut classification might exaggerate the differences between countries that fall into separate categories <ref type="bibr">(Nord et al. 2025, 50-51)</ref>, it allows us to differentiate groups of relatively more consolidated (liberal) vs relatively less consolidated (electoral) democracies and exclude non-democracies. We used the RoW typology to identify electoral and liberal democracies at the time of the start of the most recent survey rounds in both Europe and Africa and to characterize the democratic trajectory of these countries since the first survey round included in the analysis. For instance, Belgium has been a liberal democracy from 1994 to 2017, so we classify it as "Liberal Democracy: Stable". South Africa, on the other hand, had been a liberal democracy according to the RoW classification since 1999 but has been an electoral democracy since 2013 and therefore we classify it as "Electoral Democracy: Downgraded". We thus end up with three different types of current democracies in Africa (electoral democracies that have been stable, up-or downgraded -there are no liberal African democracies at the time of the most recent round of the Afrobarometer) and five different types in Europe (electoral democracies that have been stable, up-or downgraded, as well as liberal democracies that have been stable or upgraded).    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Integrated Values Survey</head><p>"Having a strong leader who does not have to bother with parliament and elections" and "Having the army rule the country" rated "very good" to "very bad" (4-point scale)</p><p>Afrobarometer "Elections and Parliament are abolished so that the president can decide everything" and "The army comes in to govern the country" rated "strongly disapprove" to "strongly approve" (5-point scale)</p><p>Notes. The two items on disapproval of non-democratic political systems were combined into one index (mean average) for inclusion in the analysis. We use the full scales for the analysis normalized to a range of 0-1. Item-non-response are treated as random and exclude from the analysis <ref type="bibr">(Hu et al. 2025</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A3 Statistical Approach</head><p>Our hypotheses require age-period-cohort analyses to determine whether the outcome variables are a product of getting older (age), the historical context (period), or the shared experiences of people belonging to a generation (cohort). To that end, age-period-cohort analyses ascertains the relative contribution of the three time-related variables to the outcome in question. "Age" is defined as the current age of an individual at the point of data collection. "Period" refers to the broad socio-historical influences that affect all individuals living through that period of time, often necessarily defined in research by the different rounds of a repeated survey (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Wuttke et al. 2022)</ref>. "Cohort" denotes groups of individuals who were born at a similar time and thus also share other commonalities such as being in their formative years during the same period. Dominant statistical frameworks for age-period-cohort analysis utilize generalised additive models to differentiate these effects, estimating them as the outcome variable = age + period + cohort effect (e.g., Grasso 2014). However, age, period, and cohort effects are inherently interdependent. <ref type="bibr">Mannheim (1928</ref><ref type="bibr">/1952b</ref><ref type="bibr">) and later Sears (1975)</ref> both emphasised that the point in one's life (age) that one experiences significant historical events (period) mediates the strength of the period effect. Mannheim argued that individuals are most influenced by these events during their 'formative years' (which he suggested was in the range of 18 to 25). Those older than this he considered to have more set worldviews and be less strongly affected by events, while those who were younger than this range may not fully process or understand the events in a meaningful way at the time. In other words, this literature conceptualizes cohorts as period minus age <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Luo and Hodges 2022)</ref>. This indicates that the dominant generalised additive age-period-cohort models are insufficient as they cannot circumvent the inherent challenge of differentiating between invariantly conflated variables.</p><p>In order to address this conceptual discrepancy, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Luo and Hodges (2022)</ref> have proposed the age-period-cohort-interaction model (APCI), which assesses the cohort effect through age-by-period interactions. This model enables the assessment of whether cohorts deviate from the main effects of age and period. In instances where period effects are consistent across age categories, the presence of a statistically significant interaction between age and period is rendered moot and the hypothesis of cohort effects would be rejected. As the authors point out, the notion that cohort effects are age-byperiod interactions has been present in the literature for decades <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Clogg 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fienberg and Mason 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Holford 1983</ref>). The APCI model appropriately aligns statistical modeling with this concept of cohort effects.</p><p>Hence, we applied the APCI model to test our hypothesis. As a generalised model, it is specified as (Luo and Hodges 2022): 𝑔 (𝐸(𝑌 𝑖𝑗 )) = 𝜇 + 𝛼 𝑖 + 𝛽 𝑗 + 𝛼𝛽 𝑖𝑗(𝑘) , for age groups 𝑖 = 1, 2, … , 𝑎, periods 𝑗 = 1, 2, … , 𝑝, and cohorts 𝑘 = 1, 2, … , (𝑎 + 𝑝 -1). 𝐸(𝑌 𝑖𝑗 ) is the expected value of the outcome variable 𝑌 (support for democracy, rejection of authoritarian alternatives) for the 𝑖th age-group and 𝑗th period, and 𝑔 is the link function (generalised model). 𝜇 is the global mean, 𝛼 𝑖 stands for the mean difference from the global mean 𝜇 associated with the 𝑖th age-group, 𝛽 𝑗 is the mean difference from the global mean 𝜇 associated with the 𝑗th period, and 𝛼𝛽 𝑖𝑗(𝑘) finally is the age-by-period interaction term between the 𝑖th age-group and 𝑗th period group that corresponds to the effect of the 𝑘th cohort on the outcome variable 𝑌. The effect of a cohort includes multiple age-by-period interaction terms that lie on the same diagonal in a table with ages in the rows and periods in the columns.</p><p>The APCI model has recently been implemented as an R package <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Xu 2025</ref>) which we utilize to estimate the age-by-period interactions in testing our hypothesis, specifying a Gaussian link function. A notable disadvantage of the APCI model is its incapacity to "freely" define cohorts. As they are conceptualized as interaction effects, their definition is contingent upon the categorization of the age and period variables. Since neither the Integrated Values Survey nor the Afrobarometer are yearly surveys but were repeated in (slightly irregular) intervals, the cohorts follow suit and are hence also irregular.</p><p>The age categorization needs to sufficiently differentiate between various younger cohorts and identify those in their formative years. We categorize age into seven groups, that follow commonly used classifications <ref type="bibr">(Foa et al. 2020b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Grassi et al. 2024</ref>  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Sample of European and African countries and democratic trajectory</figDesc><graphic coords="7,72.00,87.87,450.69,567.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. European Liberal Democracies: Main Period (A), Main Age (B), and Cohort Deviation (C) Effects for Support for Democracy</figDesc><graphic coords="10,136.70,101.09,279.90,405.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. European Electoral Democracies: Main Period (A), Main Age (B), and Cohort Deviation (C) Effects for Support for Democracy</figDesc><graphic coords="11,132.20,109.31,288.95,620.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. African Electoral Democracies: Main Period (A), Main Age (B), and Cohort Deviation (C) Effects for Support for Democracy</figDesc><graphic coords="13,113.32,101.09,327.25,604.63" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. European Liberal Democracies: Main Period (A) and Cohort Deviation Effects (B) Rejection of Authoritarianism</figDesc><graphic coords="14,109.70,489.07,334.45,259.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. European Electoral Democracies: Main Period (A) and Cohort Deviation Effects (B) Rejection of Authoritarianism</figDesc><graphic coords="16,82.70,101.09,388.30,459.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. African Electoral Democracies: Main Period (A) and Cohort Deviation Effects (B) Rejection of Authoritarianism</figDesc><graphic coords="17,72.00,195.89,453.50,442.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>or generational economic outcomes (Romero-Vidal and Talukder 2025). Only by disentangling the forms, and understanding the drivers, of attitudinal deconsolidation can scholars and policymakers formulate interventions to prevent short-term disaffection from escalating into systemic democratic decay.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 8. Attitudinal Deconsolidation Types</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>from https://theconversation.com/only-6-of-gen-z-actually-favour-dictatorshipnot-half-as-some-reports-would-have-you-believe-250945 (accessed 25 June2025).Easton D(1975). A Re-Assessment of the Concept of Political Support. British Journal of Political Science 5 (4), 435-457.Erhardt J andFilsinger M (2024). A spectre of democracy: are populist citizens less supportive of democracy? West European Politics, 1-30. EVS. 2022. EVS Trend File 1981-2017. EVS (2025a). Data and Documentation -EVS Trend File. Available from https://staging-9bbd-europeanvaluesstudy.wpcomstaging.com/methodology-datadocumentation/evs-trend-file-1981-2017/data-and-documentation-evs-trend-file/ (accessed 10 April 2025). EVS (2025b). EVS Methodology. Available from https://staging-9bbd-europeanvaluesstudy.wpcomstaging.com/methodology-data-documentation/evs-methodology/ (accessed 10 April 2025). EVS (2025c). Integrated Values Surveys (IVS) 1981-2022. Available from https://staging-9bbd-europeanvaluesstudy.wpcomstaging.com/methodology-datadocumentation/integrated-values-surveys/ (accessed 10 April 2025).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fienberg</head><label></label><figDesc>SE and MasonWM (1985). Specification and Implementation of Age, Period and Cohort Models. In Mason WM and Fienberg SE (eds), Cohort Analysis in Social Research. New York, NY: Springer New York, pp. 45-88. Foa RS et al. 2020a. Youth and Satisfaction with De mocracy: Reversing the Democratic Disconnect? Foa RS et al. 2020b. Youth and Satisfaction with Democracy: Reversing the Democratic Disconnect? Ntodwa E, Dulani B and Masumbu M (2024). Lived Poverty and the Fate of African Democracies. African Journal of Political Science 12 (1). Open Society Foundation. 2023. Open Society Barometer: Can Democracy Deliver? Pemstein D et al. 2024. The V-Dem Measurement Model: Latent Variable Analysis for Cross-National and Cross-Temporal Expert-Coded Data, 9th. V-Dem Working Paper 21. Przeworski A and Limongi F (1997). Modernization: Theories and Facts. World Politics 49 (2), 155-183. Sears DO (1975). Political socialization. In Greenstein FI (ed), Handbook of political science. Reading, Mass. Addison-Wesley, pp. 93-153. Stewart F (2012). The Impact of Global Economic Crises on the Poor: Comparing the 1980s and 2000s. Journal of Human Development and Capabilities 13 (1), 83-105. Tsatsanis E et al. (2021). Generational and Ideological Gaps in Democratic Support: Seeds of Deconsolidation in Post-Crisis Southern Europe? South European Society and Politics 26 (2), 209-237. Voeten E (2016). Are People Really Turning Away from Democracy? SSRN Electronic Journal. Welzel C (2021). Democratic Horizons: what value change reveals about the future of democracy. Democratization 28 (5), 992-1016. Wuttke A, Gavras K and Schoen H (2022). Have Europeans Grown Tired of Democracy? New Evidence from Eighteen Consolidated Democracies, 1981-2018. British Journal of Political Science 52 (1), 416-428.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure1provides an overview of all countries in the sample and how they are classi-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure A3a. European Liberal Democracies: Main Age Effects Rejection of Authoritarianism</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure A3c. African Electoral Democracies: Main Age Effects Rejection of Authoritarianism</figDesc><graphic coords="42,120.38,111.97,311.79,523.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="40,120.48,72.00,311.78,442.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="41,134.65,103.74,283.45,601.77" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1a .</head><label>1a</label><figDesc>Attitudinal Deconsolidation Types per Democratic Trajectory: Europe</figDesc><table><row><cell>Region &amp; Democratic Trajectory</cell><cell>Upgrade</cell><cell>4) Youth Cohort Stable</cell><cell>(5) Youth Cohort Downgrade</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Temp. Generalised Downturn None (5) Youth Cohort Effect After (4) Youth Cohort Effect After Temp. Age-Sensitive Downturn (1) Generalised: Youth-led European Liberal Democracies Support for Rejection of Authoritarian Regimes Democracy European Electoral Democracies Electoral: AFR Youth Cohort Effect After Temp. Generalised Downturn Youth Cohort Effect After Temp, Age-Sensitive Downturn Stable (2) Generalised Upgrade (3) Generalised: Youth-resisted AFR Electoral: Rejection of European Liberal Democracies Youth Cohort Effect After Temp. Age-Sensitive Downturn Authoritarian European Electoral Youth-led generalised Alternatives Democracies attitudinal deconsolidation</cell><cell cols="2">Effect After Temp. Age-Sensitive Downturn Stable EUR Electoral: EUR Electoral: none Youth Cohort Effect After Effect After Temp. Generalised Downturn EUR Liberal: Upgrades Temp. Age-Sensitive Down-none EUR Electoral: None Downgrade Stable EUR Liberal: AFR Electoral: / turn Upgrade Downgrade Youth Cohort Effect After / Temp. Generalised Downturn Youth Cohort Effect After Youth Cohort Effect After Temp. Temp. Generalised Downturn Generalised Downturn</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1b .</head><label>1b</label><figDesc>Attitudinal Deconsolidation Types per Democratic Trajectory: African Electoral Democracies</figDesc><table><row><cell>Region &amp; Democratic Trajectory</cell><cell>Upgrade</cell><cell>Stable</cell><cell>Downgrade</cell></row><row><cell>Support for Democracy</cell><cell>none</cell><cell>Youth-led generalised attitudinal deconsolidation</cell><cell>Generalised attitudinal deconsolidation</cell></row><row><cell>Rejection of Authoritarian Alternatives</cell><cell>Youth-resisted generalised attitudinal deconsolidation</cell><cell>Youth-led generalised attitudinal deconsolidation</cell><cell>Youth-led generalised attitudinal deconsolidation</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table A1b .</head><label>A1b</label><figDesc>Integrated European &amp; World Values Surveys Rounds 3-7: Liberal Democracies in 2017 with Regimes of the World Classification based on 1994-2017 (Cyprus has been classified as electoral democracy since 2023 after the cut-off in 2017). b Latvia was classified as electoral democracy in 2013 and 2016. ( c Slovakia has been classified as electoral democracy since 2018).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Notes.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Country/RoW-Type 1994 to 2017</cell><cell>upgraded</cell><cell>stable</cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell>Austria</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>6136</cell><cell>6136</cell></row><row><cell>Belgium</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>7358</cell><cell>7358</cell></row><row><cell>Cyprus a</cell><cell>4050</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>4050</cell></row><row><cell>Czechia</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>10920</cell><cell>10920</cell></row><row><cell>Denmark</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>8104</cell><cell>8104</cell></row><row><cell>Estonia</cell><cell>7389</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>7389</cell></row><row><cell>Finland</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>6963</cell><cell>6963</cell></row><row><cell>France</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>8189</cell><cell>8189</cell></row><row><cell>Germany</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>18687</cell><cell>18687</cell></row><row><cell>Greece</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>3842</cell><cell>3842</cell></row><row><cell>Iceland</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>5029</cell><cell>5029</cell></row><row><cell>Ireland</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>4242</cell><cell>4242</cell></row><row><cell>Italy</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>10174</cell><cell>10174</cell></row><row><cell>Latvia b</cell><cell>5957</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>5957</cell></row><row><cell>Luxembourg</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>2821</cell><cell>2821</cell></row><row><cell>Netherlands</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>12296</cell><cell>12296</cell></row><row><cell>Norway</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>6654</cell><cell>6654</cell></row><row><cell>Portugal</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>4953</cell><cell>4953</cell></row><row><cell>Slovakia c</cell><cell>6567</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>6567</cell></row><row><cell>Slovenia</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>7595</cell><cell>7595</cell></row><row><cell>Spain</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>15168</cell><cell>15168</cell></row><row><cell>Sweden</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>8615</cell><cell>8615</cell></row><row><cell>Switzerland</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>8298</cell><cell>8298</cell></row><row><cell>Great Britain</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>11743</cell><cell>11743</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>23963</cell><cell>167787</cell><cell>191750</cell></row></table><note><p>a</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table A1c .</head><label>A1c</label><figDesc>Integrated European &amp; World Values Surveys Rounds 3-7: Electoral Democracies in 2017 with Regimes of the World Classification based on 1994-2017 Georgia was classified was electoral autocracy in 2008-2009. ( b Hungary has been classified as electoral autocracy since 2018, after the cut-off in 2017). c Moldova was classified as electoral autocracy in 2005-2009. d North Macedonia was classified as electoral autocracy in 2012-2016.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Country/RoW-Type 1994 to 2017</cell><cell>downgraded</cell><cell>stable</cell><cell>upgraded</cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell>Albania</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>4968</cell><cell>4968</cell></row><row><cell>Bosnia and Herzegovina</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>5636</cell><cell>5636</cell></row><row><cell>Bulgaria</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>7165</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>7165</cell></row><row><cell>Croatia</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>5211</cell><cell>5211</cell></row><row><cell>Georgia a</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>8404</cell><cell>8404</cell></row><row><cell>Hungary b</cell><cell>8147</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>8147</cell></row><row><cell>Lithuania</cell><cell>5975</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>5975</cell></row><row><cell>Malta</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>3362</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>3362</cell></row><row><cell>Moldova c</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>4589</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>4589</cell></row><row><cell>Poland</cell><cell>8996</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>8996</cell></row><row><cell>Romania</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>11126</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>11126</cell></row><row><cell>North Macedonia d</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>4667</cell><cell>4667</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>23118</cell><cell>26242</cell><cell>28886</cell><cell>78246</cell></row><row><cell>Notes.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>a</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table A1d .</head><label>A1d</label><figDesc>Afrobarometer Rounds 1-9: Electoral Democracies in 2021 with Regimes of the World Classification based on 1999-2021 Burkina Faso was classified was electoral autocracy in 2015 (and since 2022 after the cut-off in 2021). b Niger was classified as electoral autocracy in 2009-2010 (and since 2023). Sierra Leone was classified as electoral autocracy in 2012 (and since 2023). d (Tunisia has been classified as electoral autocracy since 2023).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Country/RoW-Type 1999 to 2021 Botswana Burkina Faso a Cabo Verde Lesotho Liberia Malawi Mauritius Namibia Niger b São Tomé and Príncipe Senegal Sierra Leone c South Africa Tunisia d Total Notes. A2 Variables</cell><cell>downgraded 10798 x x x x x 6000 x x x x x 19209 x 36007</cell><cell>stable x x 9795 x x 13215 x 10782 x 3596 9600 x x x 64558</cell><cell>upgraded x 7200 x 10735 7198 x x x 5998 x x 5981 x 5999 43111</cell><cell>Total 10798 7200 9795 10735 7198 13215 6000 10782 5998 3596 9600 5981 19209 5999 143676</cell></row></table><note><p>a c</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table A3 .</head><label>A3</label><figDesc>Items for support for democracy and rejection of non-democratic alternatives</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Diffuse support democracy</cell></row><row><cell>Integrated Values</cell><cell>"Having a democratic system" rated "very good" to "very bad" (4-</cell></row><row><cell>Survey</cell><cell>point scale)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Choice between:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>"Democracy is preferable to any other kind of government",</cell></row><row><cell>Afrobarometer</cell><cell>"For someone like me, it doesn't matter what kind of govern-ment we have",</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>"In some circumstances, a non-democratic government can be</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>preferable"</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Rejection authoritarian alternatives</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Availability Statement</head><p>All rounds of the Integrated Values Survey, of the Afrobarometer, and the V-Dem Regime of the World Index are publicly available. Upon acceptance for publication, the authors will make the replication code for merging and analysing the data available via the BJPolS Dataverse site.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.   <ref type="bibr">1994-1998, 1999-2004, 2005-2010, 2010-2014, 2017-2022 1999-2001, 2002-2003, 2005-2006, 2008, 2011-2013, 2014-2015, 2017-2018, 2019-2021, 2021-2023</ref> Target The V-DEM Liberal Democracy Index <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Coppedge et al. 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pemstein et al. 2024</ref>) is an expert index that utilizes a multifaceted approach to assess the quality of democratic governance. This index involves the consultation of five experts per country-year case, who provide their insights on a range of indicators designed to evaluate the integrity</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A1 Sample Overview</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Round 9 Survey Manual</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Afrobarometer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.afrobarometer.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/AB_R9.-Sur-vey" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-04-10">2022. April 10, 2025. Manual_eng_FINAL_20jul22</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">African insights 2024: Democracy at risk -the people&apos;s perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Afrobarometer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Afrobarometer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.afroba-rometer.org/surveys-and-methods/" />
		<title level="m">Surveys and methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-04-10">2025. 10 April 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breaking with mainstream politics while engaging with polarized: determinants of young Europeans&apos; support for democracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amc</forename><surname>Belchior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Teixeira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Youth Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="986" to="1005" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recession experiences during early adulthood shape prosocial attitudes later in life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bietenbeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Sunde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thiemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">243</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105327</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does Public Support Help Democracy Survive? American Journal of</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Claassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Public Support for Democracy in the United States Has Declined Generationally</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Claassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Magalhães</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Public opinion quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="719" to="732" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cohort Analysis of Recent Trends in Labor Force Participation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Clogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="479" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">V-Dem Dataset v14: Varieties of Democracy (V-Dem) Project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Coppedge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Only 6% of Gen Z actually favour dictatorship, not half as some reports would have you believe. The Conversation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Duffy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Morini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025. 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Democratic Disconnect</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Foa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mounk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Democracy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Signs of Deconsolidation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Foa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mounk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Democracy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Democratic Deconsolidation in developed democracies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Foa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mounk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">2019. 1995-2018</date>
			<publisher>Open Forum Paper</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Young People&apos;s Attitudes towards Democracy and Political Participation: Evidence from a Cross-European Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Efg</forename><surname>Grassi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Portos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Felicetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Government and Opposition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="582" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Age, period and cohort analysis in a comparative context: Political generations and political participation repertoires in Western Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Grasso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electoral Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Haerpfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">World Values Survey</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">2024. 1981-2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Trend File</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term income trajectories and the evolution of political attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Helgason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rehm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Political Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="264" to="284" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Estimation of Age, Period and Cohort Effects for Vital Rates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">311</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Inglehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Modernization and Postmodernization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Much Should We Worry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Inglehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Democracy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kriesi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Is There a Crisis of Democracy in Europe? Politische Vierteljahresschrift</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="260" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Youth, Institutional Trust, and Democratic Backsliding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Behavioral Scientist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1366" to="1390" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linkage versus Leverage. Rethinking the International Dimension of Regime Change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Levitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Way</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">379</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How democracies die</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Levitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ziblatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Problems of democratic transition and consolidation: Southern Europe, South America, and Post-communist Europe</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York; Baltimore, Md</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Johns Hopkins Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">2019. 1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regimes of the World (RoW): Opening New Avenues for the Comparative Study of Political Regimes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lührmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tannenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Lindberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Politics and Governance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Age-Period-Cohort-Interaction Model for Describing and Investigating Inter-cohort Deviations and Intra-cohort Life-course Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hodges</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological methods &amp; research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1164" to="1210" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The problem of generations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mannheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Essays on the sociology of knowledge</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mannheim</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1928">1928/1952a</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="320" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Essays on the sociology of knowledge</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1928">1928/1952b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Democracy in Africa: Demand, supply, and the &apos;dissatisfied democrat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mattes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Afrobarometer Policy Paper February</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anti-democratic youth? The influence of youth cohort size and quality of democracy on young people&apos;s support for democracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Nkansah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bartha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contemporary Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nord</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">25 Years of Autocratization -Democracy Trumped?</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025. 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is Western Democracy Backsliding? Diagnosing the Risks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Norris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">HKS Faculty Research Working Paper Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-03">2017. March 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wvs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.worldvaluessur-vey.org/WVSContents.jsp" />
		<title level="m">Fieldwork and Sampling</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-04-10">2020. 10 April 2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;source=web&amp;rct=j&amp;opi=89978449&amp;url=https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/APCI/APCI" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>pdf&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjv8JHogre-MAxXfzAIHHVp5KvYQFnoECBcQAQ&amp;usg=AOvVaw2F6VP5P3ntz2ixUY41ZAj</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Democratic deconsolidation revisited: Young Europeans are not dissatisfied with democracy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zilinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research &amp; Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">205316801881433</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Results of an APCI-analysis specifying a Gaussian link function</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Stable liberal democracies: Austria</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Belgium, Czechia, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Luxembourg, Netherlands, Norway, Portugal, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Great Britain; Estonia, Latvia, Slovakia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cyprus</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
