<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Adolescents&apos; Resilience and Treatment Needs for Mental health in Indian Slums Statistical Analysis Plan Version: 0.3 (Final)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-06-24">24 June 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Arpita</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
							<email>aghosh@georgeinstitute.org.in</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Billot</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kanaka</forename><surname>Sandhya</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Graham</forename><surname>Yatirajula</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pallab</forename><surname>Thornicroft</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-6835-6175</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Maulik</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Adolescents&apos; Resilience and Treatment Needs for Mental health in Indian Slums Statistical Analysis Plan Version: 0.3 (Final)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-06-24">24 June 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4D87A7BA133CBEA392A1B28E7055BA8D</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-23T06:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>1 Administrative Information 1.1 Study identifiers • Protocol Version 9.0 22/02/2024 • Clinical Trials Registry -India, Identifier: CTRI/2022/ 02/040307. Registered on 18 February 2022 1.2 Revision History Version Date Details 0.1 25 April 2024 First draft 0.2 21 May 2024 Addressed comments from all authors on first draft and revised tables and shells 0.3 24 June 2024 Finalized SAP 1.3 Contributors to Statistical Analysis Plan Title and name Affiliation Role on study Contribution to the SAP Dr Arpita Ghosh The George Institute for Global Health India Study statistician Developed the SAP Prof Laurent Billot The George Institute for Global Health Study statistician Reviewed and edited every version Dr Sandhya Kanaka Yatirajula The George Institute for Global Health India Project Manager Implemented the project and is helping with data analysis plan Prof Graham Thornicroft King's College London CoPI Reviewed and provided critical input to all versions Prof Pallab Maulik The George Institute for Global Health India PI Reviewed and provided critical input to all versions</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Approvals</head><p>The undersigned have reviewed this plan and approve it as final. They find it to be consistent with the requirements of the protocol as it applies to their respective areas. They also find it to be compliant with ICH-E9 principles and, in particular, confirm that this analysis plan was developed in a completely blinded manner, i.e. without knowledge of the effect of the intervention(s) being assessed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Doctor Arpita Ghosh</head><note type="other">27</note><p>June Professor Laurent Billot 26 June Doctor Sandhya Kanaka Yatirajula 27 June Professor Graham Thornicroft 26 June Professor Pallab K. Maulik 3 Introduction</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Purpose of this document</head><p>This statistical analysis plan (SAP) describes the statistical methods and data presentations to be used in the summary and analyses of data from Artemis study. This document is based on Artemis PROTOCOL Version 9.0 dated 22/02/2024. It describes the final analyses for evaluation of intervention at 12 months from randomization. Health economics modelling are not a part of this SAP. The document should be finalised before database lock and unblinding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Study Synopsis</head><p>The study aims to test clinical effectiveness and effectiveness of implementation strategies to identify and reduce depression, other significant emotional or medically unexplained complaints and suicide risk among adolescents living in urban slums. We hypothesise that:</p><p>1. a community-based anti-stigma campaign will lead to significant improvements in community behaviours toward adolescents with depression, other significant emotional or medically unexplained complaints, and increased risk of self-harm/suicide; and 2. a mobile device-based decision support system will improve the treatment of adolescents at high risk of depression, other significant emotional or medically unexplained complaints, and increased risk of self-harm/suicide for this project and lead to higher remission rates from depression and reduced suicide risk.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Study Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Trial design</head><p>This is two-arm cluster randomised trial across two geographical locations -slums in Delhi and Vijayawada. Slum cluster (constituting 1-5 slums located in the same area) is the unit of randomisation. Each slum cluster has a population of ~8000 and is serviced by at least one primary care doctor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Eligibility</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">Slum cluster eligibility</head><p>• Non-contiguous slum clusters, within a radius of 60 km from the field office in both cities, Delhi and Vijayawada, were selected, to get a total adolescent population of around 69600. • Each slum cluster has a minimum of one community women volunteer/non-physician health worker (NPHW) per 1000 population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.2">Participant inclusion criteria</head><p>All consenting adolescents in the age group of 10 -19 years were eligible for screening for stress, depression and increased risk of self-harm/suicide to identify both a high-risk and non-high-risk cohort. To be eligible for the high-risk cohort participants must have at least one of the following:</p><p>• High risk of depression based on a Patient Health Questionnaire-9 item (PHQ9) score ≥ 10</p><p>• Positive response (score ≥2) to the suicide risk question on the PHQ-9</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.3">Participant exclusion criteria</head><p>• Participants with severe ill-health that would prevent them from giving consent or participating in the study • Adolescents or their guardians who do not provide informed written consent • Participants who are temporary residents of the slums The implementation team ensured reasonable accommodation of adolescents who manifest physical or mental impairment and field investigators were provided training in lines with the Guidelines on Disability Inclusion in Research.</p><p>Two cohorts were generated from this screening process.</p><p>1. High-risk cohort -defined as either: a PHQ-9 score ≥ 10, AND/OR a positive response (≥2) to the suicide risk question on the PHQ-9. Because there was some time delay between screening and randomisation these participants were rescreened to assess if they still met the inclusion criteria prior to randomisation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Non-high-risk general adolescent cohort:</head><p>A second cohort of adolescents per slum cluster not at high risk for stress, depression and self-harm/suicide was identified by selecting a random sample from the remaining screened population stratified by sex (male and female) and age group (10-14 and 15-19 years). This is the 'non-high-risk' cohort.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Randomization</head><p>Slum clusters at each site were randomized to the two arms in a 1:1 allocation ratio using stratified randomization. Four strata of slum clusters were created within each site based on adolescent population size and proportion positive during rescreening, categorized using site-specific median. In one site, there were 2 strata with 8 clusters and 2 with 7 clusters; and in the other site, there were 2 strata with 6 clusters and 2 with 9 clusters. In strata with even number of clusters, half were randomized to one arm and half to the other. In the two strata with 7 clusters, we randomly selected 3 clusters in one stratum and 4 clusters in the other stratum and assign them to one arm; we assign the remaining clusters in the two strata to the other arm. Similarly, we divided the clusters in the strata with 9 clusters into the two arms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Sample size</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>High-risk cohort</head><p>Assuming a 50% remission rate in the control arm at 12 months based on published data 1 and 30 clusters per intervention arm, at least 27 subjects per cluster are needed to detect a 15% absolute improvement in the intervention arm (65% intervention vs 50% control) at 12 months with 90% power. This assumes a 2-sided significance level of 0.05 and an intra-class correlation coefficient (ICC) of 0.1 based on pilot data 2 and recent (unpublished) analyses. For secondary outcomes, this sample size will also provide 86% power to detect a standardised mean difference of 0.3 in PHQ-9 scores considering an ICC of 0.1. The hypothesised effect size is consistent to that published in a recent Indian study on provision of mental health services using lay health workers in community settings. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> To account for up to 20% of participants lost to follow-up, we will aim to enrol at least 33 participants per cluster for a total sample size of 1980 adolescents (60 clusters × 33 adolescents). We anticipate a prevalence of approximately 3% and will therefore aim to screen about 1,100 adolescents in each cluster. Further assuming that 5% of eligible adolescents will refuse to participate, we aim to screen 1,160 adolescents in each cluster i.e. a total of 69,600 adolescents (60 clusters × 1,160 adolescents).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Non-high-risk cohort</head><p>Assuming a conservative ICC of 0.1 (0.01 in our pilot and 0.04 in similar studies) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> , 20% loss to follow-up and a 2-sided significance level of 0.05, 60 clusters and a mean cluster size of 66 per cluster (33 high-risk and 33 non high-risk) will provide more than 90% power to detect a standardised mean difference of 0.3 in mean behaviour scores between the intervention and control arms at 12 months. Assuming baseline mean behaviour scores of 2 (SD 1) and a 20% improvement in the control arm based on pilot and published data, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> this corresponds to 12-month behaviour scores of 1.6 (20% improvement) and 1.3 (35% improvement) in the control and intervention arms respectively.</p><p>The sample has more than 80% power at 2α = 0.05 to assess sex disaggregated estimates for both the primary outcomes, assuming equal proportion of male and female adolescents in the high-risk and non-high-risk cohorts. Research suggests that among adolescents depression is equally distributed in males and females.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Framework</head><p>We will test for superiority of the primary and secondary outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.6">Statistical interim analysis and stopping guidance</head><p>No interim analyses were conducted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.7">Timing of final analysis</head><p>Final analysis for all outcomes will be conducted after 12-month intervention is completed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.8">Timing of outcome assessments</head><p>The following table shows the timing of the assessments that will be used to define primary and secondary outcomes.</p><p>Outcome Baseline 3-month 6-month 12-month Combined cohort Behaviour score (KAB tool) x x x x Knowledge score (KAB tool) x x x x Attitude score (KAB tool) x x x x Stigma score (BACE tool) x x x x High-risk cohort PHQ-9 score x* x x x Remission at 12 months (PHQ-9 &lt;5, and suicide risk score &lt;2)</p><p>x * Values from rescreening were considered as baseline assessments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Statistical Principles</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Confidence intervals and P values</head><p>All statistical tests will be 2-sided and will be performed using a 5% significance level. We have two primary outcomes, but they are assessing different components of the intervention, and they apply to different cohorts. No multiplicity adjustments will be made.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Adherence and Protocol deviations</head><p>In the combined cohort, individuals in the intervention arm will be expected to participate at least once in all components of the anti-stigma campaign (pamphlets and brochures; multi-media resources e.g. videos of people with mental disorders talking about their conditions; and street plays a about mental disorders, which was performed live or shown as a video). In the high-risk cohort, individuals in the intervention arm will be expected to be seen by a doctor at least once during the intervention phase.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Analysis populations</head><p>All analyses will be based on the principle of intention-to-treat (ITT), i.e. by analysing subjects according to the group they were randomised to and regardless of whether they received the intervention as intended. The intention will be to include all subjects; however, some might be excluded from analyses due to missing data and may be subject to sensitivity analyses e.g. imputations (see Section 7.3 for details about missing data handling).</p><p>'Per-protocol' and 'as-treated' analyses will not be part of main analyses and will be conducted posthoc as secondary analyses/separate publications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Trial Population</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Recruitment</head><p>CONSORT diagram comprising the number of people screened, rescreened, randomised, and followed-up follow-up will be presented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Withdrawal/lost to follow-up</head><p>All withdrawals/lost to follow-up will be listed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Baseline patient characteristics</head><p>Participants will be described with respect to their background characteristics such as age, sex, education, marital status, occupation, behavioural risk factors, medical history, treatment history, family history of any mental health problem, experience of domestic violence and intimate partner violence, any stressful event in last one year, and receipt of social support, separately for the two arms. Categorical data will be summarised by numbers and percentages. Continuous data will be summarised by mean, SD, median, IQR, and range. Tests of statistical significance will not be undertaken for baseline characteristics.</p><p>Slum cluster characteristics such as adolescent population size, proportion found to be positive upon screening, proportion found to be positive upon rescreening, and slum adversity index will be presented for the two arms. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">mHealth component (high-risk cohort) Primary</head><p>Proportion of high-risk adolescents achieving remission (defined as all of the following: PHQ-9 &lt;5, and suicide risk score &lt;2) at 12 months. Secondary PHQ-9 scores at 12 months In protocol, doctor visits were mentioned as a secondary outcome. However, since the mhealth component is about ensuring that adolescents at high risk of depression and increased risk of self-harm/suicide visit a doctor, this will be used as a measure of intervention fidelity rather than a secondary outcome. Details of doctor visits in both arms will be presented but no tests will be conducted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Analysis methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.1">Main analysis of primary outcomes 7.2.1.1 Behavior score in combined cohort</head><p>The behaviour score will be derived by summing the ordinal responses (with disagree strongly, disagree slightly, neither disagree nor agree, agree slightly and agree strongly scored as 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5, respectively) to the behaviour questions in the KAB scale -I would be willing to live with someone with a mental health problem, I would be willing to work with someone with a mental health problem, I would be willing to live nearby someone with a mental health problem, I would be willing to continue a relationship with a friend who developed a mental health problem. 'Don't know' will be coded as neither disagree nor agree (i.e., 3) for the purposes of determining a total score (see Appendix 1). <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> The behaviour score will be analysed using a repeated measure linear mixed model. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> The outcome (dependent variable) will include the behaviour score at 3, 6 and 12 months. Fixed covariates will include the baseline behaviour score, the intervention, the visit (3, 6 or 12 months), the intervention by visit interaction, and variables used for stratified randomization: 7 slum adolescent population size and proportion positive during rescreening. The stratification variables will be treated as continuous variables and a linear relationship with the outcome will be modelled. To model within-cluster correlations, the cluster will be included as a random effect. Correlations between repeated measures on the same subject will be handled by specifying that residual errors are correlated and will be modelled using unstructured covariance. The effect of the intervention will be estimated as the adjusted mean difference at 12 months together with its 95% confidence interval. The effects at 3 and 6 months will be estimated from the same longitudinal model utilizing data from all visits and 3-and 6-month estimates will be presented as part of additional analyses (please see section 7.4.3). This analysis will include all subjects with a baseline behaviour score and at least one post-baseline behaviour score. This main analysis model will be valid in case of data missing at random. Sensitivity analyses which make different assumptions about the missing data mechanism are described in Section 7.3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.1.2">Remission at 12 months in high-risk cohort</head><p>For the high-risk cohort, remission between randomization and end of trial will be defined as PHQ-9 score &lt;5 and suicide risk score &lt;2 at 12 months. It will be analyzed using mixed effects logistic regression with remission as a binary outcome, treatment group and stratification variables as fixed effects and slum clusters as random effects. The effect of the intervention will be estimated as the odds ratio together with its 95% confidence interval. The main model will be run with no baseline covariates. A second model will be fitted by adding the baseline PHQ-9 score as a continuous covariate. Risk difference along with 95% CI will be estimated using the Gaussian distribution, under both marginal approach (generalized estimating equations) and conditional approach (linear mixed model) (<ref type="url" target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0398762023001815">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0398762023001815</ref>). 8</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.2">Analysis of secondary outcomes 7.2.2.1 Knowledge and attitude scores in combined cohort</head><p>Mean difference at 12 months in knowledge and attitude scores in the combined non-high-risk and high-risk cohort will be analysed using the same approach as the one used for behaviour score (see Section 7.2.1.1) i.e. using repeated measure linear mixed model with the corresponding baseline score, the intervention, the visit (3, 6 or 12 months), the intervention by visit interaction and the stratification variables as fixed covariates. As with the behaviour score analysis, slum-level random effects will be included and unstructured covariance will be used to model correlations between repeated measures within subjects. Knowledge and attitude scores will be derived by summing over the responses to corresponding questions in KAB scale, following the same approach as used to construct the behaviour score (see Appendix 1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.2.2">Stigma score in combined cohort</head><p>Mean difference at 12 months in stigma perceptions as assessed by Barriers to Access to Care Evaluation-Treatment Stigma Subscale (see Appendix 1) in the combined cohort will be analysed using the same approach as the one used for behaviour score (see Section 7.2.1.1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.2.3">PHQ-9 score in high-risk cohort</head><p>Mean difference in PHQ-9 score (see Appendix 1 for instrument) at 12 months in high-risk cohort will be assessed using a similar approach as the one used for behaviour score in combined cohort i.e. using repeated measure linear mixed model with PHQ-9 scores in high-risk cohort participants at 3, and 12 months as the outcome (dependent) variable and the corresponding baseline score, the intervention, the visit (3, 6 or 12 months), the intervention by visit interaction, and the stratification variables as fixed covariates and slum clusters as random effects. Unstructured covariance will be used to model correlations between repeated measures within subjects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Missing data</head><p>The main analysis for behaviour score (a repeated-measure linear mixed model) makes valid inference under the missing at random (MAR) assumption. In case of more than 5% of subjects in combined cohort with missing behaviour scores at 12 months, we will perform controlled multiple imputation using the approach described by Cro et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> As a starting point, we will first run an imputation model under the missing at random (MAR) assumption. This MAR imputation model will use fully conditional specification (FCS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> and will include the following variables: behaviour score at baseline, months 3, 6 and 12, a variable indicating the cluster, a variable indicating the intervention, a variable indicating the cohort (high-risk vs not high-risk) and all key socio-demographic, clinical and medical baseline variables (e.g. sex, age, occupation and medical history) collected for both the high-risk and non-high-risk cohort participants. Behaviour score and other missing continuous variables will be imputed using linear regression while categorical variables will be imputed using either a logistic model (for binary variables) or a discriminant function method (for nominal variables). One hundred sets of imputed data will be created and analysed using the models described in Section 7.2.1.1. Estimates of the treatment effect and its standard errors will be combined to obtain a pooled common adjusted mean difference and 95% CI.</p><p>Using the same 100 sets of imputed data as our base, we will then assume different behaviour scores for subjects who had missing data at follow-up visits and had their scores imputed. We will start by assuming that those with a missing behaviour score were more likely to have a poorer outcome than those with a non-missing behaviour score and will therefore subtract 3 from the imputed behaviour score (with a minimum score of 4) in the 100 sets of imputed data. We will then analyse the 100 modified-imputed datasets and combine the results using the same strategy as for the base set of imputed data.</p><p>A similar strategy will be applied to the high-risk cohort in case of missing PHQ-9 scores. The imputation model will include the PHQ-9 scores measured at each timepoint, a variable indicating the cluster, a variable indicating the intervention and all key socio-demographic, clinical and medical baseline variables. We will start by assuming that those with a missing PHQ-9 score at follow-up visits were more likely to have a poorer outcome than those with a non-missing PHQ-9 score. We will therefore add 5 to their imputed PHQ-9 score (with a maximum score of 27). The same imputation strategy will be applied to remission -the remission outcome will be set to 'no' for highrisk participants with a missing remission outcome at 12 months in the 100 sets of imputed data. We will then analyse the 100 modified-imputed datasets and combine the results using the same strategy as for the base set of imputed data.</p><p>We plan to apply multiple imputations to the analysis of the following endpoints: behaviour score, PHQ-9 score and remission. Additional imputation and/or tipping point analyses will be considered post-hoc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4">Additional analyses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.1">Adjusted analyses</head><p>The analyses described for the primary and secondary outcomes (sections7.2.1 and 7.2.2) will be rerun after adding the following baseline covariates: sex, age, past stressful event (yes/no), any mental disorder, CD-RISC 10 score, and substance use (yes/no). Age and CD-RISC 10 score will be entered as continuous variables and a linear relationship with outcome will be assumed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.2">Subgroup analyses</head><p>Subgroup analyses will be conducted for both the two primary outcomes -behaviour score and remission at 12 months, according to the following subgroups:</p><p>• Site (Delhi vs. Vijaywada)</p><p>• Cluster-level characteristics -adolescent population size and proportion positive during rescreening, categorized using the median • Participant-level characteristics:</p><p>o Age group: 10-14 and 15-19 years o Sex: Male vs. Female</p><p>The following subgroup analyses will be conducted for specific outcomes:</p><p>• Depression severity at baseline: high (suicide score &gt;=2 or PHQ-9≥15) vs. low (suicide score &lt; 2 and PHQ-9 &lt; 15) (only high-risk cohort) for remission at 12 months only • Risk cohort (high-risk vs. non-high-risk) for behaviour score only.</p><p>For behaviour score, analyses for each subgroup will be performed by adding the subgroup variable, its interaction with intervention and visit as well as the three-way interaction between subgroup, intervention and visit as fixed effects to the model described in sections 7.2.1.1. For remission at 12 months, analyses for each subgroup will be performed by adding the subgroup variable and its interaction with the intervention as fixed effects to the model described in sectionError! Reference source not found. 7.2.1.2. For each subgroup, summary measures, mean difference or odds ratio and 95% confidence interval will be presented. The results will be displayed on a forest plot including the p-value for heterogeneity corresponding to the interaction term between the intervention and the subgroup variable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.3">Additional outcomes</head><p>Following additional outcomes that are produced as part of primary and secondary analyses will be reported</p><p>• Mean difference in behaviour, knowledge and attitude scores and mean difference in stigma scores in the combined cohort at 3 and 6 months. • Mean difference in PHQ9 scores at 3 and 6 months in high-risk cohort • CD-RISC score at 12 months in combined cohort</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.4">Disaggregated analyses, by sex and geography</head><p>• All analyses will be carried out separately by sex (male and female) and geography (Delhi and Vijayawada) and will be reported either as supplementary material or in a separate paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.5">Exposure to intervention</head><p>Variables measuring exposure to the interventions -the mHealth component in the high-risk cohort and the anti-stigma campaign in the combined cohort, will be summarized to understand the extent of exposure to these components. Specifically, the following variables will be analyzed and descriptive summaries will be presented:</p><p>• Proportion that witnessed the anti-stigma campaign • Proportion of adolescents participating in specific components of the campaign • Proportion of adolescents participating in all components of the campaign • Proportion of high-risk adolescents followed up by community health workers (CHWs) at least once • Average number of times a high-risk adolescent has been followed up by CHW • Number of times a high-risk adolescent has been seen by doctor • Proportion of recommended follow-up visits that were actually made</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.6">Treatment history during intervention</head><p>Variables measuring receipt of treatment for mental health condition, capturing place and mode of delivery of treatment, adherence to prescribed medicines/counselling, and reasons behind nonreceipt of treatment and non-adherence to prescribed medicines/counselling, will be examined using descriptive statistics. Frequency tables and bar graphs will be used to present distributions across the two treatment arms.</p><p>I would be willing to live with someone with a mental health problem.</p><p>Disagree strongly Disagree slightly Neither disagree nor agree Agree slightly Agree strongly Don't know</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1 2 3 4<label>5 3</label></formula><p>I would be willing to work with someone with a mental health problem I would be willing to live nearby someone with a mental health problem I would be willing to continue a relationship with a friend who developed a mental health problem.</p><p>Knowledge, attitude, and behaviour scores for each respondent will be derived by adding together the response values for the questions in that category.</p><p>The response 'Don't know' has been assigned a neutral value of 3 (that is, the same as 'Neither disagree nor agree') for the purposes of deriving a total score. Little interest or pleasure in doing things Feeling down, depressed, or hopeless Trouble falling or staying asleep, or sleeping too much Feeling tired or having little energy Poor appetite or overeating Feeling bad about yourself, or that you are a failure or have let yourself or your family down Trouble concentrating on things, such as reading the newspaper or watching television Moving or speaking so slowly that other people could have noticed? Or the opposite -being so fidgety or restless that you have been moving around a lot more than usual Thoughts that you would be better off dead or of hurting yourself in some way PHQ-9 score will be calculated by summing over the response values for the 9 questions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A2. PHQ</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A3. Barriers to</head><p>Access to Care Evaluation-Treatment Stigma Subscale and stigma score. Question Response Score Concern that I might be seen as weak for having a mental health problem This has stopped, delayed or discouraged me from seeking care Not at all A little Quite a lot A lot 0 1 2 3 Concern that it might harm my chances when applying for jobs Not applicable □ Concern about what my family might think, say, do or feel Feeing embarrassed or ashamed Concern that I might be seen as 'crazy' Concern that I might be seen as a bad parent Not applicable □ Concern that people I know might find out Concern that people might not take me seriously if they found out I was having professional care Not wanting a mental health problem to be on my medical records Concern that my children may be taken into care or that I may lose access or custody without my agreement Not applicable □ Concern about what my friends might think, say or do Concern about what people at work might think, say or do Not applicable □</p><p>The BACE-treatment stigma subscale score for a respondent will be the mean of response values for the applicable items.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mean (SD)</head><p>Median (Q1, Q3) Min-Max ¥ Unorganized sector: agricultural labourer, manual labourer, farmer, skilled worker, business/trader; Organised sector: Government employee, private employee. € ridiculed either by parents, teachers or friends for the way you look; difficulty in getting up early in the morning for work/school; pressure to perform in school/abiding by school rules; lack of freedom and not having enough time for leisure and fun activities after work/school hours; financial pressure; natural disaster or forced migration leading to loss of income or property; death/injury/serious illness/arrest/assault of a family member /loved ones/close friend; sad/upset/worried because a family members/close friend struggled with addiction; experience any major crime or were a victim or witness of a major crime like theft, assault/beating, murder/attempted murder or sexual violence; self/friend cheated by or separated from another close friend # close relatives (mother, father, brother, sister, uncles or aunts who are related by blood) had ever suffered from any mental disorder diagnosed by a doctor?</p><p>Table 7. Missing data pattern -reasons for loss to follow-up. Reason High-risk cohort Non-high-risk cohort Intervention Control Intervention Control Died Temporary shift Permanent shift Lock-up Refused Table 8. Analysis of outcomes (at 12 months). Mean (SE) or % at 12 months Mean difference (continuous outcomes) or Odds ratio (OR)/Risk difference (binary outcomes) (95%CI) pvalue Intervention Control High-risk cohort Primary outcome % achieving remission % achieving remission (adjusted for PHQ-9 at baseline) Secondary outcomes PHQ-9 score Combined cohort Primary outcome Behaviour score Secondary outcomes Attitude score Knowledge score Stigma score Table 9. Analysis of additional outcomes. Mean (SE) or % Mean difference (continuous outcomes) or Odds ratio (OR) (binary outcomes) (95%CI) pvalue Intervention Control High-risk cohort PHQ-9 score at 3 months PHQ-9 score at 6 months Remission component: PHQ-9 score &lt;5 at 12 months Remission component: PHQ-9 score &lt;5 at 12 months (adjusted for PHQ-9 at baseline) Remission component: suicide score &lt;2 at 12 months Remission component: suicide score &lt;2 at 12 months (adjusted for PHQ-9 at baseline) Combined cohort Behaviour score at 3 months Behaviour score at 6 months Attitude score at 3 months Attitude score at 6 months Knowledge score at 3 months Knowledge score at 6 months Stigma score at 3 months Stigma score at 6 months CD-RISC score at 12 months    Table A3. Analyses of outcomes -adjusted for key covariates. Mean (SE) or % at 12 months Mean difference (continuous outcomes) or Odds ratio (OR) (binary outcomes) (95%CI) Pvalue Intervention Control High-risk cohort Primary outcome % achieving remission Secondary outcomes PHQ-9 score Combined cohort Primary outcome Behaviour score 0 1-5 6-10 11-20</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>-stigma component (combined high-and non-high-risk cohorts) Primary Behaviour score at 12 months Secondary Knowledge, attitude and stigma scores at 12 months</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>2 weeks, how often have you been bothered by any of the following problems?</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Trial profile.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 .Figure 3 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Missing data pattern Figure 3. Distribution of scores at each visit, by arm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Forest plot for primary, secondary and additional outcomes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Forest plot for subgroup analyses.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We need to adopt a far more tolerant attitude toward people with mental illness in our society.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Behaviour</head><p>Appendix 2: Proposed tables and figures        </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating remission from untreated major depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Whiteford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mckeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1569" to="1585" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common mental disorders and risk factors in rural India: baseline data from the SMART mental health project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kallakuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Devarapalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Tripathi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Maulik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BJPsych open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Healthy Activity Program (HAP), a lay counsellordelivered brief psychological treatment for severe depression, in primary care in India: a randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Weobong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">389</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10065</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of an anti-stigma campaign related to common mental disorders in rural India: a mixed methods approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Maulik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Devarapalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kallakuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and psychometric properties of the reported and intended behaviour scale (RIBS): a stigma-related behaviour measure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Evans-Lacko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Epidemiology and Psychiatric Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="271" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mixed model for repeated measures for cluster randomized trials: a simulation study investigating bias and type I error with missing continuous data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Key considerations for designing, conducting and analysing a cluster randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hemming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taljaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1648" to="1658" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance of models for estimating absolute risk difference in multicenter trials with binary outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pedroza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Truong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC medical research methodology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sensitivity analysis for clinical trials with missing continuous outcome data using controlled multiple imputation: a practical guide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kenward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics in medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2815" to="2842" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fully conditional specification in multivariate imputation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Buuren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Groothuis-Oudshoorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rubin</forename><surname>Db</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of statistical computation and simulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1049" to="1064" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple imputation of discrete and continuous data by fully conditional specification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Buuren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical methods in medical research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
