<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Space motion theory</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Wenjing</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
							<email>uu002200@163.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Bionic Engineering (Ministry of Education)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jilin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>130022</postCode>
									<settlement>Changchun, Jilin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P. R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Space motion theory</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1DB91FB14017550C0E6981886E65B1B2</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-21T13:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Space motion background</term>
					<term>Energy velocity</term>
					<term>Entropic information energy</term>
					<term>Relative invariance</term>
					<term>Special relativity</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The special theory of relativity discovered the relation between motion and time, and proposed that motion and time are all relative, determined by reference frames. Herein, the other possibility that motion and time are all absolute, regardless of reference frames, is proposed. It is concluded that space is composed of the sum of the distributions of all particles in the universe and free vacuum energy; D∝M/R 2 , where D is the distribution density of a particle at a position, M is the absolute mass of the particle, and R is the distance of the point from the momentum center of the particle. Every point in space has a specific motion, and a large uniform space forms a space motion background. Every elementary quantity, energy, mass, time or length, requires an object of reference to define its size. The absolute quantities of an object vary with the velocity relative to the space motion background, named energy velocity (v), while the relative quantities have invariability, named relative invariance.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>It was the notions from human early practical cognition that motion is relative and time is absolute until relativity theory discovered a strict one-to-one relationship between velocity and time. If this relationship is correct, there are only two possibilities: motion and time are all absolute, or time and motion are all relative. Einstein chose the latter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Absolute and relative quantities</head><p>Measurement and observation are two different processes; however, they are often confused in analyses. In this theory, observers are used to measure quantities; a light source can also be called a sender, while the recipient of the photons is called the recipient, but cannot be called the observer.</p><p>Absolute quantities: absolute energy (E), absolute mass (M), absolute time (T), absolute length (L), absolute velocity (V) and absolute quantum frequency (N) are the quantities of an observed thing measured by the quantities of standard objects static to and at the observer. The observer's quantities must be invariant within the scope of the analysis.</p><p>Relative quantities: relative energy (e), relative mass (m), relative time (t), relative lengths (l), and relative quantum frequency (ν), are the quantities of a system or at a point that are measured by the quantities of the system or at the point themselves or measured by the relevantly local quantities. It should be noted that the energy velocity of an object (v) is measured by the higher system.</p><p>Quantity ratios: E q =E/e, M q =M/m, T q =T/t, Lx,y or z q =Lx,y or z/l, Vx,y or z q =Vx,y or z/v and N q =N/ν are the ratios of the absolute quantities of an object to the relative quantities of the object. Quantity ratios can also represent systemic changes in quantities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Space motion background</head><p>The existence of vacuum fluctuations has been predicted by quantum field theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and has been proven by many experiments. The vacuum energy density is called the cosmological constant and is usually denoted by Λ. However, the theoretical calculations of Λ are 120 orders of magnitude greater than what is observed <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> .</p><p>According to the present knowledge, three forces, electromagnetic force, strong nuclear force and weak nuclear force, form particle structures, the energy of which is named particulate information energy or internal energy (Es). The energy of particles that spreads over the universe is named matter information energy or information energy (Ei), including Es and entropic information energy (Ee).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ei=Es+Ee</head><p>(1)</p><p>Vacuum energy can move, has inertia and is the only source of energy. Matter information of particles will absorb free vacuum energy (Ev) into Ei.</p><p>A large uniform vacuum energy (relative to a substance in it), of which the motion state is hardly affected by the substance, is the space motion background or the space background of the substance.</p><p>A train is traveling on a planet at a velocity v. v (v1) is relative to and measured by the time and length of the space motion background mainly provided by the planet (t2 and l2), v1=l2/t2. The velocity of a particle relative to and measured by the time and length of the space motion background is known as the energy velocity of the particle.</p><p>Ei, Ee, absolute mass (M), distribution density (D) and v are hierarchical. For example, the motion of a train on the earth has a v1 relative to the earth, which has a v2 relative to the surrounding space, which has a v3 relative to the galaxy-scale space, and so on, until a vn relative to the universe. The velocity of an Ei is relative to the space motion background, and the space motion background is moving in a larger space motion background, which corresponds to planets, stellar systems, galaxies and more enormous structures.</p><p>Vcm=Vc(m+1)/γ(m+1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> (2.1) in the moving axis, which is because V=L/T; T increases by the factor γ and L decreases by the factor γ, where γ is the Lorentz factor and γ=(1-v 2 /c 2 ) -1/2 , while</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Vcm=Vc(m+1)/γ(m+1) (2.2)</formula><p>in the other two axes because L does not change in the two axes.</p><p>Vc=Vmax; vmax=c. For example, assuming the earth moves at v2 in the surrounding space, the absolute velocity of a photon on the earth (Vmax1) equals the absolute velocity of a photon in the surrounding space (Vmax2) divided by γ2 2 in the earth moving axis and divided by γ2 in other two axes. If a photon leaves the earth to the surrounding space in the moving axis, it will have a red shift or blue shift because of absolute velocity change <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> ; if it leaves the earth to the surrounding space in other two axes, it will not change because γ conforms to Pythagoras' theorem. Not only the absolute velocity of the maximum relative velocity Vc but also the absolute velocity of any relative velocity, such as V0.5c and V0.00001c, conforms to (2.1) and (2.2).</p><p>The density Λ is the density sum of the maximum level of hierarchical Ei (Eimax) of all particles in the universe and Ev; Λ can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Λ=(ΣEimax+Ev)/(LxLyLz)<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Ev will not be steady in the universe; it will be absorbed by particles, which may induce the inflation of the universe.</p><p>If there is not Ev at a point in space, Λ is ΣDmax and the absolute velocity of the point (Vs) can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">V s ⃑⃑⃑ = ∑ D maxn V n ⃑⃑⃑⃑ Λ ⁄ (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">)</formula><p>where Dmaxn represent the distribution density of the particle n at the point; Vn denotes the absolute velocity of the particle n. (This formula mainly conveys that every Vs is definite. In this formula, all particles are regarded as being distributed separately in the universe. However, in actual analyses, motion hierarchy may need to be considered. In addition, the motion of Ev is determined by the momentum conservation of the universe. This theory suggests a universe is a black hole, which has a specific entire motion.)</p><p>4 The deduction of entropic information energy: Ee=Mv <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> If Ei represents all the energies of a particle, Es represents the internal energy of the particle, which forms the particle structure, and Ee induces the motion for the particle and forms the thermodynamic entropy. Ee cannot be detected by particle-exchange actions but has gravity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ei=Es+Ee=E0+Ek</head><p>(5</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">)</formula><p>where E0 is the energy of a particle static in the space motion background and Ek, kinetic energy, is the increased energy when the particle moves at v. Respectively, M0, T0, L0, etc. denote the quantities of a particle static in the space motion background.</p><p>The Planck-Einstein equation is E=hN (which is the expression of absolute quantities corresponding to E=hν), where h is Planck's constant; this equation is considered valid for all particles besides photons. Es=hNs and Ee=hNe.</p><p>Ee forms the motion with de Broglie waves. According to the formula of the de Broglie wavelength λ=h/p, where p represents momentum and p=Mv, it can be obtained that λ=h/(Mv). Consequently, Ee/h=Ne=v/λ=Mv 2 /h, where v is the energy velocity; besides, Ne, λ, p and M are also measured by and relative to the observer static in the space motion background.</p><p>Therefore, given that Ee/h=Ne=v/λ=Mv 2 /h, Ee can be expressed as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Ee=Mv 2<label>(6)</label></formula><p>The motion of a particle is hierarchical and every level of Ee conforms to Een=Mnvn 2 ; Ein=Es+Ee1+Ee2…+Een.</p><p>In special relativity, E=mc 2 =γm0c 2 ; the corresponding expression of absolute quantities is Ei=Mc 2 =γM0c 2 =γE0. Given that Ei=Es+Ee=Mc 2 , Es=Mc 2 -Mv 2 =Ei/γ 2 .</p><p>According to Ei=γM0c 2 =γE0, the kinetic energy Ek can be expressed as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Ek=Ei-E0=(γ-1)M0c 2 =(γ 2 -1)M0c 2 /(1+γ)=M0v 2 γ 2 /(1+γ)=Mv 2 γ/(1+γ)<label>(7)</label></formula><p>(If the absolute quantities are measured by the observer static in the space motion background, the absolute quantities can be regarded as relative quantities, such as M0 and M being the same with m0 and m.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Principle of relative invariance</head><p>The change of particles in Es induces systemic changes in the other inner absolute quantities, such as Lorentz-Fitzgerald contraction (length contraction) and time dilation, whereas the internal relations between the inner quantities of particles are invariant; this invariance effect is called the relative invariance of inner quantities. Therefore, relative quantities are invariable. In contrast to the principle of relativity, the systemic quantity changes induced by energy velocity variations are real and absolute.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Internal energy is directly proportional to the time rate; Es∝1/T</head><p>The same change occurs on the earth, at another place, and at an observer, such as an atomic clock passing by 1 s. Measured by the observer, the change on Earth requires time Te, the change at another place requires time Tx, and the change at the observer requires T=t 1 s; where Te/t is the time dilation coefficient on Earth (T q e) and Tx/t is the time dilation coefficient at another place (T q x). T represents time amount while 1/T means the time rate.</p><p>In a system with relative invariance, Νs q =1/T q . Furthermore, Ns=Es/h, and ν=e/h; thus, Ns q =Ns/ν=Es/e=Es q .</p><p>Therefore, the following relation can thus be obtained: Es q =1/T q or Es∝1/T.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Time dilation with velocity T/T0=γ</head><p>Because Es0 is E0, given that Es∝1/T and E0/Es=γ, T/T0=(1/Es)/(1/Es0)=E0/Es=γ.</p><p>Therefore, the factor of the time dilation with v is γ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Length and internal energy</head><p>Es q =Lx q Ly q Lz q or Es∝LxLyLz This theory suggests that the systemic changes in length are induced by the change in internal energy, i.e., Es q =Lx q Ly q Lz q or Es∝LxLyLz, where Lx q , Ly q , and Lz q are the quantity ratios of length with respect to x, y, and z, respectively.</p><p>Given that Es=Ei-Ee=Mc 2 -Mv 2 and v=c, the Es of photons equals 0. Therefore, electromagnetic waves are Ee waves and the entropy of photons reaches the maximum. At the beginning of a universe, all particles are accelerated or destroyed into photons.</p><p>At that time, matter information has no Es, internal time (T) or internal length (L), as Es∝1/T∝LxLyLz. And, there is not electromagnetic force, strong nuclear force or weak nuclear force at that time until photons change into massive particles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">The invariance of energy velocity</head><p>As a relative quantity, energy velocity v has relative invariance.</p><p>If a person on a great celestial body does not perceive the variance of velocities or the variance of lengths on the celestial body when the motion state of the celestial body change, the change in velocity V q should be equal to the factor of the length contraction in the direction of the velocity Lv q divided by the factor of time dilation T q , i.e., V q =Lv q /T q . For example, if a celestial body moves from a state static in the space background to a state with an energy velocity v, the absolute velocities of movements on the celestial body in the direction parallel to the vector of v will increase by the factor V q : V q =Lv q /T q =(1/γ)/γ=1/γ 2 ; the absolute velocities of movements perpendicular to the vector of v will increase by the factor V q : V q =Lv q /T q =1/γ.</p><p>The speed of light c is the fastest energy velocity; vmax=c. The v of c vmax is a constant but the V of c Vmax is variable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Relativistic-like mass</head><p>The information energy Ei will increase with the energy velocity v by the factor γ while the internal energy Es will reduce with the increase of v by the factor γ; m:m0=m0:ms=Ei:E0=E0:Es=γ. From the side of a rest object, m0 is the rest mass and the mass of a moving object is the relativistic mass m while from the side of the moving object, ms seems the rest mass and m0 seems the relativistic mass.</p><p>6 Relative energy velocity va is the energy velocity of A, vb is the energy velocity of B, and vba represents the relative energy velocity of A to B. The impact energy of A to B can be approximately calculated by vba when va and vb is unknown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The relation between vba and va and vb:</head><p>At low-speed, v ba ⃑⃑⃑⃑⃑⃑ = v a ⃑⃑⃑ -v b ⃑⃑⃑⃑ .</p><p>At high speed and in the case in which v a ⃑⃑⃑ and v b ⃑⃑⃑⃑ are in opposite directions, according to the theorem of the addition of velocities in relativity W=(v+w)/(1+vw/c 2 ), vba=(va+vb)/(1+vavb/c 2 ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Position velocity</head><p>The position velocity of A relative to B (Vba) is the velocity at which A leaves B (or B ' ) in the direction from B (or B ' ) to A, and is measured by B. If the velocity is measured by C; it is expressed as Vba(c) (A and B ' are at the same position and B ' is static with respect to B based on absolute lengths).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">The distribution density and gravity</head><p>Besides the motion effect, the distribution density is related to gravity effect.</p><p>Because the density Λ is a constant and is limited, D∝M/R 2 is invalid when R is too short. And, when two objects get closer, the total Ei of them will decrease, which is related to the issues of accelerating universe, black holes, and other issues relevant to general relativity. D∝M/R 2 has mainly two reasons: one is that because Λ is a constant and the visible universe is even regarding celestial bodies, the visible space can be filled up by this distribution of celestial bodies, which forms a fundamental uniformity of density and Ev could be the least; the other is ∝M/R 2 is consistent with gravity.</p><p>However, this research is mainly corresponding to special relativity; the content relevant to general relativity will be analyzed and discussed later.</p><p>(In addition, the terminologies and abbreviations in this research were defined temporarily, which could be improved based on more comprehensive considerations.)</p></div>		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><head>Funding Declaration</head><p>This research was not supported by any funding.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data availability</head><p>All data generated or analyzed in this study are included in the published article (and its supplementary information files).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions</head><p>Wenjing Qu is the sole authors of this manuscript. The author declares that he is responsible for all aspects of the manuscript.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declaration of Competing Interest</head><p>The author declares no competing interests.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is the universe a vacuum fluctuation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Tryon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/246396a0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/246396a0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">246</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="396" to="397" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coherence and multimode correlations from vacuum fluctuations in a microwave superconducting cavity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lahteenmaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Paraoanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hassel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hakonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ncomms12548</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms12548" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12548</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The vacuum energy crisis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vilenkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.1128570</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1128570" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">312</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5777</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Red shifts of photons and massive particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wenjing</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31219/osf.io/4ahwn</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.31219/osf.io/4ahwn" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">OSF Preprints</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
