<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Let’s go WILD: Increasing Inclusivity in Theories of Developmental Psychology</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cambridge University Press (CUP)</publisher>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-05-23">2025-05-23</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kim</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bard</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-7956-839X</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Heidi</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0009-0003-6216-1467</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Leavens</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-6538-4891</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Culture and Language</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern Denmark</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Odense</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Danish Institute for Advanced Study</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Southern Denmark</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Odense</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Let’s go WILD: Increasing Inclusivity in Theories of Developmental Psychology</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Behavioral and Brain Sciences</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Behav Brain Sci</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0140-525X</idno>
						<idno type="eISSN">1469-1825</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge University Press (CUP)</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="60"/>
							<date type="published" when="2025-05-23" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">95367587AE5635415EA5883D8EADBE7F</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1017/s0140525x25000044</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We are persuaded by Bard et al.'s argument that cross-cultural work in psychology requires not only a greater diversity of participants but also a greater diversity of theories. We encourage the authors to consider that the solution lies not only in improving experimentally-oriented theories, but also in adopting non-experimental methods, including purely ethnographic methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main text</head><p>We agree with Bard et al. that, beyond the problem of unrepresentative samples, researchers need to reflect on how psychological science itself might be culturally blinkered. This is something we discussed in our book, Psychology's WEIRD Problems (2023), which we were pleased to see the authors engage with. Our argument in the book was that overreliance on unrepresentative samples, although a real issue, is actually a symptom of a deeper set of conditions. Psychological science is WEIRD not only in its subject pool, but also in its metatheoretical commitments, its methodological assumptions, and the institutional structures that give shape to experiments. There are many points of convergence with Bard et al.'s article. Building upon this common ground, we would like to challenge the authors to sharpen their critique on two fronts, relating, respectively, to methods and metatheory.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>(1) Methodological WEIRDness. Bard et al. describe five steps toward making developmental theories more inclusive. We broadly agree with their suggestions. However, we would like to invite the authors to expand on the first step: conducting ethnographic work on the target population. <ref type="bibr">Bard et al. treat</ref> this as a preliminary step on the way to formulating more inclusive experiments. Ethnographic work can, however, be valuable in its own right, independently of whether it informs later experimental research.</p><p>A notable example of cognitive ethnographic research focused on child development is the work of Barbara <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Rogoff (1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Rogoff ( , 2003))</ref>. A recurring theme in Rogoff's work is the role of guided participation in how children develop skill in tool use, planning, problem solving, and so on. In WEIRD societies there is commonly a clear separation between the world of adult work and child-specific spaces and activities; caregivers "take responsibility for organizing children's involvement by managing their motivation and by instructing through the provision of lessons" <ref type="bibr">(Rogoff et al. 1993, p. 151)</ref>. In many indigenous societies, in contrast, it is common for children to participate in adult activities as side-participants. The result is that, in these societies, children are socialized gradually into adult activities without formal schooling, with the children themselves taking "the responsibility for managing their efforts" <ref type="bibr">(1993, p. 152</ref>).</p><p>Rogoff's work is an example of a successful research program investigating the cultural specificity of behavior using primarily observational rather than experimental methods. Indeed, it investigates child development at a scale that could not possibly be captured in a laboratory experiment. Ethnography is a tool for "rewilding psychology" (Baggs and Sanches de Oliveira 2024), regardless of the implications (if any) that this work may have for experimental research. We submit that promoting experiments as the primary method for knowing about development is itself WEIRD!</p><p>(2) Metatheoretical WEIRDness. The authors criticize Shared Intentionality Theory on the grounds that it relies on data from WEIRD participants, and Attachment Theory on the grounds that it does not generalize to children in non-WEIRD contexts. We would add that these theories are WEIRD in metatheoretical terms as well. They take for granted that the aim of psychological science should be to uncover the contents of a universal human nature. Interestingly, Bard et al. seem to have no problem with this. They write in their conclusion, "Psychological theories that exclude data and perspectives from the majority of the world cannot accurately represent human nature." The notion of human nature, however, already commits the researcher to certain WEIRD metatheoretical assumptions <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Laland and Brown 2018)</ref>, such as the assumption that explanations of group outcomes should ultimately be reducible to processes inside the individual. There are good reasons to doubt that the individualistic explanatory strategy is always appropriate when applied in non-WEIRD contexts.</p><p>A compelling illustration can be found in Thomas <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Gladwin's (1970)</ref> classic work on Micronesian navigation. The Micronesian system of navigation allows sailors to reach distant islands without the aid of Western compasses or charts, instead using stars, wave patterns, and other sources of information. It is, in short, a highly intelligent system. However, this does not mean that WEIRD ideas about the nature of intelligence and associated testing methods are well-suited for studying it. <ref type="bibr">Gladwin (1970, p. 228 ff.)</ref> tried to measure the cognitive abilities of the master navigators using a Western-style logic puzzle in which the participant is asked to find pairwise combinations of colored poker chips. He found that the islanders were unable to solve this puzzle, with the exception of two islanders who had completed a Western-style education. This anecdote suggests that the Western conception of intelligence as a general capacity for problem-solving may be ill-suited to capture systems of behavior that developed outside the influence of Western schooling. As Gladwin warns us, "we must not slip into the assumption that Puluwatans view their navigators as highly intelligent. They do not. They view them as navigators" (p. 220).</p><p>The two points above can be considered independently from each other. We would like to mention an important point of convergence. ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) Being open to a diversity of methods (getting over our WEIRD obsession with laboratory experimental research), and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) being open to different ways of construing mind and behavior (getting over our WEIRD assumptions about the universality of psychological phenomena), are relevant to psychological science as a whole. Engaging with these critical points can inform better research practices even within WEIRD contexts. A good example of this is an ethnographic research program we've discussed elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Baggs and Sanches de Oliveira, 2024)</ref>, Roger Barker's behavior settings program, carried out in a small town in <ref type="bibr">Kansas between 1947</ref><ref type="bibr">and 1972</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Barker, 1968</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, Barker et al, 1978</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">, McGann et al. 2024)</ref>. Barker sought to identify how settings-classrooms, sports meetings, grocery stores, and so on-are important in giving shape to behavior, including the key finding that small schools encourage greater participation in extra-curricular activities, a finding which challenged the school consolidation program at the time <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Barker and Gump, 1964)</ref>.</p><p>In short, we echo Bard et al.'s call for more cross-cultural research, and we would add that casting off our WEIRD theoretical and methodological baggage promises to improve psychology as a whole, including how research is conducted even in WEIRD contexts. Going WILD is, we suspect, the path to making psychological science not only more inclusive, but also more accurate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding statement</head><p>Guilherme Sanches de Oliveira is supported by the grant "Embodied Cognitive Science and Scientific Expertise in Reading" (22831/SF/24), funded by the 'Saavedra Fajardo' sub-programme of Fundación Séneca, the Science and Technology Agency of the Region of Murcia.</p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Correspondence: guilherme.sanches@um.es</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicting interests</head><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author information</head><p>Guilherme Sanches de Oliveira Department of Philosophy, University of Murcia, Murcia, Spain Minimal Intelligence Laboratory (MINT Lab), University of Murcia, Murcia, Spain guilherme.sanches@um.es</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rewilding psychology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sanches De Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2023.0287</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2023.0287" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">379</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20230287</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Barker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Gump</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Big school, small school: high school size and student behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ecological psychology: concepts and methods for studying the environment of human behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Barker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Stanford, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Barker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Associates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Environments, habitats, and human behavior: studies in ecological psychology and eco-behavioral science from the midwest psychological field station, 1947-1972</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Jossey-Bass</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gladwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">East is a big bird: Navigation and logic on Pulawat Atoll</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The social construction of human nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Laland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Why we disagree about human nature</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hannon</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lewens</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="145" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">People, places, things and communities: expanding behaviour settings theory in the twenty-first century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcgann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lucas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mchugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Barrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2023.0282</idno>
		<ptr target="http://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2023.0282" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37920230282</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rogoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Apprenticeship in thinking: Cognitive development in social context</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford university press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guided participation in cultural activity by toddlers and caregivers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rogoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mistry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Göncü</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mosier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chavajay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Heath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monographs of the Society for Research in Child development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">179</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rogoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The cultural nature of human development</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford university press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Psychology&apos;s WEIRD Problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sanches De Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Baggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/9781009303538</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009303538" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
