<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Racialized Heteroscedasticity in Connectome-Based Predictions of Brain-Behavior Relationships</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIAAA</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_Xk2qESk">
					<orgName type="full">National Institute of Mental Health</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIMH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">NIH Office of Research on Women&apos;s Health</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">ORWH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute of Justice</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIJ</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">CDC -Division of Adolescent and School Health</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Endowment for the Arts</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NEA</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_N5ZBa3b #_hvUqH8F #_RQVzNDX #_ywbhskC #_2p7cMBx #_4eGVsZF #_95U5bAV #_u2P9gC6 #_DZqaf54 #_VxT8Jcd #_HdSr7uk #_kkFRGQg #_jMWjSAV #_wSCDEBm #_WnFSenV">
					<orgName type="full">National Institutes of Health</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute on Drug Abuse</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIDA</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Cancer Institute</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NCI</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NIMHD</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NHLBI</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_nASnRu3">
					<orgName type="full">NIMH</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_BPWjPG8">
					<orgName type="full">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">CDC</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Yale ASCEND</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NINDS</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NICHD</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">NIH Office of Behavioral and Social Sciences Research</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">OBSSR</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSF</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fields</surname></persName>
							<email>christopher.fields@yale.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Program for Recovery and Community Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Magnetic Resonance Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Radiology and Biomedical Imaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.S</roleName><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><surname>Rosenblatt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Magnetic Resonance Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Radiology and Biomedical Imaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><surname>Aina</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Morgan State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jannat</forename><surname>Thind</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Program for Recovery and Community Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Annie</forename><surname>Harper</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Program for Recovery and Community Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MSW, PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Chyrell</forename><surname>Bellamy</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Program for Recovery and Community Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Raimundo</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Magnetic Resonance Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Radiology and Biomedical Imaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Xin</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Fahmi</forename><surname>Khalifa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Morgan State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Dustin</forename><surname>Scheinost</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Magnetic Resonance Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Radiology and Biomedical Imaging</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Associate Research Scientist</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Yale School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Connecticut Mental Health Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Third Floor 34 Park St</addrLine>
									<postCode>06519</postCode>
									<settlement>New Haven</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Racialized Heteroscedasticity in Connectome-Based Predictions of Brain-Behavior Relationships</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">ED4B28A61633517E03437158546080F2</idno>
					<note type="submission">This work is a preprint and has not yet been peer reviewed.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T20:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Resting-state fMRI</term>
					<term>racialized heteroscedasticity</term>
					<term>connectome-based predictive modeling</term>
					<term>neuroimaging</term>
					<term>predictive modeling</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Background: Racialized heteroscedasticity, characterized by unequal variance in neuroimaging data across racial groups, may challenge the assumptions underlying brain-behavior predictive models. These models often assume homoscedasticity, a fundamental assumption in linear clinical models like Connectome-based predictive models (CPM), particularly when applied across diverse populations. This study investigates the presence of heteroscedasticity across racial groups in functional connectivity data from the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) study and examines its implications for predictive modeling using resting-state fMRI (rs-fMRI) data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods:</head><p>This study analyzed neuroimaging data across six modalities-Diffusion Tensor Imaging (DTI), T1-weighted structural MRI (SMR), resting-state fMRI (rs-fMRI), and task-based fMRI (Monetary Incentive Delay, Stop-Signal Task, and nBack tasks)-from 5,084 participants in the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) study. Variance differences between Black and White participants were assessed using Levene's test, adjusting for demographic and socioeconomic covariates with False Discovery Rate (FDR) correction. Behavioral variance across 36 cognitive and psychological measures was also evaluated. We predicted CPM employed to predict performance on behavioral tasks, with bootstrapping used to estimate prediction intervals and assess variance in model accuracy across groups.</p><p>Results: Racial differences in variance were observed across neuroimaging modalities, behavioral measures, and CPM variance interval analyses. After covariate regression, 68.9% of DTI features and 6.6% of rs-fMRI connectivity edges showed greater variance in Black participants, while no significant differences remained for SMR. Task-based fMRI and behavioral variance analyses revealed consistently greater variability in Black participants, with 87.8% of behavioral measures showing significant differences. Increased prediction uncertainty was observed for CPM models with Black relative to White participants across 8 out of the 15 measures tested.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p>Our findings underscore the importance of accounting for racialized heteroscedasticity in neuroimagingbased predictive models. Failing to account for differences in variance may exacerbate health disparities and lead to less reliable predictions for Black participants. These findings emphasize the need for diverse sampling and adaptive modeling approaches to ensure equitable predictive performance across populations. Addressing these disparities is essential for the development of more equitable predictive models in neuroscience and psychiatry.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p>Recent studies have highlighted the importance of considering racial and ethnic differences in neuroimaging research. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> These differences may arise from the interaction of genetic, environmental, and sociocultural factors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> For instance, experiences of racial discrimination have been shown to impact brain structure and function, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> potentially contributing to observed differences in neuroimaging data between racial groups.</p><p>The concept of heteroscedasticity, or unequal variance across groups, is well-established in statistical literature but has received limited attention in the context of neuroimaging studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> In predictive modeling, the assumption of homoscedasticity (equal variance) is often made, which may lead to biased or less accurate predictions when this assumption is violated. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> Given the growing application of neuroimaging-based predictive models in clinical decision-making, it is essential to investigate whether heteroscedasticity exists between racial groups and how it might impact the reliability and equity of these models.</p><p>The Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) study provides an unparalleled opportunity to examine these issues, leveraging a large and diverse dataset of adolescents. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> Its comprehensive neuroimaging, cognitive, and behavioral assessments allow for a detailed exploration of variance differences across racial groups, offering novel insights into how race-related factors influence brain-behavior relationships.</p><p>This study aims to address a critical gap in the literature by examining racialized heteroscedasticity in rs-fMRI connectivity and its implications for neuroimaging-based psychiatric prediction models. By focusing on differences between Black and White participants, we seek to shed light on potential disparities in prediction certainty. Understanding these differences is crucial for developing more equitable and accurate predictive models in neuroscience and psychiatry, ultimately contributing to improved clinical applications and personalized interventions across diverse populations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Population</head><p>This study utilized baseline demographic and year 1 neuroimaging data from the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) study, which includes neuroimaging, cognitive, and behavioral assessments of youth aged 9-10 years (at baseline) from 22 research sites across the United States. Participants included in the analysis were required to have complete rs-fMRI data, demographic information (age, gender, and parental income), and the absence of severe motion artifacts. Motion artifacts were defined as a mean framewise displacement exceeding 0.2 mm. This analysis focused on Black and White participants due to the sample size and availability of racially stratified data, allowing for robust statistical comparisons.</p><p>All participants were scanned using standardized imaging protocols across sites, and site effects were adjusted using statistical methods outlined below. Head motion was accounted for by including mean framewise displacement as a covariate in all analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Neuroimaging Data Processing</head><p>Resting-state fMRI data were preprocessed using the ABCD pipeline, which included motion correction, slice-timing correction, coregistration, and normalization to a standard MNI space. Participants with mean framewise displacement exceeding 0.2 mm were excluded to minimize motion-related artifacts, and scans were visually inspected to identify additional anomalies not captured by automated thresholds. Functional connectivity matrices were computed for each participant by extracting the mean time series from 268 regions of interest (ROIs) defined by the Power atlas. Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated between each pair of ROIs, yielding a 268 x 268 connectivity matrix representing the strength of functional connections. To focus on unique and biologically meaningful patterns, redundant and diagonal edges were excluded, resulting in 35,912 unique connectivity edges for analysis.</p><p>To ensure consistency across the 22 research sites within the CPM models themselves, site-specific variability was addressed through statistical harmonization. Site effects were regressed out during preprocessing, ensuring that differences in imaging protocols and equipment did not confound the results. Additionally, nuisance regressors, including head motion parameters, were incorporated into the preprocessing pipeline to further reduce noise in the connectivity matrices. Connectivity values were z-transformed to normalize the data across participants and facilitate direct comparisons. These preprocessing and modeling steps ensured that the resulting data were of high quality and observed differences in model performance are more likely reflective of true racial differences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Behavioral and Cognitive Measures</head><p>Fifteen behavioral and cognitive tasks from the ABCD dataset were included in this analysis to capture a broad range of neurodevelopmental and mental health outcomes. These tasks assessed domains such as working memory (lmt_scr_perc_correct), processing speed (pcps_speed), cognitive flexibility (nihtbx_cardsort_uncorrected), inhibitory control (nihtbx_flanker_uncorrected), and verbal intelligence (nihtbx_picturevocab_uncorrected). Additional tasks evaluated reading ability (nihtbx_reading_uncorrected), impulsivity (uppps_y_ss_positive_urgency, uppps_y_ss_negative_urgency), delay discounting and decisionmaking (cash_choice_perc_higher, ddl_total_cum_dscore, ddl_indifference_point), and motivational influences (nacc_reinforce_bias). Pre-morbid intellectual functioning was assessed using the Wechsler Test of Adult Reading (wtar_uncorrected).</p><p>These measures were chosen based on their relevance to brain-behavior relationships and their utility in predicting neurodevelopmental trajectories. Tasks were selected to ensure a representative sampling of cognitive, emotional, and behavioral domains, allowing for robust analysis of variability across racial groups. Behavioral scores were standardized across participants to facilitate direct comparisons, and any missing data were excluded pairwise to maximize the sample size for each task. These measures were selected to capture a range of cognitive and behavioral domains relevant to neurodevelopment and mental health outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p>To test for differences in variance between Black and White participants, Levene's test was conducted for each of the 35,912 unique resting-state fMRI connectivity edges, using race as a grouping factor. This approach was chosen for its sensitivity to heteroscedasticity, enabling the detection of group differences in variance.</p><p>Demographic covariates, including age, gender, parental income, and head motion, were included to account for potential confounding effects. Multiple comparisons were corrected using the False Discovery Rate (FDR) method, with significant results identified at p &lt; 0.05.</p><p>For the Connectome-Based Predictive Modeling (CPM) analysis, whole-brain rs-fMRI connectivity was used as predictors to model performance across 15 cognitive and behavioral tasks. The dataset was split into training and testing sets, employing a "leave-3-sites-out" cross-validation approach to mitigate site-specific variability and improve generalizability. Prediction intervals for Black and White participants were estimated using bootstrapping procedures, generating 95% confidence intervals based on 1,000 iterations. Differences in prediction intervals between the two groups were assessed using permutation tests, with FDR correction applied to ensure robust comparisons across multiple tasks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Software</head><p>All analyses were conducted using Python and MATLAB for data preprocessing, statistical analysis, and Connectome-Based Predictive Modeling (CPM). The CPM analysis specifically used the code package provided by the Yale Magnetic Resonance Research Center (Yale MRRC), which is publicly available at <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/YaleMRRC/CPM">https://github.com/YaleMRRC/CPM</ref>. Python packages such as NumPy and SciPy were used for statistical tests, and pandas was employed for data management. Bootstrapping procedures and model evaluations were implemented using custom Python code, and results were visualized using Matplotlib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical Approval</head><p>The ABCD study operates under a centralized Institutional Review Board (IRB) at the University of California, San Diego, as well as local IRBs at each of the 22 participating recruitment sites. All participants and their parents/guardians provided written informed consent and assent for data collection. The present analysis was conducted on de-identified data obtained from the ABCD study's publicly available repository, in accordance with all relevant ethical guidelines and regulations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Racial Differences in Variance in Structural, Resting-State, and Task-Based Connectivity</head><p>We examined differences in variance across six key neuroimaging modalities-Diffusion Tensor Imaging (DTI), T1-weighted structural MRI (SMR), resting-state fMRI (rsfMRI), and task-based fMRI during the Monetary Incentive Delay (MID), Stop-Signal Task (SST), and nBack tasks-between Black and White participants in the ABCD study. For Diffusion Tensor Imaging (DTI, FA), 151 features corresponding to white matter tracts were examined. For T1-weighted structural MRI (SMR), 151 features representing regional gray matter volumes and cortical thickness were included. For fMRI, we constructed a connectivity matrix comprising 71,854 edges (from a 268 x 268 matrix). After excluding redundant connections, 35,912 unique edges were tested for differences in variance using Levene's test. We focused on these unique edges to ensure that analyses captured non-redundant, meaningful patterns in functional and structural connectivity. Across all modalities, significant differences in variance were observed between Black and White participants, with the majority of features showing greater variance in Black participants. When covariates were not included in the models (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>), significant findings emerged across all six imaging modalities.</p><p>For DTI fractional anisotropy (FA), 29.1% (44/151) of the features showed significant variance differences, with 75% (33/44) exhibiting greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;0.001). Similarly, for T1weighted structural MRI (SMR-T1), 20% (30/151) of the features displayed significant variance differences, with 63% (19/30) showing increased variance in Black participants (p=0.199).</p><p>In the resting-state fMRI analysis, 2.5% (875/35,912) of the unique edges exhibited significant differences in functional connectivity variance between groups, with 70% (573/875) showing greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001).</p><p>For the task-based fMRI modalities, a similar pattern of increased variance in Black participants was observed. During the Monetary Incentive Delay (MID) task, 6.7% (2409/35,912) of edges showed significant variance differences, with 95.7% (2330/2409) demonstrating greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001). For the Stop-Signal Task (SST), 1.9% (678/35,912) of edges exhibited significant variance differences, with 95.1% (672/678) showing increased variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001). Finally, for the nBack task, 0.87% (311/35,912) of edges displayed significant differences in variance, with 84.9% (152/311) showing greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001).</p><p>When including covariates (age, sex, head motion) and site correction in the Levene's test, significant racial differences in variance persisted across modalities (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>). The exception here was T1-weighted structural MRI (SMR), which did not have any features that survived the addition of covariates to Levene's test.</p><p>For DTI fractional anisotropy (FA), 68.9% (104/151) of features showed significant variance differences, with 100% (104/104) demonstrating greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001). In the resting-state fMRI analysis,</p><p>6.6% (2373/35,912) of edges exhibited significant differences in functional connectivity variance, with 66% (1204/2373) showing greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001). Task-based fMRI modalities similarly demonstrated persistent differences. During the MID task, 16.3% (5398/35,912) of edges were significant, with 92% (4953/5398) exhibiting greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001). For the Stop-Signal Task (SST), 11.0% (3968/35,912) of edges showed significant variance differences, with 87% (3451/3968) demonstrating greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001). Finally, for the nBack task, 5.9% (2126/35,912) of edges showed significant variance differences, with 83% (1762/2126) exhibiting greater variance in Black participants (p&lt;.001). These findings indicate that racialized variance differences are robust even when controlling for site and demographic factors. This racial skew in Levene's test results was further validated using chi-square tests, as detailed in Supplementary Table 1. We analyzed the number of features showing significantly greater variance in one group compared to the other across neuroimaging modalities. Supplementary Table 1 provides a breakdown of features with significantly greater variance in Black participants versus White participants, as determined by Levene's test.</p><p>The chi-square test assessed whether the distribution of features with greater variance differed significantly between the two groups. The results demonstrated a pronounced skew toward greater variance in Black participants across most modalities, even after accounting for demographic covariates and site effects.</p><p>While controlling for multiple comparisons is a rigorous approach for identifying significant differences, edge weight selection for CPM models is typically not subjected to multiple comparison correction, as it prioritizes predictive utility rather than strict statistical significance. Nonetheless, even after controlling for multiple comparisons, robust increases in variance across neuroimaging measures were observed for Black compared to White participants. Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> presents the variance histograms for all modalities under the less strict FDR threshold (pN), while Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> presents the variance histograms under the more strict FDR threshold (pID). Additionally, Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> and Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> provide pN and pID variance histograms for covariate adjusted Levene's analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Behavioral Variance Differences Across Racial Groups</head><p>In addition to neural measures, we analyzed variance differences across 36 behavioral measures from the ABCD dataset, using Levene's test to assess differences in variance between Black and White participants (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). These measures spanned several domains, including cognition, personality traits, emotional regulation, and behavioral health. Both non-covaried and covaried models were used, with the covaried models controlling for age, gender, parental income, study site, and head motion. To account for multiple comparisons, False Discovery Rate (FDR) correction was applied to the results.</p><p>As shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, of the 36 behavioral measures analyzed, 33 measures (87.8%) exhibited significant differences in racial variance as measured by Levene's test. Of these, 29 showed significantly greater variance in Black participants compared to White participants. Among these measures, several from the Child Behavior Checklist (e.g., rule-breaking, aggression, and attention problems) and personality domains (e.g., sensationseeking and impulsivity) exhibited the most pronounced differences. These findings suggest that race-related factors contribute to greater behavioral heterogeneity across multiple psychological and cognitive domains, even after accounting for demographic and site-related covariates. This pattern parallels the increased variability observed in neural measures, further indicating that racialized experiences may influence a broad range of behavioral outcomes.</p><p>Conversely, a smaller subset of measures exhibited greater variance in White participants. In the noncovaried models, 4 measures showed significantly greater variance in White participants. These measures primarily involved domains related to cognitive abilities, such as reading performance and crystallized intelligence. While the proportion of measures with greater variance in White participants was smaller, these results highlight the importance of considering variability patterns across racialized groups for specific behavioral constructs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Connectome-Based Predictive Modeling (CPM) Variance in Prediction Intervals</head><p>We conducted Levene's tests to assess racial differences in variance for composite CPM scores correlated with each of the 36 behavioral measures (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). CPM scores were calculated as is typically done in Connectome-Based Predictive Modeling, with each score optimized to correlate most strongly with the corresponding behavioral measure, selecting the top 10% of edges. The results, presented in Table <ref type="table">X</ref>, revealed significant racial differences in variance for 13 out of the 36 behavioral measures. These findings suggest that variance differences between Black and White participants extend beyond neuroimaging features and into the predictive performance of CPM models.</p><p>Building on this, we evaluated how these variance differences manifest in the prediction intervals of CPM models. Using whole-brain rs-fMRI connectivity as predictors, we modeled performance across 15 cognitive and psychological test outcomes from the ABCD dataset. The CPM approach links brain connectivity patterns with behavioral and cognitive outcomes, allowing us to assess the variability in prediction intervals for Black and White participants. The variance estimates for the prediction intervals were calculated by fitting CPM models across the 15 cognitive/psychological tests. Ninety-five percent confidence intervals (CIs) were generated using a "leave 3-sites out" bootstrapping method, which involved leaving out data from three of the 21 ABCD research sites in each iteration. This method was repeated 1,000 times to ensure robust cross-validation and reliable variance estimates for model predictions in both racial groups. Significantly wider variance intervals were observed for Black participants compared to White participants across several cognitive and behavioral domains.</p><p>For example, Black participants had significantly greater variance in the prediction intervals for the NIH Toolbox Card Sorting Task, a measure of executive functioning, as well as for the Fluid Cognition Composite, which evaluates cognitive flexibility and problem-solving abilities. Similarly, the NIH Toolbox List Sorting Task, assessing working memory, and the Pattern Comparison Task, a measure of processing speed, both showed wider variance intervals for Black participants. In total, 8 out of the 15 tested models demonstrated significantly greater variance intervals for Black participants after FDR correction (p &lt; 0.05).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Our study reveals significant differences in the variance of resting-state functional connectivity (rs-fMRI) between Black and White participants in the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) study, as well as disparities in the prediction intervals of connectome-based predictive models across various cognitive and behavioral tasks. These findings have important implications for neuroimaging research, particularly in the context of diverse populations and the development of predictive models for clinical applications. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> The observation that 10.5% of the examined rs-fMRI connectivity edges showed significant differences in variance between Black and White participants, with 98.5% of these edges demonstrating greater variance in Black participants, is a striking finding. This pervasive heteroscedasticity suggests that the assumption of homogeneous variance across racial groups in neuroimaging studies may be flawed. Such an assumption could lead to biased or less accurate predictions when applying models developed primarily on one racial group to another. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> The greater variability in connectivity patterns among Black participants persisted even after controlling for socioeconomic and demographic factors. This suggests that race-related factors beyond commonly considered variables like socioeconomic status may influence neural connectivity patterns. These factors could include experiences of racial discrimination, differences in environmental exposures, or other sociocultural influences that may impact brain development and function. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> The wider prediction intervals observed for Black participants across several cognitive and behavioral domains in our connectome-based predictive modeling (CPM) analysis further underscore the importance of considering racial differences in neuroimaging-based predictive models. The significantly greater variance in prediction intervals for 8 out of 15 tested models, including measures of executive functioning, cognitive flexibility, working memory, and processing speed, indicates a higher degree of uncertainty in model predictions for Black participants. This increased uncertainty has critical implications for the application of these models in clinical settings. If not properly accounted for, it could lead to less reliable predictions or misinterpretations of brain-behavior relationships in Black individuals. This finding aligns with growing concerns about the generalizability of neuroimaging findings across diverse populations and the potential for exacerbating health disparities through the uncritical application of predictive models. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> Several factors may contribute to the observed differences in variance and prediction uncertainty between Black and White participants. Genetic diversity within African populations could contribute to increased variability in brain structure and function. However, it's crucial to note that genetic explanations alone are insufficient and can perpetuate harmful racial stereotypes if not contextualized within broader socioenvironmental factors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> Differences in environmental exposures, including pollution, nutrition, and access to healthcare, may contribute to greater variability in brain development and function among Black participants.</p><p>These factors are often linked to systemic racial inequalities and may have cumulative effects on brain health. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> Chronic stress related to experiences of racial discrimination and systemic racism can impact brain structure and function. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> The variability in these experiences and individual coping mechanisms could contribute to greater heterogeneity in brain connectivity patterns among Black participants. It's also possible that current neuroimaging techniques and analysis methods may be less sensitive or more variable when applied to Black participants due to factors such as differences in brain morphology or hemodynamic responses. This highlights the need for developing and validating neuroimaging methods across diverse populations. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> Our findings emphasize the need for more nuanced approaches to neuroimaging research and predictive modeling that account for potential heteroscedasticity across racial groups. Neuroimaging studies should prioritize diverse and representative sampling to capture the full spectrum of variability across populations. This includes not only racial diversity but also considerations of socioeconomic status, geographic location, and other relevant demographic factors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> The observed differences in variance and prediction uncertainty between racial groups raise important ethical considerations for the development and application of neuroimaging-based predictive models. Researchers must be cautious in interpreting and communicating these findings to avoid reinforcing harmful stereotypes or biological determinism. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> It is crucial to emphasize that these differences likely reflect a complex interplay of social, environmental, and biological factors rather than inherent racial characteristics. Responsible reporting of these results should always contextualize them within the broader societal and historical factors that contribute to health disparities. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> We use the term "racialized heteroscedasticity" to acknowledge that the observed differences in variance are not inherent to race itself, but rather are a result of societal processes of racialization. This terminology emphasizes that race is a social construct, and the disparities we observe are likely due to the lived experiences, environmental factors, and systemic inequalities associated with racial categorization in society. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> By framing it as "racialized" heteroscedasticity, we aim to shift the focus from biological determinism to the social and structural factors that contribute to these disparities in neuroimaging data.</p><p>While our study provides important insights into racialized heteroscedasticity in neuroimaging data, several limitations should be considered. First, the binary categorization of race (Black vs. White) does not capture the full spectrum of racial and ethnic diversity. Future studies should examine these patterns across more diverse racial and ethnic groups. Second, while we controlled for several demographic and socioeconomic factors, there may be other unmeasured confounding variables that contribute to the observed differences in variance.</p><p>More comprehensive assessments of environmental exposures, experiences of discrimination, and cultural factors, particularly those gathered through community-engaged research, could provide additional insights. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref> In conclusion, our study highlights the presence of racialized heteroscedasticity in rs-fMRI connectivity and its impact on connectome-based predictions of brain-behavior relationships. These findings underscore the importance of considering diversity and potential sources of variability in neuroimaging research and predictive modeling. By acknowledging and addressing these differences, we can work towards developing more equitable and accurate predictive models that serve diverse populations effectively. Moving forward, it is essential for the neuroimaging community to prioritize diverse sampling, develop adaptive modeling techniques, and engage in responsible interpretation and communication of results. By doing so, we can advance our understanding of brainbehavior relationships across diverse populations and contribute to more equitable and effective applications of neuroimaging in clinical and research settings. modalities. Figure 1A presents results without covariates, and Figure 1B includes covariate regression and site correction (age, sex, head motion, and site). Neuroimaging modalities include (A) resting-state fMRI (rsfMRI), (B) Monetary Incentive Delay task (MID), (C) nBack task, (D) Stop-Signal Task (SST), (E) Diffusion Tensor Imaging fractional anisotropy (FA), and (F) T1-weighted gray matter structural MRI (T1 GM). The x-axis represents the difference in variance (positive values indicate greater variance in Black participants, while negative values indicate greater variance in White participants), and the y-axis represents the count of features with corresponding variance differences. Across all modalities, features demonstrating significant variance differences (p &lt; 0.05) are included. This figure illustrates the 95% variance intervals for Black and White participants in Connectome-Based Predictive Modeling (CPM), using resting-state fMRI connectivity to predict performance across 15 behavioral and cognitive tasks. The wider variance intervals for Black participants indicate increased variability in model</p><p>predictions. Confidence intervals (CIs) were generated using a leave-3-sites-out bootstrapping approach over 1,000 iterations. In 10 of the 15 tasks, the variance for Black participants was significantly greater than for White participants (p &lt; 0.05, FDR-corrected), demonstrating higher prediction uncertainty for Black participants. The tasks evaluated in this analysis include lmt_scr_perc_correct, which assessed working memory, and pcps_speed, which measured processing speed. Cognitive flexibility was measured by nihtbx_cardsort_uncorrected, while nihtbx_flanker_uncorrected evaluated inhibitory control and attention. nihtbx_picturevocab_uncorrected assessed verbal intelligence, and nihtbx_reading_uncorrected evaluated reading ability. Impulsivity measures included uppps_y_ss_positive_urgency for positive urgency and uppps_y_ss_negative_urgency for negative urgency. The Monetary Choice Task was represented by cash_choice_perc_higher for delayed gratification and cash_choice_perc_smaller for preference for smaller immediate rewards. Additional tasks included cpt_dprime, which measured sustained attention, and ddl_total_cum_dscore and ddl_indifference_point, both assessing decision-making in delay discounting. Motivational influences on decision-making were evaluated by nacc_reinforce_bias, and wtar_uncorrected was used to assess pre-morbid intellectual functioning. In these tasks, the variance intervals were consistently wider for Black participants, particularly in measures related to working memory, inhibitory control, and impulsivity, underscoring the importance of accounting for variance differences when developing predictive models to ensure more equitable outcomes.</p><p>Table 1. Variance differences in behavioral measures between Black and White participants. The table presents results of Levene's test for variance differences across 36 behavioral measures, including the p-value  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Histograms depict the distribution of variance differences (Black-White) across six key neuroimaging</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Variance Intervals for Black and White Participants Across Cognitive and Behavioral Tasks.</figDesc><graphic coords="18,72.00,36.00,406.98,472.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>(</head><figDesc>p_behavior), F-statistic (f_behavior), and standard deviations for Black (b_sd) and White (w_sd) participants.The ratio of standard deviations (b_sd/w_sd) quantifies the relative variability between the two groups, with values &gt;1 indicating greater variability among Black participants and values &lt;1 indicating greater variability among White participants. Measures with statistically significant variance differences (p &lt; 0.05) are highlighted.Sample sizes (N) vary across measures due to data availability. These results highlight racialized patterns of variability in cognitive, emotional, and behavioral domains, with most measures showing greater variability among Black participants.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Results of Levene's tests for racial differences in variance in composite CPM scores across behavioral measures. Each row corresponds to a behavioral measure, with Levene's test statistics (lev_stat) and associated pvalues (p_value) reported. Composite CPM scores were calculated using the top 10% of edges most strongly correlated with each behavioral measure. Significant results (p &lt; 0.05) are highlighted, indicating behavioral measures where variance differed significantly between Black and White participants. These results emphasize the presence of racialized heteroscedasticity in CPM models and its potential impact on predictive accuracy across behavioral domains.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="19,72.00,339.57,488.40,365.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="22,72.00,137.19,504.00,353.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="23,72.00,36.00,504.00,348.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="24,72.00,36.00,504.00,338.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="25,72.00,36.00,504.00,339.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="26,72.00,36.00,504.00,315.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="27,72.00,36.00,504.00,315.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="28,72.00,36.00,400.70,603.79" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments:</head><p>The authors would like to thank the <rs type="institution">ABCD Study Consortium</rs> for providing access to the data, as well as the participants and families who contributed to this research. Special thanks to the <rs type="funder">Yale School of Medicine</rs> for its institutional support through the <rs type="programName">ASCEND grant program</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><p>Funding: The <rs type="projectName">Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study</rs> was supported by the <rs type="funder">National Institutes of Health (NIH)</rs> and additional federal partners under the following awards: <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041022</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041025</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041028</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041048</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041089</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041093</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041106</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041117</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041120</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041134</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041148</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041156</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U01DA041174</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">U24DA041123</rs>, and <rs type="grantNumber">U24DA041147</rs>. The ABCD federal partners include the <rs type="funder">National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Cancer Institute (NCI)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">NIH Office of Behavioral and Social Sciences Research (OBSSR)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">NIH Office of Research on Women's Health (ORWH)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) -Division of Violence Prevention</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Institute of Justice (NIJ)</rs>, the <rs type="funder">CDC -Division of Adolescent and School Health</rs>, the <rs type="funder">National Science Foundation (NSF)</rs>, and the <rs type="funder">National Endowment for the Arts (NEA)</rs>. This work was supported by grant support to the authors: <rs type="funder">National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">F32MH129052</rs> to CTF; and <rs type="funder">NIMH</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">5R01MH121095-05</rs> and <rs type="funder">Yale ASCEND</rs> grant to DS. The funding organizations had no role in the analysis and interpretation of the data, preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript, or the decision to submit the manuscript for publication. This manuscript reflects the views of the authors and may not represent the opinions or views of the <rs type="funder">National Institutes of Health (NIH)</rs> or the ABCD consortium investigators.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_BPWjPG8">
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">ASCEND grant program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_N5ZBa3b">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041022</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_hvUqH8F">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041025</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_RQVzNDX">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041028</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_ywbhskC">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041048</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_2p7cMBx">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041089</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_4eGVsZF">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041093</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_95U5bAV">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041106</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_u2P9gC6">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041117</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_DZqaf54">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041120</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_VxT8Jcd">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041134</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_HdSr7uk">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041148</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_kkFRGQg">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041156</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jMWjSAV">
					<idno type="grant-number">U01DA041174</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_wSCDEBm">
					<idno type="grant-number">U24DA041123</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_WnFSenV">
					<idno type="grant-number">U24DA041147</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Xk2qESk">
					<idno type="grant-number">F32MH129052</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_nASnRu3">
					<idno type="grant-number">5R01MH121095-05</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Availability:</head><p>The data supporting the findings of this study were obtained from the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study. Due to restrictions, the data are available upon reasonable request from the corresponding author or from the ABCD Study Data Access portal. The source data used in this study were openly available prior to its initiation. The ABCD data used in this report came from the fast track data release 5.1, which is accessible to qualified researchers through the NIMH Data Archive (NDA). The raw data are available at <ref type="url" target="https://nda.nih.gov/study.html?id=2313">https://nda.nih.gov/study.html?id=2313</ref>, and the data dictionary for ABCD can be found at <ref type="url" target="https://data-dict.abcdstudy.org/">https://data-dict.abcdstudy.org/</ref>. Additional details about the measures assessed for the ABCD study are provided at <ref type="url" target="https://wiki.abcdstudy.org/release-notes/start-page.html">https://wiki.abcdstudy.org/release-notes/start-page.html</ref>. Instructions for obtaining NDA data use certification are available at <ref type="url" target="https://nda.nih.gov/nda/access-data-info">https://nda.nih.gov/nda/access-data-info</ref>.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Contributions:</head><p>CTF led the conceptualization and performed data analysis, data interpretation, and the initial draft of the manuscript. MR and JA conducted statistical analysis, contributed to data interpretation, and revised the manuscript. JKT, AH, CB, and RR contributed to data interpretation and manuscript revision. XZ and FK supervised the project, assisted with data interpretation, and revised the manuscript. DS provided project supervision and contributed to manuscript revision. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Figures</head><note type="other">Supplementary Figure 1</note></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is a representative brain? Neuroscience meets population science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hyde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17615" to="17622" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sample composition alters associations between age and brain structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Lewinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sheridan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mclaughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">874</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Health Disparities due to Diminished Return among Black Americans: Public Policy Solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Assari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Issues and Policy Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unequal Gain of Equal Resources across Racial Groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Assari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Health Policy Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Governance for Anti-Racist AI in Healthcare: Integrating Racism-Related Stress in Psychiatric Algorithms for Black Americans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fields</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Thind</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PsyArXiv</note>
	<note>Preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">More than skin deep&quot;: stress neurobiology and mental health consequences of racial discrimination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sarnyai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stress</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial Discrimination and White Matter Microstructure in Trauma-Exposed Black Women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of heteroscedasticity on the prediction efficiency of genome-wide polygenic score for body mass index</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Baek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1025568</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Simple Test for Heteroscedasticity and Random Coefficient Variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Breusch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1287" to="1294" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The robustness, reliabiligy and power of heteroskedasticity tests</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Godfrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Orme</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometric Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Heteroskedasticity-Consistent Covariance Matrix Estimator and a Direct Test for Heteroskedasticity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The conception of the ABCD study: From substance use to a broad NIH collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Volkow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Koob</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Croyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Cogn Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of racism on Black American mental health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cogburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ransome</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Addy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jordan</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissecting racial bias in an algorithm used to manage the health of populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Obermeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Powers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Vogeli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mullainathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="453" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confronting racially exclusionary practices in the acquisition and analyses of neuroimaging data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ricard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dhamala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Allsop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brain-phenotype models fail for individuals who defy sample stereotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Greene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Noble</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">609</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022. 7925</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-ethnicity/race generalization failure of behavioral prediction from resting-state functional connectivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bzdok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1812</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racism May Interrupt Age-related Brain Growth of African American Children in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Assari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mincy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatr Child Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smaller Hippocampal Volume Among Black and Latinx Youth Living in High-Stigma Contexts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hatzenbuehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Weissman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mcketta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="809" to="819" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racism and Health: Evidence and Needed Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lawrence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racism and Health I: Pathways and Scientific Evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mohammed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Behav Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of race in clinical algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Basu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2704</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An empirical characterization of fair machine learning for clinical risk prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pfohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Foryciarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Biomedical Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genetic structure and history of Africans and African Americans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tishkoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Friedlaender</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">324</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1035" to="1044" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 5930</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Neuroscience of Socioeconomic Status: Correlates, Causes, and Consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Farah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Socioeconomic status and the developing brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hackman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Farah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Cogn Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association of Racial Discrimination With Neural Response to Threat in Black Women in the US Exposed to Trauma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ressler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1005" to="1012" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The neurophysiological consequences of racismrelated stressors in Black Americans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Webb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ressler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurosci Biobehav Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105638</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Taking race out of human genetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yudell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Desalle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tishkoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">351</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6273</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="564" to="565" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>SCIENCE AND SOCIETY</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Race as biology is fiction, racism as a social problem is real: Anthropological and historical perspectives on the social construction of race</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smedley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Smedley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Omi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Winant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Racial formation in the United States</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge/Taylor &amp; Francis Group</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Third edition. ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community-based participatory research with Black people and Black scientists: the power and the promise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Breland-Noble</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Streets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jordan</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic review of barriers and facilitators to minority research participation among African Americans, Latinos, Asian Americans, and Pacific Islanders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Duran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Norris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
