<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting History, Reshaping Memory: The Effects of Confronting Ingroup Atrocities *</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-01-26">January 26, 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>De Juan</surname></persName>
							<email>alexander.dejuan@uni-osnabrueck.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Professor of Comparative Politics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Osnabrueck University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anton</forename><surname>Peez</surname></persName>
							<email>peez@em.uni-frankfurt.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Post-Doctoral Researcher</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Peace Research Institute Frankfurt (PRIF)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Frankfurt; Associate Fellow</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sascha</forename><surname>Riaz</surname></persName>
							<email>sascha.riaz@eui.eu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Peter Mair Assistant Professor in Comparative Politics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">European University Institute</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Julian</forename><surname>Voß</surname></persName>
							<email>julian.voss@uni-osnabrueck.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">PhD Candidate</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Osnabrueck University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alberto</forename><forename type="middle">López</forename><surname>Ortega</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elias</forename><surname>Dinas</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Hix</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Teresa</forename><forename type="middle">Esteban</forename><surname>Casanelles</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Noam</forename><surname>Lupu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kasia</forename><surname>Nalewajko</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jane</forename><surname>Gingrich</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Federica</forename><surname>Genovese</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Rueda</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lukas</forename><surname>Stoetzer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Pierskalla</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename><surname>Piotrowska</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giovanni</forename><surname>Capoccia</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting History, Reshaping Memory: The Effects of Confronting Ingroup Atrocities *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-01-26">January 26, 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BD55F35A3C57ED2C113592C7FC2D5B25</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-22T02:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Memory culture</term>
					<term>Wehrmacht exhibition</term>
					<term>Ingroup atrocities</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>How do voters react to challenges of collective memories? We study the controversial "Wehrmacht exhibition" (1995)(1996)(1997)(1998)(1999), which exposed the German public to graphic evidence challenging the "myth of the clean Wehrmacht"-the false narrative that only the SS, not the military, systematically committed war crimes and perpetrated the Holocaust.</p><p>To study the exhibition's effects, we leverage survey data of over 830,000 voters in a staggered difference-in-differences setup. We complement this analysis with evidence from over 1,200 letters to the editor, an original survey of Germans born around the end of WWII, and interviews with public figures who spoke at exhibition openings. We find that the exhibition triggered political backlash, particularly among the children of WWII soldiers. However, this backlash was localized and short-lived. We also show that the exhibition effectively shifted public discourse on the Wehrmacht, demonstrating that memory entrepreneurs can overturn self-serving narratives without lasting political repercussions.</p><p>Word count-11,503 (excluding bibliography).</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In 1998, a visitor left an angry note in the guestbook of an exhibition on the German military during World War II (WWII) in Dresden, Germany: "I won't let anyone say anything negative about the German Wehrmacht! It was the world's greatest army! My father was also in the Wehrmacht, and I am proud of him! He fought honorably for the German Fatherland. However, he was not a murderer. This exhibition is a disgrace to the German people. " <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref>This note illustrates one of the most contentious public debates on Germany's Nazi past in the country's post-war history. The first so-called "Wehrmacht exhibition" <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(1995</ref><ref type="bibr">-1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wehrmachtsausstellung)</ref> exposed the German public to details about crimes committed by the German army during WWII, forcefully challenging the -until then -widespread myth of a "clean" Wehrmacht that exclusively attributed Nazi atrocities to the notorious Schutzstaffel (SS) and its subdivisions.</p><p>More than 850,000 people visited the exhibition, which was shown in 33 German and Austrian cities in the span of four and a half years <ref type="bibr">(NDR 2022)</ref>. In dozens of right-wing protests, citizens accused the exhibition organizers of betraying fallen German soldiers. These protests were met by counter-protests that supported the exhibition's challenge of self-serving narratives about Germany's Nazi past. For years, the exhibition received sustained coverage in local, regional, and national media and triggered intense public debates in federal and statelevel parliaments.</p><p>Such conflicts over the commemoration of historical ingroup atrocities are not specific to Germany. In many countries, they have recently moved to the center of broader "culture wars. "</p><p>In the United States, they have manifested as protests around the removal of Confederate monuments and debates about the definition of school curricula <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bevan 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kaufmann 2022)</ref>.</p><p>Spain experienced protests in 2019 when the remains of fascist dictator Francisco Franco were moved from a vast mausoleum to a family crypt to end the glorification of the authoritarian ruler (Jones 2019). In contrast, in an attempt to court conservative voters, French President Emmanuel Macron has resisted pressure from civil society organizations to revise France's commemoration of its violent past, highlighting in 2020 that "The Republic will not erase any trace or name from its history. " <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Williamson 2020</ref>). Although "memory wars" <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Malinova 2021)</ref> play an important role in many societies, we still know relatively little about their political implications. How do voters react to challenges to collective memories of ingroup atrocities?</p><p>Several recent studies have found that exposure to information about victims of ingroup violence can induce positive attitudinal changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Turkoglu, Ditlmann and Firestone 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Light, Creţan and Dunca 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Charnysh and Riaz 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Balcells, Palanza and Voytas 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Balcells and Voytas 2023)</ref>. Other studies have investigated the effects of challenges to memories of ingroup perpetrators, generating mixed results. While <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Rahnama (2024)</ref> finds evidence that such challenges can improve attitudes towards victim groups, <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Villamil and Balcells (2021)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Rozenas and Vlasenko (2022)</ref> find that they increase support for political parties ideologically close to the perpetrators of past violence.</p><p>We aim to add to the latter strand of research. Thus far, analyses have focused on investigating the effects of the outcomes of local memory conflicts, arguing that they signal the dominance of specific narratives and thereby trigger processes of alignment or opposition mobilization. We contribute to this research by examining the politics surrounding the initial challenges to self-serving narratives. Understanding initial public reactions is crucial to understanding why political and social actors often refrain from challenging established self-serving narratives, contributing to the persistence of such narratives.</p><p>We argue that challenges to self-serving historical narratives can trigger backlash against political actors perceived as the primary initiators or supporters of these challenges. According to social identity theory, people derive self-esteem from a positive ingroup image. Selfserving collective memories downplay past ingroup atrocities and thereby help maintain this image. Memory entrepreneurs that challenge these memories and suggest that the ingroup has committed immoral acts threaten positive ingroup images and, therefore, can trigger de-fensive reactions. Family histories play a crucial role in this process, as family experiences can influence the relevance and nature of self-serving collective memories and thus may moderate the intensity of the backlash against these challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Welzer, Moller and Tschuggnall 2014)</ref>. The more individuals are exposed to family memories that reinforce one-sided collective narratives, the more likely they are to react defensively to challenges against these narratives.</p><p>We test this argument in the context of the 1995-1999 Wehrmacht exhibition. We consider this an "extreme case" in terms of our explanatory variable of interest. The exhibition challenged a strong, deep-seated collective memory of a particularly gruesome ingroup transgression. Compared to other challenges of narratives-such as the removal of statues or the renaming of streets-the exhibition was a very comprehensive attack on a self-serving memory. It directly exposed hundreds of thousands of people to historical evidence and shocking images, forcefully dispelling preexisting myths. By centering on the crimes of the 17 millionman Wehrmacht rather than the Nazi elite and selective SS, the exhibition had immediate personal implications for the vast majority of German families in the late 1990s. The widespread impact on millions of families and the intensity of the historical challenge in this context increase our ability to detect political effects.</p><p>At the same time, we consider this to be a particularly relevant case. Narratives of WWII feature prominently in the collective memories of many states as well as in the family identities of their citizens <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(Welzer 2007)</ref>. Surveys show that a majority of citizens across many countries see WWII as the most important event of the past 100 years <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Pennebaker, Páez and Deschamps 2006)</ref>. Most countries directly involved in WWII later propagated narrow and self-serving narratives of their role in the war <ref type="bibr">(Lebow, Kansteiner and Fogu 2006)</ref>. As such, the case allows us to investigate the effects of challenges to self-serving narratives in a context that is relevant to a larger set of countries.</p><p>To study the political effects of the Wehrmacht exhibition, we leverage high-frequency survey data of more than 830,000 voters. Our identification strategy leverages spatial and temporal variation in exposure to the traveling exhibition in a staggered difference-in-differences setup. In our preferred specification, we compare respondents in counties that hosted the exhibition to respondents in counties that applied to host the exhibition but were not selected for idiosyncratic reasons. We complement this analysis with information from 1,200 handcoded letters that citizens sent to newspaper editors across Germany to voice their sentiments toward the exhibition and with an original survey of Germans born before 1950.</p><p>Drawing on geo-coded letters to the editor as well as on survey data gauging the salience of different political issues, we first show that the exhibition generated significant public interest and contention in the treated localities. Our main analyses indicate that this translated into political backlash against the main political proponent of the exhibition, the German Social Democratic Party (SPD). Following the opening of the exhibition in a given locality, the SPD loses about eight percentage points in electoral support, on average-a substantial drop.</p><p>However, we also find that the political effects of the exhibition are localized and relatively short-lived. We find that voters return to their pre-treatment political preferences after the traveling exhibition moves on to its next location.</p><p>In order to explore the mechanisms driving these effects, we test for treatment effect heterogeneity across age cohorts. We find that the backlash was particularly pronounced among respondents of age groups whose fathers were particularly likely to have served or died in WWII. Drawing on an original survey of around 1,300 Germans born around the end of WWII, we find evidence that this result is likely attributable to ingrained, glorifying family narratives about fathers who served or fell in the war, rendering challenges to the "clean Wehrmacht myth" particularly threatening to people's self-image and group identity.</p><p>To assess the plausibility of our assumptions and main findings within the historical context of the Wehrmacht exhibition, we conducted semi-structured qualitative interviews with public figures who spoke at exhibition openings throughout Germany. These included highranking politicians and well-known personalities, such as one former state governor (Ministerpräsident) and one of Germany's most well-known publicists and public figures. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> We asked about the exhibition organization, the positions of political parties, the degree to which the SPD was identified as the main party proponent of the exhibition, local and national debates, and the nature of the backlash against the exhibition.</p><p>As a further extension of our study, we investigate whether the Wehrmacht exhibition had a lasting impact on the public discourse surrounding the Wehrmacht. In other words, did memory entrepreneurs successfully shift collective memory in this context? Did the exhibition succeed in overturning the "clean Wehrmacht" narrative? We draw on Google Ngram data to examine this question. We find that after the exhibition launched in 1995, discussions of Wehrmacht war crimes in German-language books increased sharply and persistently. Although the political backlash was brief, the exhibition's effect on collective memory was profound. It rendered the "myth of the clean Wehrmacht" untenable and fostered a lasting shift toward a more nuanced view of the Wehrmacht's-and thus German society's-involvement in World War II atrocities.</p><p>These findings make two main contributions: First, we contribute to an emerging research field studying the dynamics and consequences of contentious social and political debates on reinterpretations of history <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Balcells, Palanza and Voytas 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Balcells and Voytas 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Balcells, Purdue and Voytas 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Rahnama 2024;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Rozenas and Vlasenko 2022;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Villamil and Balcells 2021)</ref>. Adding to previous studies, we show how challenges of historical narratives can trigger substantive backlash against the actors associated with such challenges. This may explain why such challenges to self-serving memories are relatively rare and why such memories tend to be particularly persistent. Importantly, however, our results also show that (i) the political backlash against these challenges is short-lived and localized and that (ii) challenges to deeply entrenched collective memories can be successful in shifting public discourses. Thus, while the anticipation of strong counter-reactions may deter potential memory entrepreneurs, our findings suggest that the long-term benefits of challenging self-serving collective memories can outweigh any short-term political costs.</p><p>Second, the effect heterogeneity we demonstrate across birth cohorts highlights the crucial role of personal and family experiences in moderating the effects of challenges to established historical narratives. This finding may help explain the seemingly contradictory results in prior research. The time span between the historical episode of violence and the challenge to the self-serving narrative determines the population shares with personal or proximate family experiences-i.e., the share of the population that is most likely to defend the mnemonic status quo, according to our findings. Thus, while early historical reinterpretations may trigger backlash due to greater personal proximity to perpetrators (e.g., Rozenas and Vlasenko 2022), challenges after longer time periods may have better chances of leading to substantive shifts in public discourses (e.g., Rahnama 2024).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Self-serving memories of a "dark past"</head><p>Collective memories are sets "of ideas, images, and feelings about the past" <ref type="bibr">(Irwin-Zarecka 2017, 4)</ref>. Contrary to what is usually referred to as "history, " memories are not "objective" representations of past events. They are the product of interactions between various social and political actors engaged in "memory politics, " aimed at promoting a specific interpretation of a group's collective past <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Berger and Niven 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Malinova 2021;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Wertsch 2009)</ref>. Typically, these interpretations aim at reinforcing a positive self-image of the community, such as highlighting its purportedly glorious history and achievements <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Wertsch and Roediger III 2008)</ref>.</p><p>However, in many countries, memory entrepreneurs aiming to advance positive ingroup images must deal with their respective communities' "dark past": "a large-scale or systematic human rights atrocity that occurred in the past and for which the state bears some responsibility, either directly or as a successor to the regime that perpetrated the crimes" <ref type="bibr">(Dixon 2018, 15)</ref>. In trying to maintain a positive self-image after such episodes of ingroup violence, communities have tried to advance collective memories that either omit or re-interpret their own role in committing atrocities.</p><p>For example, after Francisco Franco's death in 1975, Spanish right-and left-wing parties concluded an informal pact of collective amnesia (Pacto del Olvido; Pact of Forgetting) about violence during the Spanish Civil War <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Malinova 2021</ref><ref type="bibr">(Malinova , 1000))</ref>. Investigating the development of collective memories in post-war Germany, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kansteiner (2006)</ref> shows how elites, institutions, and the media advanced public narratives designed to "lift the moral burden of Nazism" from the shoulders of the population (p. 582). Still, other states have employed a more repressive approach: the Turkish censorship regarding the 1915 genocide of Armenians is one example of a state punishing the public acknowledgment of its "dark past" <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Bilewicz 2016)</ref>.</p><p>The resulting self-serving narratives tend to be "sticky"-transmitted through physical manifestations and social practices such as monuments, ceremonies, archives, museums, and school curricula. However, in many cases, memory entrepreneurs eventually challenge these dominant collective memories. How do such challenges of self-serving narratives affect citizens' political attitudes and behavior?</p><p>Relatively few quantitative studies have addressed this question systematically. A first group of studies investigates the effects of exposure to victim-centered information about past episodes of violence-highlighting the suffering of victims of ingroup violence. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Turkoglu, Ditlmann and Firestone (2023)</ref> find that exposure to local memorials that commemorate victims of atrocities by the Nazis reduces support for a revisionist far-right party in Germany. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Light, Creţan and Dunca (2021)</ref> analyze how people react to a visit to a transitional justice museum in Romania and find that the visit increased people's support for remembrance of violence as well as their passion and empathy towards victims of violence. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Balcells, Palanza and Voytas (2022)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Balcells and Voytas (2023)</ref> find evidence of similar effects in a systematic experimental study in Chile. They found that students who visited a transitional justice museum showed more support for victim compensation and less support for the punishment of perpetrators. Rather than polarizing visitors, the visit thus fostered convergence on divisive topics.</p><p>A second group of studies investigates the effects of challenges of collective memories of ingroup perpetrators of atrocities. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Rahnama (2024)</ref> finds that the removal of Confederate symbols in the US decreased racial resentment-presumably because the removal signaled a shift in dominant public norms. <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Villamil and Balcells (2021)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Rozenas and Vlasenko (2022)</ref>, on the other hand, find that the removal of symbols of past periods of violence and oppression triggers a backlash, increasing support for political parties ideologically close to perpetrators of past violence in Spain and Ukraine. Both studies attribute this effect to political competition.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Rozenas and Vlasenko (2022)</ref>, changes to commemorative practices indicate a shift in the distribution of power in favor of political actors and parties advocating for change.</p><p>This may then prompt competing political actors to mobilize their constituencies to counteract this shift.</p><p>These studies shed light on the outcomes of "memory wars" over symbolic representations of ingroup histories. They investigate the effects of the actual removal of statues, the destruction of monuments, or the renaming of streets and squares. The observable effects result from the fact that these "victories" in memory wars signal shifts in the dominance of certain norms and/or political actors, triggering processes of attitudinal alignment or counter-mobilization.</p><p>We complement this research by zooming in on the initial stages of these memory wars: How do voters react when counter-narratives emerge that challenge deeply entrenched, self-serving narratives about ingroup perpetrators and atrocities?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">How challenges of collective memories trigger backlash</head><p>While processes of alignment and counter-mobilization may explain the effects of the outcomes of memory wars, we argue that perceived identity threats can explain backlash<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> against the initial challenges and challengers of self-serving collective memories. The following two subsections introduce our main argument and our expectations regarding effect heterogeneity for challenges to collective memories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Self-serving narratives, identity threats, and defensive reactions</head><p>Collective memories constitute an essential element of social identity formation, as they "preserve the store of knowledge from which a group derives an awareness of its unity and peculiarity" <ref type="bibr">(Assmann and Czaplicka 1995, 130)</ref>. In fact, collective memory and collective identities are so closely intertwined that some scholars perceive them as "two sides of a coin rather than different phenomena" <ref type="bibr">(Olick 1999, 342)</ref>. Thus, while self-serving collective memories underpin positive group identities, challenges of these memories will threaten positive group images.</p><p>Research in social psychology shows that such identity threats can trigger defensive reactions. According to social identity theory, people derive self-esteem from their group identity. Thus, they want to perceive their ingroups in a positive light-as good and moral. Conversely, negative attributes of ingroups affect individuals' self-concept negatively <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Tajfel and Turner 2004)</ref>. When an ingroup is considered responsible for immoral behavior, individuals can feel collective guilt or shame. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">4</ref> In order to reduce negative effects on individuals' self-concept, people will seek to downregulate these negative perceptions <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Branscombe et al. 1999)</ref>.</p><p>People can use a variety of strategies to reduce negative feelings of collective guilt and shame. They may try to minimize ingroup responsibility <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Bilali, Tropp and Dasgupta 2012)</ref>, use "motivated forgetting" about violence committed against outgroups <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Rotella and Richeson 2013)</ref>, or they may place responsibility for ingroup transgressions on a few individual "black sheep" <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Marques, Abrams and Serôdio 2001)</ref>. Finally, people may also try to defend collective memories against re-interpretation in order to reduce the social identity threat associated with exposure to the transgressions of ingroup members <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Branscombe and Wann 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Tajfel and Turner 2004)</ref>.</p><p>One possible element of such a defensive strategy is the derogation of the source of the identity threat: individuals criticize or denounce the attackers to discredit them and to mitigate the threat <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Petriglieri 2011)</ref>. Empirical studies show that ingroup criticism can indeed motivate people to punish individuals who are deemed responsible for identity threats (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Hornsey and Esposo 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Thürmer and McCrea 2023;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">De Hoog 2013)</ref>. In light of this research, we hypothesize that challenges of self-serving collective memories will lead many voters to distance themselves from the perceived sources of such challenges.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Collective memories meet family experiences</head><p>Individuals do not simply "absorb" (self-serving) collective memories uniformly. They adopt those parts of collective interpretations that reflect their personal experiences and memories <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Rosenthal 2015)</ref>. The result is an "amalgam" of collective and individual memories <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Reese and Fivush 2008)</ref>. Families play an essential role in this merging process. Maurice Halbwachs' pioneering work on the social construction of memories highlights families' role as "mnemonic intersections" that transmit and transform higher-level collective memories according to the specific experiences of the family members <ref type="bibr">(Erll 2011, 308)</ref>. Recent empirical studies have shown how memories of war in particular are transmitted and sustained within families <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Lemoli and Gennaro 2024)</ref>. Against this background, we expect family histories to moderate the effects of challenges to self-serving memories in two important ways.</p><p>First, family experiences influence the relevance of self-serving collective memories to individuals' identities. Gerber and van Landingham (2021) demonstrate how the salience of certain collective memories depends on family connections to the respective historical events.</p><p>If parents, grandparents, or other relatives were directly involved in past episodes of ingroup violence, collective memories of these episodes will be more personally relevant and salient to individuals. Moreover, kinship ties to such events make it easier to relate to the participants in the violence emotionally. Thus, we expect a stronger role of self-serving memories and consequently also a more pronounced backlash against the challengers of these narratives among people whose close family members belong to the group of perpetrators in the respective historical episode of ingroup violence.</p><p>Second, in addition to salience, family experiences may also strengthen or weaken the onesided and selective nature of self-serving collective memories. Through their daily interactions, family members transmit their own memories and interpretations of experienced events to the next generation. This way, parents and grandparents serve as agents of "mnemonic socialization" that shape how children understand their ingroup history <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Reese and Fivush 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Erll 2011)</ref>. Thus, the more individuals are exposed to family memories that reinforce one-sided collective memories of ingroup perpetrators, the more likely it is that challenges to these collective memories trigger defensive reactions and backlash against the source of these challenges.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Background: the 1995-1999 Wehrmacht exhibition</head><p>The first Wehrmacht exhibition (Wehrmachtsausstellung) was a traveling exhibition examining the crimes of the Wehrmacht during World War II in the Soviet Union and the Balkans, titled "War of Annihilation. Crimes of the Wehrmacht, 1941-1944. " 5 It was shown in 33 cities in Germany and Austria between March 1995 and October 1999. 6 The exhibition was ultimately withdrawn and revised due to several errors in the labeling and attribution of photos.</p><p>Nonetheless, these errors did not change the exhibition's key message and societal lessons surrounding the refutation of the 'myth of the clean Wehrmacht. ' A second exhibition, titled "Crimes of the Wehrmacht. Dimensions of the war of annihilation, 1941-1944, " 7 was shown in 13 cities from November 2001 to March 2004. We focus on the 1995-1999 Wehrmacht exhibition because it first publicly challenged important post-war narratives, received far more attention, and sparked greater debate than the second exhibition did (see SI Section A).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Set-up and content of the exhibition</head><p>The exhibition set off a major public debate surrounding the war crimes committed by the German military, which had previously been shrouded by the 'myth of the clean Wehrmacht. ' This widespread, false narrative held that the Wehrmacht was not implicated in war crimes and generally behaved honorably, while the SS and the Nazi Party alone were responsible for the Holocaust and all other German atrocities and war crimes. Countering this myth meant implicating not only the selective and voluntary SS and former German elites but also the 17 million men who served in the Wehrmacht during World War II <ref type="bibr">(those born 1910</ref><ref type="bibr">-1927;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kroener, Müller and</ref><ref type="bibr">Umbreit 1988, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Overmans 2004</ref>), mostly through universal 5 "Vernichtungskrieg. Verbrechen der Wehrmacht 1941 bis 1944. " 6 Six Austrian cities and 27 German cities, including Hamburg twice, for a total of 34 showings in 33 cities. 7 "Verbrechen der Wehrmacht. Dimensionen des <ref type="bibr">Vernichtungskrieges 1941</ref><ref type="bibr">Vernichtungskrieges -1944. " . "</ref> conscription. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">8</ref> This, in turn, meant that the vast majority of German families were confronted with the reality that their fathers, husbands, and brothers had been part of a massive criminal endeavor.</p><p>The exhibition was curated and run by the Hamburg Institute for Social Research (Hamburger Institut für Sozialforschung), with local and state civil society organizations or government institutions hosting it for an average length of about five weeks per city. It consisted of 1,433 photographs and other documents printed on large, white display panels and contextualized with explanatory captions (Hamburger Institut für Sozialforschung 1997; Arbeitskreis <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Militärgeschichte 2000)</ref>. Many of these photographs showed graphic violence and cruelty, covering the harrowing prelude, execution, and aftermath of mass murder and war crimes.</p><p>They were largely photographed by Wehrmacht soldiers themselves, either as private keepsakes or through the Wehrmacht Propaganda Companies (Propagandakompanien). The subject matter and set-up of the exhibition made attending it an intense, personal experience for many visitors (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Beckermann 1996</ref>).<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">9</ref> </p><p>For instance, the exhibition documented the Wehrmacht's involvement in the 29/30 September 1941 Babyn Yar massacre in Kyiv, Ukraine, in which 34.000 Jews were murdered within 36 hours. The SS and the Wehrmacht's Sixth Army under Field Marshal Walter von Reichenau closely cooperated in preparing and carrying out the massacre and many other atrocities in Ukraine <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Rüß 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hoppe 2021)</ref>. Other sections of the exhibition documented German atrocities in Belarus and Serbia. Notably, the exhibition also critically examined the glorification of Wehrmacht soldiers and officers in postwar popular culture. In films, novels, and magazines, the war was depicted in equal parts as a gripping adventure abroad and as a national tragedy, with Wehrmacht soldiers as both keen daredevils and innocent victims of a system that betrayed them. This narrative emphasized qualities such as bravery, camaraderie, and loyalty while omitting any mention of the widespread atrocities soldiers had committed throughout Europe and elsewhere-thereby contributing to the image of a 'clean Wehrmacht' <ref type="bibr">(Hamburger Institut für Sozialforschung 1997, 8-18)</ref>.</p><p>To illustrate the nature of the images shown and how they were captioned, the following page shows three photographs from before and after the Babyn Yar massacre and a fourth photograph from before the 1941 Lubny massacre, all of which were shown in the exhibition.</p><p>While the documentary evidence and the content of the exhibition were well-established from a historiographic perspective at the time, it was not common knowledge among the German general public. [Please note that these include a graphic image of a corpse.]</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Public reactions and attention in Germany</head><p>The exhibition was a major news item in Germany for years.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">10</ref> Parliamentary debates in March and April 1997 over whether the exhibition was to be shown in the chambers of the Bundestag are considered to be among the great moments in the Federal Republic's parliamentary history (BPB 2017) and were mirrored in many state parliaments.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_7">11</ref> Exhibition openings were routinely met with aggressive far-right and neo-Nazi protests, which in turn triggered large democratic counter-protests.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_8">12</ref> On 09 March 1999, the exhibition site in Saarbrücken was the target of a bombing, most likely by neo-Nazi elements (SR 2024). <ref type="foot" target="#foot_9">13</ref>Within this sustained national media coverage, the exhibition had three major peaks in public attention: its opening in Munich in February 1997 and the massive neo-Nazi protests and bombing in February and March 1999, as well as a smaller peak surrounding the 1999 controversies regarding the labeling of several photographs. We visualize temporal trends in national media coverage of the exhibition in Figure A.1 in the SI. Furthermore, local attention spiked wherever the exhibition was shown, as we discuss further in Section 6.1.</p><p>Examples of photographs and captions shown in the exhibition.</p><p>"Victims on the road to Babyn Yar. " "Uniformed men rummage through the belongings of the murdered. "</p><p>"The murder sites. " "Lubny, 16 October 1941: The Jewish population before its mass shooting. "</p><p>Note: These images were shown in the exhibition and the exhibition catalog; Hamburger Institut für <ref type="bibr">Sozialforschung (1997, p. 78-81)</ref>. Note that these color versions were only shown in the second exhibition. The first exhibition used black-and-white copies. On the provenance and usage of these photographs, which came to be known as the "Hähle Photos, " see Hamburger Institut für Sozialforschung (2021).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Partisanship and the exhibition</head><p>The exhibition split public opinion on major issues of German history and reckoning with the past (Vergangenheitsbewältigung), often along party lines. Importantly for our research interest, the Social Democratic Party of Germany (SPD) supported the exhibition and was clearly the party that was most closely associated with it, especially at the local and state level. Conversely, the Christian-democratic CDU and their Bavarian counterpart CSU overwhelmingly opposed the exhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Tagesschau/ARD 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">WDR 2007)</ref>. These clear-cut party dynamics</p><p>were confirmed in all of our interviews (see SI Section F).</p><p>Of the 28 exhibition openings held in Germany, 20 featured at least one SPD official (71%) as a speaker, by far the highest share among all parties (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). <ref type="foot" target="#foot_10">14</ref> The Greens had speakers at three openings (11%), and the CDU, FDP, and PDS were represented at one opening each (4%).</p><p>Of the 37 speakers who were elected or party-nominated officials at the time, more than threequarters were SPD members (29; 78%), 11% were Greens (4), and 3% were CDU, FDP, and PDS representatives each <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(1)</ref>. Many of these SPD politicians were very well-known-they included state governors (Ministerpräsidenten), mayors of major cities, and elder statespeople<ref type="foot" target="#foot_11">15</ref> -while the other parties were mainly represented by local politicians, if at all.</p><p>The SPD not only objectively played a prominent role in supporting the exhibition but was also perceived by the public as its main advocate. In a survey we conducted with approximately 1,300 German citizens in November 2024-nearly thirty years after the exhibition first opened-we asked respondents which party they recalled to have most strongly supported the Wehrmacht exhibition (see Section 7 and Appendix Section B.3 for detailed survey information). Among those who remembered the exhibition, about 50 percent identified the SPD as its strongest supporter.</p><p>The exhibition constituted a potent challenge to an established, self-serving collective memory and was strongly associated with the SPD in the public eye. Accordingly, our the- </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exhibition applicants:</head><p>We additionally collected information on localities that applied to host the exhibition but were not selected as venues for idiosyncratic reasons. We identified these locations ('applicant counties') on the basis of archival correspondence between the HIS and interested parties, mostly local civil society organizations or local and state government institutions. The process for selecting cities to host the exhibition was informal and driven by expressions of interest sent to the HIS. No formal application criteria were set by the HIS except for adequate space and financial backing. The selection of exhibition locations was primarily driven by the timing of the application as well as the organizer's preferences, which tended to favor larger cities (see <ref type="bibr">Figure C.8)</ref>. The spatial distribution of applicants and selected venues for the Wehrmacht exhibition is visualized in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. It should be noted that the vast majority of exhibition venues were located in West German cities. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_12">16</ref> We thus do not have statistical power to examine heterogeneity between West Germany and the territories of the former GDR, which had a distinct memory culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Wolfrum 2008)</ref>.</p><p>Voting intentions: Our main outcome variable measures support for the Social Democratic Party (SPD), i.e., the main proponent of the Wehrmacht exhibition (see Section 4.3). To measure granular changes in SPD support immediately before and after the exhibition's opening, we draw on a high-frequency representative survey conducted by the survey company Forsa. Each day, a cross-section of about 500 eligible voters are asked which party they would vote for if there were a federal election next Sunday (Sonntagsfrage, 'Sunday question'; see SI Section B.1 for details). This is the most common survey item to elicit party preferences in Germany. In addition to voting intentions, we observe several individual-level socioeconomic characteristics and the county in which respondents reside. In total, we observe the voting intentions of 837,079 eligible voters surveyed between <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">1995 and</ref><ref type="bibr">2000 (see Figures C.4 and</ref><ref type="bibr">C.5</ref> for the number of observations by county and cohort). Our main outcome variable is a binary indicator 𝑌 𝑖,𝑡 that equals one if respondent 𝑖 interviewed in time period 𝑡 intends to vote for the SPD and zero if not. We present summary statistics of this survey data in Table <ref type="table">C</ref>.6 in the SI.</p><p>Issue salience: In addition to party preferences, we examine the exhibition's impact on the perceived salience of different political issues. To do this, we use an open-ended question </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exhibition shown Applicants</head><p>Note:</p><p>The figure shows the localities where the Wehrmacht exhibition was shown between 1995 and 1999 (red dots) and localities that applied to host the exhibition but were not selected as venues (grey triangles).</p><p>from the Forsa survey, asking respondents to identify the most important political issues in Germany at the time of the interview. We aggregated these responses into four relevant categories: immigration, right-wing extremism, foreign deployments of the German military (Bundeswehr), and violent conflicts in general (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">B</ref>.3 in the SI). For each category, we created a binary variable indicating whether a respondent mentioned an issue related to that category.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Letters to the editor:</head><p>To examine the exhibition's salience at the local level, we draw on a comprehensive collection of letters to the editor regarding the exhibition held by the HIS. We drew a random sample of 1,247 letters to the editor from a corpus of about 4.000-5.000 total items. This collection was compiled by the HIS as the exhibition was being shown by con-tracting two media monitoring agencies specialized in collecting, filing, and labeling physical press clippings. We hand-coded these letters on key information such as publication date, author gender, location, overall sentiment towards the exhibition, and an inductively developed set of the most common reasons for exhibition support and opposition. We provide more details on this data source in Section B.2 in the SI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Empirical strategy</head><p>To study political backlash against the exhibition among German voters, we estimate the causal effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on voting intentions measured in high-frequency geocoded survey data. The Wehrmacht exhibition traveled from city to city and thus opened at different times in different cities, i.e., voters in different localities were treated (i.e., experienced exhibition onset) at different times. Accordingly, we estimate a staggered differencein-differences specification. Following the approach and notation of Callaway and Sant'Anna (2021), we proceed in two steps. First, we estimate group-time average treatment effects:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ATT(g, 𝑡) = E [ 𝑌 𝑡 (𝑔) -𝑌 𝑡 (0) | 𝐺 𝑔 = 1 ]</formula><p>where 𝑡 indicates the time period and the groups 𝑔 are defined by the time period in which a unit first becomes treated, i.e., when the exhibition opens in a given county. 𝑌 𝑡 (𝑔) indicates unit 𝑖's potential outcome in time period 𝑡 if treated at time period 𝑔. 𝑌 𝑡 (0) indicates the potential outcome under control status. 𝐺 𝑔 is defined as a binary variable that is equal to one if a unit is first treated in period 𝑔. In the second step, we partially aggregate these countyspecific estimates. Specifically, we are primarily interested in the average treatment effect conditional on the length of exposure:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">𝜃 (𝑒) = ∑ 𝑔∈G 1{𝑔 + 𝑒 ≤ T }𝑃 (𝐺 = 𝑔 | 𝐺 + 𝑒 ≤ T )𝐴𝑇𝑇 (𝑔, 𝑔 + 𝑒)</formula><p>which gives the average effect of exposure to the Wehrmacht exhibition 𝑒 months after its opening. For our main results, we set 𝑒 = 1, i.e., we estimate the average treatment effect one month after the exhibition opening in a given location. We show event-study estimates for varying lengths of exposure (𝑒) in Figure D.11 in the SI.</p><p>As noted above, we observe treatment assignment at the county level. At the individual level, we thus not only consider those who personally attended the exhibition as "exposed, " but also those segments of the local population who were indirectly confronted with the discourse, controversy, and debate following the local opening of the exhibition. Between 1995 and 1999, over 750,000 people viewed the exhibition in Germany, yet its impact extended to many millions more. This indirect treatment exposure encompasses highly controversial debates in local newspapers,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_13">17</ref> second-hand exposure through friends and family,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_14">18</ref> or having large Nazi protests and democratic counter-protests in one's own city. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_15">19</ref> Hence, the vast majority of county residents were exposed to the exhibition, either directly or indirectly.</p><p>Analogous to the canonical difference-in-differences setup with two groups and two time periods, the group-time average treatment effects ATT(g, 𝑡) are identified under the parallel trends assumption. In other words, our identification strategy requires that in the absence of treatment, average potential outcomes for group 𝑔 and average outcomes in the control group would have followed parallel paths in the post-treatment period 𝑡 ≥ 𝑔. Crucially, this approach does not require treated and control localities to be similar ('balanced') with respect to background characteristics (e.g. population size or unemployment). The design accommodates level differences between treated and control groups and only requires that the two groups follow parallel trends (over-time changes) in the absence of treatment. We The construction of the control group involves a trade-off between its size and similarity to the treated group. We illustrate this trade-off in Figure C.8 in the SI, which visualizes average treated-control differences along a series of covariates for three reasonable choices for the control group: (1) all never-treated counties, (2) never-treated counties that applied to host the exhibition but were not selected for idiosyncratic reasons ('applicant counties, ' see 5.1), and (3) applicant city counties, i.e., further narrowing down the group of applicant counties to larger cities. Finally, we can also use ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) not-yet-treated units as the control group. This latter choice implies the comparison of over-time changes in electoral preferences between counties where the exhibition opened earlier and counties where the exhibition opened at a later point in time.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, we use applicant counties (2) as the main control group throughout our empirical analysis. However, we demonstrate that our substantive conclusions and point estimates remain virtually unchanged for different choices of the control group (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</p><p>This provides further evidence that covariate level differences between treated and control localities are of minor importance for identification in our setting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Manipulation check</head><p>Before presenting our main results on political reactions to the Wehrmacht exhibition, we conduct a manipulation check to show whether the treatment of exhibition onset was perceived by voters in host localities. Specifically, we examine whether the exhibition (1) garnered significant attention at the local level and, more broadly, (2) altered the perceived salience of different political issues among voters.</p><p>We begin by examining the politicization and salience of the exhibition following its opening in a given locality. To do this, we test whether the volume of published letters to the editor about the exhibition increases in treated locations in the days and weeks immediately following the exhibition's opening. We draw on a geocoded sample of exhibition-related letters to the editor printed in local and national newspapers, which we collected in the HIS archives (see Section 5.1 and SI Section B.2). We geocoded these letters using information on the author's place of residence, which is typically listed next to their name. We then calculated the aggregated count of letters at the county-day level and analyze this data using a regression discontinuity in time (RDiT) approach. We present the results in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>, which shows the average daily rate of published exhibition-related letters ten weeks before and after the exhibition's opening in a treated county. We find a clearly visible, statistically significant spike in the volume of exhibition-related letters published following the opening of the exhibition in a given locality (𝑝 &lt; 0.01, see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.10). <ref type="foot" target="#foot_16">20</ref> We interpret this finding as strong evidence that the exhibition generated significant public interest and discussion in the treated localities.</p><p>These effects persist for about six weeks, after which the daily rate of exhibition-related letters recedes to its pre-treatment level. The temporal persistence of these effects closely maps onto the average duration of the exhibition: on average, the exhibition was shown for about 5 weeks in a given locality. We do not find strong evidence for anticipation effects, i.e., we do not find a substantial increase in the daily rate of exhibition-related letters in the days immediately before the opening of the exhibition. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.10 in the SI additionally disaggregates these results by letter sentiment. Following the exhibition's opening in a given locality, we find a spike in both letters expressing opposition to and support for the exhibition. As outlined in Section 4, public opinion about the exhibition was divided, which is mirrored in the sentiments expressed in exhibition-related letters to the editor. However, we note that (1) the overall share of negative letters is substantially higher than the overall share of positive letters <ref type="bibr">(Figure C.6</ref> in the SI; 67% vs. 30%) and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) the increase following the exhibition is likewise higher for negative letters (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.10 in the SI). Overall, negative reactions to the exhibition predominated in letters to the editor.</p><p>Common arguments from those who opposed the exhibition were that it was historically inaccurate, driven by a "political agenda" or that the Wehrmacht's crimes were not exceptional compared to other armies (see Figure <ref type="figure">C</ref>.7 in the SI).</p><p>Next, we examine whether exposure to the exhibition affected voters' general political views and attitudes beyond the exhibition. Specifically, we examine the effects of the Wehrmacht exhibition on the perceived salience of different political issues as measured in the Forsa survey (see Section 5.1). The results for four aggregated issue areas-immigration, right-wing extremism, foreign deployments of the German armed forces (Bundeswehr), and violent conflicts in general-are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. As expected, we find that the Wehrmacht exhibition raises the political salience of issues related specifically to the German armed forces. We find statistically insignificant effect estimates of small magnitudes for all other issue areas, which are less directly related to the exhibition's themes. Overall, the results of both manipulation checks support the validity of our main analysis by confirming that local exposure to the Wehrmacht exhibition elevated voters' attention to the exhibition specifically and the German military more generally. We now turn to examine the effects of the exhibition on voting intentions to examine the political reactions to and backlash against the exhibition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Main results</head><p>We present our main results for the effects of exhibition exposure on electoral support for the SPD-the main proponent of the exhibition-in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. In our preferred specification (column 1), we estimate that the Wehrmacht exhibition caused an eight percentage point drop in SPD support in treated localities from one month to the next. This is a substantively significant effect: for context, in the 1994 federal election, the SPD secured 36.4% of the nationwide vote. These effects are driven by an increase in the share of voters ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) without a clear party preference and (2) who support the center-right CDU/CSU, which maintained a much more critical stance towards the exhibition (see Figure <ref type="figure">E</ref>.16 in the SI). Overall, we find evidence of a strong backlash against the exhibition and its main supporters right after its opening in a given locality.</p><p>Our substantive conclusions remain unchanged for different choices of constructing the control group, i.e., for different choices of striking the trade-off between covariate balance and sample size (see the discussion in Section 5.2). The results for using (i) applicant city counties, (ii) never-treated counties, and (iii) not-yet-treated counties as the control group are shown in columns 2-4 in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. Across model specifications, we estimate a statistically significant, negative effect of exposure to the Wehrmacht exhibition on electoral support for the SPD, the exhibition's most prominent supporters (recall Section 4.3). The effect estimates are stable across specifications, which indicates that covariate differences between treated and control localities are of minor importance for identification in our difference-in-differences setting.</p><p>To examine the durability of these effects, we present ATT estimates for varying exposure lengths in Figure D.11 in the SI. Our analyses suggest that the political backlash against the exhibition materializes during the first month after the exhibition's opening. This effect du- ration mirrors the average time the exhibition stayed in a given locality: about 5 weeks. We find that voters return to their pre-treatment political preferences after the exhibition moves on to its next location. In other words, the backlash against the exhibition-while it is politically salient at the local level-temporarily reduces SPD support but does not result in voters forming a lasting attachment to another party (see Figure <ref type="figure">E</ref>.16 in the SI). To further examine the duration of these effects, we also estimate a difference-in-differences specification using county-level election data for the federal elections of 1994 and 1998. The results from this analysis align with the event-study estimates. We do not detect electoral losses for the SPD in the 1998 federal election in treated localities (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.11 in the SI). Overall, we find that the Wehrmacht exhibition triggered a substantial political backlash that was, however, localized and relatively short-lived.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Robustness &amp; additional tests</head><p>We conduct a series of additional tests to ensure the robustness of our results and to address concerns about identification.</p><p>Spillover effects: For our main specification, we only code counties in which the exhibition was shown as treated. However, it might be the case that the exhibition likewise attracted attention in neighboring counties, as citizens may have commuted to the exhibition within a limited distance and heard about it in the regional press. To address this concern, we proceed in two steps. First, we estimate the plausible geographic scope of spillover effects. Using the letters to the editor discussed in Section 6.1, we quantify the distance radius within which the exhibition attracted public interest and discussion (see Figure <ref type="figure">E</ref>.15 for details). As expected, we find that public interest in the exhibition strongly decays with greater distance from the exhibition venue. However, we also find that the exhibition attracted limited public attention within a distance of up to 60 kilometers around a given host city. Accordingly, it might be the case that our main effect estimates are downward biased, as a small number of control counties might, in fact, likewise experience political backlash against the exhibition. To address this concern directly, we conducted an additional robustness test that enforces a minimum distance of at least 60 kilometers between treated and control counties. Specifically, we construct a new control group comprising all never-treated counties at least 60 kilometers from the closest exhibition venue 21 . We find that our main substantive conclusions and point estimates remain unchanged (column 4 of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">D</ref>.8).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Political selection of exhibition venues:</head><p>Next, we address the concern that political factors (e.g., anticipated backlash) may have affected the selection of exhibition venues from the pool of all applicants. To address this concern, we revisited the archival correspondence between the exhibition organizers (HIS) and applicant counties. Based on the official correspondences, we identified a small number of cases (𝑁 = 8) where political factors may have played a role (e.g., where a local city council strongly opposed the exhibition). In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">D</ref>.8, we present the results when using a narrowed-down control group of applicant counties that excludes these eight localities. Our substantive conclusions and point estimates remain unchanged when using this alternative control group.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outliers:</head><p>We rule out concerns that our results are driven by individual treated locations through jackknife resampling. We estimate our main specification, excluding treated counties from the analysis one by one. Figure <ref type="figure">D</ref>.12 shows treatment effect estimates in each subsample.</p><p>We find that our main effect estimates remain stable and statistically significant across these 21 We use county centroids to approximate the distance to the closest exhibition venue.</p><p>tests.  Randomization inference: Finally, we conduct a randomization test. To do this, we use placebo variations of the treatment assignment mechanism and compare the resulting distribution of the test statistic to our main estimate. Specifically, we randomly reshuffle the treatment dates between treated counties. We present the resulting distribution of placebo effect estimates across 500 iterations in Figure D.14. We find that our main effect estimate is larger than any of the placebo estimates (𝑝 &lt; 0.01). We conclude that our main results are highly unlikely to be the result of random chance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Temporal heterogeneity:</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Mechanisms</head><p>In this section, we explore the mechanisms driving our results. To do this, we first examine treatment effect heterogeneity across birth cohorts. This allows us to examine empirical implications derived from our theoretical framework, in particular regarding the moderating role of family experiences of historical phases of violence.</p><p>Specifically, we expect heterogeneous treatment effects depending on respondents' personal and/or family experiences in the Wehrmacht and WWII. We test this implication of our argument by estimating treatment effects for cohorts that vary in terms of the shares of respondents (i) who themselves served in the Wehrmacht, (ii) whose fathers served in the Wehrmacht and/or (iii) who lost their fathers in the war. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_17">22</ref>The first cohort comprises all respondents born before 1928. As the vast majority of men born before 1928 were subject to the compulsory draft for the Wehrmacht (see Figure <ref type="figure">C</ref>.9 in the SI), a high share of (male) respondents in this birth cohort personally experienced WWII as Wehrmacht soldiers. Only a small share of respondents (i.e., only the very youngest) in this cohort had fathers who themselves fought and/or fell in the war. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_18">23</ref>The second cohort includes all respondents born between 1928 and 1945. The men in this cohort were too young to be drafted for the Wehrmacht. However, as Figure <ref type="figure">4b</ref> illustrates, this cohort was most likely to have (i) grown up with a father who fought in WWII or (ii)</p><p>suffered the loss of their father during WWII (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Franz, Hardt and Brähler (2007)</ref> and Section C.5 in the SI).</p><p>Finally, we also investigate treatment effects in four post-war cohorts. Respondents born between 1946 and 1961 neither fought in WWII themselves nor lost their fathers in the war.</p><p>However, a substantial share of these respondents' fathers did fight in WWII (see Figure <ref type="figure">4b</ref>).</p><p>Respondents in later birth cohorts are unlikely to share any of these specific family war experiences.</p><p>We present heterogeneous treatment effects across these cohorts in Figure <ref type="figure">4a</ref>. Panel (a)</p><p>shows average treatment effect estimates from staggered difference-in-differences specifications estimated within the cohort subsets of our data. The model specification is equivalent to our main results presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Panel (b)</ref> shows the link between (respondents')</p><p>birth years and the likelihood that their father served (gray line) and died (black line) on the battlefield (see SI Section C.5 for details).</p><p>The results presented in Figure <ref type="figure">4a</ref> have three important implications for our main argument. First, we find no evidence of linear age effects. The backlash against the SPD was not more or less pronounced among particularly old or young respondents. Instead, the backlash was concentrated in one specific cohort: respondents born between 1928 and 1945. Second, the figure shows that the cohort driving the backlash against the exhibition is the cohort with the highest proportion of individuals whose fathers served or died on the battlefield. Third, the null results for the preceding and succeeding cohorts suggest that neither respondents' own war experience nor the military service of their fathers alone determined Germans' response to the Wehrmacht exhibition.</p><p>Why did the 1928-1945 birth cohort react particularly strongly to challenges of the myth of the "clean" Wehrmacht? Previous research discussed in Section 3 highlights that family narratives can interact with collective memories-weakening or reinforcing their one-sided nature ("memory type") and their relevance to the individual ("memory salience"). (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Welzer 2007)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research on commemoration of the</head><p>In line with this research, previous biographical studies on WWII veterans specifically illustrate how their battlefield experiences significantly shaped the war narratives within their families. Many former soldiers struggled to communicate the atrocities they witnessed and the crimes they committed, not due to denial of their own actions but rather because they believed their families could not comprehend these experiences. Conversely, family members often refrained from inquiring about these types of experiences, fearing the possible confirmation of their husbands', sons', or fathers' involvement in wartime atrocities (Goltermann 2009). Consequently, when veterans did discuss the war, they typically focused on less distressing topics, such as detailed descriptions of war tactics, peaceful interactions with civilian populations, and the perceived superiority of the Wehrmacht <ref type="bibr">(Rosenthal 1991, p.36)</ref>. As a result, many family narratives emerged that emphasized the hardships soldiers endured, their resilience, and the injuries they sustained (Goltermann 2009).</p><p>Analyzing 30 biographies in East and West Germany, <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Seegers (2013)</ref> shows how families of fallen soldiers developed similar narratives about the war. Family stories idealized their loyalty, sense of duty, and bravery. Their roles in the Nazi party or on the battlefield were often downplayed. Moreover, many families constructed narratives of "conversion, " suggesting that the fallen soldiers had distanced themselves from the Nazi regime prior to their deaths as a result of their war experiences. Contrary to the families of returning veterans, accounts of the war and personal victimization played a prominent role in many families of fallen soldiers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Seegers (2013)</ref> shows how accounts of fathers killed in action circulated among families like an "imaginary family photo album"; many homes prominently displayed photographs of fallen soldiers in their Wehrmacht uniforms.</p><p>It seems plausible that such family narratives reinforced similar self-serving collective memories, explaining the strong backlash among members of age cohorts with high shares of respondents whose fathers served and/or were killed in WWII. These families developed particularly salient and one-sided narratives of the war, the role of the Wehrmacht and its soldiers. In light of the important roles of these narratives in family identities, family members reacted particularly strongly to the perceived challenges to these identities.</p><p>In fact, defending the perceived honor of fathers and family members was a common theme of the political backlash and demonstrations surrounding exhibition openings. Peter Gauweiler, the Munich CSU chairman and a state MP at the time, sent a four-page personal letter to 300,000 Munich households severely criticizing the exhibition in its opening weeks <ref type="bibr">(taz 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Pohl 2024)</ref>. The exhibition's insinuation that all Wehrmacht soldiers were guilty of war crimes-though its organizers explicitly did not claim this (Hamburger Institut für Sozialforschung 1997, 7)-was, in Gauweiler's words, a "slap in the face" of millions of German families who had lost sons, husbands, and fathers, as well as a "late, deliberate humiliation of countless men who served honorably" (Gauweiler 1997, 4). Similar accusations were levied against many of the opening speakers we interviewed (see SI Section F).</p><p>In order to investigate the plausibility of our explanation in more detail, we administered an online survey-targeting the hard-to-reach population of German respondents born before 1950, i.e., those cohorts that seem to be driving the backlash against the exhibition. In total, 1,294 respondents completed the survey (see additional information on the survey design in SI Section B.3; for summary statistics, see Table <ref type="table">C</ref>.7).</p><p>We use these original survey data to explore associations between the war experiences of respondents' families, the content of war-related family narratives, and their attitudes toward collective memories of the Wehrmacht and WWII. We provide an overview of the wording of the specific survey items that we used in B.3. Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> shows associations between respondents' fathers' experiences during WWII and items gauging the type (left-hand panel) and salience (right-hand panel) of family memories of the Wehrmacht and WWII.</p><p>The left-hand panel of Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> indicates that survey respondents whose fathers served or were killed in WWII tend to show stronger support for statements that cast the Wehrmacht in a favorable light along several measures: (1) an index assessing perceptions of the Wehrmacht's role (e.g., Other warring parties were just as guilty during the war as the Germans), (2) an index evaluating attitudes toward World War II and Wehrmacht commemoration (e.g., Too little attention is given to German victims of World War II ), (3) a survey item directly asking about the Wehrmacht's involvement in war crimes and the Holocaust, and (4) an index focused on the content of family narratives, particularly the extent to which discussions highlighted the selflessness and heroism of German soldiers. We note that while all partial correlations point in the same direction, only some reach conventional levels of statistical significance. Notably, we do not find significant differences between respondents whose fathers returned from the war and those whose fathers were killed. Moving from memory types to the salience of those memories, the right-hand panel of Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> shows that respondents reporting that their fathers served or fell in WWII (1) engaged more frequently in discussions about their family members' wartime experiences, (2) are more likely to attribute their perspectives on WWII to family influences, (3) are more convinced that WWII is integral to their family history, and (4) more strongly agree that WWII shaped their family's identity. Notably, response patterns differ based on the nature of family war experiences: respondents who lost their fathers in the war are significantly more likely than those whose fathers returned to emphasize the impact of WWII on their personal family history and identity.</p><p>Overall, the descriptive analysis of our original survey data supports our interpretation of the main results highlighted earlier: family war experiences exert long-term influences on narratives and memories of WWII and the Wehrmacht. Some of these effects appear to be more pronounced among respondents whose fathers were killed in action. These patterns correspond with the findings depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">4a</ref>: the backlash against the Wehrmacht ex-hibition was most pronounced in the birth cohort with a high proportion of children of both surviving veterans and fallen soldiers-while families of both of these groups seem more likely to have developed family narratives that clashed with the content of the Wehrmacht exhibition, this clash is likely to have been particularly threatening to the identity of the children of fallen soldiers.</p><p>In addition to probing the mechanisms driving our main results, this survey also allows us to assess to what extent our findings may be specific to (a) the Wehrmacht exhibition as a particular form of challenge to a self-serving memory as well as (b) to the SPD as the primary memory entrepreneur associated with this challenge.</p><p>To examine these potential scope conditions of our findings, our survey included a brief vignette that informs respondents of a controversy regarding the commemoration of the Wehrmacht within the contemporary German armed forces. In 2018, Ursula von der Leyen, the then-Federal Minister of Defense and a member of the CDU, revised the so-called "Tradition Decree, " which outlines the preservation of tradition within the German armed forces.</p><p>This amendment declared the Wehrmacht as a whole "not worthy of shaping tradition" (nicht traditionswürdig) because it "served the National Socialist regime of injustice and was culpably involved in its crimes" (Bundesministerium der Verteidigung 2018, 4).</p><p>If challenges to self-serving narratives provoke backlash against the respective mnemonic entrepreneurs, regardless of (a) the form of the challenge and (b) the general political orientation of the respective entrepreneur, we would expect this declaration to elicit negative reactions towards the Christian Democrats (CDU). We test this hypothesis in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.12 by regressing respondents' support for the statement, "If the CDU maintains its position on the Tradition Decree, that would be a reason for me to vote for another party" on their family war experiences. Consistent with our theoretical framework, there is stronger support for this statement among respondents whose fathers either served or were killed in World War II.</p><p>This finding supports our interpretation that our main results reflect a backlash against any challenges of self-serving narratives-independent of the form of the challenge or the political orientation of the challenger.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Long-term effects on collective memory</head><p>The Wehrmacht exhibition aimed to challenge and overturn the prevailing "clean Wehrmacht" narrative (see Section 4). Did it achieve this goal and shift collective memory?</p><p>Measuring the exhibition's ultimate impact on collective memory is difficult. Ideally, we would track changes in attitudes and beliefs regarding the Wehrmacht's involvement in WWII war crimes over time in a nationally representative sample. However, longitudinal data that would allow us to measure changes in these beliefs over time are not available in our context.</p><p>Instead, we use a proxy based on Google Ngram data for German-language books (see Section B.4 in the SI for details on data processing). Specifically, to measure whether the exhibition undermined the "myth of the clean Wehrmacht, " we measure over-time changes in the cooccurrence of the terms "Wehrmacht" and "Verbrechen" (crimes). The underlying assumption of this approach is that references to Wehrmacht war crimes in written texts proxy for changes in collective memory linking the Wehrmacht to these atrocities. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Share of Wehrmacht Ngrams referencing War Crimes</head><p>Note: The y-axis shows the yearly share of Google Ngrams referencing war crimes in connection with the Wehrmacht. We calculate this by subsetting to Ngrams mentioning the Wehrmacht and computing the share that also references "crimes" ("Verbrechen"). Ngrams mentioning "exhibition" (e.g., "Ausstellung") are excluded.</p><p>The light grey area marks the exhibition period <ref type="bibr">(1995--1999)</ref>, and the blue and red horizontal lines indicate the average shares before and after the exhibition. See SI Section B.4 for additional details on data processing.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> shows the results. Prior to the Wehrmacht exhibition, the "clean Wehrmacht" narrative prevailed: we find virtually no linkage between the Wehrmacht and (war) crimes before 1995 (red line) in written texts. 24 This changes discontinuously with the exhibition's opening. We observe a sharp, sustained increase in the discussion of war crimes attributed to the Wehrmacht after 1995. In Figure <ref type="figure">E</ref>.18 in the SI, we demonstrate null results for a set of Wehrmacht-related placebo terms, suggesting that the shift we observe is driven by an increased discussion of war crimes specifically rather than a general shift in the discourse surrounding the Wehrmacht. These findings suggest that, although the political backlash against the exhibition was short-lived, its impact on collective memory was profound. The exhibition rendered the "clean Wehrmacht" narrative untenable, an insight also relayed to us in many of our interviews (see SI Section F). It fostered a lasting shift toward a more nuanced view of the Wehrmacht's-and thus German society's-involvement in WWII atrocities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">Discussion</head><p>Self-serving narratives on past ingroup atrocities play an important role in the collective memories of many societies across the world-narratives related to colonization, slavery, repressive autocratic rule, or other forms of mass violence. Focusing on one of the most intense "memory conflicts" in Germany's postwar history, we demonstrate that challenges of such narratives can trigger a backlash against political actors challenging the self-serving memory.</p><p>Our analyses allow us to specify this backlash in two important ways. First, we find evidence of strong defensive reactions predominantly among segments of the population with personal connections to ingroup perpetrator groups-indicating that backlash did not result from threats to collective (national) identities but rather from challenges to more narrow family narratives. Second, while the magnitude of the backlash is substantial, it is also localized and short-lived. We find a drop in public support for the "political face" of the challenge only in areas close to locations where evidence against the narrative was on display and only while 24 The Wehrmacht exhibition is one link in a long process of historical reckoning in Germany. During the 1980s and 1990s, there was a broader engagement with the role of the German population in the Holocaust, exemplified by the Historikerstreit and the publication of <ref type="bibr">Goldhagen (1996)</ref>. This is reflected in the rise of Ngrams referencing the Holocaust starting in 1980 (see Figure E.17). However, this trend does not align temporally with the opening of the Wehrmacht exhibition. Moreover, earlier milestones of historical reckoning focused on the Holocaust more generally rather than specifically addressing the involvement of ordinary German soldiers, as evidenced by the pre-1995 trends shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>.</p><p>the evidence was on display. Furthermore, SPD representatives maintained or even increased their support and presence at openings during the second iteration of the Wehrmacht exhibition,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_19">25</ref> suggesting that the original backlash was not sustained enough to reconsider this support.</p><p>We do not know if the observable backlash ended because public debates refocused on other issues or because public opinion converged on a new memory consensus. However, our analyses clearly show that memory entrepreneurs face only short-lived political costs among certain segments of society when trying to reshape even deeply entrenched, self-serving collective memories. Indeed, our findings indicate that while memory entrepreneurs may only incur short-term political costs, their actions can have a lasting impact on public discourse that persists long after the initial controversy subsides. The Wehrmacht exhibition exemplifies this dynamic: a short-lived backlash ultimately gave way to a profound transformation in how society interprets its past.</p><p>Our single-case study does not allow us to empirically assess the generalizability of these findings to other countries and historical cases. However, we can identify relevant scope conditions based on (social) identity theory, on which we base our theoretical argument. First, we expect backlash reactions only in response to challenges of a certain type of collective memory: entrenched narratives about a large group of perpetrators involved in mass violence committed in the ingroup's recent history-only for this kind of narrative will challenges constitute significant, immediate identity threats for a large share of the population, increasing the likelihood of defensive reactions.</p><p>The second condition refers to the type of challenge. The Wehrmacht exhibition was based on a large body of historical, photographic evidence on crimes committed by Wehrmacht soldiers. This kind of evidence-based challenge leaves little room for alternative (non-defensive) socio-psychological reactions to identity threats, such as downplaying the gravity of the ingroup wrongdoing or reinterpreting perpetrators and victims.</p><p>The third condition refers to the type of memory entrepreneur challenging the collective narrative. Defensive reactions will most likely result in political backlash if the challenge can be associated with one specific actor-for example, a specific political party. Conversely, diverse coalitions of memory entrepreneurs will make it more difficult to blame challenges on the vested interests or specific political ideology of any particular actor.</p><p>Thus, we believe that our findings on the case of the 1995-1999 Wehrmacht exhibition in Germany can provide important lessons for memory politics in countries such as Spain, France, Italy, the UK, and Turkey. In present-day Germany, the previously widespread "myth of the clean Wehrmacht" is no longer part of mainstream collective memories of WWII. The Wehrmacht exhibition triggered the process that led to the narrative's demise, despite presenting a direct challenge to the identities of many millions of German families. The political costs that supporters of the exhibition faced were substantial but short-lived. Thus, our findings indicate that memory entrepreneurs' concerns over the political costs of challenges to self-serving narratives may often be overstated. Potential memory entrepreneurs' hesitation may constitute a greater obstacle to re-interpretations of collective narratives than the actual backlash against such challenges does. URL: https://www.bpb.de/themen/erinnerung/geschichte-und-erinnerung/39814/geschichteder-erinnerungskultur-in-der-ddr-und-brd/  <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">A</ref>.1 are phrased so as to exclude coverage of the kidnapping that also mentioned the exhibition in passing. 1 9 9 5 -0 7 1 9 9 6 -0 1 1 9 9 6 -0 7 1 9 9 7 -0 1 1 9 9 7 -0 7 1 9 9 8 -0 1 1 9 9 8 -0 7 1 9 9 9 -0 1 1 9 9 9 -0 7 2 0 0 0 -0 1 2 0 0 0 -0 7 2 0 0 1 -0 1 2 0 0 1 -0 7 2 0 0 2 -0 1 2 0 0 2 -0 7 2 0 0 3 -0 1 2 0 0 3 -0 7 2 0 0 4 -0 1 2 0 0 4 -0 7</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Coverage of the exhibition in national and local news</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Month Number of newspaper articles</head><p>Note: This figure shows the monthly number of articles in German media discussing the Wehrmacht exhibition. The two dotted vertical lines represent the dates of the exhibition opening in Munich (24 February 1997) and the bombing of the exhibition in Saarbrücken (9 March 1999). Newspaper data is taken from the Genios database (http://www.genios.de). We identify articles that contain the terms 'wehrmachtsausstellung', 'reemtsma' + 'wehrmacht', 'hannes heer' + 'wehrmacht', or 'die verbrechen der wehrmacht' + 'ausstellung'. See Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">A</ref>.1 for the number of articles by news outlet. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B Data collection and processing B.1 Forsa survey data</head><p>The 'Forsa Bus' survey asks around 500 respondents per weekday (as a repeated cross-section) about their electoral preferences and socio-demographic attributes. The survey is based on computer-assisted phone interviews and is representative of the German voting-age population. For our main analysis, we merge the annual datasets from 1994 to 2000 into a single data set <ref type="bibr">(Forsa 2013a</ref><ref type="bibr">(Forsa , 1998a</ref><ref type="bibr">(Forsa , 2013b</ref><ref type="bibr">(Forsa , 1998b</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(Forsa , 1999</ref><ref type="bibr">(Forsa , 2013c</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Forsa , 2001))</ref>. We check all variables for changes in their coding between years and harmonize variables where needed.</p><p>Using the county key contained in the survey, we are able to determine the county of a respondent's place of residence at the time of the survey. We are not able to map the place of residence of approx. 9% of respondents to a contemporary county due to administrative changes in the 1990s, mostly in areas of the former GDR. However, this has little impact on our analysis as the Wehrmacht exhibition was predominantly shown in West Germany (recall Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> in the main text). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.2 Letters to the editor</head><p>We were granted access to a large systematic collection of letters to the editor concerning the exhibition, written and published between 1995 and 2000 in Germany and Austria and commissioned by the HIS at the time. The collection covers the entire span of the exhibition from March 1995 to October 1999, as well as another year through December 2000. The collection was compiled by two firms specializing in media monitoring, including collecting and labeling physical press clippings. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_20">26</ref> It is held at the HIS archive in Hamburg.</p><p>The collection encompasses 23 binders of clippings <ref type="bibr">(Figure B.2)</ref>. Typically, each press clipping was contained in the collection at least twice: once as an original cut from the newspaper and pasted on a sheet of paper with standardized information such as the date and newspaper, once as a photocopy of this sheet, and sometimes as further photocopies.   Our unit of analysis is the individual letter to the editor. Many of these press clippings contain multiple letters compiled by the newspaper into a single 'letters to the editor' page. We ultimately hand-coded a random sample of 1,247 letters that were directly related to the Wehrmacht exhibition, which we estimate to cover about 20-30% of the entire collection.</p><p>As these are published letters to the editor, there are likely several selection mechanisms at play. On the one hand, newspaper editors assumedly screened out views that were considered extremely right-wing at the time. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_21">27</ref> On the other hand, letters were likely also selected for particularly interesting content and viewpoints, such as first-hand experience as a Wehrmacht soldier. Finally, because the exhibition directly covered a formative phase of their lives, Wehrmacht veterans were certainly more likely to write in than most other Germans in the first place. The strong over-representation of self-identified Wehrmacht veterans among the letter-writers-18% of letters vs. perhaps 3% of the German population at the time-suggests that these mechanisms were indeed at play.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sampling procedure:</head><p>We generated a series of random numbers to be used to count off and select letters in the 23 binders, the largest of which contained about 300 different letters. The first round of coding was completed in eight working days (05-14 February 2024). As we still had two remaining working days in the archive (15 and 16 February), we generated another 21 random numbers between 1 and 300 which had not previously been used and appended these to the coding sheets.</p><p>Coding procedure and descriptives: We coded letters for simple demographic characteristics (gender, age if given), newspaper details (publication, location), sentiment towards the exhibition (negative, positive, or neutral), and the stated arguments for or against the exhibition. Figure <ref type="figure">C</ref>.6 shows that the majority of these letters to the editor (67%) voiced criticism of the exhibition, while about three in ten supported it (29%). 86% of letter-writers were male, 11% were female, and 4% could not be determined (e.g., anonymous letters). 18% of authors claimed to have served in the Wehrmacht, and another 5% said that close family members did (while they themselves did not), for a total of 23% of letters explicitly mentioning family ties to the Wehrmacht.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.3 Contemporary survey of Germans born before 1950 B.3.1 Design and implementation</head><p>In order to probe the mechanisms driving our main results, we implemented an online survey targeting German citizens above the age of 75 (i.e., born before 1950). We defined a target sample size of 1,300 respondents for the survey. As our main analyses revealed that treatment effects seemed to be driven by men born before the end of the war, we set a minimum quota of 400 male respondents aged 79 or above (i.e., born before 1946). The data collection was implemented by the survey company Bilendi/Respondi. Fieldwork began on November 11, 2024, and was completed on November 23. In total, 1,294 eligible respondents completed the survey, including 558 respondents born before the end of WWII (412 male, 146 female). Table <ref type="table">C</ref>.7 provides summary statistics for the final sample.</p><p>The survey instrument featured four main sections. The first section focused on basic demographic information (e.g., home state, education). The second section aimed to collect information on respondents' parents, e.g., the war experiences of their fathers. The two remaining sections included questions on (1) respondents' family memories and personal attitudes on WWII and the Wehrmacht, as well as on (2) respondents' awareness and perceptions of the Wehrmacht exhibition. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">B</ref>.4 provides an overview of the survey items used in the analyses presented in the main paper. The survey design and content received ethics clearance from the institutional review board of the home institution of one of the authors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table B.4: Overview of survey variables</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Variable Item(s)</head><p>To what extent do you agree with the following statements? WW2 Memory (Index) "I doubt that everything reported about the extent of the Wehrmacht's crimes is true. "</p><p>"Too little attention is given to German victims during the Second World War. "</p><p>"When remembering the Second World War, more emphasis should be placed on the courage and sacrifices of German soldiers. "</p><p>"No one paid a higher price for the war than the children who lost their fathers in the war. "</p><p>If your family talked about the wartime experiences of its members, how often were the following topics emphasized?</p><p>Family Narratives on WW2 (Index) "The suffering and sacrifices of German soldiers during the war. "</p><p>"The selflessness of German soldiers. "</p><p>"The actions German soldiers had to commit. "</p><p>"The heroism of German soldiers. "</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(Continued on next page) Table B.4 (continued) Variable Item(s)</formula><p>Which of the following statements about the Second World War do you agree with? WW2 Attitudes (Index) "Other warring parties were as guilty during the war as the Germans. "</p><p>"The German soldiers at the time fought honorably. "</p><p>"Although German soldiers were involved in mass crimes, they were simply following orders. "</p><p>To what extent do you agree with the following statement?</p><p>Wehrmacht crimes "The Wehrmacht was actively involved in numerous war crimes, including the Holocaust. "</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Family war memory intensity</head><p>How often was the wartime experience of your family members discussed in your family?</p><p>To what extent do you agree with the following statements? WW2 part of family history "The Second World War is part of my family history. "</p><p>WW2 shaped family identity "The Second World War has shaped my family identity. "</p><p>Note: The table lists the variables used in the analysis of our survey data. Index variables are constructed by averaging the corresponding items and standardizing the resulting measure.</p><p>To assess respondents' perceptions of their own father, our survey included an open-ended question asking participants to list characteristics (adjectives) that best described what kind of person their father was. We rely on ChatGPT 4o-mini to systematically code these responses.</p><p>Using the prompt below, we ask the model to identify whether individual descriptions mirror classical militaristic values associated with the German Wehrmacht:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I have a dataset of free-text survey responses to the question: 'Nennen Sie bitte drei Merkmale (Adjektive), die Ihrer Ansicht nach beschreiben, was für ein Mensch Ihr Vater war. '</head><p>The responses contain adjectives and short descriptions. I want you to evaluate each response to determine whether it reflects classical militaristic values associated with the German Wehrmacht. These values include: Discipline, Duty, Loyalty, Obedience, Bravery, Leadership, Order, Resilience, Patriotism.</p><p>If the response reflects these values, respond with '1'. Respond with '0' in all other cases. Ignore any neutral or ambiguous phrases that do not clearly align with these traits.</p><p>For example: Input: 'musikalisch' Output: '0' Input: 'kameradschaftlich' Output: '1'</p><p>Input: 'Preußische Tugenden' Output: <ref type="bibr">'1'</ref> Use this structure for all responses and respond only with '1' or '0'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.4 Google Ngrams</head><p>We use data from Google Books Ngram (2012) to trace the effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on collective memory. The data is based on a cleaned subset of the Google Books corpus, covering about eight million digitized books <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(Lin et al. 2012)</ref>. The term "n-gram" refers to a contiguous sequence of n items from a given text, where 𝑛 can be any number. "Technology has changed the world" is a 5-gram, for example.</p><p>For our analysis, we only use the corpus of German-language books and retrieve all 5grams that contain the word "Wehrmacht". To ensure that our analysis reflects general discourse rather than discussions of the Wehrmacht exhibition itself, we excluded n-grams that directly relate to the exhibition. Specifically, we removed any n-grams containing one of the following keywords: "Verbrechen der Wehrmacht 1941", "Verbrechen der Wehrmacht 1941-1944", "Ausstellung Verbrechen der Wehrmacht", "Ausstellung über Verbrechen der Wehrmacht", "Verbrechen der Wehrmacht 1941 bis", "Verbrechen der Wehrmacht 1 94", "Wehrmachtsausstellung", and "Ausstellung". We identified these keywords manually by examining all unique N-grams in our data.</p><p>Next, we identified n-grams containing the term "Verbrechen" (meaning "crime" or "crimes") to determine how frequently the Wehrmacht was connected to war crimes in published books. By calculating the annual share of these references, we assessed the proportion of Wehrmacht mentions that also included war crime associations each year. We compare these rates before and after the exhibition to evaluate its impact on collective memory and the portrayal of the Wehrmacht in German-language books (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>).     </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.2 Letters to the editor</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.3 Contemporary survey of Germans born before 1950</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Note:</head><p>The figure visualizes level differences between treated (𝑁 = 27) and control counties across multiple pretreatment covariates. We regress each covariate on a dummy variable indicating treated counties that received the exhibition. We compare treated counties to three groups of comparison: (1) all never-treated counties that did not receive the exhibition (𝑁 = 366), (2) never-treated counties that applied to receive the exhibition but did not receive it (𝑁 = 70), and (3) applicant city counties (Stadtkreise) that applied to receive the exhibition but did not receive it (𝑁 = 34). The group of never-treated counties excludes counties that received the Wehrmacht exhibition in its 2 nd phase (see Section 4). Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.5 Exposure to WWII by birth cohort</head><p>In Figure <ref type="figure">4a</ref>, we use cutoffs to examine heterogeneity between citizens who personally experienced WWII and their children who do not have personal frontline experiences. In this section, we provide additional background information on how cohort birth years correspond to personal and family experiences based on 1970 census data (5% sample; N ≈ 3 million). These data are available from the Forschungsdatenzentren der amtlichen Statistik ('FDZ').</p><p>First, we identify the male birth cohorts most likely to have served in WWII by examining the male-to-female population ratio by birth year (see Figure C.9). Men are notably underrepresented among the cohorts born between 1900 and 1927, consistent with historical data on the WWII draft <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Wurdack 2002)</ref>. Starting with the 1928 birth cohort, the male-to-female ratio spikes and approaches parity. Although some men born in 1928 died in combat, battlefield losses affected only a small share of this cohort. For our analysis, we therefore consider the 1900-1927 cohorts as drafted.  Next, we link the birth year of children to their father's experiences during WWII. This is more challenging, as there is no single data source that allows us to simultaneously observe (1) the father's year of birth, (2) the children's year of birth, and (3) the father's war experiences. To circumvent this issue, we combine the census data with information on battlefield deaths by birth cohort compiled by <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Wurdack 2002)</ref>.</p><p>To estimate the probability that a child's father died during WWII based on the child's year of birth, we first define the following random variables:</p><p>• Let 𝑌 𝐶 denote the child's year of birth.</p><p>• Let 𝑌 𝐹 denote the father's year of birth.</p><p>• Let 𝑌 𝑀 denote the mother's year of • Let 𝐷 𝐹 be an indicator variable where 𝐷 𝐹 = 1 if the father died during WWII, and 𝐷 𝐹 = 0 otherwise.</p><p>• Let 𝑆 𝐹 be an indicator variable where 𝑆 𝐹 = 1 if the father served in WWII, and 𝑆 𝐹 = 0 otherwise.</p><p>Using these definitions and the law of total probability, we can express the probability that a child's father died in the war as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">𝑃 (𝐷 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ) = ∑ 𝑦 𝑓 𝑃 (𝐷 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 , 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ) 𝑃 (𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 | 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ). = ∑ 𝑦 𝑓 𝑃 (𝐷 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 ) 𝑃 (𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 | 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ).</formula><p>assuming that battlefield death of fathers (𝐷 𝐹 ) is independent of children's year of birth (𝑌 𝐶 ), given father's year of birth (𝑌 𝐹 ). We note that this assumption only holds for children born before 1945 (more on this below). Now all that is left for us to do is to estimate 𝑃 (𝐷 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 ) and 𝑃 (𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 | 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ).</p><p>• 𝑃 (𝐷 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 ) represents the probability that a father born in year 𝑦 𝑓 died during WWII. This probability is obtained from battlefield death rates compiled by <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Wurdack (2002)</ref>. To ensure consistency with our estimates for 𝑃 (𝑆 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 ) (see below), we set 𝑃 (𝐷 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 ) = 0 for the birth cohorts 1928/29 and those born before 1897. This discards a very small share of deaths (0 -2%) in these cohorts.</p><p>• The term 𝑃 (𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 | 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ) is the conditional probability of the father's birth year given the child's birth year. We estimate this distribution using data from the 1970 census, assuming that fathers are, on average, four years older than mothers (i.e., 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑌 𝑀 + 4). We have to make this assumption because we can only link children to mothers, but not fathers. We base this assumption on the facts that (1), on average, men born between 1900 and 1927 (i.e., drafted cohorts) married women 3.76 years younger than themselves, and (2) more than 90% of children were born in wedlock during the post-war period <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(Statista 2024)</ref>. To estimate the probability that a child's father served in WWII, we assume that all men born between 1910 and 1927 were drafted <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Wurdack 2002)</ref>. For men born between 1897 and 1909, we estimate p1942 based on the number of drafted men as of 1942 <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(Wurdack 2002)</ref>. Therefore, we define:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">𝑃 (𝑆 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 ) =                   0, if 𝑦 𝑓 ≤ 1886, p1942 , if 1897 ≤ 𝑦 𝑓 ≤ 1909, 1, if 1910 ≤ 𝑦 𝑓 ≤ 1927, 0, if 𝑦 𝑓 ≥ 1928.</formula><p>Using this, the probability that a child's father served is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">𝑃 (𝑆 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ) = ∑ 𝑦 𝑓 𝑃 (𝑆 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 ) 𝑃 (𝑌 𝐹 = 𝑦 𝑓 | 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ).</formula><p>The results from the estimation are presented in Figure <ref type="figure">4b</ref>. Our estimates are consistent with a 2003 survey, which reported that 19% of individuals born before 1947 experienced the loss of their father <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Franz, Hardt and Brähler 2007)</ref>.   Note: This figure shows estimates for the effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on the intention to vote for the SPD in federal-level elections based on specifications using two alternative control groups. Column 1 shows an estimate from a model using only the set of applicant counties that rejected hosting the exhibition for apolitical reasons. Column 2 is an estimate from a specification using never-treated counties, excluding respondents from counties within 60 kilometers of an exhibition location (see Figure E.15).  We generate permutations by randomly reshuffling treatment dates within the set of counties that at some point received the exhibition. All estimates are obtained through our main specification using applicant counties as the control group. The red vertical line indicates the point estimates from our main results.   Min. distance between never-treated county and closest exhibition venue (km) Effect of WME on volume of letters to the editor (RD estimate)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C.6 Nazi indoctrination by birth cohort</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.2 Alternative control groups</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.4 Effect heterogeneity before and after the Munich exhibition</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.5 Effects of the Wehrmacht exhibition on sample composition</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E Additional results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.1 Effects of the Wehrmacht exhibition on letters to the editor</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.2 Estimating the geographic scope of potential spillover effects</head><p>Note:</p><p>The figure shows the results from a series of regression discontinuity analyses that estimate the effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on the daily rate of exhibition-related letters to the editor printed in local newspapers. The analysis is analogous to the specification presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.10 (column 1) with one crucial difference: this analysis focuses on the group of never-treated counties that did not host the exhibition. For each untreated county, we code a 'placebo exhibition opening date, ' which is defined as the date at which the exhibition opened in the most geographically proximate treated county. We present results as we vary a minimum distance caliper between 0 and 100 km. For a distance caliper of 0km, we do not restrict the sample of treated counties to code the placebo exhibition opening date. For a distance caliper of 50km, for example, we code the placebo exhibition opening date based on the closest treated county that is at least 50 km away from a given never-treated county.</p><p>All distance calculations are based on pairwise distances between county centroids. The analysis is based on a randomly drawn sample of letters to the editor, which we retrieved from the archives of the Hamburg Institute for Social Research (see Section B.2 in the SI for details). Error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.3 Effects of the Wehrmacht exhibition on other parties</head><p>Figure E.16 presents the ATT estimates for exhibition onset across all political parties covered by the Forsa dataset on voting intentions. The estimated -7.97 percentage-point effect on SPD support is the main result discussed in the text. This negative effect appears to be driven by voters temporarily shifting to the CDU/CSU (+2.98 percentage points, p &lt; 0.1) and voters moving to the undecided/does not intend to vote category (+4.37 percentage points, p &lt; 0.01).</p><p>We also detect a slight negative effect for the Republikaner party (-0.39 percentage points, p &lt; 0.05), a small right-wing party that enjoyed several local, regional, and European successes in the 1980s and 1990s. We presume that this decline stems from some members of the Republikaner publicly aligning themselves with Neo-Nazi protesters at exhibition openings, along with the far-right National Democratic Party of Germany (NPD). These protests garnered significant media attention, perhaps leading less hardline supporters to question their party preference and turn their backs on the party.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.4 Long-term electoral effects of the Wehrmacht exhibition</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.6 References to the Holocaust in Google Ngrams</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Count of Holocaust Ngrams</head><p>Note: The y-axis shows the yearly count of Google Ngrams referencing the Holocaust. The light grey area marks the exhibition period <ref type="bibr">(1995)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1996)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1997)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1998)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1999)</ref>. See SI Section B.4 for additional details on data processing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.7 Google Ngrams Placebo test</head><p>To validate that the increase in references linking the Wehrmacht to war crimes was due to the Wehrmacht exhibition and not a result of idiosyncratic trends, we also conduct a placebo test. Specifically, we repeat our analysis using a set of neutral terms commonly associated with the Wehrmacht: "waffen" (weapons), "eingezogen" (drafted), "Kapitulation" (capitulation), "deutsche/n" (German), and "Soldaten" (soldiers). We identified all 5-grams containing the term "Wehrmacht" along with any of these placebo terms while again excluding n-grams that directly relate to the exhibition itself (see above). As shown in Figure E.18, the share of these neutral terms remains stable over time, showing no substantial change after the exhibition. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Share of Wehrmacht Ngrams referencing placebo terms</head><p>Note: The y-axis shows the yearly share of Google Ngrams referencing selected placebo terms associated with the Wehrmacht. This share is calculated by filtering for Ngrams mentioning the Wehrmacht and identifying those that also include placebo terms ("waffen", "eingezogen", "kapitulation", "deutsche", "deutschen", "soldaten"). Analogous to Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>, Ngrams referencing the exhibition (e.g., "Ausstellung") are excluded. The light grey area represents the exhibition period <ref type="bibr">(1995)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1996)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1997)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1998)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1999)</ref>, and the blue and red horizontal lines indicate the average shares before and after the exhibition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E.8 Gendered effects of the Wehrmacht exhibition</head><p>In addition to the analyses of treatment effect heterogeneity across birth cohorts, we also examine variation between men and women. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.13 shows average treatment effect estimates from staggered difference-in-differences specifications estimated in male and female subsets of our data. The model specification is equivalent to our main results presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. While we find significant treatment effects in both subsets for most specifications of the control group, effect sizes are close to twice as large for men than for women. This pattern is consistent with the results of descriptive analyses of our letters to the editor sample (see Section B.2). These analyses likewise indicate higher levels of politicization and backlash against the exhibition among men. Men submit the vast majority of letters to the editor concerning the exhibition (84.5%). Additionally, there is a higher proportion of negative letters opposing the exhibition among men compared to women. We can only speculate about the reasons for these gendered effects. One potential explanation that would be in line with the socio-psychological foundations of our main argument is related to the specific character of the self-serving myths of German perpetrators in WWII. Cynthia Enloe has argued that "nationalism has typically sprung from masculinized memory, masculinized humiliation, and masculinized hope. " <ref type="bibr">(Enloe 2014, 45)</ref>. Similarly, positive narratives of war and violence tend to emphasize masculine cultural themes, such as honor, patriotism, bravery, and duty <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Nagel 2019)</ref>. This gendered character of self-serving memories of WWII soldiers may explain why (1) the respective narratives played a less prominent role in "mnemonic socializers" interactions with female family members and why (2) these memories played a less prominent role in women's self-identification. As a consequence, challenges of these norms would have constituted a less pronounced identity threat for women, inducing less defensive reactions.</p><p>To further investigate the gendered effects of the Wehrmacht exhibition, we utilize data from our original survey. Specifically, we examine two types of survey items to determine (1) whether female respondents encountered family narratives about the war less frequently and/or (2) whether the idealized portrayal of their fathers as "ideal" soldiers (i.e., brave and heroic) holds less significance for them compared to male respondents.</p><p>In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.8, we first analyze the correlation between respondents' gender and their answers to a survey item that asked if their fathers received decorations during the war. Our findings indicate that male respondents are significantly more likely to report that their fathers were awarded medals for their wartime behavior. Given that the gender of the soldiers' children is independent of their fathers' actions during the war, we interpret this result as evidence that male respondents were either more exposed to this information or that it holds greater relevance for them, thereby increasing their likelihood of remembering it.</p><p>Additionally, we asked respondents to identify three attributes that they believe best characterize their fathers through open-ended responses. We then compared these characteristics to elements of the ideal German Wehrmacht soldier as depicted in public discourse-e.g., "brave, " "loyal, " and "disciplined. " For each respondent, we counted the number of adjectives reflecting these Wehrmacht ideals. In the second column of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">E</ref>.8, we compare the frequency of these attributes across genders. Again, we find support for the notion that the portrayal of fathers as ideal Wehrmacht soldiers is more pronounced in the socialization of male respondents compared to their female counterparts. Notes: The table presents the results from OLS regressions of two different variables on an indicator for male respondents: (1) a binary variable indicating whether respondents reported that their father was decorated during WWII, and (2) the number of adjectives used to describe their father, reflecting Wehrmacht ideals. Both models control for year of birth, education, religious affiliation, and state. Heteroskedasticity-robust standard errors are reported in parentheses. Signif. Codes: ***: 0.01, **: 0.05, *: 0.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F Qualitative evidence: interviews with opening speakers and contemporaries</head><p>To assess the plausibility of some of our assumptions, we conducted semi-structured qualitative interviews with public figures who spoke at the Wehrmacht exhibition throughout Germany (as well as one speechwriter), drawn from the HIS archival record of opening ceremonies. We asked about the exhibition organization, the positions of political parties, the degree to which the SPD was identified as the main party proponent of the exhibition, local and national debates surrounding the exhibition, and the nature of the societal and electoral backlash against the exhibition.</p><p>We split these interviews into three parts: First, we asked open-ended questions about how they were contacted about speaking, why they decided to do so, and their recollections about public debates at the time and the opening itself. Second, we asked about the party politics surrounding the exhibition, both regarding the specific opening in question and at the national level from 1995 to 1999. We then shared our finding that about three-quarters of openings had speakers who were SPD officials (recall Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> in the main text), while all other parties were far less represented. We then asked the interviewees why this might have been the case and whether they had any memories of how this was seen by the public. Third and finally, we summarized some of our key results, including the -8 percentage point loss for the SPD on average and the 1928-1945 birth cohort driving this effect. We then asked our interview partners for their thoughts and reactions to this finding. We saved this third step for last so as not to prime the interviewees.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">F</ref>.15 lists our interview partners, which openings they spoke at, and contains short biographies and how they were billed at the respective opening ceremony. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Partisanship and the exhibition</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Wehrmacht exhibition sites, 1995-1999</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>provide evidence in support of this assumption in Figure D.11 in the SI. Before the opening of the exhibition in a given location, treated and control counties follow parallel trajectories in their SPD support.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Politicization of the Wehrmacht exhibition</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Effects of the exhibition on sample composition: Next, we address the concern that the exhibition could have differentially affected the survey response rate of different groups of voters. To assess if the exhibition had any effect on the composition of the Forsa survey sample in treated locations, we estimate our main specification using several socio-economic characteristics as placebo outcome variables (seeFigure D.13). We find no evidence that the exhibition affected the composition of survey respondents in terms of gender, age, education, or household size. This reassures us that our results are not driven by respondents systematically opting in or out of the survey in response to the exhibition.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 4: Exploring the mechanisms (a) Treatment effect heterogeneity by birth cohort</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 5: Family experiences and collective memory</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: References to Wehrmacht War Crimes in German-Language Books</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure A. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure A.1 and TableA.1 describe coverage of the exhibition in national and regional newspapers from 1995 to 2004. TableA.1 shows two clear peaks in media attention: the February 1997 exhibition opening in Munich and the March 1999 bombing in Saarbrücken. TableA.2 lists all eight instances of the exhibition being featured in the eight o'clock Tagesschau-by far Germany's most-watched news program-from 1995-1999.Jan Philipp Reemtsma, the wealthy director and patron of the HIS, initiator of the exhibition, and a well-known public figure in his own right, was kidnapped and held for ransom from 25 March to 26 April 1996. This kidnapping received significant media attention but was not related to the exhibition and had purely financial motives. The search queries shown in Figure A.1 and TableA.1 are phrased so as to exclude coverage of the kidnapping that also mentioned the exhibition in passing.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure A.1: Wehrmacht exhibition news coverage</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure B.3 shows the headers of the press clippings, as compiled by the media agency covering the German press.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure B. 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure B.2: The archival collection of letters to the editor.</figDesc><graphic coords="54,72.00,303.71,451.28,174.27" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure B. 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure B.3: Header for German press clippings as compiled by the media agency.</figDesc><graphic coords="54,72.00,524.30,451.28,205.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure C.4: Sample size per exhibition county</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure C.5: Sample size per cohort</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure C.6: Letters to the editor by sentiment</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure C.7: Stated reasons for negative sentiment</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>28   </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure C. 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure C.9: Male to female gender ratio by birth year</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Finally,</head><label></label><figDesc>𝑃 (𝐷 𝐹 = 1 | 𝑌 𝐶 = 𝑦 𝑐 ) = 0 by definition if 𝑦 𝑐 ≥ 1946; fathers of children born after 1946 must have survived the war.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure C. 10</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure C.10 illustrates the number of years German youths were legally required to be members of the Hitler Youth (Hitlerjugend). The Hitler Youth, established by the Nazi Party, aimed to indoctrinate German children and adolescents with Nazi ideology, focusing on loyalty to Adolf Hitler, racial purity, and militarism. In March 1939, membership became mandatory for all youths aged 10 to 18, covering four sub-organizations for boys and girls aged 10-14 and 14-18 years. The cohorts born between 1927 and 1929 experienced the highest exposure to this indoctrination, spending at least six years in the Nazi Youth organization.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure C.10: Mandatory Hitler Youth membership by birth cohort</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure D.13: Effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on sample composition</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Figure E. 15</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Figure E.15 examines the geographic scope for potential spillover in the effect of exhibition onset. It does so by estimating the effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on the daily rate of exhibition-related letters to the editor printed in local newspapers at different distances between never-treated counties and the geographically closest exhibition venue. Details are provided in the Figure caption.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure E.15: Estimating the geographic scope of potential spillover effects</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>Figure E. 16 :</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Figure E.16: Effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on support for other parties</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure E.17: References to the Holocaust in German-language books</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_27"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure E.18: Ngram placebo test</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on issue salience The table shows the effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on the salience of four different political issues. We report estimates for the first month after the exhibition's opening. Never-treated counties that applied for the exhibition constitute the control group. Standard errors are clustered at the county level. Signif.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">DV: Issue mentioned (0/1)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Bundeswehr Migration Right-wing extremism Int. wars / peace</cell></row><row><cell>ATT</cell><cell>0.019**</cell><cell>0.013</cell><cell>-0.014</cell><cell>-0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.009)</cell><cell>(0.036)</cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell>(0.003)</cell></row><row><cell>N</cell><cell>206,802</cell><cell>206,802</cell><cell>206,802</cell><cell>206,802</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: Codes: ***: 0.01, **: 0.05, *: 0.1.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on SPD support The table shows the effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on SPD support in federal-level elections. We report estimates for the first month after the exhibition's opening. Standard errors are clustered at the county level. Signif. Codes: ***: 0.01, **: 0.05, *: 0.1.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">DV: SPD voting intention</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell></row><row><cell>ATT</cell><cell>-0.08***</cell><cell>-0.087***</cell><cell>-0.072***</cell><cell>-0.073***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell>(0.021)</cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.024)</cell></row><row><cell>N</cell><cell>323,680</cell><cell>213,001</cell><cell>837,059</cell><cell>154,735</cell></row><row><cell>Control group</cell><cell>Never-treated applicant counties</cell><cell>Never-treated applicant city counties</cell><cell>All never-treated counties</cell><cell>Not-yet-treated counties</cell></row></table><note><p>Note:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>In TableD.9, we examine whether the local effects of exhibition exposure are moderated by the nationwide discourse surrounding the exhibition. Specifically, we test for heterogeneity before and after the opening of the exhibition in Munich's city hall in February 1997. The Munich opening was particularly controversial, increasing the national-level salience of the exhibition (see Sections 4.2 and 4.3). It marked the Wehrmacht exhibition's first appearance on the 8 o'clock Tagesschau news and sparked sustained national media coverage of many subsequent openings (see TableA.2). We find that the exhibition had a statistically significant negative effect on local SPD support both before and after its Munich debut. However, we find marginally larger effect estimates after February 1997, suggesting that increased media attention and heightened public awareness amplified the local effects.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table A .</head><label>A</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">1: Wehrmacht exhibition news articles by outlet</cell></row><row><cell>Newspaper</cell><cell>No. of exhibition articles (1995-2004)</cell></row><row><cell>Bonner General-Anzeiger</cell><cell>96</cell></row><row><cell>DER SPIEGEL</cell><cell>76</cell></row><row><cell>DIE ZEIT</cell><cell>93</cell></row><row><cell>Der Tagesspiegel</cell><cell>280</cell></row><row><cell>F.A.Z. Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung (FAZ)</cell><cell>329</cell></row><row><cell>FOCUS</cell><cell>62</cell></row><row><cell>Frankfurter Allgemeine Sonntagszeitung (FAS)</cell><cell>66</cell></row><row><cell>Handelsblatt</cell><cell>15</cell></row><row><cell>Handelszeitung</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Mitteldeutsche Zeitung</cell><cell>195</cell></row><row><cell>Nürnberger Nachrichten</cell><cell>117</cell></row><row><cell>Rhein-Main-Zeitung</cell><cell>151</cell></row><row><cell>Saarbrücker Zeitung</cell><cell>413</cell></row><row><cell>Stuttgarter Zeitung</cell><cell>125</cell></row><row><cell>Süddeutsche Zeitung (SZ)</cell><cell>525</cell></row><row><cell>WirtschaftsWoche</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>taz. die tageszeitung</cell><cell>454</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: This table shows the total number of articles about the Wehrmacht exhibition per newspaper.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table B</head><label>B</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>.3: Issue aggregation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Answer label</cell><cell>Issue category</cell></row><row><cell>German military deployment in Bosnia</cell><cell>Bundeswehr</cell></row><row><cell>German military deployment in Yugoslavia</cell><cell>Bundeswehr</cell></row><row><cell>General German military deployments</cell><cell>Bundeswehr</cell></row><row><cell>German involvement in Iraq</cell><cell>Bundeswehr</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Germany's involvement in NATO alliance case (Afghanistan) Bundeswehr</cell></row><row><cell>Deaths of German soldiers in foreign deployments</cell><cell>Bundeswehr</cell></row><row><cell>UN deployment of the German military</cell><cell>Bundeswehr</cell></row><row><cell>Peace / preservation of peace</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>Conflict in Afghanistan</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>Conflict in Liberia</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>Conflict / deployment in Congo</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>Costs of the Kosovo war</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>War in Yugoslavia, Yugoslavia</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>Wars in the world</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>US operations against terrorism, debate about Iraq war</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>Planned US operations (Syria)</cell><cell>Int. wars/peace</cell></row><row><cell>Asylum seekers, asylum policy</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Asylum seekers, asylum law</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Asylum debate, asylum topic</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Emigrants and resettlers</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Foreigners</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Foreigners (overpopulation)</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Foreigners' crime</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Foreigners' policy</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Debate about immigration</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Refugees</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>War refugees</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Muslims in Germany, headscarf debate</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Dual citizenship</cell><cell>Migration</cell></row><row><cell>Attacks on Jewish establishments in Germany</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>Antisemitism</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>Xenophobia</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>NPD ban</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>Right-wing extremist marches</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>Right-wing extremist violence</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>Right-wing radicalism, right-wing extremism</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>Republicans</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>Electoral success of right-wing extremist parties</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row><row><cell>Organized right-wing extremism</cell><cell>Right-wing extremism</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: This table lists codings for the aggregation of individual answers to the survey question "In your opinion, what are the three biggest problems in Germany at the moment?" into four broader issue areas.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Note: This table contains summary statistics for the survey data.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="8">Table C.7: Summary statistics contemporary survey data (continued)</cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell cols="7">Table C.7: Summary statistics contemporary survey data N Mean SD Min Max</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: Saxony</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.07</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.26 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Variable State: Saxony-Anhalt</cell><cell></cell><cell>N 1,294 0.03 Mean</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">SD Min Max 0.17 0 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Year of birth State: Thuringia</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="5">1,294 1945.38 3.38 1930 1949 1,294 0.03 0.16 0 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Gender: Female</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.3</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.46 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Gender: Male</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.7</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.46 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Religion: Catholic</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.18</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.39 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Religion: Protestant Religion: Other C.4 Characteristics of treated and control localities 1,294 0.34 1,294 0.02</cell><cell cols="2">0.48 0 0.13 0</cell><cell>1 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Religion: None</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.45</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.5 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">Education: None Education: Elementary / Lower secondary 1,294 0.19 1,294 0 Figure C.8: Covariate characteristics of treated and control counties 0.03 0 0.39 0</cell><cell>1 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Education: Polytechnic secondary school 1,294 0.04 Education: Intermediate 1,294 0.29 CDU/CSU Vote Share 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.19 0 0.45 0</cell><cell>1 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Education: Upper secondary Education: University degree SPD Vote Share 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.11 1,294 0.37</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.31 0 0.48 0</cell><cell>1 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Education: Other Left Vote Share 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.01</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.1 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Father served in WW2 Father killed in WW2 Right-Wing Protests p.c. 1991-1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.77 1,294 0.07</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.42 0 0.25 0</cell><cell>1 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Father decorated Unemployment Rate 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.09</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.28 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">WW2 memory</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,122 0</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell cols="2">-2.49 1.95</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">WW2 attitudes FDP Vote Share 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,079 0</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell cols="2">-2.78 1.47</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Wehrmacht crimes Family narratives on WW2 soldiers Employment Rate 1994</cell><cell>1,178 5.86 1,078 0</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">1.51 1 1 -1.51 2.75 7</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Family war memory intensity GDP p.c. 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,267 2.51</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.98 1</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Family main info source about WW2</cell><cell>1,276 3.54</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.14 1</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">WW2 part of family history Population Density 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,265 4.63</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.95 1</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">WW2 shaped family identity No. of Wehrmacht adjectives Protests p.c. 1991-1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,219 4.07 1,294 1.14</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.93 1 0.99 0</cell><cell>7 3</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: Schleswig-Holstein Greens Vote Share 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.06</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.23 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: Hamburg State: Lower Saxony Total Population 1994</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.03 1,294 0.09</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.18 0 0.29 0</cell><cell>1 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: Bremen</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>1,294 0.01 0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell cols="2">0.1 0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: North Rhine-Westphalia State: Hesse</cell><cell cols="6">1,294 0.17 Mean level difference between 0.37 0 1,294 0.08 0.27 0 treated and control counties (in s.d.)</cell><cell>1 1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: Rhineland-Palatinate State: Baden-Württemberg State: Bavaria</cell><cell cols="6">1,294 0.04 1,294 0.1 1,294 0.12 Baseline: all never-treated counties Baseline: never-treated applicant counties 0.21 0 0.3 0 0.33 0 Baseline: 1 1 1 never-treated applicant city counties</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: Saarland</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.01</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.12 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: Berlin</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.09</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.28 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">State: Brandenburg</cell><cell></cell><cell>1,294 0.05</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.22 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">State: Mecklenburg-Western Pomerania</cell><cell>1,294 0.02</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.14 0</cell><cell>1</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table D .</head><label>D</label><figDesc>9: Treatment effect heterogeneity pre-/ post-Munich exhibition opening This table shows estimates for the effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on the intention to vote for the SPD in federal-level elections before and after (including) the exhibition in Munich. Standard errors are clustered at the county level.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>(6)</cell><cell>-0.098**</cell><cell>(0.038)</cell><cell>47,859</cell><cell cols="2">Not-yet-treated</cell><cell cols="2">counties</cell></row><row><cell>Post Munich</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>-0.092***</cell><cell>(0.024)</cell><cell>80,870</cell><cell>Never-treated</cell><cell cols="2">applicant city</cell><cell>counties</cell></row><row><cell>DV: SPD voting intention</cell><cell>(3) (4)</cell><cell>-0.049** -0.088***</cell><cell>(0.021) (0.026)</cell><cell>68,992 143,306</cell><cell cols="4">Not-yet-treated Never-treated applicant counties counties</cell></row><row><cell>Pre Munich</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>-0.067***</cell><cell>(0.017)</cell><cell>94,652</cell><cell>Never-treated</cell><cell cols="2">applicant city</cell><cell>counties</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>-0.065***</cell><cell>(0.013)</cell><cell>143,661</cell><cell>Never-treated</cell><cell cols="2">applicant</cell><cell>counties</cell></row><row><cell>Period:</cell><cell></cell><cell>ATT</cell><cell></cell><cell>N</cell><cell cols="2">Control</cell><cell cols="2">group</cell><cell>Note:</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table E .</head><label>E</label><figDesc>10 shows that exhibition onset significantly increased the volume of published letters to the editors in local newspapers, both negative and positive. The table presents the results from a series of regression discontinuity in time analyses. The outcome variable is the daily count of exhibition-related letters to the editor in counties that hosted the Wehrmacht exhibition. Columns 3 -6 differentiate between letters that express support vs. opposition to the exhibition. Models are estimated using optimal bandwidth selection and robust bias-corrected standard errors<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Calonico et al. 2017</ref>).</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="7">Table E.10: Effect of Wehrmacht exhibition on letters to the editor in local newspapers</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">All Letters</cell><cell cols="2">Positive Letters</cell><cell cols="2">Negative Letters</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>(6)</cell></row><row><cell>Estimate</cell><cell>0.12***</cell><cell>0.12***</cell><cell>0.04***</cell><cell>0.04***</cell><cell>0.06***</cell><cell>0.06***</cell></row><row><cell>Polynomial</cell><cell cols="6">Linear Quadratic Linear Quadratic Linear Quadratic</cell></row><row><cell>Bandwidth (days)</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>292</cell><cell>187</cell><cell>350</cell><cell>174</cell><cell>328</cell></row><row><cell>Note:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>*** indicates p-value &lt; 0.01.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table E .</head><label>E</label><figDesc>11: Effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on SPD federal election result The table shows the results from OLS estimations of two difference-in-differences models. We use county-level election results from 1994 and 1998. We code all counties where the exhibition was shown prior to the 1998 election as treated. Standard errors clustered at the county level in parenthesis.</figDesc><table><row><cell>DV:</cell><cell></cell><cell>SPD vote share</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Full sample</cell><cell>Treated + Applicant</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>counties</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell></row><row><cell>Post × Treated</cell><cell>-0.0015</cell><cell>-0.0008</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0047)</cell><cell>(0.0051)</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.980</cell><cell>0.985</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>801</cell><cell>186</cell></row><row><cell>Year FE</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✓</cell></row><row><cell>County FE</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✓</cell></row></table><note><p>Notes: * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001 E.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>5 Scope condition test contemporary survey</head><label></label><figDesc>The table presents the results of an OLS regression of the item asking respondents if the position of the CDU regarding the recognition of Wehrmacht members would lead them to vote for another party. We control for year of birth, education, religious affiliation, and state. Heteroskedasticity-robust standard errors are reported in parentheses. Signif. Codes: ***: 0.01, **: 0.05, *: 0.1.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Table E.12: Collective memory and voting</cell></row><row><cell>DV:</cell><cell>Vote other party</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell></row><row><cell>Father served in WWII</cell><cell>0.2937  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1626)</cell></row><row><cell>Father killed in WWII</cell><cell>0.4761  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.2785)</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.062</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>1,125</cell></row></table><note><p>Notes:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table E</head><label>E</label><figDesc>The table shows the effect of the Wehrmacht exhibition on SPD support in federal-level elections split by gender. We report estimates for the first month after the exhibition's opening. Standard errors are clustered at the county level. Signif. Codes: ***: 0.01, **: 0.05, *: 0.1.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">.13: Treatment effect heterogeneity by gender</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">DV: SPD voting intention</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell>(4)</cell><cell>(5)</cell><cell>(6)</cell></row><row><cell>ATT</cell><cell cols="6">-0.094*** -0.054* -0.105*** -0.059* -0.088** -0.047</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.024)</cell><cell>(0.028)</cell><cell>(0.032)</cell><cell cols="3">(0.032) (0.036) (0.041)</cell></row><row><cell>N</cell><cell cols="2">144,159 179,521</cell><cell>94,381</cell><cell cols="2">118,620 68,433</cell><cell>86,302</cell></row><row><cell>Sample</cell><cell>Men</cell><cell>Women</cell><cell>Men</cell><cell>Women</cell><cell>Men</cell><cell>Women</cell></row><row><cell>Control group</cell><cell cols="2">Never-treated applicant counties</cell><cell cols="2">Never-treated applicant city counties</cell><cell cols="2">Not-yet-treated counties</cell></row></table><note><p>Note:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table E .</head><label>E</label><figDesc>14: Gender differences in mentions of father decorations and</figDesc><table><row><cell>Wehrmacht ideals</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>DV:</cell><cell>Father decorated (0/1)</cell><cell>No. of Wehrmacht</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>adjectives</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>0.0449  *  *  *</cell><cell>0.1041  *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0161)</cell><cell>(0.0612)</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.052</cell><cell>0.044</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>1,294</cell><cell>1,294</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table F .</head><label>F</label><figDesc>15: Interviews with opening speakers and contemporaries</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Interviewee Interview date Opening Opening date Short bio and/or organizational billing at the time</head><label></label><figDesc>Author, lawyer, talk show host. Functionary, Central Council of Jews in Germany. Chair of the host institution, state MP and deputy chair, SPD parliamentary group. Minister President of Saarland, patron/sponsor of the Saarbrücken exhibition.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Michael Burkert 28 November 2024 Saarbrücken 21 February 1999 Opening speaker. President of the city-district of Saarbrücken.</cell><cell>Michel Friedman 04 December 2024 Bremen Münster 28 May 1997 21 August 1998 Opening speaker. Elisabeth Abendroth 05 December 2024 Frankfurt 13 April 1997 Speechwriter to Hans Eichel (opening speaker), Minister President of Hesse.</cell><cell>Armin Lang 17 December 2024 Saarbrücken 21 February 1999 Opening speaker. Reinhard Klimmt 14 January 2025 Saarbrücken 21 February 1999 Opening speaker.</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Quote drawn from the authors' analysis of exhibition guestbooks at the Hamburg Institute for Social Research (HIS).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Reinhard Klimmt and Michel Friedman, respectively.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>We follow<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Alter and Zürn (2020)</ref>, who understand backlash politics as a movement that aims to return to a prior condition, challenges broadly shared norms or narratives and shapes public discourse.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>For a review, see<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Branscombe and Doosje (2004)</ref>.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_4"><p>17.3 million men served in the Wehrmacht between 1939 and 1945, 0.9 million served in the Waffen-SS;<ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Overmans (2004)</ref>.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_5"><p>One of our interviewees recalled the intensity with which visitors studied the exhibition's images, see SI Section F.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_6"><p>Between February 1997 and November 1999, it was featured on the main eight o'clock news program, Tagesschau (watched, on average, by around 10 million people), eight times. TableA.2 in the SI lists these news segments with URLs to archival footage.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="11" xml:id="foot_7"><p>The latter were described in detail in several of our interviews, see SI Section F.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_8"><p>Many of our interviewees relayed recollections of severe protests against the exhibition, see SI Section F.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_9"><p>We interviewed three opening speakers of the Saarbrücken exhibition, see SI Section F.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="14" xml:id="foot_10"><p>This share stands at 79% if we include public figures known to be simple party members, rather than only elected and party-nominated officials.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="15" xml:id="foot_11"><p>E.g., Johannes Rau (Minister-President of North Rhine-Westphalia and soon-to-be Federal President of Germany), Hans Eichel (Minister-President of Hesse), Jutta Limbach (President of the Federal Constitutional Court), and Hans-Jochen Vogel (leader of the SPD from 1987-1991).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="16" xml:id="foot_12"><p>From 1995 to 1999, the exhibition was only shown in three East German cities (excluding Berlin), namely Erfurt, Dresden, and Potsdam.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="17" xml:id="foot_13"><p>This was stressed by many of our interviewees, see SI Section F. See also our insights from letters to the editor in Section 6.1 and SI Section B.2.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="18" xml:id="foot_14"><p>For instance, many high school classes visited the exhibition.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="19" xml:id="foot_15"><p>See Table A.2 in the SI.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="20" xml:id="foot_16"><p>We note that the y-axis levels in Figure3and point estimates in TableE.10 underestimate the true volume of letters to the editor. This is because we coded a random sample of all exhibition-related letters, approximately 25-30% of all letters in the HIS archives. Accordingly, the true daily rate of letters is likely underestimated by a factor of about 3-4.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="22" xml:id="foot_17"><p>In a supplementary analysis, we also examine effect heterogeneity by gender. While we find significant treatment effects in both male and female subsets, the estimated effect magnitude is nearly twice as large for men as for women (see TableE.13). These gendered dynamics may reflect the more central role of self-serving WWII narratives for men's identity formation, thus making challenges to these narratives particularly threatening. In SI Section E.8, we present additional survey-based evidence that supports this interpretation.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="23" xml:id="foot_18"><p>This cohort of Germans, especially those born between 1927 and 1929, was also highly exposed to Nazi indoctrination, particularly through the Hitler Youth. The Hitler Youth, established by the Nazi Party, aimed to indoctrinate German children and adolescents with Nazi ideology, focusing on loyalty to Adolf Hitler, racial purity, and militarism. In March 1939, membership became mandatory for all youths aged 10 to 18 (see SI Figure C.10 on Hitler Youth exposure by birth cohort).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="25" xml:id="foot_19"><p>For instance, State Minister for Culture Julian Nida-Rümelin (SPD), who reported directly to Chancellor Gerhard Schröder (SPD), spoke at the second exhibition's overall opening in Berlin.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="26" xml:id="foot_20"><p>Argus Media in Germany and Observer in Austria, who have since merged.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="27" xml:id="foot_21"><p>Note that this has since changed; many of the printed letters would today likely be deemed outside the bounds of acceptable public speech in democratic German civil society.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="28" xml:id="foot_22"><p>We note, however, that the draft was incomplete among older cohorts(1900( -1910( , see Wurdack (2002))). We also note that while year of birth strongly predicts WWII participation, this is an imperfect approximation; a small proportion of men in drafted cohorts did not serve as soldiers due to exemptions, such as medical disqualifications.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D.3 Jackknife resampling</head><p>Appendix References <ref type="bibr">Forsa, Berlin. 1998a</ref><ref type="bibr">. "Forsa Bus 1995</ref>. " GESIS Data Archive, Cologne. ZA2983 Data file Version 1.0.0, https://doi.org/10.4232/1.2983. <ref type="bibr">Forsa, Berlin. 1998b</ref><ref type="bibr">. "Forsa Bus 1997</ref>. " GESIS Data Archive, Cologne. ZA2985 Data file Version</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conceptualising backlash politics: Introduction to a special issue on backlash politics in comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Karen</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Alter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Zürn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1369148120947958</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/1369148120947958" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The British Journal of Politics and International Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="563" to="584" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Publisher: SAGE Publications</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pressebericht der Kommission zur Überprüfung der Ausstellung &quot;Vernichtungskrieg. Verbrechen der Wehrmacht 1941 bis 1944</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arbeitskreis</forename><surname>Militärgeschichte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://web.archive.org/web/20160312204937/http://portal.akmilitaergeschichte.de/sites/akm/nlarchiv/NL" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Newsletter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective Memory and Cultural Identity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Assmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Czaplicka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/488538" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">New German Critique</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="133" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What Difference Do Museums Make?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laia</forename><surname>Balcells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elsa</forename><surname>Voytas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordhb/9780198704355.013.40</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780198704355.013.40" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Oxford Handbook of Transitional Justice</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Meierhenrich</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laban</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remembering the Violent Past in Ethnically Divided Societies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laia</forename><surname>Balcells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Olwen</forename><surname>Purdue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elsa</forename><surname>Voytas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Nationalism and Ethnic Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do Transitional Justice Museums Persuade Visitors? Evidence from a Field Experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laia</forename><surname>Balcells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Valeria</forename><surname>Palanza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elsa</forename><surname>Voytas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/714765</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/714765" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="496" to="510" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>The University of Chicago Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Jenseits des Krieges (East of War)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ruth</forename><surname>Beckermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://shop.ruthbeckermann.com/streaming/jenseits-des-krieges" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Writing the History of Memory. A&amp;C Black</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bill</forename><surname>Niven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>KddBAgAAQBAJ</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Bevan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Monumental Lies: Culture Wars and the Truth about the Past</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Verso</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1 ed. London</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attributions of responsibility and perceived harm in the aftermath of mass violence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bilali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Linda</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rezarta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nilanjana</forename><surname>Tropp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dasgupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peace and Conflict: Journal of Peace Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Place: US Publisher: Educational Publishing Foundation</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dark side of emotion regulation: Historical defensiveness as an obstacle in reconciliation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michal</forename><surname>Bilewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Inquiry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Place: United Kingdom Publisher: Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bpb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.bpb.de/kurz-knapp/hintergrund-aktuell/244026/vor-20-jahren-eine-ausstellung-ueber-verbrechen-der-wehrmacht-polarisiert-deutschland/" />
		<title level="m">Vor 20 Jahren: Eine Ausstellung über Verbrechen der Wehrmacht polarisiert Deutschland</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Collective Guilt: International Perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nyla</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Branscombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bertjan</forename><surname>Doosje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Google-Books-ID</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>cS5fqn3KJKIC</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective self-esteem consequences of outgroup derogation when a valued social identity is on trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nyla</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Branscombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="641" to="657" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The context and content of social identity threat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nyla</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Branscombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Naomi</forename><surname>Ellemers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Russell</forename><surname>Spears</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bertjan</forename><surname>Doosje</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Social identity: Context, commitment, content</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford, England</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Blackwell Science</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Die Tradition der Bundeswehr. Richtlinien zum Traditionsverständnis und zur Traditionspflege</title>
		<ptr target="die-tradition-der-bundeswehr-data.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bundesministerium der Verteidigung</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 23234/6a93123be919584d48e16c45a5d52c10/20180328</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Difference-in-differences with multiple time periods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brantly</forename><surname>Callaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pedro Hc Sant'</forename><surname>Anna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">225</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">rdrobust: Software for regression-discontinuity designs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sebastian</forename><surname>Calonico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matias</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cattaneo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Max</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Farrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rocio</forename><surname>Titiunik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Stata Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="404" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">After the genocide: Proximity to victims and support for punishing ingroup crimes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Volha</forename><surname>Charnysh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sascha</forename><surname>Riaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Political Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Processing of social identity threats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>De Hoog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Natascha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dark Pasts: Changing the State&apos;s Story in Turkey and Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bananas, beaches and bases: Making feminist sense of international politics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cynthia</forename><surname>Enloe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Univ of California Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Locating family in cultural memory studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Astri</forename><surname>Erll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Comparative Family Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="318" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vaterlos: Langzeitfolgen des Aufwachsens ohne Vater im Zweiten Weltkrieg</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jochen</forename><surname>Hardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elmar</forename><surname>Brähler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/oct/24/franco-exhumation-spain-dictator-" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zeitschrift für psychosomatische Medizin und Psychotherapie</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="216" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Madrid Kansteiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wulf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Pursuit of German Memory: History, Television, and Politics After Auschwitz</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Google-Books-ID: xWtVZWmQkDAC</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The new culture wars: Why critical race theory matters more than cancel culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Kaufmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/ssqu.13156</idno>
		<ptr target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/ssqu.13156" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="773" to="788" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">_eprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organisation und Mobilisierung des deutschen Machtbereichs. Band 1. Number 5-1 in</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><surname>Kroener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rolf-Dieter</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Umbreit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Das Deutsche Reich und der Zweite Weltkrieg</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organisation und Mobilisierung des deutschen Machtbereichs. Band 2. Number 5-2 in</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><surname>Kroener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rolf-Dieter</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Umbreit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Das Deutsche Reich und der Zweite Weltkrieg</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctv11cw204" />
		<title level="m">The Politics of Memory in Postwar Europe</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Lebow</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wulf</forename><surname>Ned</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claudio</forename><surname>Kansteiner</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Fogu</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Collective Memories of Violence and Political Attitudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Giacomo</forename><surname>Lemoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gloria</forename><surname>Gennaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<publisher>OSF Pre-Print</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transitional justice and the political &apos;work&apos; of domestic tourism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Duncan</forename><surname>Light</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Remus</forename><surname>Creţan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreea-Mihaela</forename><surname>Dunca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13683500.2020.1763268</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13683500.2020.1763268" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Issues in Tourism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="742" to="754" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Publisher: Routledge _eprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Politics of Memory and Nationalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Olga</forename><surname>Malinova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/nationalities-papers/article/politics-of-memory-and-nationalism/F11C33FD461ECEA9039899F259F0DF76" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nationalities Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="997" to="1007" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Being better by being right: Subjective group dynamics and derogation of in-group deviants when generic norms are undermined</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">José</forename><surname>Marques</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dominic</forename><surname>Abrams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rui</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Serôdio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="447" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>American Psychological Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Masculinity and nationalism: Gender and sexuality in the making of nations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joane</forename><surname>Nagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Celebrating 40 Years of Ethnic and Racial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="122" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Brandanschlag-Überlebende fordern Aufklärung</title>
		<idno>NDR. 2022</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.ndr.de/geschichte/chronologie/Wehrmachtsausstellung-loest-1995-Proteste-aus,wehrmachtsausstellung100.html" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective Memory: The Two Cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Olick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/370189" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Sage Publications, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Deutsche militärische Verluste im Zweiten Weltkrieg 3. A. De Gruyter Oldenbourg</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rüdiger</forename><surname>Overmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The social psychology of history. Defining the most important events of the last 10, 100, and 1000 years</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Pennebaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Páez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Deschamps</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psicología Política</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>PromoLibro</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Under threat: Response to and the consequences of threats to individuals&apos; identities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Petriglieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Louise</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="641" to="662" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Academy of Management</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dieter</forename><surname>Pohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.nsdoku.de/lexikon/artikel/wehrmachtsausstellung-874" />
		<title level="m">nsdoku.lexikon: Wehrmachtsausstellung</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monumental Changes: Confederate Symbol Removals and Racial Attitudes in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roxanne</forename><surname>Rahnama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/730713</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/730713" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<publisher>The University of Chicago Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The development of collective remembering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elaine</forename><surname>Reese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robyn</forename><surname>Fivush</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Memory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">German war memories: Narrability and the biographical and social functions of remembering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gabriele</forename><surname>Rosenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oral History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The social construction of individual and collective memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gabriele</forename><surname>Rosenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Theorizing Social Memories. Routledge</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="55" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motivated to &quot;forget&quot;: The effects of ingroup wrongdoing on memory and collective guilt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Katie</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Rotella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Richeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Psychological and Personality Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="730" to="737" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Real Consequences of Symbolic Politics: Breaking the Soviet Past in Ukraine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arturas</forename><surname>Rozenas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anastasiia</forename><surname>Vlasenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/718210</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/718210" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1263" to="1277" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>The University of Chicago Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wer war verantwortlich für das Massaker von Babij Jar?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hartmut</forename><surname>Rüß</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1524/mgzs.1998.57.2.483/html</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1524/mgzs.1998.57.2.483/html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Militärgeschichtliche Zeitschrift</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="508" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vati blieb im Krieg&quot;: Vaterlosigkeit als generationelle Erfahrung im 20</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Seegers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jahrhundert-Deutschland und Polen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Wallstein Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anschlag auf Saarbrücker Wehrmachtsausstellung seit 25 Jahren unaufgeklärt</title>
		<idno>SR. 2024</idno>
		<ptr target="https://web.archive.org/web/20240414172548/https://www.sr.de/sr/home/nachrichten/panorama/jahresta" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tagesschau</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">/</forename><surname>Tagesschau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.tagesschau.de/multimedia/sendung/tagesschau𝑣𝑜𝑟20𝑗𝑎ℎ𝑟𝑒𝑛/𝑣𝑖𝑑𝑒𝑜-260929.ℎ𝑡𝑚𝑙" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-02-24">1997. 24 February 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">08</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Social Identity Theory of Intergroup Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Henri</forename><surname>Tajfel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Psychology Press. Num Pages: 18. taz. 1997</idno>
		<ptr target="https://taz.de/Geschichte-mit-Gauweiler/!1407810/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Geschichte mit Gauweiler</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Political Psychology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavioral consequences of intergroup sensi-tivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Thürmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sean</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lukas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mccrea</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social and Personality Psychology Compass</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>Place: United Kingdom Publisher: Wiley-Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Commemorating local victims of past atrocities and far-right support over time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oguzhan</forename><surname>Turkoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ruth</forename><surname>Ditlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Berenike</forename><surname>Firestone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.2221158120</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.pnas.org/doi/full/10.1073/pnas.2221158120" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Publisher: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>28):e2221158120</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do TJ policies cause backlash? Evidence from street name changes in Spain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Francisco</forename><surname>Villamil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laia</forename><surname>Balcells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/20531680211058550</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/20531680211058550" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research &amp; Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20531680211058550</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>Publisher: SAGE Publications Ltd</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wdr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www1.wdr.de/stichtag/stichtag2934.html" />
		<title level="m">24. Februar 2007 -Vor 10 Jahren: Wehrmachts-Ausstellung in München eröffnet. &quot; WDR</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Der Krieg der Erinnerung: Holocaust, Kollaboration und Widerstand im europäischen Gedächtnis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harald</forename><surname>Welzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://books.google.de/books?id=vbsWAQAAIAAJ" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fischer Geschichte Fischer Taschenbuch Verlag</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">» Opa war kein Nazi «: Nationalsozialismus und Holocaust im Familiengedächtnis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harald</forename><surname>Welzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sabine</forename><surname>Moller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Karoline</forename><surname>Tschuggnall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>S. Fischer Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Wertsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Memory in mind and culture</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, US</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="137" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective memory: Conceptual foundations and theoretical approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Wertsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iii</forename><surname>Roediger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Memory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="318" to="326" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Place: United Kingdom Publisher: Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Colonial abuses haunt France&apos;s racism debate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lucy</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-53095738" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Geschichte der Erinnerungskultur in der DDR und BRD</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Edgar</forename><surname>Wolfrum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">2008. 1995-1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Table A.2: Wehrmacht exhibition coverage in the Tagesschau 8 o&apos;clock news</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exhibition opening, Munich URL 01 March 1997 -1:34 Neo-Nazi protests and counter-protests in Munich -13 April 1997 11:26 0:30 Exhibition opening, Frankfurt am Main</title>
		<idno>URL 30 January 1999 08:11 0:35</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Neo-Nazi protests and counter-protests in Kiel URL 09 March 1999 07:01 1:29 Bombing in Saarbrücken URL 04 November 1999 02:43 1:29 Exhibition moratorium URL Note: Footage</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Date Timestamp Duration Topic</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Neo-Nazi protests and counter-protests in Dresden. from 01 March 1997 is not available to the public online due to an injunction proceeding</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4232/1.2985</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4232/1.2985" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GESIS Data Archive, Cologne. ZA3162 Data file Version 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Berlin</forename><surname>Forsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4232/1.3162</idno>
		<idno>.0.0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4232/1.3162" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Forsa-Bus 1998</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GESIS Data Archive, Cologne. ZA3486 Data file Version 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Berlin</forename><surname>Forsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4232/1.3486</idno>
		<idno>.0.0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4232/1.3486" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Forsa Bus 2000</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GESIS Data Archive, Cologne</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Berlin</forename><surname>Forsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4232/1.11780</idno>
		<idno>ZA3063 Data file Version 2.0.0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4232/1.11780" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Forsa-Bus 1994</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GESIS Data Archive, Cologne. ZA2984 Data file Version 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Berlin</forename><surname>Forsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4232/1.11785</idno>
		<idno>.0.0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4232/1.11785" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Forsa Bus 1996</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GESIS Data Archive, Cologne</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Berlin</forename><surname>Forsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4232/1.11786</idno>
		<idno>ZA3289 Data file Version 2.0.0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4232/1.11786" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Forsa-Bus 1999</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Syntactic Annotations for the Google Books Ngram Corpus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yuri</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jean-Baptiste</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erez</forename><surname>Lieberman Aiden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jon</forename><surname>Orwant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Will</forename><surname>Brockman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Slav</forename><surname>Petrov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://aclanthology.org/P12-3029.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 50th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the 50th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anteil der nichtehelich geborenen Kinder in Deutschland</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Statista</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://de.statista.com/statistik/daten/studie/1059666/umfrage/anteil-der-nichtehelich-geborenen-kinder-in-deutschland/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2024" to="2036" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Der Wehrdienst in der Wehrmacht -Ein Überblick</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jörg</forename><surname>Wurdack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.lexikon-der-wehrmacht.de/Soldat/Wehrdienst.htm" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
